All right, so we just did all that work, all that mathematics to derive this weird, odd result for
kinetic energy, which is as follows, which is defined as gamma minus one times and C squared.
Now, from a first glance at this, it seems like it doesn't look anything like our classical version
of kinetic energy.
You know, one half and squares when the world is going on here.
Let's try and understand this.
Let's unwrap this new equation using a binomial expansion.
What I'm going to say is that the answer and the meaning behind this is wrap underneath this result
within the individual binomial that the polynomials that can be used to express this and when we unwrap
it, when we unwrap those layers, it's going to become evident and it's going to become more clear.
But what we know right now is that we see this weird entity squared parameter popping out, and we do
see that relativistic effects that tend to occur at high velocities are popping up.
So our intuition that if it's harder to push an object, a higher velocities to attain additional velocity,
then that must mean you any more and more energy to pump into a system to get an individual amount of
velocity.
Add it to it now.
If we take this and plot it up, we start to see the full picture.
And what I have here are plots showing the kinetic energy versus our relativistic velocity with a classical
and a relativistic result.
And what we're going to find by unwrapping the binomial expansion is that the relativistic and classical
result, which all work through shortly, do indeed convey the same result at low velocity.
So it does converge upon a classical result, which is good.
All results should do that and special relativity.
But what we see is that our intuition was indeed right as we get closer to the speed of light.
We see that in order to increase the velocity a bit more, we have to build up more and more energy
in the y direction for each Delta X for each change of policy, which means that, you know, that's
really compensating for that additional inertia that builds up that we discovered with the momentum
equation.
Another interesting fact is that as we approach the speed of light, the energy goes to infinity.
So that sort of implies and this is not a direct result, but a sort of implies that we would need infinite
energy to reach the speed of light and go beyond it.
So that sort of is showing that.
The cap, the second part of the special relativity imposes upon a velocity as we start accelerating
it, saying that the loss cannot go beyond the speed of life is sort of showing up in our energy equation
because we would need infinite energy to go to the speed of light, which is an impossible fact.
I cannot happen, right?
So this is sort of showing that the second part of the special relativity, this cap on velocity gives
rise to relativistic effects in energy close to the speed of light, which is interesting.
But let's continue with unwrapping our equation and see what kind of information we can divulge that's
inherent within this result we got here.
So if you recall, maybe you studied the binomial expansion.
I hope you have.
If you have not, what its needs is that if we have this guy here, this polynomial OnePlus X to the
end, some kind of exponential power that can be expressed as the sum from K will zero to infinity of
an end, choose K to have these this polynomial x to the K.
So if we start putting out terms, the first term is the one we get an X.
You can see it builds up in power increase in power.
OK.
So in our case, what we have is this one over square root of one plus B or C squared one plus x two.
Basically, it's this guy here, which is equivalent to organic factor.
So we're going to have to make use of this and we're going to subtract one and then multiply by SC Square.
So if we plug in a negative one half, we get one here minus one half.
And I have to plug what happened to this guy, so it's a negative one half minus one, what is that?
That's make it three or two times negative one half.
So that's a three or four times at two.
So that's a three over eight and positive Times Square, and we could keep expanding this out until
infinity, right?
That's what I'm saying.
We're unwrapping we're pulling out all these polynomials to see how each turn comes into play here.
Well, what's really interesting is the reason why we like binomial expansions is because if X is really
small, that means if you square a very small number infinitely small, then it's going to be much smaller
magnitude than if you take the regular values.
Yes, x squared is much less than x OK.
I've shown this many times in my course on Lagrangian mechanics.
You could do an experiment, put in a small number in four x squared and compare it to the small number
itself.
It's going to be much smaller then if you cube it.
It's going to be even smaller.
So these guys sort of drop out and their effects do not become apparent until X becomes much larger.
OK, so what we're going to do is we're to take the limit as V is much less than C or if you ever see
approaches zero.
And when we do that, we can see that this guy and this guy are going to drop off their insanely small
when compared to this.
And we literally just end up with a falling so we can plug in x r.
You know, this guy, I'm going to write it out.
So the gamma.
And if you don't recall, is one over square root of one minus v overseas squared.
You should be super familiar with this guy.
This is the essence of special relativity, but if we take this, it's literally one minus this guy
squared to the negative one half so we can use the binomial expansion to express this in terms of the
phone.
So we have one that comes along for the ride.
And then the first leading term in terms of X, we plug this guy in a negative velocity square that
gives us a positive one half times the quantity VRC squared, plus all this massive.
It's super small in this limit.
OK, so we do that, we can use this to express this guy.
So this is no different than this guy minus one Times Square.
So the kinetic energy, the relativity kinetic energy is approximately equal to one plus one half times
B or C squared.
We're going to take that drop all the leading terms in this limit.
Subtract a one right here and then multiply by and c squared.
And when we do that, we see that the one cancels with the one.
And we end up with this term here.
So what's really interesting is we see a sea squared here and a sea squirt here.
All these guys are going to cancel out.
Bam, bam.
And what we end up with is a very, very interesting result, which I sort of hinted to at the beginning
with the grass one half in the square.
So at low velocities.
The relativistic equation does converge upon the result we expect won't have and B squared and as V
approaches the speed of light.
These terms here start to pick up pick up until they just blow up and go to infinity.
That's when it starts to diverge away from the classical result.
OK, so we see that what we obtained.
Jostle for intuition, as described here, drives off what we discovered with momentum and what we could
do is we're going to take this and we're going to try to unwrap it a bit further to see what else it
can divulge for us and what it's going to tell us.
What it's going to communicate is going to be mind boggling.
A huge, huge discovery that Einstein made an uncertain.
OK, so we're going to do that by rearranging the sky because we know this literally is our kinetic
energy of particles.
So if we take the kinetic energy and ANC squared up here, what we end up with is the following and
this is the important conclusion.
Pay attention.
So it states that Ghana and not c squared.
So I'm trying to emphasize that this is a rest mass mass you you measure when an object is at rest.
That is equal to M.C. squared, plus your kinetic energy.
OK.
And this is really interesting to spin the face of what we we observe in classical mechanics, what
we would say is that our total energy is going to be the change in the kinetic energy.
We didn't care about any kind of potential energy or any kind of reference.
We used to measure energy because energy is always measured in terms of our reference.
We are interested in the change in the kinetic energy, but what we see here is that there's much more
to energy than just, you know, the kinetic energy and the potential energy.
We get this guy here, which I'm going to assert as a rest energy.
I want to ask you the question What is this equation conveying to us?
What is it communicating?
It's basically asserting that mass is no different than a manifestation of energy.
Yes.
As Einstein stated, energy and mass are equivalent.
And when you hear that, that's that that's a mind shattering idea.
Right.
This goes outside of our conventions.
This was completely new for the day and age in which it was discovered.
But if we think about a lot of classical ideas, classical physics, it should not be that surprising,
right?
Because let's think about thermodynamics and thermodynamics.
We had this quantity in which we described matter and different compounds, so on and so forth, known
as internal energy and the change in internal energy, which was in essence, the energy composed inside
matter, inside atoms, so on and so forth.
The change in the internal energy gave rise to work, which we could use to generate electricity or
spin a shaft.
So on and so forth right now is the essence of thermodynamics.
So even back in the day of thermodynamics, we knew that matter in and of itself carried energy that
was sort of measured by temperature, right?
We use temperature and pressure along with different tables to look up internal energy of atoms and
mass and so on and so forth.
So this should not be super surprising.
What we're going to state is that all matter all mass, regardless of what it is throughout the universe,
has an inherent energy instantiate instantiated inside of it, right?
That mass is an expression of energy, in essence.
And what we're going to call it is a rest energy and not c squared.
Even when something is move is not moving.
It has inherent energy and it's quite a lot of energy.
This is what made nuclear physics possible.
Fission fusion, what that stating that stating that matter atoms.
When we take a look at atoms deep down, right, we have subatomic particles, protons, neutrons,
electrons, those electrons are zooming by moving pretty fast.
So it sort of insinuates that even though matter seems to be at rest for us, it's sort of actually
is in motion.
And that gives rise the movement of the subatomic particles to this internal energy, this rest energy.
OK, so should not be surprising that mass and energy are equivalent.
And what this is stating is that the total energy gamma and North C squared e is equal to a rest energy
energy that is inherent in the mass in the atoms, plus kinetic and the energy that is added by moving
that matter in a macroscopic kind of sense, but in a microscopic sense, looking at the subatomic particles,
there's a ton of energy in here.
OK?
As I was saying, this gave rise to nuclear power because what we do is we take the mass and we annihilate
a, we destroy it.
We convert that mass into what it really is.
We make use of the energy inherent in it, right?
We break apart those those particles and energy is released because in essence, it is energy.
It's rest energy, right?
So what this insinuates also is that one principle we take for granted in classical physics isn't quite
right.
On a macro, on a microscopic scale that is the idea of conservation of mass, right, because if mask,
if really change between the mass and energy, you cannot stop flowing into a situation with a certain
amount of mass and flowing out with a different kind of mass, which means that what's happening conservation
of mass is not always true on a macroscopic level.
We know it gives us good results.
We see that in chemical engineering, you know, mass flow in equals mass flow out.
That tends to be right.
But we see when we go down to a very microscopic scale and I'll give you examples of this, that conservation
of mass no longer holds.
So this really throws a wrench into our conception of energy and also what we found with with momentum,
just mechanics in general, right?
This idea of special relativity, of redefining our space time, redefining our conception of how time
and space flows and is instantiate in the universe really creates a ripple effect that changes are conception
of energy, mechanical mechanics and everything we really know in regards to it.
So I hope you enjoyed that discussion.
We got this earth shattering energy squared kind of idea that is super super famous that I came up with.
Next, we're going to try and figure out how we can use this to do calculations at microscopic levels
and make use of these results.
Stay tuned.