All right.
To derive that better measurement for microscopic levels that we're going to deal with primarily in
this course and in particle physics.
What I'm going to do is I'm going to walk you through some basic electrostatic, which you're usually
exposed to in electricity and magnetism course, which is usually traditionally in college.
The second physics course you actually take.
So a lot of textbooks just throw this measurement out and expect you to use it.
I want you to have intuition.
I want you to understand where it came from and what it's actually communicating, what the measurement
the unit actually signifies, OK?
So what I'm going to do to find a more appropriate measurement for energy when I call our past studies
of electric circuits and the work that's required to move a charged particles, the scenario I want
you to consider is, let's say we have a congregation of point charges.
Q one two three four.
How many charges you want anywhere in space.
This is going to signify surrounding environment charges.
And what we know is that any kind of charge is going to give off an electric field, which is specified
by E!
So these guys here, if we have a charged particle, which we're going to use as an electron Q and we
want to do work so we can move this from point A to point B, what's going to happen is any kind of
source charged with an electric field.
E is going to produce a force that either opposes or attracts this charge.
And what we know from the Lorenz Force Law, which I should underline right here, is that the force
that this electric field exerts on any kind of other charge Capital Q is Q times the electric field,
plus the velocity of the particle crossed into the magnetic field.
Now in this scenario.
We're going to assume there's no magnetic field, so this guy is going to drop off and we're left with
just Huie.
Now this guy is sort of if that doesn't look familiar to you and you've studied electrostatic, what
I want you to recall is that this is no different than after you put an E in the electric field.
You'd get this equation here one over four pi epsilon.
Not well, this is the permeability of space times.
The two charges Q Q, and this would be the sum of its the.
All these charges over the distance are square between the source and the point charge that you're interested
in.
What we see here is that it's sort of like the electric field is nothing more than the force over the
Q.
Now if we take this scenario and we want to move this guy over here, what we're doing is we're moving
this against the force that is created from these guys to see what's going to try to repel it.
So we have to exert a force that is equivalent to Q times e or greater in the opposite direction to
move it along this guy here.
And what we know from physics went along with we've just studied in deriving the kinetic energy is that
any kind of work we exert or put into a system is defined as the integral from A to B, from the two
distances that the two displacements of the force data into the actual length that it moves along the
lever arm.
It moves along, right?
So if we move along this path, any kind of path we have to exert or rather the energy in the work we
put into in moving it is described by this equation.
We're going to do the same exact thing that we did with kinetic energy, with relativistic energy.
We're going to do is we'll plug into the forest and just plug plug in shock.
OK, so.
For the force, we know well, we just arrived the Lorentz force law here, Huey.
That's the force that we have to act against in moving these guys.
And it's sort of similar.
An analogy I'm going to take a little side is sort of similar to potential energy if that jives more
with you and you haven't studied this with potential energy.
What you do is if you have some kind of object here, you have a force of gravity that's acting down.
In order to move this to this position, we have to exert a force equivalent to the mass times, the
gravity, the force of gravity equal to, but opposite to move it up to there.
What are the same exact thing here?
All right.
It's the same exact parallel, same exact phenomenon that's going on here.
So we take the force here and it's going to be in the opposite direction.
So we put in a negative.
We pull that in here and we get an expression here that's like, Oh, that doesn't really that doesn't
really get us anywhere.
So we have to sort of chug along a bit further.
So what we can do is we can pull out this cue the negative Q.
So this is a constant and we get this guy right here.
And if you studied electrostatic electric dynamics, this guy, this integral ETR should be a very special
special formula.
It should look like the formula for potential potential.
All right.
That's an important term.
An electrostatic but.
Well, we also know is that the electric field e is equivalent to the negative of a gradient of a potential
ft.
OK.
This is sort of like what we've seen in Physics 101 classical mechanics, where the force is equal to
the negative gradient of the potential energy.
And if we look at these two guys here, if this is confusing you.
This is no different than this guy.
In essence, it's just this the what if IQ, right?
The electric field is sort of like the force sport per charge, and that's useful because we just multiply
by any charge we want to see the force upon and that yields us, the force.
Similarly, the potential is sort of like the energy you divide up IQ.
OK, so.
If we take this guy here and we literally plug it in for Ether, the native grading of B, we get this
guy here and we could solve this because if we take the integral of a gradient over a distance D.R.
where we can use the fundamental theorem of calculus after we get rid of these negative signs, they
cancel out.
And the fundamental theorem of calculus says that if you integrate your gradient, you get nothing more
than the original quantity at the final result, minus the initial result, which is VB minus IPA.
So the net result we get is that in order to prove this charge against this electric field, we have
to.
Do the following work, the following work we do is the charge Q times, the change in potential, the
potential drop that we're moving across.
So if we take this, we can use it to formulate a new measurement of energy that's going to be more
applicable for the situation if we're going to be working with four microscopic scenarios.
Well, you know, we don't have a lot of mass, but we have very high velocities, OK?
So thus, if we try to move an electron across a potential difference of one volt, which is in essence
a potential drop, we can assert the following we could take a circuit.
We say we have some kind of battery of one volts and we can move across that volt.
The Bolt has an electro motor force and MF that wants to push this electron through the circuit, right?
That's how we get current.
That's how we get the flow of electrons of charges, charged particles.
So if we want to reverse that direction and go in the opposite direction, we're going to have to go
over one volt.
We're going to have a one volt potential drop, the potential difference of one volt.
What's the energy we're going to need to put into the system?
We can use what we just arrive or taking a look at an electrostatic.
So we can take this exactly as it is for an electron and we just literally use it as such.
So we plug in the charge mcluhan's for an electron.
And you know, that's a negative charge.
So we get a negative one point six zero two two times 10 to the minus 19 coolant.
That's how we measure how we we measure, charge and we multiply that by our potential drop, which
is a negative one volt.
We know that a volt Coulomb is a jewel and we end up with the phone.
We get to work that is one point six, zero, two, two and 10 to the minus 19th joules.
And you're probably thinking scratching your head.
You're like, Wait a second.
That energy is close to the same magnitude we had previously.
Well, instead of using this, what we're going to do is want to say, Yeah, we're going to be working
with these charged particles.
We're going to be moving them around.
So maybe we can have a new unit using this as a reference.
So as I said, using this as reference, we could derive a more useful measurement known as the electron
volt.
This is the new unit of energy we're going to use in special relativity or news particle physics to
get used to it.
I'm going to help you get used to it.
OK, so we take this.
This is the energy or take movies over one voltage drop.
We take this and say one electric electron volts is going to be equal to this, this amount of energy
and joules.
And in doing so, we get this new measurement of energy.
OK, so it's a new measurement of energy.
It seems to be on the scale that we're seeing that's cropping up with these small particles.
However, you still do not have intuition with that, right?
So I'm going to erase this.
The circuit and what we're going to do is we're going to revisit the problem we were just describing
with the rest energy of an electron.
And what we want to find is that this gives us a really nice way to measure energy.
It's on the same scale of the situations that we generally analyze.
So what we can do is we could take we could say, Oh, previously we took the electron and we said it's
less energy is equal to N-not c squared.
But we already did our calculation, right?
Well, all of that, that was nearly eight point one nine nine.
Times.
Ten in the negative 14 jewels.
So how do we express this in terms of electron volts?
Well, we can say, OK, we can drop this down here to make more space.
That's merely just eight point one nine nine times 10 to the minus 14.
Is that correct?
Yes, it is joules.
And then we just use loo.
We just arrived.
So we multiply by one electron volt, which is what we want.
We divide by the one point six zero to two times 10 to the minus 19 joules.
We cancel out this macroscopic unit and we end up with red drum roll.
Five point one one times 10.
To the fifth election ballots and what you'll usually see this expressed as is the following we can
divide by bring this over here and then that becomes 10 to the six.
So that's just zero point five one one MAGA, which is 10 to the 6th electron volts band.
And we look at that.
When we see the first energy for an electron, your first calculation you've ever put into play here.
Is just following its, you know, 0.5 one mega electron wolf.
What are you there to work with this?
It's much more convenient because we don't have to put a times 10 to the minus 19 jewels all the time.
And furthermore, you know, if you didn't have a calculator would be much easier to work with this
breast energy here.
So we can see at a microscopic level with situations that we're going to deal with.
All right.
This guy is more useful, if more practical.
OK, now to go a step further and to really emphasize the energy mass equivalence that we just discovered.
What I've got to say is that all your calculations are going to do special relativity, particle physics,
so on and so forth, where relativistic effects tend to crop up.
We're going to express the energy in terms of the electron volts.
But when you expressed the mass, we're going to redefine units for mass and be very easy.
It's going to be very straightforward.
What we're going to say is that.
Instead of reporting the mass in terms of a kilogram and then we have to go through this insane operation,
we have a kg rate multiply by the speed of light squared.
We have to convert to electron volts.
That's a lot of work, right?
What I mean, more convenient.
If we said, Oh well, the mass, the mass of an electron is nothing more than 0.5 one one mega electron
volts overseas squirt.
Now it seems sort of weird to write it like that, but all I did was literally took the C squared what
we wrote left side hook that got divided by C squared and we ended up with falling.
What's really useful is that by taking this and you'll find tables and in your textbook online, so
on and so forth, you look up the massive electron in a special relativity book.
You're you should find this guy.
It's going means expressed in terms of electron volts over squared because we could just take this for
the rest energy.
We don't have to do any calculations.
They owe the rest energy, which we're going to find.
We're going to deal with energy in particular because we're just falling just 0.5 one meg electron volts
and you no calculation.
Let's do this year after year, the conversion do not to plug it into my calculator.
It's much more effective, much more practical.
After you get used to this, you're going to like it a bit much more.
OK, so we're going to do our calculations in terms of this, and what we're going to find is the energy
and momentum in particular and the rest of energy here.
This is going to really drive our calculations, drive our approach to analysis, and we're going to
try to get rid of our reliance upon math.
Because as I mentioned in the previous video and we're going to explore in the next video is that if
mass is nothing more than a manifestation of energy and it can change freely between being mass or energy
or not, we shouldn't even think about as as such, mass literally is energy.
Mass is just our conception of energy, it's just an extra manifestation of it.
So if we can change freely, right, that sort of insinuates that conservation of mass no longer holds.
And on the going to divulge more about that, I talked about it a bit in the last video.
But if we can't rely upon that anymore, we can't use conservation of mass.
What we're going to see is really it's just basic physics principles, conservation of momentum, conservation
of energy and band.
So it's going to be more useful to express energy as such.
And we're going to find that we're going to redefine momentum units eventually.
And I'll make note of that when we do it, and it'll be more efficient to express a sort of in terms
of an electron volt calculation.
So there you have it, that is the electron volts.
I want to spend some time with the electrostatic.
If you're not really going to electrostatic, that's fine.
Take what you will know that redefining energy to make it more appropriate for the scales in which we're
doing calculations.
And, yeah, a lot of textbooks really do not go through this exercise.
But I want you to understand that literally it's just we're saying, OK, we're dealing with charged
particles.
Let's figure out what the energy is to move it across a potential drop, something that we use on a
general basis.
And then we're just going to generalize it for our calculations of special relativity.
So that's electron volts.
That's what we're going to do.
We're going to explore a bit more this mass energy equivalence idea.
And I'm going to show you how mass yes, it's going to change really between being a new mass or manifestation
of energy to actually being release energy.
And in doing so, I hope you get more intuition, ballboy intuition with this idea and start feeling
more comfortable with this idea that Einstein introduced.
Stay tuned.