All right, now that we have a proper way for measuring this new form of energy was just discovered.
What I want to do is take a deeper, closer look at this ripple effect we've identified within the body
of theoretical physics.
OK.
In particular, what we're going to look at is the notion of mass energy equivalence, which we've sort
of talked about previously, right?
What do we talk about?
We found that mass is nothing more than a manifestation of energy.
That energy has a way of expressing itself in multiple different forms.
And when we talk about this from a classical sense, right, this should not be surprising, right?
Even from physics, one or one from the conception of physics.
We know that energy, whether it be potential energy, kinetic energy, he energy, chemical energy,
you name it.
We know that energy converts into different forms pretty freely, right?
That's a basic concept of physics in a particular.
We take kinetic energy when a body is moving as the most physically identifiable source of energy.
You can actually see it moving.
You can see it being energetic.
But what we found in special relativity is that even when an object is at rest in virtue of being rest,
it still has energy inherent in it.
Right?
That's what we call rest energy.
The energy that is built into its mass.
And in fact, what we found the last video is that the energy inherent in that mass is gigantic, especially
in the macroscopic world.
OK.
So if energy can be composed in mass and it can freely change into kinetic energy because energy can
express it in multiple different itself, it can express itself in multiple different ways.
What kind of implications does that have about conservation of mass?
Is this true?
Is it not valid?
Well, as I talked about previously, a few videos back, I asserted that conservation mass is not true
because of mass energy equivalence.
So what we're going to do in this video is we're going to investigate that validity.
And this is going to give us an opportunity to run through some example problems.
You can build up your intuition with these weird ideas and start doing some special relativity calculations.
Now, when I assert that conservation of mass is not valid, that begs a lot of questions, right?
The first thing that comes to mind is the following If conservation of mass, which we tend to take
for granted and is pretty practical, we use it in a lot of practical applications.
If it's wrong, if it's not valid, well, why didn't we discover that in the first place?
Why has it taken so long to discover this?
And me myself personally, I worked in the chemical engineering industry, and I know that conservation
a mess is a basic principle that drives a lot of ideas.
It makes a lot of ideas and the production of chemicals, for example, possible.
So what's going on here?
Who's right?
Is relativity right in saying that it's not valid?
Or are we correct in looking at in a macroscopic scale and saying, Hey, conservation mask, it gives
us practical uses and it seems to be correct from our measurements.
What's going on here?
Who is right?
And furthermore, if it is incorrect, how can we have not measured this before, right?
Physics is an old discipline that goes back many, many years.
It's a very old idea.
How come this law has been prevalent for centuries?
Right?
Well, what's going on here?
So let's investigate this.
Let's look into this, and let's settle this once and for all.
So to investigate the validity of conservation matter of mass.
What we're going to do is we're going to consider a macroscopic situation with a microscopic situation.
Sorry about that with a macroscopic analog so that we have a situation that we're used to looking at
in a macroscopic, ask a situation, you know, like a a mass ring system.
And we're gonna equate that to a situation of having atoms that are composed in a molecule now when
atoms are composed in a molecule.
Right?
Unstable atoms, which may be radioactive.
We may have radioactive isotopes, which what is going to happen is they may spontaneously fly apart
or they combine together to form a new molecule.
So for example, if we have a radioactive isotope, which may typically be depicted here with different
atoms of different colors.
We may find that sometimes some kind of event triggers the separation of these guys as they fly apart.
Now the question then becomes what happened to the mass?
All right.
If this guys are rest and they suddenly fly apart, we had to get that kinetic energy from somewhere.
Where did it come from?
And what are we going to find?
Is that with less energy inherent in the mass was actually converted into kinetic energy, which allowed
these guys to fly apart.
The Converse situation is sometimes we're going to have reflective or or attractive or repulsive forces
that you know, can form new molecules, right?
And that repulsive or attractive force is sort of equivalent to some kind of electrostatic force, which
we just talked about in a previous video.
And when you sort of talk about these forces, you talk about potential, right?
When you move these guys closer together, that builds up the potential and that route word should make
you think of potential energy so we can think about this situation and analyze it in a macroscopic scale.
Using a mass springs system to blast, we're going to blocks mass M1 and M2 if we take the top situation
and we compress that spring together.
And put some latch this blue last year so that they can't fly apart.
We know that this has endured energy in it.
Right.
The compression of that spring put potential energy into the system.
And when we have some kind of event such as kicking that latch off.
That potential energy is going to be released, it's going to be converted, the energy is going to
express itself now as kinetic energy, right?
You knock this guy off and I can press spring is going.
It's going to push these guys in opposite directions.
Get it that velocity.
He was at potential energy.
Conversely, when we look at the situation, when atoms come together and form a molecule, we can have
two flying together with kinetic energy compresses this spring and that kinetic energy gets transformed
into potential energy.
Right, right.
We study this many times before this is it's one to one principles.
So the question then becomes OK, if the kinetic energy is being compressed into potential energy.
My question for you is.
What is that potential energy when you compress that spring?
Is the spring becoming more massive?
Well, what we found from mass energy equivalence is that if the kinetic energy disappears, it has
to go somewhere.
And what I'm going to search and I'm going to use as analog here between the two situations, is it
that that spring as you compress it, as you put energy into it and your kinetic energy is converted?
What you're doing when you build up potential energy is you're building up rest.
Energy equals M.C. squared.
So energy increases to the mass mass also increase.
Another way of thinking about this is that as you compress that spring.
What happens is.
The different parts of the spring, the helix is build up gravitational mass, there's more gravitation
between them.
And as a result of that, that builds up your potential energy until you release it.
Another way of thinking about this in a nice, tiny and kind of way is that as you compress it, the
space time is being curved or you're bending space time, which builds up gravitation.
OK, so the analogue between gravitation and gravitational mass implies that as the kinetic energy gets
converted into perpetual energy, you are in fact building up that mass.
OK, let's take a closer look at this by analyzing these two situations where we have a microscopic
scenario and a macroscopic scenario where we have a lot of intuition.
We're going to find is the intuition I just described, which should be, you know, that should be
something you take for granted.
This will guide us in understanding the weird relativistic effects on a microscopic scale.
OK, so to do that, what we're going to do, we're doing is conservation of energy.
We're going to directly show that the system is that is not conserved, right?
You know, the energy is going to be transformed.
Let's back up, either the mass is going to be transformed into kinetic energy or the kinetic energy
is going to be transformed into mass.
Sounds radical sounds insane because something you've never really dealt with, you can't really observe
it.
But you know what?
Looking at the situation, you understand this.
You understand the situation.
You've seen it many times before.
You can visualize it and you've studied this.
OK, so the situation we're going to take is this part here, the top portion here where we have combined
mass began.
We unleashed the latch.
There's some kind of mechanism.
It's radioactive isotope where the particles separate.
They don't ask the directions that builds up.
Energy is released now.
From a relativistic standpoint, what we say is that, OK, conservation of energy that must hold,
that's a basic physics principle.
So we say the energy in step one must equal the energy and say to, OK, let's fill in the details.
Let's see what we find.
So initially, we know we have mass big air, which is composed of M1 and M2, or so we think that's
what we say in the classical standpoint.
But we know we have a total mass arm of this hotel system.
We're calling it big m c squared, right?
It's at rest.
We know it has less energy now thanks to Einstein out and stick to what we know is that when it flies
apart, this velocity is going to give rise to kinetic energy.
So for System one and System two, system one, system two, we're going to have kinetic energy and
rest energy.
OK, so we have K1.
Kinetic energy was N1.
The massive system one ton c squared.
We have the same thing for System two, kinetic energy two plus the massive system two Times Square.
Now the question I want to ask you is when you look at this equation here, what can you say about NASA's?
What can you say about the massive?
Now, if K1 and K2 kinetic energy, right, that is usually expressed as.
Hey, is he got you one half and b squared?
Mass is not negative that that doesn't even make sense.
This guy is always positive.
So K1 was K2 is positive.
And this guy over here is being converted into what is on the right.
This implies inversion of K1 and K2 being positive that M1 and M2 cannot equal big M..
What I'm saying is that because of this, M1 plus M2 does not equal big M..
Contrary to what we usually see in classical mechanics, right?
So that that's sort of weird, right?
This implies that the initial mass m must be larger than the final mass M1 plus M2 because K1 was K2
is greater than zero.
Well.
How big is this difference, and can we measure this difference?
Because, you know, this is a big implication.
We should be able to observe that right?
This basically says what we see here and taking the tenants of special relativity that conservation
mass cannot hold cannot be valid, right?
We just proved it right here.
So some of the mass got converted into the kinetic energy here, and it expressed itself differently.
Strange idea.
Let's let's check along a bit more.
So if we click and want to see square enough to see squared and what what I'm over on the left side
here, what happens is.
The change in the math from the initial state to the final state or dealt a big M, which is M minus
the of mass and one percent to multiply that by C squared.
This gives us really K1 plus K2, which is the energy released as the bodies fly apart.
OK, so all we want to do.
We're going to work on next is we're going to run through a sample problem which takes this framework
we put together here using the intuition here and.
We throw in numbers, so what we want to find is if we put in all these different energy values, which
we just worked so diligently in figuring out how to measure with the electron volt.
How much mass was lost?
All right.
How much mass changed and.
Can we actually measure that difference if it's small, that might insinuate that conservation of mass
on a microscopic scale at a macroscopic scale is immeasurable.
And our notions of conservation of mass are still sort of valid in a certain sense, and we could still
utilize that and do practical things.
OK.
Stay tuned for that example.