All right.
And our last video, we invest a lot of time and energy and putting together this nice relationship
between momentum and energy, and in doing so, it gave us really two main advantages.
What exactly were they?
Number one, the first advantage we got is that we were able to determine this invariant quantity that
is true in any reference frame, regardless of how an event is perceived or the perspective that actually
viewed it.
OK.
In other words, it allowed us to bridge the gap between an infinite set of perceptions or perspectives.
In addition to this, I also noted that it gave us a lot of analytical leverage and ability such that
we can run through problems more efficiently.
However, I haven't really demonstrated that.
So what I want to do is I want to take everything we've been doing, including this relationship, all
the equations we've put together, all the ideas, all the concepts, and I want to sort of bring them
into the full picture right here into this this lesson by running through some example problems that
really highlights the anukul efficiency and ability we obtain from all these relationships, ideas,
concepts, so on and so forth in particular.
So you can get comfortable with doing calculations in special relativity, right?
What I like to like and what we've done is putting together all these different puzzle pieces to the
full puzzle, the full picture.
Now what we're going to do is we're going to take this puzzle pieces, drop them into place, see how
they interact with one another.
And in doing so, this is going to show the big picture is going to have everything come together,
and it's going to give you that nice aha moment in showing you how to run through different special
relativity problems.
OK?
So the first problem we're going to run through is it's pretty simple, pretty straightforward.
It's going to build off of what we did maybe a few videos ago.
If you recall, we looked at an electron that had some kind of velocity and we determine its mass,
which then allowed us to determine its energy.
And I showed you the different units we were able to to use with that, and I said that would be a better
unit using in our analysis.
Let's jump into the problem.
Let's see how that helps us run through this quickly, given the different tools, the different puzzle
pieces we've put together, OK?
So the primary to look at, as I mentioned, is the like John.
And the problem statement says that if an electron e is moving with a total energy e of 1.3 mega electron
volts, and that's the new unit we're using for energy recall, we talked about the electron volt previously.
What we want to do is determine its momentum, speed and kinetic energy.
Now is these three quantities we're trying to determine.
And I'm sort of guiding you through the problem because in order to determine the kinetic energy, what
you're going to find is we would need to run through all these things before it in order to get some
information that would allow us to determine that kinetic energy.
So is a quick picture of what we're seeing.
We have an electron, we some velocity b we don't know what that is, but we know the total energy.
Perhaps we measured that perhaps somebody gave it to us.
Who knows, but we have this, this quantity here.
So first thing we want to do if we have an electron and we know its total energy, we also know it's
rest energy because as you know, previously, well, we calculated it.
But when you run into these problems, what you want to do is you want to get that mass, the mass or
the rest energy of that particle so we can look up an electron.
We know the electrons.
That's energy is zero point five one one mega electron volts over C square.
That new unit we used and if we know the rest energy and we know the total energy, we want to figure
out the momentum.
Well, there's only one missing thing we have in the moment of energy relation we put together previously,
right?
We have this guy here.
So what you'll find is that in all these problems, if you have energy, you want to get momentum,
you want to get rest mass and then you can all throw those puzzles puzzle pieces into this nice equation
here and here to any missing entity.
OK, so we're missing the latter.
So what we could do is we can isolate this PC term, throwing these values we have previously and then
plug and chug and get a result.
Let's do that right now so we can take the main relationship right here.
We can say, OK, I'm a PC squared.
I'm going to sort of flip this guy, subtract and that's the square from the E Square over here, and
we have to take a square root to get rid of this guy.
And it's the relationship we get.
We have all these quantities we can plug them in.
We can solve a problem.
Now, when we plug these guys in, this is going to really highlight the elegance of expressing mass
and shortly momentum with this new different unit here.
But we haven't seen this come into play.
We haven't seen this in action really yet.
Very briefly.
OK.
So let's plug in Chuck Energy total.
1.3 million electron volts, plus that guy in here squared subtract, we need the rest energy.
So what we can do is we plug in the mass.
Point five, one one.
That's the rest, mass, of course, as mega electron volts over C squared and you multiply by C squared.
And what's really cool is you see what that guy pops off.
We don't have to do any insane calculations.
We don't have to do a lot of work.
It's right there.
We're sort of priming the fact that we want to use it for energy.
So we express in terms of energy units over C squared.
And when we take this, this expression here.
And we throw it into a calculator, a Wolfram Alpha Mathematica.
My personal fear MATLAB.
What are you going to end up with is we saw for PC.
It's an energy term and we get a one point two mega electron volts.
So I know what you're thinking about.
Whoa, wait.
A second, probably thinking we were all that's on.
What in the world is this PC PC?
What does that mean?
Well, what I'm going to say is just like rest mass.
How KG were not very useful?
Well, we're going to see what momentum, you know, kg meter per second are, you know, Marston's
velocity.
I don't want to have to convert to electron volts.
That's going to take a lot of work.
So what we could do is we could say, OK, let's formulate a new unit of measurement for momentum.
By literally looking at usually we're going to use this relationship, so we're going to prime the unit
to be compatible with this information.
So let's just divide by AC and the momentum we get.
And this is how momentum is expressed in special relativity is just one way to make electron volts per
seat.
OK.
This is a more conventional measurement, because if we're doing these calculations, the special relativity,
all we need to do is we take this guy, we multiply by C and we get the energy unit back.
And it's very convenient, right?
It boosts our analytical efficiency.
In essence, you can see that I play.
You can see that I play.
So we're making good progress.
We got one parameter down.
The next thing you want to do after, you know, momentum, we can take advantage of that next relationship.
We had to determine velocity, right?
Because as I said, we had a dimensionless.
Relationship dimensionless quantity.
Which expressed the relative velocity v over C or beta.
As being equal to pissy over eat.
So we have all these quantities, we can put them in and quickly figure out the speed or the velocity,
the magnitude of velocity.
So we plug in.
This guy right here we can I can show you the analytical awesomeness of this firsthand, right?
So momentum is one million electron volts over.
See you plug in for P.
We're going to see and we see again, just like with rest energy, the CS cancel and we get that energy
unit back.
And then we want to divide by the total energy which we know to be 1.3 million electron volts.
Again, evaluate this guy.
What do you get?
We get a pretty high relative.
Last we had a relative velocity.
And this is not surprising because we're dealing about subatomic particle.
We get a velocity of 0.9 two and we can either use that later on in our calculations.
Or we can say, Oh, we we just take the C over here and we can express the speed as 0.9 to see band
two thirds of the problem done.
Now men are the problem is trying to figure out the kinetic energy.
And I don't have it written up here because I'm limited on board space.
But where I want to recall is that kinetic energy, as we defined it was gamma minus one.
And the rest, energy and Moxie Square.
OK.
So in other words, you're taking the total energy, subtracting the rest of energy, and we get this
equation here.
So what we could do is we could take e, we could take the rest of energy here because subtract them.
And that will give us the result, because, you know, there are multiple ways to do that, so we could
do we could say energy is equal to you and not c squared plus kinetic energy.
And we know this guy, we know this guy that could solve it.
Why don't I try and use the equation we put together to give you some more practice with using these
guys?
So obviously we need to figure out how the magnitude of relativistic effects.
So using this B, we could calculate gamma, right?
That could give us information about, Oh, maybe you want to see if there's a time difference in the
reference frame moving with the electron?
I want to see if there's some kind of time dilation going on or length contraction.
We would need this guy so we could use all this stuff to figure out the velocity and then we have to
figure out gamma.
Well, we call gamma.
Gamma is nothing more than one over the square root of one, minus the relative velocity squared, beta
squared.
So we got this guy.
We can literally plug it straight in plug and shock, baby.
So we take one.
We divide by the square root of one minus beta squared.
We plug in that point nine to you.
We square it.
And we get up a gamma value of 2.5 five, which is, you know, that's somewhat significant.
So we're going to see relativistic effects cropping up coming into play here, and we would expect some
kind of time dilation length contraction to occur and we expect somebody moving in this reference frame
to have a different experience than somebody else who is perhaps stationary or moving at a different
speed.
OK, so we could use this for all those calculations.
We're going to figure out the kinetic energy.
So what we need to do to figure that out is take this guy, plug it in here.
And when we do that, we get a 2.5 five minus one.
And then we want to multiply by the rest energy.
And since you've seen previously how the Sea Square cancels with that guy right there, I'm going to
see what I would typically do.
I wouldn't write this out because that's a little inconvenient.
So what I say is, Oh, we got a c squared and I just can't in my head.
Easy peasy, right?
So it ends up becoming this guy.
Times zero point five one one.
Mega electron volts.
And when we do that, that calculation, we end up with again, we got an energy union right there because
the seas are canceled, that guy, we end up with a kinetic energy of zero point seven nine two mega
electron volts.
OK, so that's the energy we get that is composed due to its velocity.
We got that nice guy right there.
And as a check.
What we could do is we could say, well, if we take this and add the rest of energy, that should equal
the total energy.
So OK, that's about point one plus point five.
Oh, that's one point three million electron volts.
So yes, we're doing this correctly.
That strengthens our confidence and.
What's the first problem we ran through in relativistic mechanics besides, you know, we ran through
the energy problem, but you can see here how our modifications to units, our relationships and our
momentum really drive the analysis forward.
Right.
This is a useful tool used for useful puzzle piece, which gives us a huge glimpse into the full picture,
right?
So when you solve all these problems and we're going to run through another one a bit more complex shortly,
what you want to do is you want to say, OK, I have all these tools, I have all these puzzle pieces.
How can I rearrange them and put them together?
How can they interact with one another?
So should I put the full picture together of what's happening in this example problem?
OK, so if you get lost in any kind of problem, what you should do is you say, OK, maybe I have energy
no matter what, let's calculate the energy.
Let's calculate the momentum.
Let's calculate the velocity to each one and then question, OK, they gave me another puzzle piece
How can I fit that in with the other puzzle pieces?
I have to see the full picture.
OK.
So remember, we're always going to be using conservation of energy, so relationship conservation of
momentum, so on and so forth.
And that's the name of the game in special relativity and relativistic mechanics.
OK, let's jump into another example problem.