In this video I am going to talk about
perhaps the simplest kind of problem in
time-dependent quantum mechanics, that is,
the problem of the sudden perturbations,
which happens when a potential in
a quantum problem changes very fast as
compared to all other relevant
time scales in the problem.
So another term for such a sudden change
in the potential is a quantum quench.
And this may happen, for instance,
if we have a potential which changes very
rapidly from one form to a different form.
So let's say here, for example,
I'm showing a harmonic oscillator, and
let's say for a negative time we have
a particle, let's say, just sitting
here on a stationary state described
by the usual Gaussian wave function,
which is the eigenfunction
of the ground state,
the ground state wave function
of the harmonic oscillator.
And let's imagine at t = 0,
the frequency of the harmonic
oscillator potential changes rapidly.
So it increases rapidly such that
it becomes a completely different
potential now.
So what kind of questions can we ask?
Well, before asking questions,
let's see what's going on here.
So the main sort of
insight in this problem is
that while the potential
changes very rapidly,
the wave function does not
have the time to change.
So the wave-function right before
the quench is exactly equal to
the wave-function right after the quench,
in the approximation
of an infinitely fast or an infinitely
sudden quench of the potential.
Let's say, in this case,
from one harmonic oscillator frequency to
a different harmonic oscillator frequency.
But another important insight is that
the quantum state that used to be a good,
stable stationary ground state is no
longer an eignestate of our potential.
But what is it?
So this wave-function,
the old wave-function,
is just some wave-function from the point
of view of the new Hamiltonian.
So, for instance,
let me call this guy here, psi 0 (1),
which refers to the ground state of
the old potential that we had for
a negative, where t is smaller than zero.
And now after we quench it, so
this psi 0 (1) is no longer
an eigenstate of the new Hamiltonian.
Let's say we have the Hamiltonian,
H2, when it acts on psi 0 (1),
it's no longer equal to an energy
of anything times psi 0 (1), so
it's no longer proportional to psi 0 (1),
so this state is no longer an eigenstate.
What it is, though, as always, we can use
the eigenstates of the new Hamiltonian.
So we can use these
eigenstates as a basis.
So what we can do,
we can expand our wave function,
which was the eigenstate of the old
Hamiltonian, in terms of the coefficient's
here, let me call it C sub n, and
n in this case goes from 0 to infinity,
in this particular case of
the harmonic oscillator.
And this can be expanded in
terms of the wave functions
of the new harmonic
oscillator Hamiltonian.
But, in general,
these coefficients are all non-zero.
So basically what happens after we do
this quench is that the wave-function,
which used to be a nice,
pure state with a well defined energy,
well defined frequency,
now becomes, essentially,
a bunch of incoherent harmonics
with different frequencies.
If I were to suggest a possible
classical analog of what happens here,
imagine you have a guitar string and
you generated a pure frequency,
a pure sound, with the natural frequency
of the string, and then you suddenly
changed the length of the string, well,
just pinch it at a certain distance.
So then you're going to generate all kinds
of new sounds, all kinds of harmonics,
it's no longer going to be a pure sound.
A similar thing is happening here,
but instead of the sound,
instead of the strings, we are having
quantum states which become now
a linear combination of
the new eigenstates.
So an interesting illustration, perhaps,
of physically relevant phenomenon that
can be discussed in this context here.
So let's say, again,
let me go back to this original potential.
Let's say we have many particles
sitting in the ground state.
So this basically means that there is
a Bose-Einstein condensate of sorts which
are again are produced in particular in
many experimental laboratories worldwide.
So this is now done very frequently and
routinely.
So, and let me say,
I changed the frequency of
the trap as I just showed you.
What happens is that these particles,
which used to be in the ground state of
the old potential, now get redistributed
to, essentially,
all possible states of the new potential.
And after time goes by, so
there is some relaxation going on, and
the system relaxes to a new state, but
now the temperature of the state
is going to be larger.
The temperature is actually
essentially the measure
of the typical energy of
the particle in a many-body system.
So essentially what I"m saying here
is that any change in the potential,
in this case it's a harmonic oscillator,
but it's a completely general statement,
any sudden change of
the potential always heats it up.
So it doesn't matter whether
we increase the frequency or
decrease the frequency,
if we, let's say, had
the lowest energy state in the beginning
with the lowest possible temperature,
let's say even zero, absolute zero in
this model, if we do the quench, so
the particles are going to be
redistributed among all possible energies.
And, eventually, they're going to
relax to a final temperature,
which is always higher
than the original one.
So this is an interesting phenomenon
that we can understand without any
calculations, just by this discussion.
Now, another thing, let me just mention
in the end, so here in the context
of this expansion of the original
wave function in terms of the new
eigenfunctions of the harmonic oscillator,
or any other potential for this matter.
So these coefficients determine the
probability of us finding the particle,
in the single particle case, or
the density of particles, let's say,
in the many particle case,
in a specific new eigenstate.
So Cn squared is exactly
the probability of
finding our particle in the state,
psi sub n (2), which again refers
to the potential after the quench,
well, at, oops, at t greater than 0.
Okay, it's not always working,
this writing on a tablet.
Now, so now let me move,
actually, to a similar but
physically quite different problem,
which also involves sudden perturbation,
but it's a perturbation of
a completely different type.
So the toy problem that we're going
to solve was actually a serious
research problem back 70 years ago or
so in the good old days
of theoretical physics.
And it was, actually, considered by a
famous Russian theorist mostly working in
nuclear physics, Arkady Migdal, in 1939.
So this problem I'm going to
discuss actually appears also
in the Landau-Lifshitz course
on theoretical physics for
those of you who have
access to this material.
And well, the problem itself
is quite straightforward.
So to formulate the problem,
so let's say we have an atom.
So for the sake of simplicity,
I'll be talking about the hydrogen atom.
But in principle we can consider any atom,
including heavy atoms for
which it's the most interesting due to
various applications in nuclear physics.
And let's imagine that
a nucleus of this atom,
which has its atomic electron or
electrons in its ground
state receives a sharp impulse
which gives it a velocity v.
So we kick it with the radiation or with
a hammer, or we drop it from an airplane,
or whatever you want to think about.
So and what we want to know is,
what's going to happen with the electron?
So basically here the sharp sudden
perturbation is that initially,
we have this atom at rest.
And at certain moment of
time let's say t equals 0,
this atom starts moving
with a certain velocity v.
And as it does so, we want to see,
we want to follow it, and
we want to see if
the electron gets excited.
But how do we calculate the probability
for the election to get excited?
That is to say that it would
go to an excited state with
the higher quantum number or
the atom would even get ionized.
That is to say that the electron
just leaves the atom and
goes into the continuum, and
they just go two separate ways,
the atom of the nucleus and the electron.
So here, naively, it seems that
the potential doesn't really change,
we don't quench the potential.
But, if we look at this problem a little
closer, we see that, well the atom,
when it receives this impulse or
this kick, so the atom starts moving.
And the atom is the potential, which binds
the electron to it in the first place.
So therefore, the potential in which the
electron is supposed to be bound starts
moving, and so this is sharp change.
But the wave function of the electron
does not have time to change.
So if let's say the electron was here
in the vicinity of the lowest orbit, so
it was localized in the vicinity
of the lowest orbit,
it will just try to stay there.
And the question we're asking is, whether
the atom, when it starts moving with
a certain velocity, whether it
will carry the electron with it.
Or whether it will leave it behind or
maybe whether the electron will sort
of dissipate into higher energy states.
So and for this, to solve this problem,
what turns out to be useful is to
go into another frame of reference,
which is moving together with the atom.
So essentially, we want just to
move together with the atom and
write the wave function of the electron
in this new frame of reference.
So, this is really the key
to solving the problem.
Because in the frame of reference
moving together with the atom,
the potential is exactly the same.
The Coulomb potential to begin with
is the Coulomb potential here.
And in this frame of reference the atom,
the nucleus itself, is static, but
the electron now is moving.
And so essentially, what we have to do, we
have to write the electron wave function
after the quench, after well in this case,
it's not a quench.
I'm sorry, I shouldn't have said that.
After this sort of jolt of the atom, and
this wave function will have two pieces.
So, the first piece is
going to be just this standard
ground state wave function of the hydrogen
atom, in the case of a hydrogen atom.
And there will be a piece, a new piece,
which is related to the velocity of
the electron moving with velocity v.
So here, essentially it's a plane wave.
So, a way to write the wave
function in the frame of reference
moving with the nucleus is to write
it as a product of a localized
wave function in the lowest
orbit times the plane wave.
And here again,
this mv is simply the momentum of
the electron in this frame of reference.
And this is just the standard
plane wave expression.
So now the final step is to calculate the
excitation probability of the electron,
that is, to find the total
probability of the electron going to
some higher energy state,
including the continuum states.
And well, the good thing is that
we know the wave function now.
So in this moving frame of reference,
let me just write it again.
So psi0 of r = 1 over
the square root of pi a cubed.
So this is the Bohr's radius,
e to the power -r over the Bohr radius and
times this plane wave,
e to the -i over h bar mv dot r.
So this is our wave
function we just derived,
sort of, which is by logical reasoning.
And if we want to know, let's say,
what the probability of a transition into
a higher energy state is,
let's say some other state.
I'm not going to specify what it is but
some, let's say psi sub k, whatever k is.
k could be a collection of indices,
involving the radial quantum numbers and
the angular quantum numbers.
Or it can be a label of a continuum state,
whatever this quantum label is.
So the amplitude, the transition amplitude
is going to be,
let me write it A of 0 to k will
be equal to the overlap
integral of this psi0.
Let me write it star,
although it doesn't really matter,
psi sub k of r integrated over the volume.
And the probability to go from this ground
state to an excited state, w sub k,
is going to be equal to the absolute value
squared of this transition amplitude.
So, this is what it means.
So another way to connect it to what I
talked about previously is to notice that
this wave function can be expanded in the
basis of all eigenstates of our problem.
In this case, actually it's both
the discrete states, which describe atoms,
I'm sorry, electrons localized near
the atom, and also the continuum states.
Okay, and it seems that well,
the problem is very complicated, so
we have to sum over all
these probabilities.
Well fortunately we don't have to do so
really, so
this was just a necessary comment.
As a matter of fact, if we're
interested in calculating the total
excitation probability,
we may want to notice that the total
probability to find electron in
some quantum state is equal to 1.
So the electron will stay somewhere,
right, so it will be in some state.
So therefore, the probability to
remain in the ground state plus
the excitation probability,
which is essentially the sum in
this ungeneralized sense,
it involves an integral of this w sub k.
So this must be equal to 1, and
this excitation probability is
exactly what we're trying to find.
So from this equation, we simply can
write that this excitation probability
is equal to 1 minus the probability not
to get excited, the probability to remain
in the ground state now of the moving
atom, of the moving nucleus.
Well, I just realized actually,
that there is a slight problem
with the notations here.
Because what we're actually looking for
is the transition amplitudes and
the transition probability
from an electron,
that is a moving electron relative
to the stationary nucleus.
But we want to find transition's
amplitude into a stationary states
localized near this nucleus.
So therefore, these states for instance,
they do not have this plane wave piece,
so let me just Sort of introduce
a tilde here which would refer to
the fact that these guys
are moving together with the atom.
While this state, psi0 that we
derived in the previous slide,
is actually moving with velocity
v relative to the atom.
Now, with this correction to notations and
with this comment about the total
probability of staying in the new
ground state plus the probability of
the excitation being equal to one, we can
write down this excitation probability.
Let me just do that.
Psi-star is going to be equal
to 1 minus the probability
to stay in the ground state, which
means that I have to take this integral
of psi0 with a psi0-tilde.
This is the ground state of the stationary
atom integrated over the volume, and
square the absolute value of it.
And so here,
I know everything there is to know.
So for example,
this part here is exactly this psi0-tilde
in my new inconvenient perhaps notations.
So we can just plug in these functions and
integrate over volume and
I will leave this calculation to you,
so let me just maybe write an intermediate
step and the final result.
So the intermediate step would be simply,
would simply involve writing down
explicitly this integral, so
it's going to be 1- 1 over pi a,
Bohr radius cube.
So from the normalization
factor in the ground state
wave function times the exponential,
well, integral,
of the exponential -2r
over the Bohr radius,
minus this plane wave,
i over h-bar p dot r.
And so integrated over the volume,
and everything is squared.
So this is really the integral
that needs to be calculated.
Like I could take another
five minutes to go
over with you through
the calculation of the integral, but
I think it's probably not the best
use of your time and my time too.
So let me just leave it for those who
are interested to do it on your own.
And let me just write the final result.
So the final result will be this.
1-1, divided by this ratio here, 1 over 4,
m v-squared, m-squared,
v-squared, a-squared.
And so the Bohr radius
divided by h-bar-squared, and
everything to the fourth power.
So, I'm not necessarily saying that this
is the most important illuminating result
in physics, but it's result is something
we can actually measure and check.
So what happens if we kick an atom?
So what is the probability of it being
excited, and therefore it would emit
photons and there are all kinds of
different phenomena associated with it?
So and, well, one can round the various
sanity checks on this result, so
let's say if the velocity is 0,
so we don't really kick the atom,
so it was stationary and
remains stationary, we have 1- 1.
So the probability to excite
the atom is exactly 0,
as it should be,
because we don't really do anything.
On the other hand, if the velocity here,
well in our non-relativistic case,
goes to infinity.
So the 1 over infinity is 0, so
the probability to excite
the atom is exactly 1.
So we just leave the electron behind,
that's what's going to happen,
the nucleus will just go away,
that's what's going to happen.
In any case, so this is just
an example that I wanted to show you,
it's actually two examples of this part
of time-dependent quantum
mechanical problems.
And in both these cases,
we dealt with a very sharp,
very sudden perturbations
to our Hamiltonian, and
they resulted in a redistribution
essentially of energy.
So the energy of the original state was,
well,
the original state of the old
Hamiltonian became a linear combination,
a rather complicated linear combination
of eigenstates of the new Hamiltonian.
And this is very typical for
sharp perturbations or
non-adiabatic perturbations.
Now, in the next video, we're going to
study actually the opposite case of a very
slow perturbation or
adiabatic perturbation.
Which in some sense is more interesting
in that it involves new mathematical
structures, a new phenomena,
so-called topological Berry phase.
Which is currently actually the subject
of intense research in condensed
matter of physics.