All right I want to look at this example now.
Both of these examples here are combinations of combinations and what we want to find now is what is
the equivalent resistance between points and B for each case.
And we're going to assume that every resistor here in this network each one has a value equal to Ohmes.
So how would we solve this problem here.
Let's start with case number one.
Now the case number one here the key to this problem here and the mistake that students often make is
they first try to simplify it using resistors in series.
But really the goal here is to notify or to notice that I would group them together like this.
I would first simplify this one.
These three resistors and these three resistors are all in parallel with each other.
And then I would simplify both of these resistors these two resistors here are also in parallel with
each other.
And then once I have both of those simplified then I would simply add the two of them in series with
one another.
So let's go ahead and do that.
So for the first three over here what I'm going to do is I'm simply going to apply the equation for
equivalent resistors and I know that one over our equivalent is simply one over our again here it's
going to be a plus one over our plus one over our.
So in this case it's simply three over our.
And I know the resistance here is two for each one of those.
So it's simply three over two.
So at the end the equivalent resistance for those three combinations is two over three ohms.
I can use the same argument now to find what the second combination is what you're going to find now
is our equivalent of is simply going to be one.
And here I have to say I can use the trick I can multiply them divided by the sum you multiply two times
two you get four divided by the sum which is also 4.
You get one on.
All right.
So now look at what we have.
If you go ahead and redraw this picture this is what we now have we have a point here.
I have a wire.
I have it connecting an R equivalent equal to two thirds.
And now I have another wire that is connecting a equivalent resistance equal to 1 ohm.
So this becomes pretty straight for then I go all the way to point B.
So all I have to do now is to combine both of those.
You simply apply the same trick now.
Except now we simply have two resistors that are in series with one another and if resistors are in
series with one another all you have to do is simply add them up.
So we have two equivalent resistors that are now in series.
So the total are equivalent.
The blue combination over here is simply going to be two thirds plus one.
So that is simply two thirds plus three thirds is MI 5 third's.
So the total equivalent resistance if I want to represent this whole network by 1 It simply has to be
equal to 5 thirds and that's it.
All right how about the second combination here.
The second combination is slightly different.
It looks like I have two branches here.
Here's a branch number one
that is in parallel with branch number two.
Now the way you would simplify this one is I would first simplify each branch for example and branch
number one the top branch.
I have two resistors that are in series with each other.
So the equivalent resistance of everything here in the blue highlighted region.
Again there's two resistors here.
So our equivalent for this guy is simply two plus two is me four ohms.
Now for the orange case over here I have three of them that are in series with each other.
So the equivalent resistance for this branch simply equals the 6 ohms.
So now what you've done is you have a point here we have an equivalent resistance which is our blue.
And now that goes all the way to point B.
And I have that now that is in parallel with an equivalent resistance given by the orange case.
Now just simplify the circuit again.
This is what you have.
Let's fill in our values.
We have our equivalent here which equals to forums and the orange one I found that our equivalent was
equal to 6 ohms.
So now I simply have two resistors that are in parallel with each other.
The way I simplify that is that my are equivalent.
Let's just call it the total are equivalent since there's two of them I can simply multiply them and
divided by the sum you multiply them you get four times six divided by the sum six plus four gives me
10.
So you get 24 divided by 10 which gives me 2.4 ohms.
So the equivalent resistance of this entire network is equivalent to a 2.4 ohm resistor.
So this is how you got to be a little bit careful when you're dealing with combinations of combinations.
Hopefully this example highlights the different cases.