All right here's a very complicated looking sample here it says find the equivalent resistance.
We have a whole series of resistors in this network and now we're asked to find the equivalent resistance.
How do you deal with a problem like this.
And I wanted to include this problem here just to highlight one important thing that you're able to
do and show you a trick if it does look very complicated like this one does what you're allowed to do
and all of these cases since these wires are ideal wires and we always assume that the wires don't have
any resistance themselves.
You're allowed to reshape this into something that looks more familiar to you especially like these
diagonal resistors you know when you first start looking at these it might look like this is more complicated
than it should be but you can just reshape it to make it look more kind of Cartesian like and let me
illustrate what I mean by that.
So to reshape it actually I'm only going to consider these five resistors here at the end so let me
highlight that region and we're going to show you how you can redraw it.
So let's only consider our 6.
And let me just say this whole area here.
So this is the area I want to consider.
Let me show you how you can just redraw this and make it look like something you're more familiar with
it.
So.
OK.
So how would I do this.
Well what I would first start with is if I notice that are 8 and are 10.
Both of those resistors up here those are in series with one another are 8 and 10 have to be in series
because if your current flowing through are 8 you automatically have to flow through the resistance
are 10 OK.
So I would maybe start by doing that and I'm going to make this the last branch over here.
So here's going to be the resistance are 8
and now that has to be in series with the resistance.
R10
OK.
So I've included both of those.
The next thing I have is the resistance R nine and R nine.
Actually what I'm going to do now is if I label this point here point A.
Now let's just continue this line.
So let me call this here point A.
And I know I'm going to label this point over here which is after our 10 I'm going to label this point
here point B.
I'm going to redraw like this.
So this is going to be point A and Point B.
The only thing I require now is that the resistance R 9 goes from point A to Point B.
So the going from point A to Point B would be this one right here.
So all you have to do here is just draw a line and there's only one resistance
so let me label these.
This is our 9.
This would be our 8.
This would be resistance 10 and we have all the values there.
Now let me label this point over here a point see.
OK so between Point B and point C I have to include a resistance R 7.
So let me go ahead and do that.
I can even curve this up here.
Doesn't matter.
OK.
And let me place Point C over here.
The only thing I need to do is now to include the resistance R7 between those two points.
All right.
Let's do that.
This will be resistance are seven OK.
And now the only thing I need to do is connect point A to point C and between point A and Point C I
need to include this resistance are 6.
Now rather than making another diagonal line here what I'm going to do is I'm going to go straight across.
Again I can make the wires as long as I want.
And now I can go straight down and include the resistance R6
OK.
And this is the resistance R6 now.
So everything in this orange shaded area I've represented down here by the diagram and now I can go
ahead and quickly simplify this.
So the first thing I would start off is all the way on the right hand side here I have two resistors.
That are in series with one another.
If both of those are in series with one another to get the equivalent resistance of everything in this
blue shaded area you simply have to add them up.
So this should be equivalent to a 12 Omers ister.
And then what do I have.
Well and then you have a 12 ohm resistor that is in parallel with R 9 R 9 is a 6 Omers is there.
So what I can now do is I can combine this branch with this branch.
Now if I do that I you go ahead and do this are equivalent for both of those together.
Let's call that our equivalent one.
I'm going to have a lot of different equivalent resistances here.
So I have two of them if I have two of them I can use my trick.
Multiply them and divided by the sum you get 12 multiplied by six and divided by 18 18 is six times
three actually.
And the reason I want to do that it's just easier to do the math.
What you should end up with is for alms.
So this whole you know these three resistors here at the end of my network they're equivalent to a forum
resistor
so that simplifies things a little bit.
So now when I'm going to do is I'm going to keep that in mind and I'm actually going to just simplify
this picture.
So let's get rid of that.
Let's actually get rid of all of this and watch what I'm going to do.
I'll get rid of that line get rid of that line instead of calling it our 9 what I'm now going to do
is I'm going to simply call it our equivalent one our equivalent one.
And I know that this here is equivalent to a forum resistor and get rid of both of those lines.
OK.
Now I'm kind of really simplifying the network quite a bit.
Now the next thing I notice is I have two resistors that are in series with one another because whatever
current flows here through this eq. resistants is going to flow through the are seven.
So both of those are in series with one another.
If they're in series with one another that means you can simply add up their resistances to get the
equivalent resistance.
So I don't know what I'm going to call our equivalent to is the series combination of our equivalent
one which is four plus are seven and the value of our seven was eight.
So this here is 12 ohms OK.
So now you can actually combine both of those into one.
And then that's 12 ohm equivalent resistance is then going to be in parallel with the resistance are
six look which are six is equal to it's equal to six ohms.
So what we have is a 12 ohm resistor that is in parallel with a six ohm resistor or we already did that
case.
This is exactly what we did over here.
So that means that this entire network this entire network here has to be equivalent to a four Omers
this the so I can replace everything here in this orange blob by an equivalent four ohm resistor.
So make sure you understand the steps that I took in order to achieve this value.
So now all we're going to do is well let's just simplify we've actually simplify this entire network.
So let's kind of eliminate some of this stuff here
and let's simplify the network even further and make some more room.
OK.
So this is what we have now.
So between points A and C you know this is what I'm going to have.
I have an equivalent resistance equal to forums so I'm going to draw that.
This was our equivalent.
And this here was equal to forums and that took care of everything.
Are Six are seven are eight are nine and are 10.
And this was points a in point see.
Now I have to draw the rest of the network.
OK well let's label some other points maybe call this point D.
Let's call this point E.
If I go between point C and point D I have to include a forum resistor at this point down over here
I'm sorry this sphere should be labeled point see my mistake.
OK so be go in between points see him point D.
I should have the equivalent the resistance are five
point D.
And this is the resistance are five.
Now again in order to eliminate this diagonal resistance Well that's fine.
I could just include a straight line.
I could make the wire a little bit longer.
And now between point A and Point D.
It's this one going straight down.
I have to include this resistance are four
I just don't like those diagonal resistors are for going down.
OK.
And now going from point A to Point B I'm going to include the resistance are three
call this point.
And this is the resistance are three.
All right and the last one is between point E and point D.
I include the resistance are two in rather than going on a diagonal here I'm just going to make this
wire longer and then I include this resistance are two
OK.
And now I'll just finish the diagram here.
This should go all the way to point B.
And this one will go to Point A.
But I still have to include the resistance are one up here.
Let me go ahead and do that.
OK.
And r1 is labeled here and that's the 6 ohm resistance.
All right so now we need to simplify this a little bit more again.
I'm going to start on the right hand side of this diagram.
First thing I'm going to do is I notice that between well everything all the current flowing in here.
Is going to be the same.
So that's the current that's going to flow through an equivalent resistance.
It's the current that's going to flow through the resistance are five.
So right away I can combine both of those because they are in series with one another so are equivalent
in blue.
I don't know which number we're at but let's just call it number three for now.
This here is simply going to be the forum resistor which is in series with the resistance are five
and are five.
I look back on this top diagram that was also four.
So that means this guy here has to be 8 ohms OK.
So far so good.
So now I have this outer branches basically one big 8 ohm resistor which is now going to be in parallel
with the resistance are four.
All right.
We have an 8 ohm resistor which is in parallel with the resistance are four and R for have a look.
It's also 8 ohms.
So you have eight ohms and also 8 ohms.
So what does that mean.
Well that's an easy calculation to do.
Let's call this
our equivalent oops let's call this our equivalent for
our equivalent for.
So we have eight ohms which was our our equivalent three and eight ohms from the resistance are four.
You multiply them divided by the sum eight times eight is 64 divided by 16 is me for.
All right.
So the equivalent resistance of these three resistors in my network here are equivalent to a forum resistor.
So we can actually just simplify this diagram let's simplify the diagram and just replace everything
with a forum resistor
that have columnist's are for now and replacing it with an equivalent resistance.
This is our equivalent for and it's equivalent to a forum resistor is what we found now we repeat the
same steps as we did.
Hopefully you start getting the hang of it now.
So again now if you look at this branch over here both of these resistors are three and are equivalent
four are in series with one another.
If they are in series with each other
that means the equivalent resistance let's call it our equivalent five in this case you simply add them
up.
So we have our three which is given by four and we have our equivalent for which was also four.
So you get four plus four which equals to eight ohms.
All right so now what do we have we have 8 ohms out here on this outer branch and the middle branch
here are two our two is also equal to eight.
We just did a case like that right.
So we have 8 ohms right here.
That is in in parallel with another 8 ohm.
In that case we just did right.
We just did that case right over here.
We have 8 ohms in parallel with another 8 ohms.
That's equivalent to a forum resistor.
So that means that I can actually simplify this entire is these three resistors here on the right hand
side by an equivalent four ohm resistor.
So let me go ahead and clean this diagram up.
Replace all of this.
Let's relabel this
all right.
And the last part
this is basically another equivalent resistance and this we said was going to be a four ohm resistor
because I had an 8 ohm previously that was in parallel with another 8 ohm.
That gives me a forum resistor.
All right.
On our final
breakdown is simply looking at this branch are one which is going to simply be in series with this other
our equivalent resistor.
So what do we get at the end.
The total are equivalent between points and point B.
Now you simply use the series combination that gives me six plus four.
That was a lot of work in order to get 10 ohms but this is 10 ohms is the equivalent resistance of this
entire network.
So hopefully you understand the steps only if you're given two points like this I would always suggest
kind of starting at the opposite end and kind of working your way back.
The way I did I think this is kind of a straight forward method.
Sometimes it's a little tedious like in this case but it's still pretty straightforward I think.
All right.
So maybe you have to redo this one again try it out on your own.
Remember you can always change the shape of the circuit in order to simplify things.