All right one last thing I wanted to comment on for combinations of series and parallel let's just recall
that for combinations and series to get the equivalent You simply have to add up each individual resistor.
And if they're in parallel it's 1 over are equivalent and then you add up the reciprocal of the terms.
OK and this works fine as long as they're in series and in parallel.
Now all those circuits that I've shown you so far all the different networks we were able to kind of
reduce them into combinations of series or parallel resistors.
However one thing I want you guys to be very very careful of is there are many circuits where these
tricks don't work because you can't clearly identify whether or not they're in series or in parallel.
And I'm going to illustrate it with this simple case over here.
Kind of a simple network there's only five resistors.
However if you look at them imagine we look at this forum resistor so points A and B are over here and
imagine the question was well find the equivalent resistance between points AB.
So we'd want to try to use some of our rules that we know work.
However Majel we try to group this forum resistor and while you would say well this forum resistor is
actually not in series with this forum resistor because there's another resistor here that kind of breaks
it up.
Remember the rule for them to be in series was you have to have the same current but I imagine there
is current flowing down here well some of it might go through here.
Some of it might continue down here.
We don't know.
All right so you can't say that both of these foreign resistors are in series.
Now you might be tempted to say well this forum resisted and might be in parallel with this guy.
This 3.1 to 5 ohm resistor and again that's not really true because we run into a problem when you have
this resistor in the mix.
If this resistor wasn't there then you'd be able to do a lot of simpler simpler simplifications to the
circuit.
But it is here and this complicates the matter.
There are also a lot of circuits that you're going to see that involve multiple power supplies.
And in those cases also you won't be able to use these tools over here on the right on the left hand
side in order to simplify our circuit.
So don't worry about it there are going to be other methods that we can use in order to solve these
circuits and that's all we're going to see in the next section.
But these techniques don't always work.
So just be on the lookout for them for some of those circuits.
OK.