Here's some of the key information for this problem here.
So we have a charged particle in this case it's going to be a proton if it's a proton.
We know the charge here is given by one point six times tend to the negative 19 columns and it's a proton.
Just look up this number we also know the mass of that charge which is one point six seven times tend
to the negative 27 kilograms.
Now I've got parallel plates that I've previously charged by connecting it to a battery and the separation
between the plates is one centimeter and I have a certain amount of charge here positive charge on one
plate negative charge on the other plate such that the electric field produced by these charges over
here is ten thousand Nunes per Coolum.
All right.
The first thing to consider is what happens when this charge particles moving upward over here and it's
going to enter the field region over here at some point the charge particle will enter this region over
here.
Now what happens when this charged particle is in the field region.
The first thing you have to do is let's do a free body diagram.
OK just see what are all the forces acting on this charge when it's in this electric field.
OK so the free body diagram for this proton here is pretty straightforward.
Let's just draw the proton over here.
If you look at it first of all this is a positive charge right.
It's a small positive charge little Q and when it's in that field first thing you have to realize is
there's going to be an electric force acting on this charge.
Electric force is a vector and that vector is going to point downward because it is being repelled by
the positive charge over here and it's being attracted by the negatively charged plate.
So the magnitude of this electric force is given by QE.
All right.
And that's really important.
And the force is in the same direction as the electric field in this case because this guy here is a
positive charge.
Right.
So we have two vectors that are in the same direction.
The next thing you do now is you apply new second lot of this problem a new second law says you add
up all the forces acting on that charge.
In this case all the forces are in that vertical direction here and there's only one force.
So when that atom all up it's simply the electric force and you add them all up that has to be equal
to the mass times the acceleration.
And that means that while hey the acceleration is going to be in the same direction as the electric
force.
So the electric saw the acceleration in this case we can get the magnitude of it.
You simply have to divide through by the mass and let's substitute our value for the electric force.
So at the end of the day what we end up getting is this fairly important equation over here is that
the acceleration which is Q times the magnitude of the electric field and I end up dividing through
by the mass over here to isolate the acceleration.
And this is what I'm left with.
Now we can actually get a number for acceleration here in the key point about this guy here is going
to be in the same direction as the electric field because the charge is positive and mass is always
positive.
So really the direction of the acceleration here this is in the down direction.
All right.
The other important thing to consider about this problem is this guy over here right.
The electric field for this problem is constant.
Right.
This is a constant which means it's uniform.
And if we're between these parallel plates the electric field is pretty much uniform.
So that means that this acceleration here is also constant.
It is also constant.
And the reason that this is a really really important for this problem is that if the acceleration is
constant we can now do simple Kitimat.
So let's go ahead and set up some kid thematics for this problem to analyze the motion of the charged
particle between the two parallel plates.
We're gonna have two important kinetic equations here again our acceleration is constant.
Here's the magnitude the direction we know is down.
So the kinetic equations are going to be a number one and number two here.
Number one let's just look at the vertical displacement of this charge particle.
That's the Y position y position is going to be equal to y 0.
Plus the initial velocity multiplied by time.
And I'm just gonna stick a negative front in this in the front of the acceleration turn because it's
slowing down and the acceleration is down.
It's in the down direction and I'm defining that down direction to be the negative direction.
All right.
This is my coordinate system here for this particular problem.
Everything pointing up is positive everything pointing down is negative.
So I've just taken that out of the equation.
The other thing we need to know for this problem is what is the velocity of the charge particle.
Right when it enters this field region its velocity was initially going up but since the acceleration
is down that means that the charge will slow down.
OK.
It's going to slow down and the expression for the velocity is simply going to be like this.
The initial velocity and again I'll just take the negative sign out multiplied by acceleration times
time and now you could see that having this negative sign here is really going to make the velocity
kind of slow down as time increases.
All right.
So we have our two equations and now what we want here is we want our maximum displacement in the y
velocity we actually want the charge particle to actually come and just touch the plate and then come
back down like this.
So what we want here really is that our y displacement for this problem is what we want.
We want delta y which is my final minus the initial we want this to be the spacing between the plates.
That's really important.
And the other important thing to do is if we want the charge particle to reach this point there is also
something else that's going to happen here.
So what happens is is going really fast it starts the slow down slow down slow down.
Up until it reaches this point at this maximum y displacement we want the vertical velocity here to
be equal to zero.
Right right at the turnaround point.
And then after it's going to start speeding up it's speeding up in the down direction.
So right at this point here this is really important expression here is that our vertical velocity has
to be equal to zero.
So now if we go back here and consider our equation to Well if you substitute now v y is equal to zero
what you can do is you can find how much time it takes for this charge particle to slow down and to
reach this point over here.
So let's go ahead and do that we can calculate that.
And what you're going to find here.
So go and substitute it into equation 2 We want zero equal to my initial velocity and minus the acceleration
times time and now what I do is simply substitute the expression for the acceleration that expression
for acceleration was the magnitude of the charge magnitude of the field divided by the mass and multiplied
by the time.
So at the end the time for the velocity to reach zero.
You simply have to do a little bit of algebra.
Now bring this on the other side and divide through by this term here in the bracket.
I'm going to rearrange things a little bit and my expression is going to look like this so this is how
much time it takes for the velocity to be equal to zero.
All right.
The next thing we want to do now is well we know what our vertical displacement is.
All we have to do now is go back to equation 1.
Now we have the time now that we could substitute in here.
And my goal now will be simply to solve what is that initial velocity so that it makes it all the way
to the other plate.
So let's go ahead on the other page and do this math all right.
The next thing we want and now is we wanted our vertical displacement rewrite equation one over here.
This tells me my y position equals the initial position plus initial velocity times.
Time and again minus one half 80 squared.
And really what we want in this case we want our delta y to be equal to the spacing between the plates.
So let's go ahead and do that.
If we do that is bring this guy on the other side and that becomes delta y.
All right delta y is always a Y minus some initial value.
So let's simplify equation 1 so we get that the distance between the plates and this is really what
we want time minus one half a T squared now the next thing we have remember is how much time it takes
for when the velocity equals to zero.
Right.
And we just want that charge particle to reach the other plate.
So all you have to do now is simply substitute the time for our expression up above.
Okay.
And you could also substitute acceleration for now.
Let me just kind of do it this way.
Let's go over here so we have the distance between the plates.
I'll just keep the v y over here and for my expression for time now rather than doing the second expression
let's just start off with just this one v zero divided by the acceleration that'll make the math a little
bit easier.
We won't have so many variables to tackle over here.
Let's keep acceleration like this.
And now we have this T squared and T again is initial velocity divided by acceleration and we square
that term.
Now you do a little bit of algebra what you end up getting is you get v 0 squared divided by a and then
minus one half.
And if you look at this other term here this becomes a and this becomes v zero squared and this becomes
a squared.
I have a look at this term you have an a here and you have two of them over here so you can get rid
of one and these two terms are exactly the same except the second one has a coefficient of 1 1/2 in
the front of it.
So at the end this is our expression for our displacement is 1 1/2 v 0 squared divided by acceleration.
All right.
And remember our problem right the acceleration for this problem we know what it was the acceleration
was pretty straightforward It was the charge multiplied by the electric field and divided by the mass
and rather than putting the mass kind of down below.
If I'm dividing I could just bring it to the top over here and this is my final expression over here
for the distance between the plates which I know.
So the only unknown now in this problem is what is v zero.
So we have to do a little bit of math over here just isolate the V zero you bring a couple terms over
to the other side.
Divide by the mass and then take the square root of everything and this is what we end up getting.
So v zero end up the square root of a whole bunch of different terms here.
So we get to Q The distance between the plates multiplied by the electric field and all of this gets
divided by by the mass all right here.
Here we have it folks.
So this would be the velocity such that if you give that charged particle that proton this velocity
over here you're gonna end up that the charge particle is just going to make it to the other side.
Okay so all you have to do now is simply substitute in the numbers.
Let's go ahead and do that.
You substitute the numbers over here we get kind of a big expression.
We'll get to one point six times ten to the negative 19 the distance between the plates was 1 centimeter.
So this is zero point zero one meter.
What else.
The electric field was 10000 10000 Newtons per cool.
That's already an S.I. units we don't have to convert anything in the last part.
Here was the mass the mass is one point six seven times ten to the negative twenty seven kilograms.
Put that all put all of that in the calculator.
You should get something like this one point three eight times tend to the five.
And again that will be in meters per second.
All right.
I have everything here in S.I. units.
So if that charge particle has this particular velocity here which is just a number here at the end
of the day it's actually going to just make it to the other plate and then turn around and then come
back.
Let's go ahead and see how we can set this problem up.
Now using conservation of energy right to solve this problem using conservation of energy let's consider
that this bottom plate position is going to be my initial position and this top plate here is my final
position.
And what we have here is that the total energy at this point has to be equal to the total energy at
my final position.
So initially what we have is a lot of kinetic energy and we're going to be moving in a region where
there's an electric field.
Guess what we're also going to have some electrical potential energy.
When I first enter this field region and as I move now toward the other plate and once my I reached
the other side and if I just kind of turn around over here that means that my velocity or my speed is
zero once I'm at the other plate.
So my final kinetic energy over here at the top.
K. final Allen's easy that has to be equal to zero.
And that energy had to go somewhere.
So actually it's going to be converted into electrical potential energy which I'm going to call you
final.
So the initial kinetic energy is really straightforward.
I simply have a charge particle a proton it's moving so that guy always the same thing one half mass
of that charge multiplied by that initial velocity.
And let's just rewrite all of these other terms and you final.
So there's no final kinetic energy for this problem.
So all we really have to do is evaluate what is this potential energy over here.
All right.
Potential energy if you remember now from your class you probably saw that the potential energy of a
charged particle in this case the charges Q or remember this little guy over here had a charge q and
I'm placing it now in a region where there's an electric field the amount of energy that a charge has
when it's in a region of electric field can be written as this it's the charge multiplied by the value
of the electrical potential.
Right.
So this guy here is electrical potential
This is the value of the charge and this is how much energy you have at least potential energy.
So our goal now is what we need to calculate.
What is this value.
What is the value of V.
When I am close to this plate.
So what is the value of V initial over here and what is the value of V final.
If I know that I can calculate both of these potential energy terms and then simply solve for that initial
velocity.
So carefully I am using an uppercase V to note the electrical potential versus the initial velocity
here which is lowercase v zero.
All right.
So how do we relate that.
And this is pretty simple for parallel plates.
OK.
So you're to write this down the expression that I'm writing down here is only valid for parallel plates.
So don't try to use it for point charges.
Don't try to use it for cylinders and for this case it's pretty simple it simply says that.
Again remember how would we actually obtain the system we would plug it into a battery.
Right.
You'd plug it into a battery and the voltage difference between the battery I can write as V file minus
V initial.
This is the potential difference of that of the terminals of this battery that there simply equals two
and I'm just writing it as the magnitude here as I call this Ed's formula because it's simply e the
magnitude of the electric field multiplied by the distance between the plates.
So in this case here if I have ten thousand a nuance per column and the distance between the plates
I had previously said that the distance between the plates we call it D.
And that was one centimeter so if I go ahead here and multiply this by convert it to meters which you
end up getting here is one hundred volts.
That's the difference of potential.
So that might mean here that the difference has to be one hundred so he might have this one here at
plus fifty volts and you might have this one here at negative fifty volts right so that would mean that
the difference v final minus V initial over here 50 minus minus fifty would give me one hundred volts.
So now let's go ahead and do that just substitute our values over here.
Let's go back to the expression for conservation of energy and all we really want to do now is substitute
our expressions for the electrical potential energy.
So we have our kinetic energy one half and the initial squared.
Now the initial potential energy as I enter the field region is the charge q multiplied by the value
of that potential.
And that there has to be equal to the final potential energy so it's the charge q minus V.
Final.
Now you have to do a little bit of algebra too because our goal was the final.
How fast do I have to put this charge in the field region.
So let's go ahead and do that.
So I'm going to bring this term on the other side so this becomes Q This is v final minus V initial
right.
This is the difference of potential between both of those plates which we just said was 100 volts and
all of this here has to be equal to my initial kinetic energy.
And now again you do a little bit of algebra because my goal was to find v zero.
So there's gonna be a square root term over here.
S we're gonna have the square root.
I bring the two over next door I get to Q The difference of potential which is call that delta v and
again divided by the mass m.
Now this expression might look a little bit different from the previous one because the previous one
remember I had it in terms of the electric field and the distance D.
However that's what this guy is right here.
So if you go back and you substitute that you're gonna get the exact same expression as we previously
had in that when I know the value you substitute all these values here you're going to get one point
three eight times 10 to the five.
And again that is going to be in meters per second I'm working in s units over here and that's it.
That's how you would do this problem now using conservation of energy.
I think the key is really just finding what this difference of voltages between the plates and you can
do that.
Using this Ed's formula what I call and again the key to remember here is that this formula here is
only valid for parallel plates if you have different systems of charge for example charged cylinders
the expression is going to look a little bit different than the simple expression.
The reason it looks so simple for parallel plates is because the electric field is uniform here.
So that means that the voltage varies linearly with distance between the plates.