In the first lecture, we guessed,
and, in some sense, at the form of
the Schroedinger equation, relying on
a few very basic experimental facts
such as wave particle duality and the
dispersion relation of a free electron.
But we didn't talk too much about the
meaning of the main object that appears in
the this equation, the wave function,
which was introduced in an fashion.
So, today, I'm going to talk about the
actual physical interpretation of quantum
theory formulated this week.
And we are also going to introduce a few
very important standard notations and
conventions.
That they're going to be used
throughout the course and so
they are routinely used in the standard
literature on the subject.
So, here is the Schroedinger equation.
Once again, we're going to see
it very often in this course.
And I'm also showing here
the a part of the first page of
the Original Paper by Schroedinger
published December of 1926.
And it's actually very interesting how
Schroedinger came up with this work
on this equation.
So apparently,
the story started back in 1925 or so
when he was working under Dubai, and
Dubai had just read a paper by de Broglie,
where de Broglie was introducing
his wave particle duality idea.
So, he got interested in these ideas and
suggested Schrodinger to give
a seminar on the de Broglie work.
So, currently Schrodinger dismissed
this at first saying that
he didn't even want to think
about such a silly theory, but
he had to give in because well de
Broglie was effectively his supervisor.
And so,
he was looking into de Broglie's work
trying to present it in a more
mathematically sophisticated form.
And in doing so,
he came up with the Schrödinger
equation essentially as we know it.
Which brought him the world
wide recognition and
Nobel Prize in physics in 1953.
So, another important thing that
Schrödinger did was that he used his
equation to solve a very important
problem of a charged particle and
a Coulomb potential which, essentially,
describes a quantum hydrogen atom.
And he found the energy
level structure which was
consistent with the Bohr's atom and so
actually Charles Clark is going to talk
about the solution later in the course,
but I'm going to just mention here that
this was indeed very important and
it was a clear smoking gun that
Schrodinger was on the right track.
But according to the at
least quite interestingly
Schrodinger really didn't understand
the true meaning of his own work.
He actually dismissed
the importance of it at first.
So, I don't know if it was just
de Broglie's being jealous or
it was true but certainly if you actually
read the original paper by Schrodinger.
You don't see too much insight into
the true physical interpretation of his
own equation.
And the correct interpretation
of Schrodinger's equation
was developed very shortly after
Schrodinger's work by Max Born.
Perhaps actually I should say,
not the correct interpretation but
the commonly accepted interpretation,
because scientists
actually have been arguing about
the interpretation up to these days.
And some are still not convinced
that the Born interpretation and
the Born rule that I'm going to present is
the only correct view of quantum physics.
But certainly this Born rule is
the cornerstone of a standard
quantum theory and it isn't yet
consistent with the all
experimental data as we
know it at this stage.
Now before formulating this rule,
I would like to make a few jail comments
about quantum physics and made them
in contrast to classical physics.
So in classical physics, if we have
a classical system, let's say this is
a closed classical system with some
classical particles moving around.
And if we know everything about
this system, let's say we know all
the coordinates of all the particles
at a certain moment of time and
all the velocities at
a certain moment of time.
Then classical theory predicts
with absolute certainty
the result of any conceivable experiment
that is going to happen in the future.
Which is determined by,
let's say trajectory of particles
at any subsequent moment of time.
And they in turn determine all possible
outcomes of all possible experience.
Now, this is the classical system.
So, the truth about the quantum system, so
if you look at the actual
situation with quantum systems.
So, if you have a quantum
system like that, so
with some wave function to the side.
So, even if we know everything
possible about this quantum system,
that is, if we know sine, if we know all
the forces everything about the system.
We still cannot possibly predict
with certainty the outcomes of
well posed experiments.
Let's say, if we have some detectors here,
and the measure,
well let's say detect electrons or
some other particles.
So, even if we know everything
about the quantum electrons,
we still cannot predict for
sure which detector is going to pick up
an electron at a certain moment of time.
And so this uncertainty is
intrinsic to quantum physics and
there is no way around it.
And so Born realized it and so
he also found a way to quantify this
uncertainty using the wave function.
And his, well we know now is
the Born rule is written here,
so basically he proposed and
afterwards it was confirmed.
Again by comparing with experimental data,
that the absolute value of the wave
function, related in certain position
in space, and a certain moment of time,
gives a probability density of finding
a quantum particle described by
this wave function at this position and
at this moment of time, see.
Well, the probability itself is going to
be psi, absolute value of psi squared
times the volume, the elementary volume
in the vicinity of a certain point.
This work of Max Born turned out to be
extremely influential and ground breaking
and he eventually received a Nobel Prize
for his ideas, in part In 1954.
As a matter of fact, he should have
received this award much earlier.
He was nominated by Albert Einstein
actually, back in the 30s.
But, he didn't get it due
to some political reasons.
But in any case his probabilistic
interpretation was and
actually remains a very remarkable
feature of quantum physics
which also is a source of
confusion often times.
And I'm actually supposed
to tell you now about this
probabilistic property being
a mystery of quantum physics.
And something which we will
never be able to understand.
But I would actually argue otherwise,
that there is nothing mysterious about it.
If by mysterious, we mean something
that is not consistent with our
everyday intuition, everyday experience,
especially uncertainty is a part
of our everyday lives, whether we
are dealing with a sporting event or any
other event in our lives we cannot predict
with certainty even if we know
everything how it's going to turn out.
And so I don't see a reason to demand
from psi a deterministic answer.
And nature just doesn't work in this way.
And so we should just accept this fact and
get used to it.