In the previous video, we went over
a rather technical mathematical derivation
of the continuity equation.
And this derivation involved
in a rather essential way
manipulations with the various operators.
The appearance of operators is actually
not specific to the particular problem of
continuity equation.
But they appear actually throughout
quantum mechanics and play a very
important role, generally, in the
mathematical formulas of quantum physics.
In this short video, I would like to make
a few general comments about operators,
and relate them to quantum
observable quantities.
So in order for
me to trace the origin of the operator
objects in quantum theory,
let us go back a little bit and
remind ourselves the way
the Schrödinger equation was derived.
So, I use derived here in quotes because
there's no really rigorous way to derive
the Schrödinger equation as a fundamental
equation of quantum theory.
But we sort of followed the logic
that the early practitioners such as
Schrodinger used.
And the first piece of information
which was essential was
the experimental fact that
quantum electrons and
other quantum particles may
exhibit wave-like properties.
And in order to explain this, we sort
of introduced in that whole question
a plane-wave function which would
explain the data essentially.
And in this wave function we also
introduced the momentum and the energy of
the electron, which according to another
piece of information that is known from
the theory, it must be related to one
another using this dispersion relation.
So basically kinetic energy of a free
particle, mv squared over 2 or
p squared over 2m.
Now the equation itself was
constructed in order to
ensure that the plane-wave function
would come out as its solution and
this dispersion relation
would be respected.
And so this is what equation
actually looked like,
and it involved the second
derivative with respect to
the coordinate in the first
derivative with respect to time.
Now the next step, and this is really
the first time we sort of thought of
introducing an operator, was to write
the equation in a different way.
So we had the sort of universal
left-hand side which is just i, h bar,
the derivative with respect to time.
And the right-hand side was an sort
of energy operator, the Hamiltonian.
Where we associated with the momentum
that would have appeared
in the classical theory, this guy,
which is -i h bar gradient,
which indeed is an operator that converts,
well, that acts on the wave function.
And the last step in deriving,
again, in quotes,
the Schrodinger equation was to
generalize this energy operator,
well called Hamiltonian,
from being the free energy operator,
which is just p squared over 2m to
kinetic energy plus potential energy.
And this is the fundamental
Schrodinger equation,
which remarkably describes all of
nonrelativistic quantum physics including,
and this describes atomic spectra,
and well,
even many particle systems, theory of
metals, theory of super conductivity.
Everything is contained in a compact
way in this remarkable equation.
And it's sort of also remarkable
that you can get to it from
very few simple experimental facts,
by adding small pieces together and
getting to this fundamental result.
Now but in doing so, we were forced,
indeed, to introduce well
at least three operators.
So the first one,
we have seen already many times.
It is the momentum operator,
-i h bar gradient.
And by the way I should mention
that the minus sign is really sort
of a convention which is
sort of must be consistent,
with the convention we choose to
describe a plane-wave in a sense.
It could have been plus, but
this is the convention that we use.
So apart from that we also introduce the
potential energy which enters this h hat.
And in this setup,
the potential energy naturally appears
as just multiplication operator.
So we can think about a coordinate
operator, multiplication operator,
that well there should be
actually a vector here,
multiplication operator,
that simply multiplies the wave function.
And finally, the kinetic energy itself,
sort of the first step, appeared here,
and it was the second derivative
with respect to spatial coordinates.
Now, it turns out that the appearance
of operators was not unique just to
this sort of derivation of
the Schrodinger equation.
But sort of they pop up throughout
quantum theory whenever we deal with any
analogs of classical properties.
For example, when dealing with the angular
momentum that in classical theory
is r cross p, so
all we have to do to make it
into an operator is to put a hat actually
on top of the corresponding quantity.
So p here would be replaced with -i
h bar gradient according to this.
And r will just be
multiplication operator, etc.
So we can always find a proper
generalization of classical properties.
So that's great.
We established that operators do appear in
the mathematical formulas
of quantum theory.
And from the mathematical point of
view it maybe quite interesting.
But what physical significance
do these operators really have?
Unlike their classical counterparts, which
can be measured directly in a classical
experiment, let's say we can measure
momentum, angular momentum, position.
The operators cannot be measured per se,
they're operators.
So how do we associate
an experimental observable with them?
So in order to answer this question,
we're going to use a sort of method
that oftentimes is used in science
by first answering the question
in a simple special case.
And then generalizing the results to
a more general category of objects.
So and the special case that we're
going to consider is the measurement of
a coordinate of a quantum particle.
So the Born rule tells us
that the absolute value
of the wave function squared gives us
the probability distribution function
of different positions
of a quantum particle.
Now in general if we have
a probability distribution function,
let's say capital F(x) of
some random variable x.
So if we want to find, let's say, the mean
value, the expectation value of this x,
what we're going to do is we're going to
average x, integrate x over all
possible values weighted with
this probability distribution.
So in full analogy with this we
can define the mean value of
a three-dimensional coordinate by
integrating the wave function,
absolute value of wave function squared
with the coordinate over the volume,
over the basically all
three dimensional space.
There is a square here.
So and this is a natural
definition of the mean position.
So we can rewrite this definition as so
because absolute value of psi squared,
of course,
is simply psi star times psi of r.
So now comes this generalization of
this definition of the expectation
value of a coordinate to a general case of
an arbitrary quantum mechanical operator.
So let's say we have a classical
property X, let's say, momentum,
angular momentum, coordinate,
energy, whatever.
And let's assume we know the quantum
mechanical operator associated with this,
some X hat.
So the expectation value of this quantum
observable X is going to be calculated
in full analogy with this equation
by simply replacing the coordinate
operator in this equation with
the operator X, whatever it is.
So for example, if X happens to be, so
let's say if X happens to be momentum,
then we're going to simply write it
the expectation value of momentum
is going to be an integral of V star
(-i h bar) gradient of psi, etc.
So it turns out that this
conjecture actually works in
that it is consistent with
the experimental data.
And the experimental data implies
that let's say we have an ensemble
of quantum systems,
each described by wave-function psi of r.
And if we measure some property
X of this quantum systems,
we're going to get different results.
But the average value of this measurement
is going to be consistent with
this definition of the expectation value.
And so it becomes very important and
basic principle of quantum
mechanics that I reiterate here.
Namely that, first of all,
physical observables are associated with,
what I didn't discuss,
self-adjoint operators
acting on the wave-function with
the expectation value defined as above.