In this video I am going to elaborate
a little bit on the physical meaning and
interpretation of operators
in quantum mechanics, and
in particular we are going to discuss
a very important class of problems that
appear throughout quantum mechanics
that is, so called, eigenvalue problems.
To see what they are and how they arise
let me first write down the time-dependent
Schrodinger equation, you can only go
time-dependent Schrodinger equation but
with specifically with
the time-independent Hamiltonian.
So physically this means
that the potential in which
our quantum particle is
moving is not time-dependent.
And actually most problems you
are going to see fall into this category.
So it's a very reasonable assumption.
So that neither the mass nor
the potential are time-dependent.
So in this case, it turns out there is
absolutely no need to deal with this
complicated partial differential equation
that involves the time derivative.
So the time-dependence can be factored
out of the equation in a very straight
forward way and this is accomplished by
performing a separation of variables.
So basically what we can say is,
let's look for
our solution in the following forms.
So the following function is going to be
a product of some time-independent piece,
psi(r), and this exponential which is
sort of leftover from the plane wave.
So this psi(r) does not have to be
a plane wave if the potential exists,
but it is not a plane if
there is a potential.
But the time-dependence
sort of remains the same.
And so if we plug in this ns into
the Schrodinger equation, so
we're going to have in the left-hand side,
the derivative with respect to time,
psi(r) e to the minus iEt over h bar.
So I should mention that E of
course corresponds to the energy.
And so since this lowercase
psi(r) is not depend on time,
we don't have to differentiate this part.
We're going to differentiate
just the exponential and
just essentially by construction,
we're going to get in the left-hand
side E psi(r) and this exponential.
On the other hand,
the right-hand side since there is nothing
time-dependent there, simply it reads
the Hamiltonian acting on
the position-dependent part.
And the exponential is also here, but
it's sort of irrelevant in the sense
that the Hamiltonian doesn't see it,
so the Hamiltonian only involves
the derivative with respect to
spatial coordinates or the potential,
which is just multiplication operation.
So we see that both sides of this
equation contain this exponential, and so
we can just cancel this exponential.
And we're left with, let me just switch
the order in which these guys appear.
So, we're left with the following equation
H acting on psi(r) is
equal to E times psi(r).
And this is what is known as
time-independent Schrodinger equation or
stationary Schrodinger equation.
So this category of problems where an
operator acting on a vector in some space
reproduces the same vector
multiplied by some number.
So this category of problems in math
are called eigenvalue problems.
And in the context of
this mathematical theory,
psi here represents what's known
as eigenvector, let me write it.
And E is an eigenvalue.
Of the corresponding operator.
In this case this operator is Hamiltonian.
Now let me tell you from the outset,
we shall discuss it in more details later,
that the physical significance of these
eigenvalues is in that they determine
the possible outcomes of experiment that
actually measure, in this case, energy.
So we know that, for instance in
classical physics, if I were to have some
potential will, so
let's say this is my V(x) and there is
some potential, well just one example of
problems we're actually going to study.
So if I had a classical particle I would
be able to put a classical particle
with any energy in this field, which
is oscillated between the two turning
points if there is no friction, and
I can do so for any value of energy.
It turns out,
in quantum mechanics it's not so,
and the range of available
energy is limited in this case.
So then what I would have is
decrease over discrete spectrum
by which I mean a possible
solutions to this equation.
So these levels let's say E1 or
E2 are going to come out
of this eigenvalue measure.
So we see that an eigenvalue problem for
the Hamiltonian arises naturally from
the original Schrodinger equation.
And as such, it becomes a very
important independent, in some sense,
equation of quantum theory.
And actually oftentimes when
we say Shrodinger Equation,
we're actually referring to
this H psi equals Ep psi and
not to the original one
with the time derivative.
And furthermore, so
I can value problems also appear for
other operators in quantum theory.
So it's very important, and we should
know at least a few basic properties such
as eigenvalue problems and the operators
involved in these eigenvalue problems.
So we don't have time now to go
into comprehensive theory of this.
Mathematical theories which could be,
in principle,
a subject of a year long course.
So therefore, I will just emphasize
a few things that are really crucial for
the future.
And also introduce some notations and
terms that are important.
So one such important thing is
the notion of a Hermitian operator.
That is defined by the following relation.
So let's imagine we have an operator A,
acting in the space of functions.
Psi(r), so I'm not going to define
precisely mathematically what this space
is, but we should just think about wave
functions that describe the properties of
our quantum particles.
So, one can define Hermitian-adjoint
operator, Adagger,
to the operator A by
the following relation.
So the left-hand side of this
equation is essentially identical
to what we saw in the previous
video when we defined an average or
an expectation value of operator A.
It's an integral over
the entire space of psi(r),
let's say our wave function,
times the action of our operator A on psi.
And the operator Adagger moves
from the right to the left, and
now acts on the function
which is a complex conjugate.
So, if the two expressions are equal for
any psi(r) then we have found
the Hermitian-adjoint operator.
And an important class of operators
that appear in quantum mechanics,
are called Hermitian operators.
And they are characterized by
the fact that their Hermitian-adjoint
is equal to the operator itself,
so they are called Hermitian.
The importance of the Hermitian
operators manifests itself
if we look at their properties, at the
properties of their eigenvalue problem.
So, in general if we have an eigenvalue
problem for an arbitrary operator there is
no guarantee that it's
eigenvalues are going to be real.
So in the context of quantum physics
this would lead to a bit of a problem.
Because, well, let's say,
if we have a wave function which is
described psi-sub-a, and we want to take
to measure the expectation value of the
quantity corresponding to this operator A.
So we will calculate this average value
and we're going to get if A is complex,
we're going to get an expectation value,
which is countless.
And in most cases it doesn't make sense.
So, for example, if measure energy for
particle we certainly go on to get I,
the measuring constant I.
We want to get a reasonable number that
has its counterpart in classical physics,
which does not know about complex numbers.
So, what I'm saying here,
is that if we want to describe
physically reasonable quantities.
So we want these operators to
give rise to real eigenvalues, so
this would make sense.
And the Hermitian operators have this
property, exactly this property, so
the eigenvalues of Hermitian
operators are all real.
So another crucial important property
of the eigenvalue problem for
a Hermitian operator is that it's
eigenvectors, these solutions
psi-sub-a(r) to this equation form
a basis in an appropriate space.
So that is the space
where our functions live.
So for instance,
in the context of quantum physics,
these are going to be wave functions.
And, of course, I should mention that
the statements I'm making are not
mathematically rigorous statements.
So if you want to see a precise
definition or a theorem so
there is, of course, a very rich
mathematical literature the subject.
And I would encourage
you to look into this.
But at this stage I just want to give
you an idea about the properties.
And so the property that I'm presenting
here is, that essentially, if you have any
relevant function psi(r) which has
something to do with our problem.
And this function lives in
the space where our operator x, so
then a set of all eigenvectors of this
operator, which in principle can be either
a discreet or continuous, in which case I
would have written an integral even both.
But in any case,
any such wave function can be represented
as a linear combination of
the eigenfunction, so the operator E.
And this has very important consequences,
as I said, in quantum physics.
Now going closer to quantum physics and
further away from mathematical statements,
let me just summarize things that really
are important in the context
of quantum mechanics.
So the first statement here
is the physical observables,
essentially things that we want to measure
in quantum mechanics, are described
by Hermitian operators, sometimes
also called self-adjoint operators.
So I should mention that there
exists a subtle difference,
actually mathematically, from between
the Hermitian and self-adjoint operators.
But it involves rather complicated math.
And in the framework of this course,
we can just consider Hermitian and
self-adjoint to be the same thing.
But if among you there
is some math aficionados
who want to know the difference, ask this
question in the discussion forum and
I would be happy to elaborate on this.
But anyways, so if we have
identified a quantity of interest,
our observable a, and identified an
operator associated with this observable,
so then we need to solve
the eigenvalue problem for
this operator and
the available eigenvalues
they determine a possible values that
actually can be measured in experiment.
So also let me reiterate a very important
fact which is discussed in the previous
slide, and we're going to talk a little
bit about this in the next video.
Namely that the solutions to this
eigenvalue problem, this function
psi-sub-a(r), form a basis in this
space where our wave functions live.
Which implies that any wave function
describing a physical state of a system
can be expanded as a linear
combination of the eigenvectors.
So the last comment, but not the least
important, that I'm going to make
relates to the interpretation
of these coefficients c-sub-a,
the complex numbers that
appear in this expansion.
As a matter of fact, actually, this is
probably the most important take-home
message I would like you
to take out of this slide.
So imagine that we have an ensemble
of identical quantum systems
which exist in exactly the same quantum
state described by some wave function
psi that we expanded in our
basis of these eigen states.
And let's imagine that we're
going to perform, let's say,
three identical measurements
of the identical quantity a.
So we want to measure
a in exactly the same way
with exactly the same kinds of systems.
So the weird thing about quantum
mechanics is even though
everything is the same about the systems,
we're actually going to get,
strictly speaking,
generally three different results.
So there is a chance some of them will be
the same but there's no guarantee at all.
And the probability of finding
a system in a certain state,
we sometimes refer to as a collapse of the
wave function into a certain eigen state.
So this probability,
let me call it w-sub-a,
is equal to the absolute value squared
of the coefficients in this expansion.
So this is the probability.
So, in this example again, the only
thing we can say for sure is that all
these measurements are going to result in
a value of a that belongs to the spectrum,
that is to the set of available
eigenvalues of the operation.
But which particularly value
is going to be measured?
We don't know.
We can only say which is more likely,
and we can quantify this uncertainty but
this is the maximum that we can do.
And so this principle is actually very
important in quantum mechanics, and
we're going to use it later
in the course very often.