Hi everyone.
Today I want to look at another problem in electoral statics.
I want to look at a dipole placed in an electric field this time.
So we're going to get a couple different cases.
I'm going to start with the simplest which is just a couple of dye Poles placed in a constant electric
field.
We're gonna look at the talk on the dipole.
We're going to look at the energy associated with rotating a dye pole in that field and in the second
case I want to actually make the field very in space.
So we place the dipole in an in homogeneous electric field.
We're going to see what happens to it.
So here are a couple of cases there's dipole no one cares dipole number two.
And now I'm going to place it in an electric field one.
That's just make the field lines uniform.
So I'm not telling you what produces the electric field I'm just telling you there is one in space and
I'm placing dipole number one at an angle with respect to the electric field and dipole number to them
and to place it at a different angle.
With respect to the electric field so let's go see what's going to happen to these dye poles.
First thing we can look at are the forces acting on the individual charges.
No we have a dipole so that has a positive charge and negative charge.
Separated by a distance
there will be an electric force acting on the positive charge and electric forces in the same direction
as the electric field.
The electric force acting on the negative charge is going to be in this direction.
The electric force is in the opposite direction.
The electric field for negative charges.
Well what about this guy.
Let's look at dipole number two.
Let's look at all the forces acting on dipole.
Number two we have electric force acting on the positive side and we have a force acting on the negative
side.
So there is a difference between both of these pictures right.
In case number one you notice that both of these forces are acting in opposite directions and they're
going to tend to make the object rotate like this dipole will rotate in an electric field Hello.
Case number two case number two simply have forces that are tending to stretch the dipole they don't
tend to make the object rotate.
OK.
So when we're going to look at this a little bit more detail in a minute you're going to see that these
forces on a dipole and this orientation will produce a talk on the dipole.
Whereas if the dipole is oriented in the direction of the field or opposite of the field we're going
to show that there is no torque because these forces don't tend to make the object rotate.
Where in this case they do.
So let's go to the interactive whiteboard and look at a couple specific examples.
OK.
So here we have our dipole again placed in our field the positive and negative charges are separated
by distance let's call it D.
And what I want to do now is I want to look at the torque produced by each one of these forces.
So in order to calculate the the talk I remember that the force first has a magnitude of the charge
times the electric field.
And if we want to look at the torque produced by a constant force remember what that was.
It was the distance to the pivot.
Let's put the pivot right at the midpoint.
So the distance to the pivot.
So that's where the force is being applied is deep over to.
It's the magnitude of the force which is f multiplied now times sign of the angle theta.
And remember with the angle theta is in this particular case the angle theta is defined as this and
that is the torque produced on or by the force acting on the positive charge.
We also have to consider the torque produced by the force down over here on the negative charge.
That one's going to have the exact same magnitude.
The distance to the pivot is d over to the magnitude of the force is the same because we're looking
at a dipole and the charge is the same and sign of the angle theta.
Okay so we're just about done here and we want to look at the network.
Remember this year only gives you the magnitude.
However the direction is going to be the same for both of them.
Let me add the directional were here.
If this force over here on the positive charge is the only force acting on the system it's going to
tend to make it rotate clockwise.
How about the negative one.
Again if the force down here is the only force acting on the dipole it's going to also tend to make
it rotate clockwise.
That's in the same direction.
Therefore both of those vectors are in the same direction.
So the net torque is simply going to be just the sum of both of those at the end of the day you get
to and since they have the exact same magnitude.
I'll go ahead now and substitute in the magnitude of the force F which is simply the charge times the
magnitude of the field time sign of theta.
And that's our net torque acting on the dipole.
I could simplify this a little bit.
This too will cancel without one.
Let's go ahead and just write our final equation for the talk on a dipole can be written as Q D.
E sign of theta so that's kind of a useful formula here.
Remember you can also take this a step further and that's typically what people do is we're going to
define a quantity and define a quantity you call the dipole moment.
And in this case it's the electric dipole moment the electric dipole moment.
We give it the letter P.
It's actually going to be a vector and the magnitude of the vector is simply going to be the charge
of the dipole.
So the charge of either the positive or the negative multiplied times the distance between the two charges
and the direction the convention is it points toward the positive charge points toward
positive charge.
OK so in this figure here if I'm going to plot with his vector P looks like the vector P basically points
in this direction here.
That is our dipole moment associated with that dipole.
And the reason we're gonna want to define a dipole moment is because the talk now you can actually write
it as a vector equation.
The talk is a vector can be written very simply as our dipole moment vector cross product with the electric
field.
So there you have it.
That is the same equation as the one I wrote up here.
Remember how you expand a cross product is you take the magnitude of one vector multiplied by the magnitude
of the other vector and then you multiply by sign of the angle between the two vectors.
So in this specific case let me draw the vectors on the side here.
So we have our dipole moment vector which is like this.
It has a vector P which has a magnitude of the charge.
Times the distance between the two our vector E is in this direction.
That's the direction the electric field and the angle theta that goes into our talk equation is the
angle between the dipole moment vector and the electric field vector.
So in this direction here ends up being perpendicular to the dipole moment vector and the electric field
vector.
If things are in the plane like this usually you can pick a direction for the talk is being either clockwise
or counterclockwise and that's kind of what I've done up here.
OK so there you have it folks there is the talk of produced by an electric field on a dipole so it depends
on the angle.
We have our general equation here which is P E sign of theta.
So we have a couple specific cases to look at.
For example when is the torque a maximum value
well for any given Dipole which has a dipole moment P the maximum angle or the maximum torque will be
produced when sign of theta equals the one.
When we have sign of theta equals the one that's going to produce the maximum torque for any given electric
field and dipole and we get that when the dipole moment P is perpendicular to the electric field.
Because in that case our angle theta is actually 90 degrees and the torque simply going to be the dipole
moment times the electric field time sign of 90 which is 1.
So that's it.
The magnitude of the talk is simply this.
If you want to write it now in terms of the charge remember you can simply do that with the charge.
Times the distance between the positive and negative charge.
Times the electric field and that's the magnitude of the talk.
Okay so let's compare the two cases I had on a board now.
So we have dipole one which is located in a constant electric field.
However it makes an angle of 30 degrees with respect to the electric field whereas in case number two
you have the dipole that's in the same direction as the electric field and in both cases we want to
look at the torque acting on the dipole.
Again we can look at each individual charge look at the forces however I want to use the formulae we
had in the previous case which said that the talk is p cross E for both cases.
Remember how that vector P was defined that was our dipole moment.
The vector P was the charge q TIMES the distance between the two charges and the direction was from
the negative to the positive.
Negative to positive.
So let's draw the vectors P and E for both of these cases for dipole 1 and dipole number 2.
So here's what we have for dipole number 1.
Here's the vector P.
Here's our electric field
and I've said that the angle here was 30 degrees
all right.
Compare that to case number two case number two.
Again our dipole moment vector goes from negative to positive.
So in that case it's the same magnitude.
However the orientation is different.
That's the direction of P and the direction of e is also in this direction.
So in this case the angle between them is equal to zero degrees.
So if we apply our torque equation and we want to find how big the talk is so let's just look at the
magnitude of the torque the magnitude of the talk or simply BP.
E time sign of 30 degrees so that's q TIMES THE DISTANCE BETWEEN THE POSITIVE AND NEGATIVE CHARGE.
Times the magnitude of the field and sign of 30 degrees.
So one last step.
Q d e divided by two.
All right compare that to this case the net torque acting on dipole number two is simply going to be
PS The same is the same.
However we have sign of zero degrees and sign of zero degrees is zero.
Therefore the net torque acting on dipole number two is zero whereas the net torque for dipole number
one definitely non-zero.
So what we're gonna have here is in this case we're going to get some rotation of the dipole.
In this case no rotation
I'm.
You look at the potential energy of a dive hole in a field again I'm going to use this definition of
our electric dipole moment which is a vector that pointed from the negative charge to the positive charge
and we can write the potential energy of a dipole in a constant electric field in terms of the electric
field as dipole moment as p dot e.
This is a scalar product so if you want to write that in terms of the angle between both of those vectors
and just in terms of the magnitudes simply minus p e times cos of theta so that's kind of an important
equation.
So again the energy can range over a whole whole series of values because the angle fade I can place
this dipole at any orientation with respect to the electric field you can look at when the potential
energy is a maximum.
So when when we have a maximum value for this potential energy we'd have a maximum value whenever the
angle theta is equal to 180 degrees when the angle theta is equal to 180 degrees cos of 1 A.D. minus
1.
So the energy of the dipole in the field is P is you get minus p e times coast of 180 which is minus
1 which cancels with the original one we get a minimum value of the potential energy when the angle
theta equal to zero.
In that case that's when the dipole moment is aligned with the electric field.
In that case you have a minimum potential energy and the energy of the dipole in this case is minus
p and there is a case where the potential energy is equal to zero right the potential energy equals
to zero when the angle is 90 degrees in that case zero is when our angle theta equals 90 degrees the
potential energy of the dipole is equal to zero.
Okay.
The actual values of potential energy aren't really that interesting.
What's more interesting is when you change all right when we change the energy or when we try to rotate
the dipole we might be asked how much work is needed to rotate a dipole in an electric field.
We know there's forces that the field produces on the charge.
So if I wanted to rotate I have to do work on the system.
So let's look at this specific case here down at the bottom that I've sketched out.
So I have an initial dipole where the dipole moment is aligned in the same direction as my electric
field shown in red and in the final position I simply want to rotate this dipole by 180 degrees by some
mechanism I'm not really showing you but I'm just giving you the initial and the final steps.
What the orientation of dipole looks like in the field and we want to calculate how much energy is stored
in the system or how much work did you have to do to accomplish this.
So calculate how much work you needed to do.
You simply have to look at the work needed.
Basically just the change in potential energy.
If you're not sure about this.
Think about just the mass right.
If I just have a mass on the ground and I want to lift it up all the way up to here and lift it up through
some height if I want to know how much energy is required to do this all you have to do is simply compare
the potential energy at the top versus the bottom.
In this case you usually set the potential energy equal to zero at the bottom and the potential energy
in the final step is simply M.G. H.
So the amount of energy required to raise this mass a certain distance H is simply equal to M.G. H.
You look at the change of potential energy in the system.
That's exactly what we're going to do here for the dipole except the potential energy is not simply
given by the mass times the gravity times the height above the ground.
The potential energy for a dipole in a field is given by our other expression here which is negative
dipole moment times the electric field times cos of the angle between both of those vectors.
So the work needed is the change in potential energy.
That's a final potential energy minus an initial potential energy.
Now those are going to be different from each other because the angle is different in each case.
You got to be a little bit careful.
So our final value is simply well how did we start we started.
So our final value is shown down here and that's the case where the angle is 180 between the dipole
moment and the electric field.
I've actually calculated that one right here.
That was the value of the potential energy of the dipole in the field and so it's simply P minus What's
the initial value in the initial configuration the dipole moment is a line in the same direction of
the field.
That is when the angle is zero degrees have shown that one here and the potential energy is negative
P.
So when you include everything together the work needed
it's simply going to be two times the magnitude of the dipole moment.
Times the magnitude of the electric field and that is going to be a quantity that's going to have units
of joules corresponds to the amount of energy that's required in order to accomplish this.
Notice we're gonna get a positive number.
We're gonna get a positive number because we have to do work against the electric field in order to
rotate this object.
It's not going to rotate by itself.
You have to put energy into the system.
And this is how much energy you need to put in in order to rotate this dipole.
OK.
Now when to look at what happens when the electric field is not constant compared to the constant case
over here.
Now let's just look at the talk the talk for case number one where the dipole moment is a line in the
same direction the field we just saw that the net torque was equal to zero.
We had forces acting to the right on the positive charge force acting to the left on the negative charge.
And those forces didn't produce any rotation for the case down or illustrated in the bottom figure if
the fuel is constant.
Again we had forces acting at a certain distance from the pivot and those forces produced a torque right
they would tend to make the object rotate clockwise
clockwise rotation.
The magnitude of the talk was given by our dipole moment the magnitude of the electric field times a
sign of the angle between them.
If you substituted in our value for the dipole moment or the magnitude of the dipole moment which is
simply Q times D sine and theta so that's the talk.
One thing I didn't mentioned before however it's very very important when you write this down is the
forces for case number two even for case number one the forces balance out actually is although they
do produce a talk for case number two.
The net force acting on the dipole is equal to zero because the charge is the same.
The electric field is the same.
These forces are equal in opposite directions.
They produce a torque however they don't produce an acceleration of the dipole.
You'll simply rotate it.
You're not going to move the dipole you're not going to lead to any translational motion of the dipole.
And that's kind of the big important point and the biggest difference here between the case where the
electric fuel is constant versus when the electric field varies in space.
So let's have a look at it.
Okay so now let's compare the case where the key where the electric field is not uniform in space.
For that I'm going to look at the fuel produced by negative charge and I'm going to place the dipole
with its dipole moment aligned pointing toward the negative charge and making some angle that is shown
in the bottom figure over here.
So let's look at the forces acting on the dipole.
Well you're gonna have an attractive force between the positive part of the dipole and the negative
charge.
So that's going to be a force pointing to the right and you're also going to have a repulsive force
draw it in a different shade here because these two negatives will repel each other.
So you're going to have another force pointing to the left this time.
Let's call that f 2 and call our first one EF 1.
Now one thing that is different from the case of the constant electric field is that both of the vectors
for the constant field both of the force vectors had the same magnitude.
In this case f 1
in magnitude is going to be bigger than 2.
Therefore there's going to be a net force acting on it.
The net force is not equal to zero.
Like in this case this net force acting on the dipole was equal to zero.
So that means when the dipole is gonna be attracted to the negative charge if there's a net force there's
gonna be an acceleration.
How about the torque well even in this case here there is no torque although there's a net force acting
on it.
The torque acting on the dipole is going to be zero and you can see that just by looking at the figure.
All of these forces do as the forces tend to make the object stretch right.
They're acting in opposite directions but there's no rotation no rotation
all right.
Now take the case now where our dipole moment is again at some angle.
With respect to the axis joining the negative charge producing another electric field in this particular
case again we can look at the forces acting on the dipole and the forces.
You're gonna have an attractive force acting this way.
And you're going to have again a repulsive force acting away from it.
Now these vectors have a
different directions number one.
So you're still going to have a net force acting on them.
Both of these -- vectors will never cancel out to give you zero net force because they're in different
directions.
So we're gonna have a net force
not equal to zero.
In addition you're gonna have a net torque.
You can calculate the torque by looking at each individual component and repeating the steps we did
for the regular dial and a constant field.
You can place a pivot here at the center of the dipole and look at the total torque produced by each
force and then add them up as vectors.
So we'd have to do the torque produced by the force F one as a vector plus the torque produced by the
force F 2 is a vector.
Each one of these cases I can use my equation I can use it's the distance to the pivot.
It's the magnitude of the force and time sign the angle between them.
OK.
You'd have to do a little bit more algebra but the key point is that you can have a net force in this
case and you can also have a net torque.
This is to actually calculate the magnitude is a little bit more complicated
however the concepts should be clear just by looking at the force diagrams okay.
So just to summarize the key points we define a new vector today called the DI Paul moment.
Dipole moment we gave it the letter P and the magnitude anyway it was the charge q of the dipole multiplied
times the distance between the two charges and the direction was from the negative toward the positive
charge of the dipole.
This was particularly useful because you can then use the definition of dipole moment to look at the
torque acting on a dipole.
And the talk is simply written as P cross e and if you write that in terms of the magnitude of the torque
you simply have the magnitude of the vector P the magnitude of our electric field and there's also that
angular dependence that was really important because there's some orientations in the diaper hole in
a field where there is no torque acting on it for example if it's parallel or a. parallel.
The other important point that was that the net force of a dipole in a constant electric field is zero
is constant
because you have equal and opposite forces they don't produce a net force acting on the dipole.
We also discuss potential energy.
And we looked at a case where the dipole was placed in a constant electric field.
In that case the potential energy of the dipole is simply minus Pitot e.
If you expand that scalar product you simply have pea coat of theta.
Now the actual individual values of the potential energy are really not that interesting.
What's more interesting is when you change the potential energy of a dipole so you either have to do
work or electric field does work
work on the dipole.
So we looked at one specific case where we rotated the dipole and looked at how much energy is required
in order to accomplish that rotation.
The last thing I looked at we looked at placing a dipole in a field that was in homogeneous.
So it wasn't constant
and what we found in that case you could still have a talk
depending on the orientation of the dipole moment with the electric field
and the major difference between that and the constant electric field was now the net force
is non-zero.
So the dipole will not only tend to rotate but it will also tend to accelerate.