Hi everybody.
So this is Section 5 entitled A plan Kirchhoff's rules to circuits.
So up until now we've learned quite a few things we talked about Ohm's law and looking at the potential
difference across a resistor that has a current flowing through it.
We talked about the differences between resistivity and resistance.
We've looked at ways of simplifying networks of resistors to make circuits look as simple as possible.
What we haven't done however is we haven't really looked at how to solve a complete circuit problem.
And what I mean by that imagine you take this example of a circuit I have here in front of you the tools
I'd given you up until now haven't really allowed you to calculate what is the current flowing through
each and every one of those resistors.
So that's what we're going to learn how to do.
Now the circuit can be either a single loop or multi loop like the one I'm showing you here.
Also what if you were asked to find what what if what if I attach a volt meter between two points in
a circuit.
It could be between points A and B it could be between this point and this point CND.
What would the volt meter read.
What if I tried to measure the current flowing through each in each individual resistor in this network
how can I calculate the current.
And then once I know the current flowing through each resistor I should be then able to calculate what
the power dissipated by that resistor using some of the tools we already learned how to how to use.
So in what follows here we're going to apply certain set of rules.
There are two rules they're called Kirchhoff's rules for circuits.
It's kind of like following dance steps if you want the dance to look good.
You simply have to follow the steps that I'm going to give you.
And they never fail.
The steps are pretty straightforward and I'm going to teach you how to use them and at the end you're
going to look at any circuit like this and you'll be able to analyze it with ease.