OK so it's like a full example now.
So here's a nice kind of multi loop circuit.
We've got one two three four five resistors and we've got a couple of questions here.
First is find the potential difference across the five ohm resistor.
OK.
Well that's pretty easy.
That's just really Ohm's law right.
The potential differences across any resistor is the value of the resistance multiplied by the current.
I need to find how much current is flowing through there.
And Question 2 says Find the power dissipated by this forum resistor.
OK.
Well the find the power dissipated again that's a simple equation.
It's simply the value of the resistance multiplied by the current squared.
Oh I need to know the current flowing through this forum resistor.
OK.
So this problem here boils down to we've got to find what the current is flowing through each and every
one of these resistors.
So we're going to do let's start by labeling values of currents everywhere and then we'll see how we
could proceed.
All right.
So down here through the battery I mean to call this oops I call this the current down here and this
section right through this first branch here I'm going to call this the current one I'm going to call
the current going appear to be equal to Aitu.
Oh now look what happens here.
Now there is a junction so part of the current is going to go up here part of the current is going to
go down here.
So when you call the current go into the top three current down here to be equal to I4.
All right.
Now they recombine.
So whatever current I too was going in kind of breaks up but then it recombines over here.
So you should also convince yourself you have a current Aitu flowing in this upper branch here through
the form resistor.
OK so that's what all the currents look like.
The next thing I should do is well this looks like a network that I can simplify using the equivalent
resistances.
So what I'm going to do here is I'm going to start by kind of getting rid of this.
That looks kind of complicated.
However these are just two resistors that are in parallel with each other.
So I can simplify this.
All right.
Let's just go ahead and do that up here.
Call this our equivalent one.
OK.
And if there's two of them I can apply my little trick you multiply them divided by the sum.
If you add them up that's a team you could simplify 18 18 six goes three times.
I'm left with four looks like OK.
So this whole thing here I can replace with a 400 resistor what's the next thing I can do.
Well each one of these branches now simply has two resistors.
We've gotten rid of this one and represented with a form resistor but that's fine.
And now look what we have.
So I mean redraw this.
So it's over here.
I'm going to try to make it a little bit smaller just to save on space.
So we have a 12 volt battery and we're going to make it teeny tiny here.
We have well three plus five Remember these are in series with one another.
So that's just an 8 ohm resistor.
So let's just substitute it with one value here.
OK.
And close that branch and this guy here is simply eight
or using a rule for series resistors.
And how about the top or the top I just said everything here in the orange blob is for oh then I have
another for all that's pretty easy.
It's also eight.
That's easy.
This problem is turning out to be pretty wimpy.
OK and we have another 8 ohm resistor right here.
OK so how do we combine both of these 8 ohm resistors.
Well again we can use an equivalent resistance and that's it.
This will be the last step.
So it's really the total now equivalent resistance let's just call it our equivalent if you multiply
them and divided by the sum multiply them divided by the sum you get eight times 8 64 64 divided by
16 is four.
Actually one thing you should notice by now is if the resistors are the same and they're in parallel
with each other you always get half the value.
That's always kind of a consequence of multiplying them and divided by the sum.
OK.
Hopefully you've noticed that.
All right.
So this entire network now is equivalent to one simple four ohm resistor are going to draw one last
time down here just to save on space and just remind ourselves that we have an equivalent for home resistor.
And the reason I like to do the equivalent resistance is it's fine if you're able to do it for that
particular circuit.
It's the easiest way to find the current in this bottom branch.
Right because now we have this kind of very very straightforward little circuit down here.
We know the voltage of the battery is still 12.
So guess what the current ideas are you can automatically find with the current.
As it simply the voltage of the battery divided by the total resistance.
So we have to have three amps.
So there's three amps over here and this bottom section.
All right.
Let me go ahead and kind of clear this out here.
This is not required any more.
All right.
Now let's continue.
Roger we've got to go back to our questions.
Really our goal was to find how much current is flowing through here how much current is flowing through
here.
Well maybe I should have deleted that right away.
Actually let's keep that up there for a second.
Well the reason I want to keep this up here is because look what happens.
Right.
We have two branches here that are 8 ohms.
That's the total resistance of each branch.
And we just calculate the current.
I I said there is three amps flowing through the battery and up here.
And once it gets to this junction over here guess what's going to happen if the resistance is the same
we just saw this on the previous video.
Right.
If the resistance is the same what's going to happen to those three amps.
Well it means that the current is going to be evenly divided whatever current flows through here I wonder.
And whenever current flows through here to it has to be they have to be the same because the total resistance
is the same in each one of those branches.
So we have to have that the current one equals to the current Aitu so that automatically means we know
the value because we have three going in.
And if I one has to be equal to Aitu Well guess what if you apply the junction rule here you have three
going in and that must be equal to one plus two.
But those are the same.
So this must be equal to two times I want.
So one has to be equal to three over to her 1.5 and that must be equal to the current Aitu.
OK.
So that's kind of an important relationship.
So we're getting pretty good now at kind of finding currency I think.
All right now that we know that really the currents through and now look at we know the current everywhere
in this this first branch to 1.5 guess what we know also the current up here and we don't know the current
through the six and the 12 but do we really need that for this question.
All we're asking for is what is the power dissipated by this forum resistance to know the power dissipated
by that resistance.
All we need to know is the current flowing through it and that has to be £1.5.
All right.
So the last part.
Let's go ahead and calculate.
So this will be question a question B.
So for question a the voltage between this point and this point to call it point 1 and point to that
voltage difference.
And again it's just given by Ohm's law and call a delta V or just call it V if you want against the
value of the resistance are multiplied by the current flowing through it.
We just said it was three over two.
OK.
So we get 15 divided by two.
We get 7.5 volts.
All right.
How about Part B.
Part B says Find the power dissipated in this forum resistance the power dissipated in the forum.
Resistance is given by the value of the resistance which is four multiplied by the current going through
it.
We said again it's 1.5.
Let's call it three over two.
Easier to do the math for me.
And don't forget the square that you get.
So we get four.
Why don't we get three squared is 9 2 squared is four.
Well that's convenient.
And cancel those out and at the end what you're left with is the power dissipated by that for resistance
is given by nine Watts OK.
So there's kind of a nice problem kind of we use some simplifications we use equivalent resistance to
simplify things and we also use the fact that both of these branches had equal resistances that allowed
us to kind of simplify this math a little bit and get to the answer quickly.