OK what I want to do now is look at the simple case here and this is an application sometimes referred
to as a voltage divider and all we have here are two resistors that are in series with each other.
Very very simple circuit to solve for.
Right.
If you have an M.F. of 10 volts you'd have to have a voltage drop across both of those equal to 10 volts.
That's what the Kirchhoff's loop rule would tell us.
However what if we had another piece of circuitry we had another circuit down over here somewhere but
we weren't able to use 10 volts in order to drive it because that would be supplying too much power.
What you can do actually is you can use a voltage divider.
Let me show you what the principle is so let's first begin by solving this.
Now this circuit over here.
OK.
So first thing we need to do is find how much current Do we have.
So the amount of current that we have again the total resistance.
Our equivalent for this case is simply 10 ohms.
So if the voltage of the battery is given by 10 volts you know that the current that you're going to
get has to be very straightforward.
Now what if you go ahead and let's set some points over here point a point B and point C.
Now the voltage difference between points and point B is not going to be the same as the voltage difference
between Point B and point see if you wanted to find the voltage difference across any resistance.
Well it's very easy you just apply Ohm's law.
So the voltage difference across the resistance are one is given by the resistance are one multiplied
by the current going through it.
We just call it the current I mean rather than substituting this right away elegies I'm going to get
a general formula here for the voltage divider equations and then we'll have a look at it.
Now the next thing I can do is the voltage across the resistance are two is the resistance are two multiplied
by the current.
Now remember where the current comes from the current basically came from our DMF divided by the equivalent
resistance and for this case the equivalent resistance was simply our one plus our two actually you
could see that you can multiply or you can substitute in the current directly into these voltage differences
across each resistor.
And let's see what we get.
So the voltage difference across the resistance are one.
Again it's going to be R1 divided by the total resistance of that circuit are one plus R2 and that gets
multiplied by the IMF of the battery and the voltage difference across the resistance are two ends up
being are two multiplied by the current and the current.
I'm just going to use this expression here rather than the one amp for these numerical values it's 1
amp but let's just get a general expression.
Again you get something like this are one plus are two and this gets multiplied by again the EMI.
So the nice thing about this is you see that the voltage difference across the resistance are one.
Right both of them end up being less and you could see that if you add them up plus the voltage difference
across R2 you have to get BMF of the battery.
Right and that's what you would get because you would get R1 R1 plus R2
multiplied by the IMF Plus the resistance are to divided by our one plus are two multiplied by the EMAC
again combined both of those terms you get are one plus or two in the numerator and that ends up canceling
out our one plus or two in the denominator and multiplied by the EMR.
You can cancel those out.
Those are simply equal to 1.
So you see that the voltage drop across both of those has to be equal to the voltage gain across the
MF for any numbers that you choose.
All right.
So let's go back to our example over here.
So looking at these expressions you can see there that the voltage drop across the forum resistance
is simply going to be four volts.
Right.
So that means actually if you kind of branch this out.
What if I decided to use the voltage difference to drive another circuit.
This might be another circuit altogether that's just represented by this black box over here.
A white box.
So this voltage difference across here is four volts although you didn't have a four volt battery.
You can still use combinations of resistors like this to generate you know if you had a whole different
series of values of resistance at your disposal you can set up a circuit and then you effectively use
a lower voltage to drive a different part of a circuit.
If I wanted to drive a circuit with a 6 volt battery but I didn't have one again I could set something
up like this.
The voltage difference across the six ohm resistance is six volts and you can test that out for yourself.
Right we get a resistance that is 6 ohms and we get a current That's one end.
So we get six volts across this guy over here.
So again you could branch this off and I know that I can now use this to maybe run another circuit or
drive current through motor Magin the motor doesn't want you to have 10 volts.
Power supply would be too much.
It would produce too much current in that motor.
You might want to reduce it and you can do it using a voltage divider application like this.