OK let me just say a few words about different ways of measuring current and voltage we saw we can calculate
it.
If you're doing this in a lab or you're taking a test and they ask you how would you actually measure
Well there are two kinds of voltmeters although nowadays everything is done with a multi meter.
But traditionally an AIM meter is used to measure current.
OK.
And if you're measuring current remember current has to flow through the wire.
So ammeters so their symbol is represented by this it's a circle with the letter H inside and it's wires
like this.
And the way you connect an ammeter is you always connect an ammeter in series.
So you physically cut the wire you place the ammeter in on each side.
So current is actually going to flow directly through that ammeter.
Since current is flowing through it the resistance of an ammeter.
Every electrical device is going to have some resistance but the resistance is typically very small.
Since it's in series you wouldn't want the resistance of the ammeter to be very big because then that
would change the overall current of the circuit.
So resistance is small for ammeters.
Now you'll never see ammeters connected in parallel.
That doesn't make any sense because if it's connected in parallel and you have a small resistance it
means you're going to have a lot of current going through there.
There is very little resistance to current.
So you really always want them in series.
So you could place them either next to power supplies you can replace them if you have a circuit with
several different branches you just connect the ammeter in each individual branch and you can measure
the current through each branch.
Now volt meter on the other hand here is the symbol for a volt meter here it is shown measuring the
voltage here across this resistance.
So just a circle here with the letter V a volt meter as it says it's measuring the voltage difference.
Right.
Between two points
it's always between two points.
The other important thing about the Volt Meter is that they are always connected in parallel
so you should never see volt meter connected and surgery's.
Now the volt meter itself would be constructed such that it has a very high resistance
and you want something that is connected in parallel.
If you don't want it to disrupt any of the actual circuit that you're measuring.
You want the resistance to be very very high.
So very little current is going to flow through that volt meter.
So you can always use a volt meter to for example can you place a volt meter down over here.
To measure the potential difference across this power supply or I can place a volt meter between both
of those points connected like this to measure the voltage drop across this resistor OK so just keep
that in mind whenever you're dealing with these types of meters here.
OK.
They're connected differently ones in series ones in parallel.
One has a very small resistance.
One would have a very high resistance and their symbols are different.