All right here's another example of using the current law.
So we're given this network over here with three resistors and we're asked to find the current the current
i3 in this particular case which is the current in this outermost branch of the circuit.
We're told that the current flowing through the battery is seven amps.
We're told that the current in each of these branches first two branches anyway is 2.5 and 1.5 amps.
So what's left over here.
Well again you can start by identifying what the junctions are.
Here's a junction Here's a junction You can also define these ones if you want it to.
We're going to see that these are really are needed.
You can solve the problem simply by looking at A and B.
Ok so what do we have it.
A We have seven amps going in and you have 2.5 amps flowing down here.
So if I have 2.5 amps flowing out well there has to be more flowing out this way.
And we've labeled this the current IB so this current over here IAB must be 7 minus 2.5 and 7 minus
2.5 is me 4.5 amps.
And now look at this current IAB there's 4.5 amps Coombe's per second flowing down here into this junction
and out of that 4.5 you've got 1.5 flowing down.
So what's left well you have the current I 3 over here I 3 is flowing down this way and it has to go
through this resistor then go back.
So again 4.5 going in 1.5.
Going down the current i3 must then be equal to 4.5 minus 1.5.
Pretty straightforward.
So the current i3 equals to 3 amps Okay.
So this guy here is 3 amps and that works nicely.
Now you can also apply a backwards right.
Imagine you then applied the junction rule to junction d down here.
What would you have.
Well you'd have 1.5 going into the junction.
You'd have three amps going into the junction.
That means that the current over here in this section would have to be equal to 4.5 amps if you apply
the junction rule down over here while look at whatever current flows in.
There's two currents flowing in there's ice one from the top that's 2.5 amps and you have 4.5 amps coming
in from the side.
So again that has to be equal to the total current flowing out.
So the current flowing out in this case would have to be 7 amps.
So there's seven amps everywhere in this branch.
There are seven amps flowing through the battery and seven amps up here.
All right so we know the currents now everywhere in this network using the junk will.