All right I'm going to teach you now how to apply Kirchhoff's rules or Kirchoff's voltage law when you
form close loops around a circuit.
So rule number one
pick a loop that makes sense.
So we're going to pick the loop where I started over here in the lower right hand corner and I formed
a clockwise loop that went down here and goes in that direction there.
So now you see when I go around this loop I'm going to encounter a battery then I'm going to count or
two resistors.
So when I encounter batteries or earmuffs there's only two loop tools rather
I'm either going across batteries going from the negative side toward the positive side if I do that.
Here's the rule.
So from going from A to B when I cross a battery going from the negative to the positive it means that
I'm going from a lower electrical potential toward a higher electrical potential.
So the potential difference is has to be a positive number.
So when I apply the loop rule that means I would add the potential of the battery when I'm going here.
If I would cross a battery now going in the opposite direction going from the positive toward the negative
terminal that means there's a voltage drop when I cross this battery and the magnitude of the voltage
drop is given by the IMF of the battery.
And the way I characterize a drop across a battery is by putting a negative sign in the front.
So I would put mine is 12 volts when I apply Kirchoff's voltage law.
Now the other things that we're going to encounter when we do our loops are resistors
in order to apply voltage laws to resistors.
We must first know the direction of the current.
Now in many cases we're not given the direction of the current.
In some cases it's pretty easy to guess what the direction of the current is going to be.
But some cases is not very obvious.
So rule number two pick a direction or the current
You don't have to worry about whether your gas is going to be correct or incorrect.
The voltage law is going to take care of all of that.
The only thing you have to do at the beginning of a problem is just pick a direction and just stick
with it for the rest of the problem.
Now if it's a circuit kind of like this one there is a lot of different currents that you can define.
Each branch can have its own current.
For example this center section here I may have a current like this one.
I'm just going to pick the upper branch up here.
I'm going to call this current over here.
Aitu
is the main branch here the current flowing through the battery is also it could be different.
Let's call this just the current.
I.
And how about over here.
Well I have a current Aitu that's in this upper branch
but it hits a junction over here so part of that current is going to split up part of it's going to
flow through the six ohm resistor.
Let's call this i3 part of that current is going to flow through the 12 armor's is there.
Let's call this I4.
So you see just in this one particular circuit I actually have five different currents that I have to
find.
OK so that's pretty simple right.
Rule number one pick a loop that we're going to do.
Rule number 2 says pick a current direction so we've done that.
OK.
And we've identified all the different currents through the different resistors.
So now we're going to have two rules when we cross resistors and the two rules are given here.
Now remember by picking a current direction positive current always flows from high electrical potential
toward lower electrical potential.
So this side of the five ohm resistor is at a higher electrical potential in this one.
And by picking a current direction flowing from left to right we've automatically decided that this
side is at a higher electrical potential than that one.
All right so now.
Well one we're going to do our loops are either going to go from high to low or we're going to go from
low to high depending whether or not we cross a resistor in the direction of the current or opposite
or the direction of the current.
So there's two rules.
Again let's assume here we're going from point A to Point B.
And I've decided that the current flows from left to right.
So here have decided that this case is at a higher electrical potential than this point.
If I cross 8 a B in the opposite direction again if current flows in this case from right to left than
here I would be going from a low electrical potential toward a higher electrical potential.
Ok so if you take the case here in the top figure if I cross in the direction of the current I'm going
from high to low voltage which means there is a voltage drop and the magnitude of the voltage drop is
given by Ohm's law.
It's the current flowing through the resistance multiplied by the value of the resistance.
The way I identify that it's a voltage drop is by putting a negative sign in the front right here.
So the change in potential when you cross a resistor in the direction of the current is negative.
IIR.
Now if you cross a resistance now going opposite of the current That means you're going from a low electrical
potential toward a higher electrical potential.
Now the change in electrical potential is given by Ohm's law.
That's Are the Eagles the I remember in the way we say there's an increase now going toward a higher
electrical potential is by putting a positive sign there.
So let's go ahead now and just apply our loop rules to a couple of loops Let's start with the first
one then I drew this clockwise loop starting at point A.
Let me call this loop number one.
I'll make it in blue.
OK so I've decided to go in the clockwise direction.
The first thing I encounter is a battery.
OK.
So I have to deal with the IMF rules over here.
I'm going from the low to the high which means it's really Casey over here that applies to me.
If I'm applying Kirchoff's voltage law that means I have to add the potential of the battery here.
There is a potential difference equal to 12 volts when I crossed this battery.
Now when I just traveling along a wire there is no change in electrical potential because these wires
are ideal conductors.
They don't have any resistance.
So now the first thing I'm going to encounter now is a three resistance.
So now it's the rules up here that apply when I cross a three ohm resistance in the direction of the
current.
Well again the left side of the three ohm resistance is that a higher electrical potential than the
lower one.
So when I cross it I'm going toward a lower electrical potential that means there's a voltage drop across
the three ohm resistance.
If there's a voltage drop it means it's negative.
The change is negative and the magnitude of that change now is simply given by Ohm's law which is the
value of the resistance multiplied by the current.
Now you have to be a little bit careful.
It's the current flowing through that particular resistance that matters.
All right now the next thing I'm going to encounter is a 5 ohm resistor.
Again there's a voltage drop.
Mine is five multiplied by the current I one and that equals to zero.
All right what I want to do now is let's do the same loop except what I'm going to do now.
So this was here was going around in a clockwise fashion.
What happens if I do the same loop except what if I go around in a counter-clockwise fashion.
Let's go ahead and do that.
So the first thing I encounter now is a 5 ohm resistance.
However when I cross that resist I'm going in the opposite direction of the current I'm going from a
low electrical potential toward a higher electrical potential.
So when I cross it it means that I'm going toward a higher electrical potential and the potential difference
is given by Ohm's law.
Move toward high means the difference is going to be positive in ohms law tells me the magnitude of
that difference five times I won.
The next thing I encounter is that three ohm resistance.
And again I'm moving toward a higher electrical potential.
So I get plus three.
I one that's the voltage gain across that three ohm resistance when I'm traveling in this direction.
Know the last thing I encounter Now if I'm traveling in a counterclockwise fashion is this 12 volt battery
except now I'm crossing this MF and I'm going from a high toward low if I'm crossing from high to low
electrical potential and moving toward a lower electrical potential and I'm moving 12 volts lower and
that equals to zero.
You notice the difference between both of these equations is simply a negative sign.
If I multiply my equation down here my counter-clockwise equation by negative 1 I'm going to get minus
five I won minus three times I won plus 12 volts equals zero and noticed that's the exact same equation.
So you actually haven't changed any of the physics whether you go around clockwise or counter-clockwise.
The only thing you introduce as an overall negative sign which doesn't matter at the end.