All right I'm a firm believer that practice makes perfect.
So let's go ahead and practice this voltage law again for a couple more loops we draw the loop here
let's draw this one.
Let's maybe go through the 12 ohm resistor and then through the four and then come back down to Point
A.
So let's go ahead and apply the the the different rules so the first thing I'm going to encounter here
if I start at point A and I move around this region over here I'm going to encounter a MF and I go from
a low to a high potential which means I put plus 12 loops.
Try this again plus 12.
And next thing nothing happens.
I'm just going along the wire here.
The next thing I encounter is a 12 ohm resistor.
OK.
And I'm going in the direction of the current.
If you go in the direction of the current you are going from a high potential to a low electrical potential.
So there is a voltage drop across this resistor.
The voltage drop across this resistor is given by Ohm's law.
First of all to drop.
So we represent that with a negative sign and the magnitude of the drop now is 12 multiplied by the
current.
I for Okay great.
And the last case over here the next thing I encounter here is a 4 ohm resistor.
Again I'm going to get a voltage drop because I'm going from a high electrical potential toward a lower
electrical potential.
The magnitude of the voltage drop is four.
That's the value of the resistance multiplied by the current two.
That's the current flowing through this resistance.
Now I'm at this point in the circuit circuit I go all the way back to point a Kirchoff's voltage law
says if I do a complete loop that's equal to zero pretty good.
All right.
Maybe let's try one more case let's highlight maybe what if I do a different loop let's start from a
different point let's start from this junction over here and go around this tiny little loop.
What happens if I go around just this tiny little loop up here.
Well at the plier rules right.
The only thing I'm going to encounter here are resistors.
So the first thing I encounter if I go around in a counter-clockwise fashion the first thing I encounter
is a 12 ohm resistor and I'm going in the direction of the current I4 which means I'm going from a high
to a low electrical potential so that the voltage drop the voltage drop is given by ohms law and the
voltage drop is minus 12 multiplied by 4.
Notice it's the same term is what I had my previous equation.
All right then what do I do.
I'm just going at the top and now I'm going to cross a six ohm resistor and I'm crossing a resistor
but I'm going from a low to a high electrical potential because I'm going in the opposite direction
of the current.
So this means years of voltage gain and that's given by Ohm's law which is six multiplied by the current
three and that there is equal to zero.
So that said See I have two equations here.
They introduce different values of the currents because there is different voltage drops or voltage
gains depending on the direction and depending which resistor that I'm looking at.
But C.M. able to set up a series of equations.
Now the equation one here is equation 2 I can also do another loop which could include other combinations
of resistors and introduce the current I want if I wanted to.
OK so I have different methods now to introduce different values of the currents at the end the goal
is going to be to solve for these currents so they're going to be unknown's in our equations and we're
going to need to solve them.
We'll see how to do that in just a few minutes.