All right I now want to look at single tube circuits and a little bit more detail.
There's three basic questions you need to be able to answer about single loop circuits you need to be
able to find what is the current flowing in the circuit.
You need to be able to find what is the voltage difference between any two points on this circuit.
What's the voltage difference between points being point a point to see him Point A C and B.
Doesn't matter.
Pick any two points you should be able to tell me what is the voltage difference between both of those
points and the last one you need to be able to tell me what is the power being delivered to the circuit
and what is the power being dissipated so we're going to go through all three of these.
Let's start with the current.
Notice there's a singular right.
There's only a single current everywhere there's only a single branch by conservation of charge whatever
current flows here as to be the same current flowing through the resistance are A-one same current flowing
through resistance are to in order to solve for the current one that you can use is Kirchoff's voltage
law.
We can set up an equation start at a point some all the voltage differences across the different elements
when you do a complete loop.
Again the only difference is whether you choose to go clockwise or counter-clockwise but that that'll
be the same answer or you.
In this case we could also simplify this right we have two resistors that are in series with one another
and you can represent them by an equivalent five ohm resistor and you'll get at the end of the day to
the same answer.
So let's go ahead and show you how to do that.
So first way will use the Kirchoff's voltage law first thing we do is I start at point A and I'm going
to go around clockwise I cross a 10 mile battery I go from the low to the high.
That's it.
Next thing I cross a resistor in the direction of the current.
When you do that you get a voltage drop given by the value of the resistance multiplied by the current
flowing through it.
And then I'm going across a two resistor again to get a voltage drop because I'm crossing it in the
direction of the current So I'm going from a high to a lower voltage and the voltage drop is given by
two times.
I for this case.
Then I go all the way to where I started.
That's it.
So rearrange this you can group all of those terms you get minus five.
I at the end you get I then will simply be equal to ten.
Divided by five you get two amps.
So the current in the circuit here has to be equal to two.
It's the same everywhere.
Now if you would have represented this circuit by an equivalent resistance you could have done that
he would have been the battery tenable battery.
That's the same you would have had one single resistor.
Let's give it a different color here.
What it looks something like that.
And then I just close the circuit the value of the equivalent resistance in this case would have simply
been while you simply add both of these up there in series with each other.
So you would have had a 5 ohm equivalent resistance.
And now what you could do is you could apply the voltage Kirchoff's voltage law to this simple circuit
and when you do that it just looks like Ohm's law right because you get plus 10 for here you get plus
10 and then you get a voltage drop across this resistance.
Voltage drop is given by five multiplied by the current flowing through it.
You go back to where you start.
And yes look you get the exact same equation right.
You get I which equals the two amps at the end of the day.
Pretty straightforward.
All right.
So let me go ahead and kind of clean this up a little bit.
This doesn't really get us too far.
So I'm just going to delete this part.
I just want to show you how you complete that.
All right.
So now we know the current everywhere.
The next thing we want to do is how do you find the voltage differences everywhere.
So the voltage differences that I'm going to be interested in here are what is the potential difference
here between Point B and point a.
You might call that VB.
Mine is vitæ.
How do I get that guy to find the voltage differences between two points.
What you end up doing is you're just not doing a complete loop.
So we're going to start at point A.
So right now we're going to be at some potential and this term again you typically don't include it
when you do a full loop because at the end you end up having the same term on the left hand side and
on the right hand side and then it simply cancels out.
But in this case it's not going to cancel out because we're not doing a complete loop so we're going
to start here at some potential and then we're simply going to get all the way to point B OK.
So the first thing I encounter now is a battery.
And when I cross a battery now I'm going to get a plus 10 volts because I'm increasing in electrical
potential when I get there and that's it.
Then I go all the way to point B so I'm going to be at some potential vib once I get there.
So now you have to do is rearrange this equation.
If I rearrange this equation I get VB.
Mine is vitæ.
So this here is the difference of potential between both of those points that there would be equal to
10 volts.
So that's the potential difference between two points.
Now you can choose any two points.
What if I wanted VC mine is VB.
Let's go ahead and do that.
VC mine is VB.
Which one is that where you start now.
VB that is that some potential.
And now I'm going to go again I'm going to cross this three ohm resistance in the direction of the current
So I know there's a voltage drop.
The magnitude of the voltage drop is given by Ohm's law.
That's three multiplied by 2 6 volts and then that's equal to c.
All right so now you rearrange this equation you see that V C minus VB is equal to minus 6 volts this
equation tells me that point C is 6 volts lower then point B.
All right you can imagine that
voltage B is at 10 volts right.
If voltage B is at 10 volts take an example 10 volts right here.
That means that voltage C would be a negative six plus 10 volts would be at 4 volts.
That's what this equation here would tell me.
There are some six volts lower than point B.
Now let's go ahead and maybe find a difference between Point C and point the SO in that case I'm looking
for what is the voltage difference between VD.
Mine is Visi OK in order to find that one again you started Visi and now I get to travel toward point
V The first thing I have to cross is a two arm resistor.
I get a voltage drop given by two multiplied by two and then that's equal to VD rearrange this equation.
You're going to find a D mine v c is equal to minus four volts.
Again what that equation tells me that the point D is 4 volts lower than points C so VC is for Voltz
that means VD should be at zero volts.
Now you don't have to be consecutive points like this.
I can use the same technique to find what is the voltage difference between point A and Point C in that
case I'd be looking for visi.
Mine is V.A.
Again you start at point A.
So you're at some electrical potential.
And now there's two directions you can go you can either go through the battery and through this resistor
or you can go this way.
Let's first go through point B to head toward Point C.
First thing I encounter is tenable battery.
Next thing I encounter is this three ohm resistor.
I know there's a voltage drop of six volts across there and then that's equal to point C so you rearrange
this equation you see that Visi mine is V.A
simply equal to four volts the potential difference between point and point C is four volts.
You would have gotten the same answer now if you would have went this direction here.
You could check that out for yourself.
OK so last thing we had to figure out now is how you calculate the power.
OK so to calculate the power.
Well let's look at first the power being delivered the power being delivered is power being delivered
by this power supply in this case it's our 10 volt battery.
And in this case the power being delivered to a circuit is simply the MF multiplied by the current flowing
through that battery.
We calculated the current was two amps the value the IMF was 10 volts.
Simple calculation 10 multiplied by 2 gives me 20 watts
20 joules per second.
All right the next cases we want to look at what is the power being dissipated.
What happened in my piece here.
The power being dissipated Well there's two resistors.
So each one of those resistors will dissipate some energy per unit time.
So let's find First the power being dissipated by the 3 ohm resistor.
It's kind of the same equation right.
It's the voltage across that resistor multiplied by the current flowing through that resistor.
And a lot of times we write the equation somewhat differently we use Ohm's law just to maybe eliminate
the voltage and just replace it by the resistance and the current.
So you can do that.
So instead of voltage across that resistor Sometimes you just multiply it by the value of the resistance
are 1 times the current flowing through it.
And then you still have the current that goes into the power equation.
So this here simply ends up being R R R 1 I squared like this each equation gives you the exact same
answer it doesn't matter.
So let's maybe just use this one here at the end.
OK so the power being dissipated in the 3 ohm resistor is the value of the resistance which is three
multiplied by the current and just square that current.
So you get four multiply by three you get 12 watts
OK.
So that's our power being dissipated by this resistor.
And the last one we want to know what is the power being dissipated by the 2 ohm resistor in this case
it's the value of the resistance multiplied again by the current squared the same current through all
the different components since it's a single loop circuit.
So in this case do we get to multiply by two squared.
Oh give me four times two gives me eight watts.
One thing that should be evident to you is that the total power that's being delivered to the circuit
is actually equal to the total power being dissipated.
Right.
Both of these resistors dissipate energy per unit time and they dissipate energy at the same rate as
you put in energy into the system.
Right.
Twelve plus eight gives me 20 which equals to the power being delivered by that battery.
You're always going to find this in circuits.
OK.
So anyway those are the three questions that you really need to have a good handle on for single loops
circuits.
Hopefully this clears up some of the questions you had.