In this example here I have a network of three different capacitors.
And my goal is to calculate what is the total energy stored in all of the capacitors.
Okay.
Again it's connected to a 9 volt battery.
So what I would do for this problem right here is I would probably want to simplify this and if I can
somehow simplify this and replace it with one effective circuit with a 9 volt battery let's kind of
redraw it here.
If I can represent this complicated circuit with one capacitor except it's going to be one equivalent
capacitor which I'll have to use my rules in order to apply.
All right.
So I'd still have the same battery and over here this is going to be some equivalent capacitance of
this entire network.
And then this would be very easy to calculate how much energy is stored if I have this as the electrical
energy again if I know the capacitance it would just be one half CV squared.
And this here would be the equivalent capacitance in V would be 9 volts between the plates over there.
All right.
So let's see how we can simplify this network.
So I'm gonna do it in two stages.
The first thing I'm going to do is I'm going to simplify everything here in this dashed orange line
here what we have are two capacitors in parallel so if it's in parallel you remember the rule for the
equivalent capacitance.
So again it's only representing simplifying both of those.
The rule if they're in parallel.
Call the C equivalent one is going to be equal to.
You simply have to add them up right.
C one plus C two that is the rule if they're in parallel.
So in this case it's straightforward it's simply ten plus 40.
Again everything here is in microfiber Ed so I would get 50 micro fare add for the equivalent capacitance
of this.
So now what I have is I have a simplified circuit in which I have a capacitor like this and an equivalent
capacitor which I just calculated so I've simplified that considerably.
This one here is 50 micro Farad.
And the first one I haven't touched that one yet.
This one is still 20 micro fare.
It's still the same one is over here.
So now how would I simplify both of those.
Again this is really the last step right.
I want this circuit to represent it by this guy right here.
So how do I calculate the equivalent capacitance in this case.
This is the final value.
Again I'm going to use the rule because these are in series with each other.
So if I want to calculate the capacitance of two capacitance in series what I have to do is use the
other equation to one divided by the equivalent capacitance is one divided by twenty plus one divided
by 50.
Again everything here is in micro Feride.
All right.
To evaluate this what I'm going to do is just maybe put it on a common denominator.
A hundred is a common denominator.
So what I would do would be this would be five over one hundred plus two over one hundred.
All right.
So at the end this gives me seven over one hundred.
But again I remember I have to flip the fractions so see equivalent is 100 divided by seven.
You put that in the calculator you should get something that is roughly 14 micro Feride.
All right.
So that is the equivalent capacitance right here.
So that's it.
Now I know everything.
If I want to find the total energy one half the equivalent capacitance is 14.
And now I want to get a number in jewels so I will evaluate what the micro is.
And then the voltage in this case it's connected to a nine volt battery.
And I have to square that value.
All right again you put that in the calculator.
Let me go ahead and do that one.
A nine squared is eighty one in times while 14 e to the negative six and then multiplied by one half
I'm kind of doing it backwards here I get five point six seven
multiplied by ten to the negative four and that there is measured in Joules.
Here is the total energy.
And again it's electrical energy
stored in all of these three capacitors.
This is how much energy had to be supplied by this battery in order to charge these capacitors.