I now want to consider what happens when I play something between the plates of a capacitor in this
case let's just keep the discussion to parallel play capacitors on the material that I'm going to place
is something called a dielectric and that is just another word for an insulating material.
So it's not a conductor.
You don't want a conductor between the parallel plates because then the charge is just going to leave.
So you want the charge to remain there so it has to be a material that doesn't conduct electricity very
well.
One example of that is rubber.
You can have plastic paper wood.
Again things that are they don't let the Chargers move across.
All right.
Now if I consider just this simple case where I have some charge on each plate.
All right here's the illustration down here in the left figure and I have a way that I've measured the
voltage between those plates so I use a meter over here and I've charged the plates using a battery
and I get a certain reading on that dial the capacitance for this case again.
If it's just that parallel plate capacitor we looked at this equation before it's Epsilon 0 a divided
by D.
Now the question is what happens when I place this material inside.
Well there's always something that happens and the key is that the capacitance C always goes up whatever
number I get here when there's nothing between the plates.
When I play something between the plates the capacitance always increases it will never go down.
So let me write that down capacitance will increase
always.
So how much does it go.
Does it increase by.
Well it kind of depends on what you place in that between the parallel plates.
So all of these materials are rubber plastic wood.
Okay.
They're all characterized with something called a dielectric constant.
Let me highlight this point.
The dielectric constant is usually given by the letter K or Kappa and it is dimension less it's just
the number.
Okay so this dielectric constant I mean just write it as K Number One is it's always bigger equal to
one if it's air the capacitance sorry the dielectric constant for air is very very close to one.
So that's why it behaves just like this.
So when you place the dielectric constant between the plates the capacitance increases we said and the
new capacitance is given by this equation.
See when there is a dielectric inside is equal to the dielectric constant.
Again multiplied by the capacitance when there's nothing between the plates.
So I'm gonna call this C0 when there's nothing between the plates.
So the new capacitance is written as dielectric constant multiplied by the value of the capacitance
when it's air filled or nothing between the plates.
Ok so this is really the key equation and again that dielectric constant is always bigger than one.
Which means if I multiply this by the original capacities I'm always going to get something bigger.
OK.
So why is that.
And the other question is kind of what happens to the voltage between the plates.
You can see here if I kept everything connected and I have some charge between the plates.
Look what happened to the reading right.
We had a voltage drop over here right.
V went down a little bit.
It used to be at the maximum value.
Now it's kind of gone down a little bit and it's going to go down by the dielectric constant.
And to really understand this you really have to look at what's happening to that material when you
place it between the plates.
Again we talked about this before.
And again the atoms although they're neutral they can still spread out right the positives and the negatives
are going to go in different directions because there's an electric field inside that material.
So let me draw a kind of one big atom so we can see what's going to happen.
It was a neutral atom except the positive side's going to end up here.
And the electrons are going to end up closer to the positive plates.
So there's charged separation we say there is a polarization now.
So if you have a look at it now.
So we had a voltage between the plates.
However look what happens right we have the voltage which is due to both of those.
However now look what happens.
We also have some positive charges that are going to be close to those negatives.
It basically reduces the potential difference between the plates on this side here you got negatives
that are really close to the positive.
So they have some voltage between them.
So at the end the total voltage is going to end up dropping because you end up canceling out some of
these positive charges on the plates with the negative charges from the material that are really close
to it.
All right.
So the net voltage is always a voltage drop when I have charged plates and I stick something between
them.