And now I want to look at what happens in circuits where there's more than one capacitor.
So again we have our basic equation that q equals to the capacitance multiplied by the voltage and that's
fine if there is only one capacitor one voltage.
Right.
We want to find the charge on it but what happens now if there's two and they're connected one after
another.
We say that when they're connected in this way as shown in the figure that they are in series with one
OK.
So we'd like to be able to answer how much charge is there on each capacitor and also what is the voltage
between the plates.
Is the voltage the same.
OK.
Again let's assume that they're different.
They could be the same capacitance that'll be a limiting case but let's just assume that they're different.
We'll give them some values.
Let's give a battery a voltage and let's do the calculation.
Ideally what we want to be able to do is simplify complicated circuits that have more than one capacitor
into something that's simpler.
So I'm also going to show you how you can write this circuit here how you can represent it using a one
battery the same battery that's connected up here and instead of having two what we can do is just represent
this more complicated circuit by a simplified circuit.
And what I'm doing here is I'm going to produce an equivalent capacitance that is going to be equivalent
to both values like this.
So the value over here is not C1 or C2 but it's going to be some equivalent value of both combinations.
So let me show you how to do that and how to solve this problem once we have the problem boiled down
to a simple circuit like this.
Applying my capacitor equation is super easy right.
Says that the charge is equal to C equivalent multiplied by the voltage.
All right so let's go ahead set up the problem and let's see what's going on.
All right.
So here's the simple circuit I have a two capacitors.
These are the values I'm going to take.
C One is 10 micro Feride and C two is 40 micro Feride and the voltage is 10.
Again this is an example of capacitors in series.
So we have two questions What's the voltage across each plate.
So if I was going to kind of measure the voltage here across the first one this would be v 1 and if
I measure the voltage across the second one just do it a different color this here would be the voltage
V to.
If I measure the voltage across the battery I would get 10 volts I'm going to label these points over
here so let's call this point a maybe point B C and D.
OK so the voltage v 1 may just write this down v 1 is really the difference between A and B.
So it's kind of V A mine is VB the voltage across the second capacitor is really V C minus V.
D.
OK.
What else can we say.
Again this is just a wire a wires a piece of metal.
So actually we could say to the voltage across A B and C has to be the same right VB must be equal to
V see.
This is a wire it's an equity potential
same potential the wires.
So that means that whatever voltage I have at this positive terminal the battery has to be the same
voltage everywhere here.
So this is also positive whatever voltage I have at this negative has to be the same voltage everywhere
here because it's a piece of metal so it's that plate is negative.
Again if you imagine you're an electron anywhere here what you want to do when you see a positive terminal
the electrons want to go this way so that's going to leave this positive again.
Now imagine if this now becomes positive what is that going to do to any of the charges in the middle
section over there.
It's going to attract all the negative charges and it's gonna be the same amount of charge.
Now where are those charges come from.
They came from the other plate.
So again all the electrons left.
So this one's positive and again this side is going to be negative because it's the electrons are getting
repelled by this negative side of the battery all right.
So what we have here actually which is really really important which is a property for capacitors and
series only write it down it's really only four series for series we have to have that the charge on
capacitor Q One has to be equal to the charge on capacitor Q2 what we're gonna do here is really at
the end we're just gonna call this just give it one number since through the same just call it Q All
right so let's write down our expression than we have q 1 the charge on the first capacitor is the capacitance
C1 multiplied by the voltage V1 that's an equation what else we're gonna have.
Q Two is equal to C to multiply by v 2 We're just applying our capacitor equation here for each capacitor
that I could do this is kind of true for any capacitor but now there's this simplification because these
charges are all the same so actually we could just get rid of that and again that is only four series
that I'm able to do this all right what else can we do.
So we really have a couple unknowns over here all we know right now is the capacitance we don't know
the charge q we just know it's the same but we don't know the voltage across each one but there is something
that we do know we knew do know the voltage across this battery which means that actually the voltage
across the battery has to be the voltage across this one plus the voltage across that one because if
I'm over here and I want to go right across to the other side or I can either go through the battery
so I'd have a voltage difference of 10 volts.
In this case or I could go across both capacitors.
So actually you should be able to write this expression also so this is another equation.
This is v 1 plus the voltage across the v 2.
This here has to be equal to the voltage of the battery.
Let me just call it.
Let's just keep it as V that's fine.
All right.
So this is really the second equation.
So again we want to go back and what is the voltage across each capacitor again this is equation 2.
And these ones here are kind of equation 1.
All right so we have to combine both of these in order to get to a final expression.
So the way I'm gonna do that here is I'm going to eliminate V1 and V2 here and just have the charge.
So how would you get rid of V1 V1 you can write it as Q divided by C 1 and that's using this top equation
plus q divided by C 2 and that there has to be equal to V all right.
Now you can see we only have one unknown in this equation right here so I could factor out the Q we
do that it's going to look something like this.
Let's give myself a bit of space here.
I factor out the Q I'll open up kind of a big bracket and here I have one over C one plus one over C2
and this here equals to V the voltage across the battery.
All right the last thing all you have to do now is simply bring this curly bracket term on the other
side.
OK so the final expression that you get is that the charge q is equal to some number that looks like
this one over see one plus one over C2.
And this is to the negative one because I have to bring it to the denominator and multiplied by the
voltage.
You see this form of the equation here.
It looks very very similar to this one that the charged Q is proportional to the voltage across the
capacitor except the value over here this guy here is more complicated the more complicated because
there is more than one.
So actually it turns out that you're able to rewrite this circuit here and express it as a simple equivalence
circuit and the equivalent circuit looks like this it's still the same battery again.
And now we're going to have an equivalent capacitor
in the equivalent capacitance is represented by this Terminator over here.
So C equivalent is actually if there's two of them it's one over C one plus one over C two to the negative
one.
That is the equivalent capacitance and you see if I do that now I can rewrite the equation here as the
charged q equals to my equivalent capacitance multiplied by the voltage V
so if I have two capacitors in series with each other.
This is what the equation looks like all right we should be able to calculate all our values.
Now let's go ahead and do that.
So again I'm just going to make myself a little bit of space over here and let's go ahead and do that
so we can calculate what this equivalent capacitance is and then all I have to do is multiply that by
the voltage in order to get the charge Q Okay.
So let's do that over here so the charge q
is going to be equal.
I'll.
What is my equivalent capacitance that down over here.
So this is going to be one over 10 micro Farad.
I'll just keep it in micro Feride plus one over 40 micro Feride.
Again you could put the ten to the negative six terms if you want.
At the end it's just going to give me a value of micro fare.
And OK.
So how would you calculate this you have to put this on a common denominator this would be for over
40.
So at the end this term here would be five over 40 and so see equivalent at the end should be.
And I have to take the reciprocal of that should give me eight micro Farid.
So what you end up getting here is eight micro Feride eight times 10 to the negative six and multiplied
by the voltage multiplied by 10 so this simply becomes becomes 80 micro Coolum is the charge on each
plate
it's pretty straightforward.
So I mean is a charge on each one of these plates is 80 microcosms positive 80 on the first plate negative
80 on the second positive 80 over here negative Haiti micro cool homes on the last one.
All right.
How do you calculate the voltage now between each plate or their voltage across each plate I should
say.
Again all we have to do now is go back and examine both of those because we know the charge now on each
plate.
So really all we're doing now is just using our capacitor equation for each one individually.
Let me do that at the top.
This over a little bit.
OK.
So let's use the first equation define what is the voltage V1 V1 is equal to the charge q divided by
C1 it's 80 micro columns
80 times 10 to the negative 6 and divided by 10 times ten to the negative six gives me eight volts.
So V1 over here should be equal to eight volts the voltage across the second one again I know that I
have to have ten across here and if I've already gone down two volts when I cross over here it means
there's only two volts left over here.
This guy here better be equal to two volts you see that from equation to right.
If this is eight and this is ten.
This here has to be two volts.
Well we could also use the equation right.
The second equation right here if we apply it to that capacitor is v 2 equals the charge across the
plate and the charge on the plates divided by the capacitance okay.
Here we have 80 micro Feride micro cool on having trouble today and the capacitance C2 was 40 micro
Feride at the end you could see this gives me 2 volts if I use this equation or if I use equation 2
Over here I'm also gonna get two volts.
OK so a couple of important things.
Let's look at the equivalent capacitance if I have more than two let's get a general expression.
Okay.
And just highlight again the key things to capacitors in series.
Notice that we get a bigger voltage drop across the one with the smallest capacitance you get the smaller
voltage drop across the object with the largest capacitance.
Okay so let's highlight some of those properties for capacitors in series.