All right I want to now look at a different way of connecting to capacitors again.
We're gonna have the same voltage 10 volts same two capacitors except now we've connected them slightly
differently I've defined some points A B that's points on different sides of the plates for capacitor
C one and point C and D are just on both sides of capacitor C two again the same questions we would
have how much charges on each capacitor.
So what is kind of Q1 what is Q2 again what is the voltage across the first capacitor and what is the
voltage across the second capacitor how do we use our equations.
So the first thing to notice is that this is what we say.
This is a parallel configuration here in parallel because it's actually different wires right.
There's different parts for each capacitor.
They're connected by a different wire.
They're not one right after another.
So we say that these are in parallel with each other.
You can see they kind of form parallel lines depending on how you draw them.
So what we can do is for each capacitor is we can write down our equation.
We can write that the charge on this first one has to be equal to see one multiplied by V1 you have
to have this charge on Q2 capacitors C2 is Q Q2 and that has to be equal to the value of the capacitor
multiplied by V.
We're going to take the same values here we just want to see what's the difference between both cases.
So this is kind of really equation 1.
And although there's two equations here again both of these expressions have to be true.
So all I know right now is I know the value of C1 and C2 So what happens now.
What about the voltage across each capacitor.
OK so this case is a little bit different.
So in this case here the voltage across each capacitor v 1 has to be equal to V 2 and also has to be
equal to V the voltage across the battery.
Again this is a wire this whole side here is connected to the positive terminal of the battery which
means this is all an equity potential it's a complicated looking conductor.
There's a plate here there's a plate here but again they're all connected over here.
Likewise on this side.
Right.
If this is at a negative voltage.
Everything here has to be at the same negative voltage so you have to have the same positive voltage
everywhere here.
Same negative voltage as the battery for each case.
All right.
And this is true if they're in parallel with each other you'll always have the same voltage across parallel
branches all right.
So now we can actually calculate how much charge there is on each plate because I know the value of
the capacitance and I also know that the voltage now is going to be 10 volts.
So right away you can go back to my first equations this year would be ten times tend to the negative
six fair add multiplied by 10.
So I would have I'm just gonna write this as one hundred again micro Q Long How about on the second
one you have 40 TIMES 10 TO THE NEGATIVE six and multiplied by again ten volts means you have to have
400 micro columns okay and the voltage is going to be ten for each one.
So V1 is 10 volts the two is equal to 10 volts and that's it you're all done for this one.
Actually the other thing we could do though is represent this using an equivalent circuit.
Nice thing about equivalent circuits is they're simpler.
So again we're gonna use the same battery and I'm going to represent it now using a different capacitor
that I want to simplify to and just represented as one equivalent capacitor the way that you do this
now is through this.
So the equivalent capacitor is C equivalent and the value now is basically simply going to be the sum
of both of them it's a different equation so in this case it's simply C one plus C two.
So in this example here it would be 10 micro Farad plus 40 micro Feride so C equivalent would give me
50 micro ferret.
What would be the charge now on this equivalent capacitor in the formula I would use for the charge
on the equivalent capacitor would be C equivalent multiplied by the voltage.
This is still 10 volts right here so the voltage across this capacitor has to be 10 volts at the end.
If you substitute both of this in you're gonna get 50 micro grow by 10.
You're going to get 500 micro cooling.
It's actually what we're doing right here is we're simplifying this or representing kind of both of
these plates here kind of combining them together.
And we're the same thing on the other side.
On the other side we're kind of combining both of those together.
If I combine both of those imagine they have the same area and I stick them right next to each other.
So this one has a bit of charge.
This one however has a bit of charge.
The total charge that you end up getting on this plate right here.
I would read it as something like this that the total charge is equal to Q1 plus Q2 and we calculated
both of those you could see that the number I just calculated using the equivalent capacitor is 500
micro cooling.
And again that's the number I would get if I would sum up the charges from each one one hundred micro
cool on plus 400 micro cooling gives me 500 micro cooling.
So again the key point for capacitors in parallel the voltage is the same that's really the key.
If you want to represent it using an equivalent capacitor all you have to do is you simply have to sum
up the different values.
If there's three of them that are in parallel with each other I would simply add another term over here
to calculate the charge on each one.
Again since the voltage is the same it's pretty straightforward if you know the values in the last part
is that my equivalent capacitor has a total charge equal to Q1 plus Q2.