Since the times of ancient Greece, natural philosophers inquired into the physical nature of light,
what really is light?
Where does it come from?
How is it emitted and absorbed?
And one of the most challenging sets set of questions that has kept many bright minds up to nowadays
was the question, what is it like made of?
Is it made of light particles as water waves are made of H2O molecules or is it the wave?
If it is a wave, then a wave made of what?
And traveling through what?
Or is it both a wave and a particle or is it something entirely different?
Many questions with almost no answer.
I Stotler declared that the essence of light is white color and colors are made up of a mixture of lightness
and darkness.
Well, considering this in retrospect, it was not a bad guess.
Interestingly, the idea of light being made of a mixture of lightness and darkness was taken up much
later by Johann Wolfgang Frogurt, a German writer, poet and natural philosopher living in the 18th
century.
And Gerta because Guta constructed a theory of light that indeed works.
Most physicists don't know that because they probably would never have heard of that, because nowadays
you don't learn about these things.
But in fact, it's interesting really that the three colors of Guta is in fact a theory that explains,
well, the phenomenon of colors.
In fact, he conceived light as not being something fundamental, but something that emerges from a
so-called primordial phenomenon from the German word.
Philomene means primordial phenomenon.
And this primordial phenomenon can be observed, according to Gerta, at the boundary between light
and darkness.
In this conception, cholera's never arise by light alone, but they arise as a consequence of a dark
and light or if you wish, or a black and white contrast at boundaries, edges, slits.
A quite interesting theory in its own little now this could not be disproven and it is in principle
still valid.
I would recommend everyone interested in the history and philosophy of science to take a look at KURTAS
approach.
It might still have something to teach us.
It explains light, darkness and colors from a qualitative standpoint and in some respect could be considered
as a complementary understanding to the modern physical quantitative approach.
However good the theory of callers being, a purely qualitative theory can't make quantitative predictions
as a modern quantitative science, as physics needs to be able to do.
It was a contemporary of Gerta Sir Isaac Newton, and that everyone, everybody knows, or at least
should have heard about the famous English physicist, mathematician and astronomer better known for
his law of universal gravitation, who was able to separate white light into its colored components
using an optical prism.
More relevant for our purpose was Newton's light particle theory.
Accordingly, light was seen as a flux of colored particles at the time.
This was not much more than speculation.
It was not a real understanding coming from a conclusive investigation.
In fact, Christian Harrigan's, a Dutch mathematician, physicist and also astronomer, did not share
Newton's idea and stated the contrary that light is a wave.
For a long time, there was a heated debate regarding who theory was correct.
In fact, it was difficult to imagine light as made of particles and at the same time as being a wave,
one or the other theory must be true.
Both theories being true at the same time was considered to be a logical impossibility.
In 18 03, a groundbreaking discovery settled the issue for at least a century, Tomas Young, an English
physician, performed a revolutionary experiment, the well-known double slit experiment.
He first showed that when light is emitted by a point source and is directed through a card with two
tiny nearby nearby pinholes, a colored interference pattern appears on a screen positioned at an appropriate
distance on the other side of the card with the pinholes.
Later, the same experiment was performed with two slits instead of pinholes.
How waves add or subtract at each other resulting in an interference pattern was something that already
was well known and accurately studied with mechanical ways, typically oscillating pendulums or water
waves.
Since light exhibits exactly the same characteristic behavior in the double slit experiment, this seemed
to finally prove the wave theory of light versus against the particle interpretation beyond any reasonable
doubt.
Then further insights on the nature of light came from the works of James Clark Maxwell, a Scottish
theoretical physicist who predicted the access, the existence of electromagnetic waves, Maxwell equations,
which are the mathematical foundation for modern electromagnetism.
I set off four elegant equations that are very general Anholt for electromagnetic waves in general,
the connection between light and electricity as magnetic phenomenon became clear as an obvious consequence
of the fact that it was shown how electric and magnetic fields propagate with exactly the same speed
of light.
So the issue seemed to have been settled once and for all.
Lt must be an oscillating electric and magnetic field propagating throughout space like a wave.
This wisdom was accepted as an almost final and undeniable fact for a lot of time.
Only one problem remained open.
What is the medium through which light is supposed to travel, water waves, sound waves or material
waves you suspect respectively, water, air or a solid body as a support through which they can propagate
without water or air or metal in some form, there could be no transmission of waves at all.
That's.
Almost intuitive, however, since light can travel also through empty space, this led naturally to
the question of empty space is made of some subtle yet unknown so-called nefarious ether that could
function as a medium for electromagnetic waves.
Also, the.
These ruminations kept the young Albert Einstein busy while he was working in a Swiss patent office
and led him to his famous theory of relativity.
He simply posed that there is no ether at all.
Without even knowing that this was already shown experimentally at this time at the time, Andrew,
from that the conclusions that made him world famous, the theory of special relativity.
The idea that empty space is not made of some immaterial substance that offers light a transmission
medium holds until today and does no longer cause much debate, even if it's a bit and an anti intuitive,
I would say, whereas as we shall see, our image of light being a wave and not a flux of particles
will turn out to be in need of much further and deeper clarification and analysis before continuing
in our historical analysis of the development of the nature of light.
It is necessary now to introduce an interlude that sets the conceptual foundations we will need throughout
this course.
Nothing can be said in quantum physics if we do not have a clear and rigorous understanding of how waves
and their characteristic interference phenomena are described in physics.