Another nice and clear cut piece of experimental evidence that atoms must have discrete energy levels
came only a year later after Bors proposal of his atomic model.
It was the so-called truncates experiment.
Gustaaf Lutwyche Katz was the nephew of Childhood of Hats, the German physicist we already mentioned
as the discovery of the photoelectric effect, while high likelihood of health, among other things,
prove the existence of electromagnetic waves.
Gustaaf Ludwick Earth and James Frank, where we were awarded the 1925 Nobel Prize in physics for what
the Nobel Committee expressed as their discovery of the laws governing the impact of an electron upon
an atom.
And they did so using the experiment we are going to describe now.
The experimental setup is this one, it consists of Macary gas atoms.
Inside a low pressure bulb, an electric cathode that is something like the heated filament of a light
bulb and which emits electrons.
Therefore, this part of the device emits not only light, but also negatively charged particles and
electric field is applied between the electron emitting cathode and a positively poled creating.
With a battery or some other electric source which builds up an electric potential.
Due to their negative charge, this difference in the electric potential field leads to the electrons
acceleration and conveys to them some kinetic energy, as you might recall, from school charges with
the same polarity repel each other, whereas those with opposite opposite polarity attracted to each
other when the electrons reached reached the grating, most of them will fly through because the mesh
of the grating is kept sufficiently wide to allow for that.
This first part functioned as a little electronic accelerator.
Then between the grating and a collecting plate on the right side, another field is applied.
But in this second part of their journey of the electrons flying through the gas they will experience
and inversely polarized electric field, since after passing the grating, they will be repelled because
they will begin to feel, so to speak, that negatively charged collecting plate.
This means that by using an amp meter and ampere meter, a device which measures measures the electric
current, that is the flux of electrons between the grating and the collecting plate, it is possible
to measure also the changes of the electrons energy and establish how their energy is affected by the
atoms while flying through the gas and the second part of the bulb.
Frank and had the idea was that while flying through the gas of atoms, several electrons must sooner
or later hit one or more atoms, mercury atoms, and be scattered either elastically or in elastically.
Elastic scattering means that when an object hit a target, they change course, but maintain the same
kinetic energy while.
I inelastic scattering implies that they lose part or all their kinetic energy in the collision process.
It follows that there must be a measurable difference between the energy of the injected electrons reaching
the grating.
And that of those which flew through the gas, hitting the collecting plate and which is then made clear
to the observer by the measurement of the current between the grating and the collecting plate.
It is this energy gap which tells us something about the energy absorbed by the atoms in the gas.
Therefore, if atoms absorb energy only in the form of Quanta, this implies that while we slowly increase
the kinetic energy of the injected electric electrons, we should be able to observe when, when and
to what degree.
The electrons are absorbed by the gas of mercury atoms.
This is indeed what happens as can and can be observed in the following graph.
Why they injected electrons, kinetic energy is increased steadily by applying an electric potential
from zero to about 15 volts between the cathode and the grating, the horizontal axis here, the current
of the electrons measured at the collecting plate.
Given on the vertical axis increases accordingly, but not in a linear fashion, we observed that the
electrons do not have a finer kinetic energy which increases proportionally to the electrons input energy
according to what one would expect for an elastic scattering between classical objects.
Think, for example, billiard balls.
What we see instead is that at first between zero and four volts, the relation between the input and
output on energy is more or less approximately linear, which means that the electrons are scattered
through the gas elastically.
They do not lose considerable kinetic energy.
But at about four point 4.5 volts, the first bump appears between four and five volts, the output
energy of the electrons decreases steadily despite their increasing initial energy.
This signals and inelastic scattering some of the energy the electrons had initially must have been
suddenly absorbed in the collision with the head with mercury atoms, but this does not happen before
a certain kinetic energy energy threshold of the electrons hitting the mercury atoms at about five point
eight volts.
Almost all of the kinetic energy is lost and goes into the internal excitation of the atoms.
There is, however, a remaining minimum energy gap which is shown in the figure with the vertical red
arrow here.
The difference between the first pick and the first minimum is the maximum amount of kinetic energy
the atoms are able to absorb from the electrons and therefore furnishes us the first excited energy
level of the mercury atom.
Then after about six to nine volts, the energy begins to increase again, meaning that the atoms absorb
only the that aforementioned discrete amount of the electrons energy, but not more than that.
The remaining energy goes again into elastics shattering.
As you can see, all this repeats regularly at about nine to 10 balls and about 14 balls.
The existence of these bumps, so to speak, at different input energies, means that atoms must have
several different but discrete energy levels.
Frankfurt's experiment was the first direct experimental proof, confirming Blank's idea that matter
absorbs energy in discrete quanta.
Moreover, this also validated the discrete spectral lines of light spectra, as did Borse idea to represent
the atoms in the form of a model which resembles a tiny solar system that is with electrons moving only
on specific orbits with their respective quantum numbers, which represent different but precise and
discrete energy levels.