We are now in a position to analyze the phenomenon of interference in real world physical phenomena.
We can begin with a classical example.
That is what one observes in the so-called thin film interference.
This will open up the way for us to understand the friction and the wave particle duality in this figure.
You can see a couple of light rays with a certain angle of incidence reflected by a thin film surface.
This thin film surface could be, for example, made of water or the mixing of oil and water on the
road, as you may have observed, probably on a street after a rainstorm or as in this photograph here,
that of a soap bubble.
The nice colouring of oil firms, or as we enjoyed as kids on soap bubbles, is an interference phenomenon
that can be explained as follows.
These films have a very small but not negligible thickness limited by an upper layer and lower layer.
The reflection of light onto these layers can be visualized as a first beam beam.
A light goes unperturbed through the Appalachians and will be reflected by the lower layer of the film.
And then there is also the second beam beam B, which is reflected by the upper layer.
If we examine the situation carefully, it is easy to recognize that there is a difference in the travelled
path between the two light rays, even if both both light rays are emitted at the same time from the
same source and arrive with the same angle.
That is, they are parallel to each others.
When the reach that reach the two thin film layers, they are reflected at different depths and therefore
acquire a different.
Small hour, as you can see here, that is a face difference relative to each others, their little
yellow segment of length L is given here.
You can see here the two beams then sum up and superimpose or overlay after the reflection, interfering
according to their face difference.
This phase difference is determined only by the incident angle once the thickness of the film and its
refractive index are fixed.
This implies that the outgoing light can interfere constructively or destructively or somewhere in between
for every specific reflection angle.
We will observe different resulting waves in intensity and wave length along the different angular positions
where we place our eyes or our detector.
And this is also why we can observe all the beautiful plurality of color patterns on the surface of
a soap bubble.
The same thing from interference does not only work with water layers in visible light, but also for
atomic crystal lattice layers at the X-ray wavelength.
In this case, we need very short electro magnetic wavelengths because the distances that separate the
different atomic crystalline layers, also called crystallography planes are very small.
They are of the order of few atomic sizes.
Obviously, at these wavelengths we will no longer deal with color patterns since x rays are well beyond
the human visible light spectrum.
But the underlying principle remains the same.
More precisely at the atomic scale, we can no longer speak of classical reflections on a surface layer,
but must conceive of the photons or waves absorbed by the atom and then readmitted in all directions
in the form of spherical waves.
All these spherical wavefront then sum up and form an interference pattern somewhere.
For example, on a screen.
In fact, in 1913, William Henry Bragg senior and William Lawrence Bragg, junior to British physicist,
discovered how crystalline solids produced pattern of reflected X-rays that could be interpreted only
as interference patterns and which are nowadays called brekke diffraction patterns.
They observed intense maximum M.A of reflected radiation, depending on the wavelength and and the angle
of incidence, something which could not be observed for reflect the radiation of a longer wavelength.
Here again, two incident parallel light beams will be reflected by two underlying crystallography planes
as shown in this figure.
There are essentially three physical variables that determine how the beams will be refracted and interfere.
That is how the outgoing waves will display their relative phase shift, which gives rise to the interference
pattern.
First, all depends from the wavelength of the electromagnetic waves lambda.
Then what determines the phase shift induced by the difference is also the distance the which separates
the atomic layers.
This causes a path difference.
The short red wave is segment in this figure and consentual and consequently a phase difference between
the two emerging beams.
Finally, we must also choose the angle of incidence or equivalent, equivalently, the scattering angle.
Peter.
Or two times the angle, which in any case tells us from what point of view, from which angle we are
looking at the reflected wave.
The appropriate combination of these three parameters will give rise to constructive or destructive
interference once we have chosen some material with some specific chemical composition, the crystal
lattice layers distance the is fixed.
If we maintain the wavelength of our X-ray source as constant, then also the wavelength lambda is fixed
as well.
This means that if we observe the outgoing interfering waves at different angles, then we will see
constructive interference or also destructive interference due to the fact that they correspond to different
parts of the light beams.
That is the phase difference given rise to the respective constructive or destructive interference.
In fact, if you look at the graph on the left, you can see that the waves interfere and overlap in
such a manner according to some specific angle, so that they the two peaks and valleys, so to speak,
of the waves add up and therefore we have constructive interference.
Whereas on the other side, when we have the situation given in the right picture, you can see that
at that at another at another angle, the two waves overlap in such a manner that the peaks and valleys
overlap, not peak peak Valley Valley, but Peak Valley Valley peak, and which means that they subtract
each others and we have destructive interference.
In truth, this is a simplified model, since in practice also the other planes will contribute to the
overall effect, even though to a lesser degree, and these will cause also many more small peaks and
complex diffraction and interference patterns.
But for our purposes here, this may suffer suffice to understand the principle of the fracture.
If you are still struggling with the notions of what the face of a wave is, the amplitude and so on,
I again invite you to go through the appendix lecture lecture where all these conceptual mathematical
foundations we need in this course are quickly summarized.
So this distraction and interference phenomenon can be described with Bragg's law and which tells us
what the conditions for constructive interference from successive crystallography complaints are and
which is given by this formula and times lambda equals two times the times the cosmic sine function
of theta where N is an integer number one, two, three, four, five and so on.
And obviously the angle theta, the angle of incidence and the the distance between the atomic planes
and this formula will tell us where the máxima will occur.
If we look at different scattering angles at the same time, for example, on the screen of a photographic
plate or a CCD sensor or some detector that is able to to detect the photons coming onto.
An extensive surface placed in such a manner that they let these sensors or these detectors able to
capture several beams with several angles throughout a surface, then we will observe a very interesting
diffraction pattern as, for example, in this picture.
Here we have a beautiful, symmetric pattern obtained by X-ray interference through a crystal from these
patterns, physicists and chemists are able to interfere with the crystalline atomic structure of substances.
Therefore, brak diffraction is something that allows us to reconstruct the the geometrical displacement
of atoms in the lattices.
In some sense, we might say that it is like a microscope that furnishes indirectly images of the chemical
structure of substances.
Now, you might question what what does this have to do with quantum mechanics, after all?
Well, it has a lot to do with it.
First of all, it is necessary to get rid of a frequent misconception since at a microscopic scale,
the double slit experiment displays light as a wave, while the photoelectric and the Compton effect
vindicate the particle nature of light in a microscopic domain, one might be tempted to believe that
microscopically light is in fact the particle.
In the sense that it might appear and behave like a wave only at human scales, we're looking at it
closely at the scale of molecules, atoms and particles, it is revealed to be a particle, just like
a water wave is microscopically made of tiny H2O water molecules, not so bright.
Diffraction and interference phenomena act at the size of an atomic crystal lattice layer and cannot
be explained.
With classical particle behavior only considering light as a wave, Bragg's father and son could explain
the observed phenomena just like Young could.
With the double slit experiment, Young would have been delighted to see the wave nature of light confirmed
also at the microscopic scale.
But there is much more.
One question that must arise at this point is whether this ambiguous, twofold wave particle manifestation
is something in here and only to light.
Or is it a Zemmour, since it seems to present itself as a wave or a flux of particles according to
what kind of experimental set up one chooses us, then the question arises is, does this duality possibly
hold also for material particles with the mass like electrons or protons?
It might sound unreasonable and terribly counterintuitive even to think of material particles like an
electron and what we imagine as a tiny chunk of metal, a point like particle, to behave like a wave,
as photons do, but then an attempt to put things together under the same umbrella came from the French
physicist Lui's, the parolee who was able to synthesize in a unique theoretical concept the point like
the corpuscular and the wavy nature into a single notion.
They probably realized that.
There is no logical and physical reason to believe that material particles with a mass could not have
this double corpuscular and wavy nature as well, no more or less than photons.
He imagined all the particles, also those those which make up the objects like atoms, molecules and
very material body, very material bodies in the universe, no longer as particles or waves, but as
something which contains conceptually both of these.
That is the so-called wave packett.
This was the famous library hypothesis he framed in 1924.
The idea was that to imagine every object being a travelling wave, but with a special property of being
localized in space like this, like you see in this animation.
If we see things in this perspective, we we can consider any particle with or without mass as having
a specific wavelength with the amplitude of the wave having a maximum in a region of space and which
we intuitively think of as being classically the position of the particle.
But with this amplitude decaying quickly from the center of the peak in all directions.
Here to arbitrary examples of waste packets are shown on the left, a broader wave packet and on the
right, a smaller one which differ in their wavelength.
If you look at these wave packets from large distances compared to their wavelength, say, from 20
or 30 meters, in this example, you can approximately consider them particles.
Since it's Swabi, nature is no longer discernible.
If we look at the wave packet at distances of the order of the wave length, however, or smaller wave
length, it appears to be a wave.
In this sense, we may speak of the wave length of a particle.
An expression which otherwise in the classical context would have resulted as nonsensical.
A gentle warning is compulsory here, one might be tempted to interpret the size of the wave packet
as the size of the particle or the object under consideration.
However, we shall see that this intuitive understanding is not correct for the time being.
Just take the wave packet for what it is a mathematical abstract construct that saves appearances,
so to speak.
That is that it explains.
Well, the observed four phenomena of the experiments liberally also quantified all this with a very
simple and neat formula which relates the wavelength lambda of a particle or more precisely, the wavelength
of its corresponding wave packet as being inversely proportional to its momentum.
P.
That is lamda equals H over p h, of course, as usual, the plank's constant and P is the momentum
of a particle which in classical mechanics is always given as the product of the mass of the particle
times its velocity.
V.
The right hand side, the right hand side part of the of this equation holds only four material particles
with a non-zero mass and is correct only if we can ignore relativistic relativistic effects, whereas
the term H over P is more general and has a universal validity for photons.
As for material particles and is also exact also in relativity, it associates a wavelength to any kind
of particle independently if it has a mass or not.
If it is a mass, it can be also an electron or proton or neutron.
In this case, its wavelength, which we associate with this material particles, is given by the relation
of the early.
This can be shown with a not too rigorous proof, which highlights where this equation comes from.
First of all, set, uh, in science, math and education, we know that the energy contained in a particle
of mass M is given by E equal M times C squared as C is, as usual, the speed of light.
From which follows that the math can be written as M. equal.
E over C squared.
And recalling again that the momentum of a particle is a product of its mass times, its velocity.
Then if we take seriously the idea to put photons and material particles on the same footing, we can
replace the mess and the above equation with the letter expression and the speed with that of light,
that is with the equal C to obtain P of the photon.
Equal to oversee.
This expresses the momentum of a photon of energy.
Photons.
As all other particles are able to carry and transmit certain amounts of momentum to other particles,
recall how photons, even if we do not visualize them as material particles, are nevertheless able
to give, so to speak, a kick to a material particle, as we already saw in the case of the Compton
scattering.
Now, recall also that the ever present blank formula in the form of equal age times known with.
Lou, the frequency and which is given, which can be written also as age times, sea of alarm, that
since know the frequency is nothing else, that the speed of light divided its wavelength.
Rewriting all this in terms of lamda, one obtains lamda equals H over.
You oversee this record here, and we said he oversees nothing else than the momentum of the photon,
therefore we can write this righteous also as H of a P, which is finally the the bearly relation.
This proves, in fact, the relation.
So what they really did was that to put together the concept, the concept of the wave and particle
into a single entity, the wave pacard, the wave length of the wave length of which is determined by
its momentum.
In case of material particles, that is not photons, but particles having a mass movings, Lola, is
lower than the speed of light.
It is customary to speak also of metal waves because we associate to every material particle wave.
So we speak of meter waves.
The meter wave of the Dibley hypothesis sheds also some light now on boards atomic model.
In fact, if we understand the electrons not as tiny localised point like particles which orbit around
the atomic nucleus, but as matter waves, that is waves distributed which are distributed concentrically
around the orbit, it becomes quite easy and intuitive to understand why the energy levels of atoms
must be quantized.
They must have discrete levels for the simple reason that if this matter wave has a wavelength which
does not match and not reconnect itself again at the same point along the orbital path.
See, for example, in this diagram, that is if the circumference of the atomic orbit of the electron.
Is not exactly an integral intergovernment multiple of the electrons wavelength, then constructive
interference with itself would no longer be possible and the wave packet distributed around the atomic
nucleus could not be built up as a standing wave structure, which would be like the standing wave we
already discussed, for example, the body cavity.
Here, the principle is the same, but instead of reflections of wave of a wave on a cavity wall, the
wave circulates along an atomic orbit and path and for the same reason allows only for specific oscillating
modes to exist.
The classical notion of orbital velocity of the electron around the nucleus is fixed by the fact that
the electrostatic, attractive forces between the positive electric charge of the nucleus and that of
the negative electron must be balanced by what we may, loosely speaking, call the centrifugal forces
to keep the electron in orbit.
And this, in turn, is given also by its distance from the nucleus.
But this distance cannot be an arbitrary one.
The velocity of the electron that is due to the liberalise relation, the wavelength of the electron
must match just the orbital distance where constructive interference occurs and is equal to just the
speed, which is enough to keep the electron on a circle.
Circular, stable orbit.
It is possible to calculate this in and indeed it turns out that the electron will distribute itself
naturally only on a well-defined, discrete orbit where we have this constructive interference for the
simple case of the hydrogen atom.
This can be calculated with relatively simple algebra and classical classical physics concept, plus
the devilry relation.
And it turns out that indeed only those matter standing waves are allowed to exist, which match the
quantized energy levels experimentally observed in the hydrogen atom atomic spectrum.
Both atomic model added with the Braly hypothesis seemed therefore to gain credibility credibility,
since it explained naturally why atomic levels are quantized.
Unfortunately, as we already pointed out, still, in any case, this does not explain the spectra
of all the other elements.
Nevertheless, also if we use the debris relation.
But in any case, this debris relation shed some light.
Why the atomic spectra must must be discrete levels of energy and must be must express them.
So that must manifest with.
Emission and absorption of.
Discreet packets and quanta of energy.
So go back to break the friction and clarify what we really mean by meter waves, since we can conceive
material particles as, for instance, electrons also as meter waves as we think of light waves.
And since we observed the breath diffraction for electromagnetic waves, as was shown for photons in
the case of the X-ray spectrum, the question at this point is if the Bradley fraction might hold equally
well also for material particles.
Is it conceivable that also tiny chunks of matter like electrons, neutrons, protons or whatever massive
particles can be distracted by the letters of a crystalline substance and display the nice interference
patterns as observed with x rays?
This is a question.
To check this idea, one must send no longer photons, but material particles, say electrons or neutrons
into the crystal lattice by modulating its energy.
That is its momentum, which finally means its speed.
Because this is what determines its wavelength according to the degree the relation in effect, by doing
so, one modulates according to the brain and also its wavelength.
So if the wavelength of the wave packet of the material particle matches more or less, the size of
the crystallography explains separation of the substance which is bombarded with these particles, then
one should expect to observe again, also in this case, the interference patterns.
This experiment in 1927 by the American physicist Lester Girma and Clinton Davisson and independently,
independently also by the British physicist George Thompson.
Passing a beam of electrons through a thin film of metal.
They observed how electrons are subjected exactly to the same interference law that photons are.
What they found were indeed the bread diffraction pattern like those we have seen already before for
the X-ray diffraction patterns.
So the point is also what we imagine to be rock solid chunks of matter when subjected to appropriate
physical conditions display a wavelike nature.
This was also an experimental verification of the debris debris hypothesis, which at this point was
no longer a hypothesis at all, but an experimental fact.
The interference pattern observed corresponded exactly to those expected.
If we adopt the debris relation, this is a universal property of nature, which, however, is not
at all if because from the abstract mathematical point of view, everything is clear and is nicely quantified
and experimentally measured, quantified by the formula.
And we can in fact empirically control that it works.
But from the more ontology, ontological perspective, from the more philosophical perspective, things
are not that clear.
The question is, what are the these particles we are talking about or are they only point like particles
or waves or matter waves are or what?
Are they at the microscopic level?
It is here that the philosophical journey of quantum mechanics began, and this led then to the famous
wave particle duality, the uncertainty principle of Heisenberg, the concepts of the wavefunction,
etc., as we are going now to describe in the next lecture's.