Almost everyone has sooner or later heard something about the famous wave particle duality, so much
has been said about it and so many misconceptions surround it.
One of the most frequent misconceptions is that which sounds more or less as follows.
A particle can be sometimes a wave or a particle, depending on the observer.
Apart from the fact that similar phrases, similar statements are already self-contradictory statements,
if a particle acts as a wave, it is not a particle in the first place.
That is why some physicists would like to eliminate altogether from textbooks any reference to dualities.
But one of the aims of this course is to debunk the observer myth in quantum physics, know quantum
phenomena needs a human mind or human consciousness observing anything, and there is no particle transmutations
in the sense that our naive intuition tends to suggest.
It is no coincidence that we intentionally introduced it somewhat later, dwelling first into a historical
and conceptual introduction in order to furnish you the premises to understand the deeper meaning and
implications of the wave particle duality, as also in the next lecture, Heisenberg's principle, uncertainty
principle.
We have seen that photons, and especially in the case of observable light, can behave either as waves
or as particles according to the context and the experimental arrangement.
For instance, the photoelectric effect or the content effect gives one answer and the double slit experiment
and break the fraction, give the opposite answer.
In the latter case, we have also seen how the wave character fits with material particles like electrons,
protons and so on as well.
However, we might ask at this point when, how and under which circumstances does the one or the other
aspect arise?
Is this a property that quantum objects acquire, switching from one state to another?
Is there somehow a moment, an instant in time where and not better defined entity is or behaves like
a particle and after afterwards morphs into a wave?
If so, does this happen in a continuous fashion or instantly, or is there another possible interpretation
and understanding which unites unites the two aspects of photons as waves and as matter and energy?
In some sense, we have already seen how with the Braly hypothesis, it is possible to unify this disparity
with the concept of the Wave packett.
Therefore, so far we have shed some light.
Here's the pun is intended on this wave with wave particle duality.
But the picture is still somewhat incomplete because if we think about it carefully, nobody has seen
a light wave as we can observe water waves on the surface of an ocean, for example.
What we always observe are the effects of something that we imagine by deduction after the fact to be
something that acts like a wave.
The several experiments that hinted at the particle or wave character of light did not show that light
is a particle or is a wave, but that it behaves like a particle or a waves.
A wave.
That's the difference.
We should not confuse our human mental, sometimes even ideological projections of how reality appears
with reality itself.
It is here, therefore, where Young's famous double slit experiment comes into play again in its modern
quantum version, it clarifies further some very important aspects and shed more light also literally
on the nature of physical objects in quantum physics.
So let us turn back to the young stubbles, little experiment and revise it and to see it from a different
perspective.
We have here again the transverse plane, wavefront of light, say just a beam of light coming from
a source which ideally is highly monochromatic, that is having a single or very narrow range of wavelengths
and colors nowadays, an easy task to accomplish with laser light.
We know that the slits should have a size and separation which should be comparable with that of the
wavelength of the incoming light.
Something something which even for small wavelengths, can be achieved with high precision using model
lithographic technologies.
When the plane wave years plane where it goes goes through the slits, it is refracted and is detected,
detected with a screen at some distance and the usual resulting interference pattern appears.
These fringes can be easily photographed with photographic plate or CCD camera nowadays, usually a
camera or whatever kind of sensor sensitive to that wavelength we are working with.
With Yang's experiment, the question about the nature of light seemed to receive a clear answer.
We conceive light as a wave since it behaves like a wave because of the typical interference phenomenon,
exactly as we expected it for waves.
But let us see what the more or less unaware assumption is that stands behind this conclusion, the
more or less unaware and unconscious logical background of this conclusion relies on what is called
the dark test.
That's what philosophers.
Used to say, or more precisely, more scientific terms, the objective or retroactive reasoning and
which states that if something looks like a duck, swims like a duck and quacks like a duck, then it
probably is a duck.
This is what in quantum mechanics, philosophers, philosophers mean by counterfactual definiteness,
that is the ability to assume the existence of properties of objects even when they have not been measured
directly.
However, upon closer inspection, that turns out not to be the whole story.
Let us turn to the moral schematic representation of the double slit experiment.
Here we see again the incoming planer wavefront that the diffract, the circular wavefront and the internal
interference fringes appearing on the detector plain.
If we look more precisely at the microscopic level, what happens then we would realize that things
are turned upside down because what finally is detected are always and only interactions between the
light and the detector screen in tiny localized spots.
Let us take, for instance, this little localized pest and magnify it.
Say, for instance, using a microscope or whatever, then what one observes locally is not some nice
continuous shading of the intensity between the black and white fringes, but we always observe a random
distribution of points that is of point, like localized interactions on the detection screen, just
like pixels on a monitor.
For instance, if we use as our detecting screen and old conventional photographic plate.
Develop it and then look at the photograph under a microscope, magnifying the region of the interference
pattern, we see many tiny white spots which correspond to the grains that due to the chemical reaction,
became white.
If a photon is absorbed or black, no, like no black or white, according if you look at the negative
or the positive development plate.
So, after all, when we make a measurement, what we ultimately observe are particles, not waves.
Be it a photographic plate, a modern CCD sensor or any other kind of detector which responds to an
electric signal or just clicks like a photo died or photomultiplier, what we really measure up one
or many dots, that is local point like interactions with form, an internal interference pattern.
But we never see a continuous pattern.
Even if we would build a detector, which with with the highest resolution possible, say every pixel
is an atom, the same dot, that interference pattern would emerge at smaller scales.
This should not come as a surprise, since already, from what we have learned about the black body
radiation theory, we know that matter and therefore atoms and molecules absorb quanta and not in a
continuous fashion, but in form of discrete, discrete amounts of energy.
Therefore, also in Yang's experiment, we recover and find again the corpuscular nature of light,
what seems to be directed at the slits and interferes on the screen behaves like a wave.
But what is finally observed are photons hitting the screen.
On one side, we have something we imagine to be a wave that goes through the double slit.
But at last, when we attempt to detect it, then nevertheless it shows up always and inevitably as
a localized interaction.
In a certain sense, we find ourselves again at a starting point.
What is a photon really?
If it is a wave, why when we when and how does it become a particle in order to be detected as a point
like structure?
Let us further inspect the state of affairs, if we maintain strictly the particle picture, then we
must assume that at this slits, each particle must go through one or the other slit and then travel
further in the direction of the detection screen and there show up at one or the other fringe.
That is, we have two sets of piled up particles detected only in two locations at the detector screen.
However, we know all too well that this is not the case, since we observe the all larger set of interference
fringes, there are also other lines, so to speak, appearing this naive picture is simply disproved
by facts.
If we still believe that there are only particles, we are forced to assume that something like it and
this figure in the lower right massacre, one has to assume the existence of some not well defined wave
or force of of field that guides the particle along their path so that they match the interference fringes.
But there is no wave.
This is an interpretation that is indeed taken seriously by some physicists with the so-called pilot
wave theory originally formulated by the American physicist David Bohm.
But before going into speculations that have no hard evidence supporting them, I strongly suggest you
follow and learn first what so far is known for sure before jumping into the plethora of interpretations
of quantum mechanics.
In fact, let us make a further step in our reasoning and ask ourselves what happens if only one photon
is sent towards the double slit?
Do interference, for instance, arise also with one eye, with a single photon, or are they the result?
Just interpret the interference fringes?
Are they the result of the collective interactions of many photons or which seems to be another possible
alternative interpretation?
Does even a single particle interfere with itself?
The question might look at first meaningless because we might object that there is no way to say if
a single photon is subjected to interference, since to observe these interference phenomena, we need
a collection of photons to build up as fringes on the screen.
However, there is a way to test this hypothesis.
In fact, an idea to try to deceive nature could be to look and see if and how the interference pattern
builds up.
If we sent only one photon after another and see how things develop over time, one after another means
that we shoot a single photon at the 2s.
Let's wait until the single photon hits the screen and record its position on the detector screen.
And only after that we send the next photon weight again until it is detected on the screen and so on.
Experimentally, this is not easy, but even so, not too difficult to accomplish by making the light
source extremely dim.
For example, just take a at source and limit with some almost black foil in such a manner that it emits
only one photon at a time.
And you should know by now that this is precisely what metter always does.
If you recall what we have said about the black body radiation and atomic transition spectra, then
the single photon is forced to go through one slit or the other slit.
If it is a particle, as we imagine it being in our naive intuition, then it can't go through both
slits.
If this particle travels through the first slit, then one expects to find it colliding, colliding
with the detector screen in the region of often of the upper fringe here.
And when another particle goes through the second slit, then it is expected to hit the lower fringe
here.
So since we are sending only one photon at a time, this seems to be a method to force nature to manifest
its crepuscular aspect.
This experiment proceeds as follows.
We produce only a very few photons at a time and then look at what we see at the detection screen after
a short time interval.
As you can observe here, only a few photons are distributed in an apparently random manner all over
the area where previously we observed the interference fringes.
So there is no hint that interference, of course, and we are happy with that, we believed to have
sent through the slits only one photon at a time, and we observe only tiny white spots as expected,
even though the random displacement of the photon of the photons seems already to disprove the existence
of only two lines.
If we wait a little longer and collect more, even on the detector screen, one sees something like
this and things look still clumpy.
But now there seem definitely to be no trace of the two expected white lines at this stage of the experiment.
However, one still cannot discover and clearly what the truth is.
Then after some time where we have collected a sufficient number of events on the screen, we begin
to observe indeed the interference fringes.
And if we wait even longer and collect a large number of spots on the screen, finally the whole interference
structure emerges.
What we must conclude from this is that despite having deemed our source to such a degree that it emits
only one photon at a time, the wave particle duality does not disappear.
The interference phenomenon is not a collective phenomenon whereby we might imagine many light particles
somehow interacting among themselves to produce the interference fringes.
That's not the case.
Also, single photons obey the interference law.
And that's quite strange, isn't it?
We might interpret the overall result as if the single particle goes through both slits at the same
time.
As a sort of ghostly wave that is subjected to the laws of diffraction and interference, but then when
its position is measured, suddenly collapses to a single point at the at the detector screen.
There it appears again as a little localized spot, the kind of classical model of reality we imagined
whereby only a couple of localized fringes appear without interference is at this point dead and no
longer.
Tenable at all, it is simply wrong.
What this shows instead is that as long as it is not observed, it travels and expands throughout space
as a wave.
But then when the act of measurement is performed, it chooses to place itself on a specific location.
We see that something that seems to behave as a wave suddenly collapses to a point.
We will never see the wave and particle nature at the same time.
An important aspect always to keep in mind is that nevertheless, the process is completely random in
the following sense is all what we have discussed so far is subjected to random law.
We see clear and well-defined interference for infringers.
We can say, what's the probability is where one photon displaces itself on which fringe?
And it is never if it never displaces itself where the black fringes are.
And we can describe this very well mathematically with an interference function, with a wave function.
But we will never be able to say that this that precisely that single photon will displace itself on
that fringe in this location.
Where are we to look at this interference pattern only at a small local scale, again, say with a microscope
and without knowing how the rest of the interference picture is made, there would be no way to know
if the single white dot on the Texas screen is the result of an interference phenomenon through the
two slits or simply a single photon coming from a source with or without the slits in between.
It is only when we look at the global picture that we can infer from it that interference must have
taken place.
In this sense, we say that quantum physics is governed by purely probabilistic laws.
We can only say that there is a certain probability that a photon is detected in a specific position.
But never, ever will we be able to tell in advance what this single event will turn out to be.
We can only tell what will happen statistically.
That is, after a high number of events have taken place and become statistically significant when a
statistically significant number of even's is collected.
The overall disposition of the photons on the detection plane always obeys the classical interference
law with its typical geometric disposition of the dark and white fringe pattern.
The signal, even, however, that is the displacement of a single photon on one or the other.
French is a purely probabilistic event.
There is a high probability that the single photon will be detected on the brighter fringes, but there
is no way, no method at all, even not in principle, to tell in advance which of the fringes the single
photon on which on which of the fringe is a single photon will be detected.
This hints at the quite different conception then what we intend in classical physics with the word
randomness, chance or coincidence.
In classical physics, the face that stands up by tossing a dyes, for example, is a random event in
the sense that the physical process, which determines how the dice rolls on a table, is so complicated,
so complicated and practically impossible to calculate that the outcome is simply unpredictable.
But think about it in principle.
If you would know everything about the dice, the forces that act on the dice, how it is thrown on
the table, every and we know every detail about the table itself and the precise initial conditions
of the system of the dice and so on.
We could ideally predict the outcome, say, with a supercomputer that knows everything about the laws
of classical physics empiricism.
In principle, that would not be impossible.
Therefore, this concept, this classical concept of randomness and indeterminism is in reality only
something that displays our displays our house, so to speak, ignorance on the initial conditions of
the system and the precise values of the parameters that describe the state of the system.
But in principle, if we have sufficient data and the exact initial conditions, we know everything
about the system we could implement and we know everything about the classical laws of classical mechanics
and physics, then in principle, it is not impossible to predict also the outcome of the tossing of
a dice.
Yeah.
So in this sense, we must distinguish between these two types of indeterminism.
The classical determinism has its roots in a way of thinking which is nicely summarized by the so-called
Le plus Daymon.
PFC Manolopoulos was a French mathematician and astronomer of the 19th century who isn't as follows.
We may regard the present state of the universe as the affect of its past and the course of its future
and intellect, which at a certain moment would know all forces that said nature in motion and all positions
of all items of which nature is composed.
If this intellect were also vast enough to submit these data to analysis, it would embrace in a single
formula the movements of the greatest bodies of the universe and those of the tiniest atom.
For such an intellect, nothing would be uncertain.
And the future future, just like the past, would be present before its eyes.
This conception, this idea of determinism is more or less consciously still the leading paradigm in
most sciences until today is someone themen in this case knows the precise position and momentum of
every particle in the universe.
Its dynamic evolution for any given time could be calculated with certainty from the laws of physics.
But we will see repeatedly during this journey through the weird world of quantum physics that this
is an assumption that.
Can no longer be considered true in the quantum domain, or at least we have strong indications that
it might be not longer be true, even if we know everything about the solar system and the initial condition
of a single particle.
Yeah, the single event will remain forever unpredictable.
And this not because of our ignorance as a plus believed.
And even if we have a demon knowing everything and being able to calculate quickly and precisely enough
everything, in any case, quantum mechanics, this is not allowed, nevertheless, to know the future
with absolute precision.
We can make only statistical prediction predictions, but not a certain prediction about a single event.
It seems that in quantum mechanics, things are not random in the classical sense.
But this randomness is an inherent feature and aspect of nature.
We shall take up this issue again, also in the next lecturer's.
Meanwhile, if you have followed what we learned about the electron and neutron diffraction, it should
not come as this point, as a surprise that the wave particle duality is something that holds for material
particles as well.
In fact, the double slit experiment that Young performed with light gives exactly the same result again,
if you use electrons or other material particles instead of photons.
Therefore, the only thing we can say for sure can be represented with these pictures.
Before the detection of anything, we should only imagine waits or more precisely, meter waves in the
case of material particles.
First, a plane wave hitting the screen and after the two slits, the two concentric wave fronts.
Once these hit the screen, they interact with it according to a probability amplitude dictated by the
interference amplitudes.
And suddenly this wave collapses onto a single spot at the detection site.
This is what the wave particle duality is about, the wave particle duality is about an object that
propagates and spreads out throughout space, behaving and interfering like a wave.
But when asked as to its whereabouts, it answers as a point like interaction.
More than that, we can't say.
So at this point, we should begin to become accustomed to the idea that there is no particle and neither
neither wave at all in the first place, but only a physical phenomenon which should not which we should
not even attempt to visualize with our human intuitive, macroscopic understanding of the world.
The nature of matter can be described only in terms of probability waves on or probability loss.
Note also how we coincidentally are talking about something, the grave nature of photons or matter
without detecting and measuring any wave at all, but inferring its existence only indirectly are posteriorly.
That is after the measurement of its particle nature by looking afterwards at the interference pattern,
which consists of several white spots, we talk of meter waves not by seeing waves at all.
Quite the contrary.
Paradoxically, we deduce the wave nature of matter only when several measurements of particle like
objects have been performed, as we shall see later.
This is a prelude to a typical situation occurring frequently in quantum physics, the kind of situation
where we tend to reconstruct in our mind and presumed objective reality a model of something which is,
however, already in the past and no longer in the present, but by looking at the effects it produced.
We are looking, therefore, what the effects are from that we did use a wavelike nature or whatever
kind we come to, what ever kind of conclusion, we tend to believe there was a wave in the past, despite
the fact that we observe only particles in the present time.
It is just this logical reverse engineering, so to speak.
And the question of how far we are allowed to resort to this kind of reasoning, quantum physics that
has given so many headaches to generations of physicists and philosophers.
Also, honestly, we really don't know what these objects we call photons, electrons, protons and
neutrons really are.
We even are no longer sure if it makes sense at all to ask for a description of reality that is supposed
to have an object on an objective existence and ontology independent from our mental models.
The fact is that physical reality must be a bit more complicated and counterintuitive than what we thought
it to be.
We have to deal with phenomena that refuse to be forced into an objective, ontological worldview made
of classical objects, independent from the act of measurement, at least not in the classical Newtonian
physics sense in the world out there, so to speak.
There is something that produces effects, which in turn become the causes of future events.
And that tell us tells us I am a particle when you look at me, but as long as you don't look at me,
I will continue to behave like a wave.
And it's not saying I am a wave.
I behave like a wave.
Whereas from the mathematical, purely mathematical and abstract point of view, there is no problem
at all with this, we just make all of our calculations with our unnice with packets and wave propagation
and interference laws and obtain as an answer that which is confirmed by the experimental results.
However, from the ontological point of view, things are not as easy as that it does.
It is not clear what quantum physics is trying to tell us really here about the physical world and if
it makes sense to speak about objective realities at all.
This aspect has puzzled the best minds of science and philosophy and continues to do so until the modern
days.