Another famous principle that most of you may have heard of is the Heisenberg's uncertainty or determination
principle.
Usually it is explained with a few sentences or with wrong analogies.
And people, sometimes even professional physicists, have a misleading understanding of what it is
about, therefore, to get a clear picture and avoid misunderstandings.
It is instructive to deepen further our understanding of the diffraction and interference phenomenon
for the one, two and many of its cases.
So far, we concentrated our attention on young stubbles lead case in that occasion.
We saw how when a couple of slits the a transverse plane wave, it produces the typical interference
pattern made of white maxima and dark M.A fringes on a detection screen.
And we saw that this is equally true if we sent also only one photon at a time through the slits after
sufficient number of photons have excited the single photosensitive molecules of the photographic plate
or the camera sensor.
Again, the interference fringes reappear.
The question at this point is what happens if we use only one bullet or vice versa?
What happens when we use many bullets instead?
Already at about the end of the 17th century, well before the birth of quantum mechanics, the singer
and endless interference phenomena were well known and extensively studied as every good textbook on
electromagnetism will tell you.
Also, a single bullet or a pinhole will produce an interference pattern, even though less pronounced.
We mentioned how Young studied the friction at a pinhole already before experimenting, experimenting
with the double slit, it is even an easy experiment that you can do by yourself.
Just take a piece of paper, poke a little round hole with a pin or a needle and look towards a light
source.
You will observe the image of the light source surrounded by several consistent concentric colored fringes.
We will see this pattern later.
Also, the colors appear obviously only due to the fact that fortunately the world we live in is not
monochromatic.
There are many colors.
More precisely, for example, here in this picture.
This picture shows how a plane wave behaves when one of percha, the single bullet of size A is about
five times the size of the light wavelength.
That is A equals five times lambda.
Due to the direction that occurs when whenever a wave encounters an object or Haslet, especially when
its size is comparable to the wavelength, this causes at a fraction of the plane wavefront to a spherical
or distorted wavefront, which then travels towards the detection screen.
In this case, you see that even though we are dealing with only one bullet, still some weak but clearly
with visible secondary minima and maxima fringes can be observed.
An important and important point here to keep in mind is to avoid a common misconception, and that
one reads frequently also in some popular science books, according to which only two or more states
can produce interference fringes.
Whereas for the single toilet, interference affects supposedly disappear.
However, this is not entirely correct through it is easier to produce more pronounced interference
patterns with more than one toilet or pinhole.
And that for most applications, especially when the wavelength of the incident wave is much smaller
than the size of the aperture.
These effects can be neglected.
However, strictly speaking, and this is also important for us as singers, it also produces small
diffraction and interference phenomena.
An elegant explanation of how interference comes into being also for a signal, it dates back to the
French physicist Augustus Augustine, Israel.
He borrowed an idea from Horgan's, hence the name Horgan's Fresnel principle, according to which every
point on a wavefront should be considered a point source of a spherical wave itself again.
Once the incoming plane wave reaches all the virtually infinite points along the aperture, every single
point becomes itself again, a spherical wave point source, so to speak.
All this point like sources along the A percha.
And at the same time, their own spherical wavefront, which, however, when seen from the position
on the screen, end up producing an interference pattern.
The reason for this is not so difficult to visualize since all fronts are initiated in different locations
along the aperture.
They will also travel at different parts length, which implies that they have different phase shifts
when they overlap on the screen.
For instance, in this figure of the previous slide, we show here again, the two pairs of the two
saucers from the edges are considered.
And as in the case of the double slit, these two rays have a relative phase shift by an amount Delta
V, and when superimposed together on the screen, they form a result, resultant intensity according
to the interference laws.
In this case, however, this holds not only for two ways, as in the double slit, but for an infinite
number of points.
Sources along the Aperture Fresnel, by making the appropriate calculations, was able to show that
if one sums up all these spherical wavefront wavefront coming from the points along the upper aperture
of the single slit and projects these on to all the points along the detection screen, then one obtains
indeed the known diffraction and interference pattern.
And if we repeat now the same experiment with as little that has a size close to the wavelength of our
incoming wavefront, that is instead of using a pinhole of five times lambda, that is five times the
wavelength of the incoming wavefront, but only one time the size of the.
So a equal one lambda.
So the size of the aperture is about the wavelength of the incoming wave.
Then we see that the interpret the interference fringes disappear.
As you can see in this figure here, only when the size of the slits or not of the slit of the single
slit is equal to or smaller than the wavelength.
Are the fringes definitely absent?
This is because the slit is so small that only a single point source can form a spherical wavefront
with a wavelength equal to the slit size and therefore can be.
There can be no path difference and phase shift with some other source which will produce the interference
pattern.
However, diffraction has become very large instead.
Now at this point for a equal lambda so that the photons will displace themselves on a relatively large
area on the screen, according to a so-called bell shaped distribution.
So the important point to keep in mind here is that the interference pattern, the interference phenomena
does not arise simply due to the fact that there are one or two or many states.
But it is and it is a universal phenomenon.
You can have this also on at one slit.
So it depends how large the slit is.
And these, uh, the interference fringes disappear completely only if the aperture is about the wavelength
as the size of the wavelength.
Otherwise, there is still a little bit left.
So it is important that you keep in mind this.
Let us look also quickly at what happens if we change the number.
It's a special example so we can compare three different cases.
Here on the accessor that is on the horizontal line, we have the angle of position on the screen angle
of incidence teeter between the centerline of the diffraction plane at a point on the detection screen
while on the ordinate access.
That is the vertical axis.
We have the usual intensity.
The parameters that determine the angle dependence of the interference pattern are, first of all,
the size a of the aperture of the slit relative to the wavelength here.
In this case, we have taken a equal three times lambda.
So the size of the aperture is three times the size of the wavelength.
Second, the spacing, the between the slits here I took three times eight and of course the number
capital letters and of the slits.
The intensities have been normalized in all the cases to one to to unity.
So you see that for the one solid case, you see there are some weak but clearly discernible secondary
blue lateral peaks that reduce almost to the diffraction envelope.
For the two slits, as in the case of young double slit experiment, we obtain more pronounced Frenches
traced with this red line.
Here you can see how the one slit pattern envelopes the two slits pattern.
And the interference figure of the signals led pattern is split into several more fringes.
However, notice that it would be incorrect to say, as you might hear frequently, that when we switch
from the double slit back to the single case, interference phenomena disappear.
That is in general, not the case.
What happens is that we return to the envelope of the single bullet, which contains many fewer fringes
but still might have, and in this case it has some other interference fringes, too.
Again, interference is not a phenomenon specific to the double or more slit experiment.
Interference does not disappear.
If one slit is covered, it just becomes weaker then with more slits, but it is still there.
Finally, the green curve depicts the case of 10 bullets.
This time the two slits curve turns out to be the the envelope curve of the ten slits curve.
So you can observe how this is a more general trend and phenomenon which results from the interplay
between diffraction and interference, in fact, the endless fringes and their spacing's arise due to
this combined effect between diffraction and interference.
These were only a few examples that I wanted to show you to outline how, at least intuitively, wave
interference works programmers who might be interested to recreate the infinite possibilities and possible
combinations of interference figures can find this general formula of intensity, of the intensity function
of some use if they wish.
If you wish, you can play with it.
It is sometimes interesting and amusing to see the kind of pattern that result when changing the parameters.
I place this formula here only for the interested student.
We won't need it at all in the rest of the course.
So you can also skip it if you wish.
Now, we have seen in the previous lectures, especially with the friction out, the friction and interference
phenomenon, determine the wave particle duality not only of light particles, that is photons, but
more generally hold for all particles, also material particles that have a mass and that nevertheless
behave like waves, even though we think we think of them as localized pieces of solid matter.
A question we might ask at this point is what happens with the particle if we want to know precisely
its whereabouts in space?
For example, let us determine the precise position of a particle by letting it go through a tiny pinhole,
as Isaac Newton used to do with photons and his investigations on the nature of light.
If a particle goes through that single little hole on a piece of paper, say, for example, then we
are authorized to say that we can determine its precise position in space.
In fact, this can be done, but at the cost, because on the other hand, we know that due to the wave
particle duality, we cannot forget the particle swathi aspect.
So when a particle also material particle goes through this pinhole, it will also be distracted and
afterwards position itself on the detector screen according to an interference interference pattern.
If instead of dealing with slits, so we take a tiny round hole with a size comparable to a few multiples
of the wavelength.
We obtain circler interference for injuries like shown in this figure here, and this is an intrinsic
and an unavoidable effect for all types of waves.
If particles have to be linked to weight, to a wave, according to the debris, the very relation conceiving
it as a wave packet, then we will always have the interference fringes, even with only one or oscillate,
and even with only one particle.
Recall the single photon experiment.
In this figure, we compare the two cases where the pinhole determines the position of the particle
with an aperture of a equals to lamda, which means a relatively high precision because the aperture
is only two times the wavelength as the size of two times the wavelength of the incoming wave or meter
wave, and the other case of a equal 20 times lambda, which means we determine with low precision the
whereabouts of the particle because.
The Aperture A is 20 times as large as the wavelength of the particle where, of course, lambda here
the wavelength is can be that of the photon, of the electromagnetic wave, or in case of a meter wave,
it must be associated to the to the liberally wavelength.
Therefore, if the pinhole is small.
It localizes quite well the position of the particle, it will produce a relatively broad diffraction
pattern that renders the position on the screen of the photon uncertain.
We can know in a relatively precise manner the where the photon or the matter particle went through
the piece of paper that is inside the space constrained by the Pinhas aperture.
But it will be displaced laterally on the screen anyway due to the friction and interference phenomena.
And we cannot avoid this because it is a law of nature.
A lot of the that governs the waves, of course, with a single particle producing a single spot on
the screen, no interference figure is visible.
But as we have learned with a single photon diffraction at the double slit, the probability to find
this spot is in one to one correspondence with the intensity of the interference fringes produced by
many particles.
Moreover, and this is the important point that we have already made, recall also that we can't predict
in advance where precisely this spot will appear.
If instead the pinhole is large, fringes will become less pronounced.
We will know where the photon will hit the screen with relatively good accuracy, the red spikes here,
which means it failed, so to speak, only a tiny displacement, displacement along the screen.
But by doing so, we will lose our capacity to determine where where this is.
Particle exactly went through the pinhole, since this pinhole is no longer a pinhole at all, but a
large hole.
There is no way, never, ever, not even in principle, to obtain the precise measurement of the particle
position and at the same time avoid the production of interference, fringes or at any rate, a large
deflection, one will always obtain a more or less pronounced bell shaped or peaked distribution of
white spots on the screen, not because we have not a sufficient precise measurement apparatus, but
because this is a consequence of the intrinsic wave nature of particles.
It is a universal law of nature, according to which it is hopeless to believe that we can pass a wave
through as late tiny slit and not observe any interference and diffraction phenomena.
It is against the nature of waves itself.
So if you have followed so far, it should be easy at this point to understand the essence of Heisenberg's
uncertainty principle.
Werner Heisenberg was a German physicist who around the 1930s asked himself if and how there is a way
to precisely determine the position of particle.
This one was one of the most urgent questions to find an answer for, since, after all, in classical
classical physics, everything is expressed, analyzed and described in terms of space, time, forces
and particles following accordingly precise trajectories.
If we are no longer able to describe the position in space of a particle, we are substantially blowing
up almost all know in physics, which until then relied completely on particles interacting through
forces which with each other in space and time.
So Heisenberg reasoned as follows.
Let us suppose that we want to determine with a high precision the position of a particle, notice that
in this figure here, the x axis is the vertical one, not the horizontal.
Along the vertical line, we have the X variable.
Imagine the particle coming from the left with a specific amount of momentum.
We recall that the momentum of a particle in classical, non relativistic mechanics is just the quantity
of motion of an object and is given by the product product of its mass times, its velocity.
Generally, it is a vector quantity, which means it is also a direction.
Let us also recall that as we have discussed in the lecture on the elite relation, once momentum is
given in quantum physics, we can relate to every particle.
Also a wavelength as that equal H of a p.
This particle, which we must intend as a transverse plane wave, is an incident on the diffraction
plane with one slit open hole of size Delta X.
This particle that is this plane wave, once it has passed through, the slit, will be deflected and
shortly after interact on the detection screen at the position, according to a probabilistic law,
which is determined by the interference pattern, as you certainly know by now.
So the particle, even without any interaction from outside forces and even with no physical disturbance
from the environment, and even by constructing an experimental set up, which is perfect and ideal
without any imprecision, will nevertheless be displaced on the screen.
The vertical x axis.
This happens because of our attempt to localize the particle in that tiny region, Delta X, Letter
X. We can arrange our experiment as we wish, but if the size of the slit is comparable to the wavelength
of the photon or to the temporary wavelength of a material particle, then we will always and inevitably
note that the particle after it passed the slit, the slit of six Delta X will be displaced on the screen
according to the laws of interference diffraction and to the laws determining the behavior of waves.
There is no way to avoid this interference phenomenon.
Now, this could also be interpreted as if the particle, once it has gone through the slit, will acquire
an extra momentum delta along the vertical axis, this does not happen because of the interaction of
an outside force or as we might imagine, naively by an interaction, deviation or bouncing effect of
the particle with as little edges, because in that case, we would observe a random distribution,
but not an interference pattern characteristic of waves.
This extra momentum Delta P, which displaces the particle along the detection screen, is due only
and exclusively to the wave nature of matter and light.
We might interpret this also as a scattering of the particle, but we should keep in mind that this
is a misleading terminology since there is no scattering force at all.
It does not need any scattering interaction of forces from the outside to make this happen.
So where does this extra momentum Delta P come from?
It is just the uncertainty we have about the particles momentum in the first place.
It is an inherent uncertainty of the properties of any particle due to their wave nature.
So this is the only possible conclusion if we want to avoid violation of the principles of conservation,
of momentum and energy.
The point is that we will never be able to determine with extreme precision, that is with an infinitely
small slit of size, Delta X equals zero without blurring the momentum in space around the vertical
axis, since by doing so, we inevitably will diffract the plane wavefront.
The wavelength of which is given by the debris relation, and this inevitably will displace the particle
of the photon according to a statistical law which reflects the deflection and interference laws.
So we must conclude that the smaller our uncertainty in determining the particles position, the size
of the slit, the larger will be the diffraction effects and therefore also the larger the uncertainty
over the momentum that the P of the particle that becomes therefore large in the vertical direction.
On the other hand, if I want to know the political momentum was small uncertainty, that is, I would
like to maintain Delta Small, then we will have to open up those little aperture.
This means Delta X must be large in order to reduce the disruption.
But I will never, ever be able to determine with precision both the momentum and the position of a
particle was the same at the same time.
We have to chose if we want to keep focused on one or the other, never, ever are we allowed to obtain
both.
Not because we interfere with the system.
This is also another misleading misconception, but because we are dealing with waves of.
We have, however, interference fringes here, and in principle, the particle can displace itself
also very far away from the center of the screen, especially if the slits or is dark with the slit
we have only a single single cell becomes very small.
But this also happens with a decreasing probability.
It is much more probable to find the particle hitting the screen at the central white peaks higher peaks
than at the little ones far away from the center, for practical reasons, one must set a limit as a
convention due to statistical reasons which will be clarified in the next sections.
One takes as conventional the normal distribution which states that Delta P is the width of the central
fringe corresponding to.
Sixty eight point three percent of all of the particles it contains.
Because this is a central region with high intensity and therefore that region where we have the highest
probability to detect a single particle.
In fact, as we have seen with the signals, let the secondary interference interference fringes beyond
the central one are usually quite small, usually also smaller, smaller than the in this figure.
So this means that to a specific amount of Delta X, we must expect to find also a specific amount of
Delta P?
Yeah, always.
And inevitably, by the laws of nature, Heisenberg was also able to show that the product of these
two uncertain quantities is a constant and summed up this with his famous and extremely important inequality,
which states that Delta X times Delta B is greater equal each bar half where each bar is the plank's
content constant age divided by two times pi.
This is a mathematical way to state what we have said so far.
If you force the value of the photon of a particle to be tight, it will always have an uncertainty
over the momentum of Delta P greater equal H over two times Delta X. But that is a precise measurement
of the particle position will imply and uncertainty over its momentum is more Delta X inducers delta
to become large viceversa.
If you force the value of the momentum of a particle into a narrow range of values, it will always
have an uncertainty over the position of Delta X and greater or equal age over two times.
Delta P.
This is an inequality which can be obtained in several ways, and one closely related to this is via
the so-called Fourier transforms, and that is it is a mathematical tool that the composers signal in
time, such as a complicated travelling wave into many sine and cosine functions of different frequencies,
or as it is done in modern quantum theory, Heisenberg's inequality is obtained through a mathematical
operator theory approach, which is mathematically more rigorous.
But.
Frankly, obscures somehow the deeper meaning of the Heisenberg principle, really related to the wave
nature of matter.
At any rate, always keep what was important point is always to keep in mind this little but very important
inequality, since it will turn up more or less everywhere and quantum mechanics.
Now, let us analyze what interpretation Heisenberg himself gave to this to his own principal.
He illustrated this with a famous thought experiment by thought experiment, which is kind of the meaning
comes from the German Gattung experiment in science, one means an ideal experiment which could be realized
in principle and does not as such, violate violate the laws of physics, but can't be performed in
practice due to technological limitations or other constraints.
Heisenberg's thought experiment elucidated what nowadays is remembered as the Heisenberg microscope
interpretation.
It is an interpretation that unfortunately also several professional physicists adopt, probably to
make it more understandable, understandable and appealing to the public or first year students.
But if you have followed carefully what we have said so far, you shall be able to recognize that Heisenberg's
interpretation is somewhat misleading, to say the least.
This experiment went as follows a thought experiment.
Imagine we want to detect the position and momentum of a particle in a region that acts by using an
incoming photon.
The green wavy arrow here, which hits the particle, this photon is then scattered towards some direction,
say, along the direction represented by the red wavy arrow.
We have already described something similar with a compensatory effect then so was the reasoning of
Heisenberg Heisenberg.
We can look to where the photon has been shattered and we should be able to deduce the electrons position.
So we just look with the microscope, we see the scattered photo and say are the particle was just there
in that position that X is or was at least.
However, the problem is that according to classical optics, the larger the angular aperture data of
the microscope is, the better it will resolve the position of the scattered photon and therefore deduce
the position of the electron.
But this angular aperture does not only depend on the size of the microscope lens its lens, but also
on the wavelength of the photon itself to have a high precision in determining from which direction
the photon comes.
That is, in determining the position, the original position, at least of the electron.
We must use a photon with a short wavelength.
But and this is the point, if the photon has a short wavelength, which means high frequency, it will
carry more momentum because it is more energetic due to Plank's relation, as you might recall, and
the kick it imparts to the electron will therefore be also larger.
That is, if I want to observe the precise position of the electron with this microscope, I must use
photons which will produce a larger recoil on the electron itself.
And this makes its position again, indeterminate.
On the other hand, if I want to determine more precisely the momentum of a particle, then I'm forced
to use photons with large wavelengths, since only these have a small momentum and will not displace
the electron too much through constant scattering.
But if I use long wavelengths, what long wavelength photons, the microscope optics will resolve its
position with less accuracy.
So again, we have to search for a trade off between the wavelength we use.
That is the precision, the precision over the momentum, Delta P and the microscope aperture.
That is the capability to look at the precise position.
At the precise point.
Delta X.
In the macroscopic world, this effect does not play any role for practical purposes, even though,
strictly speaking, it always holds because objects are huge and are not disturbed by tiny photons.
However, for atoms and even more for particles like electrons, a single photon can also disturb them
and scatter them away, preventing us from determining their properties.
That is why Heisenberg's uncertainty principle is invoked.
To explain that in the microscope, the microscopic world, a measurement always perturbs a system in
such a way that the scale of the measurements perturbation is about the same magnitude of the effect
it produces and therefore renders imprecise, if not at all useless.
The result?
Heisenberg was able to show that by reasoning in such manner, making the appropriate calculations,
which is to classical optics, he could indeed obtain his own famous inequality of momentum and position.
Heisenberg's microscope thought experiment boils down to the following argument.
We cannot determine the position and momentum of a particle at the same time, because when we make
an observation, we inevitably must interact with the object, with the object we want to observe,
such as sending other particles of comparable mass or energy of the particle to be observed.
And this inevitably disturbs the system, which then loses its original position and momentum that we
sought to determine.
But this interpretation, however, is in stark contrast to the wave particle nature of matter itself.
It is interpretation and interpretation that does not stand up to the test of modern modern quantum
theory.
The popular belief that Heisenberg's uncertainty principle is about the interaction between the observer
and the observed object is wrong.
Heisenberg's uncertainty principle is a fundamental law of nature, which has its rules in the way nature
of matter and has nothing to do with the interaction between the measuring apparatus and the measured
objects.
Of course, the interactions and the imperfections of measurement devices must always take, must be
always taken into account in a real laboratory.
But this adds further uncertainty to the intrinsic quantum fuzziness that is present apriori.
In fact, we shall see later on that, as strange as it might sound by now, it is nevertheless perfectly
possible to set up experiments which make measurements without necessarily interacting with the system.
And yet the Heisenberg uncertainty principle remains inescapable.
We will see this late in Coming Lecture's.
It also also shows that the principle holds also in the case where we are able to reduce to zero any
interaction with the observed object, it is an inherent law of nature that is independent from observational
interactions.
At the Times of Heisenberg, it was still legitimate to think of particles in this way, Heisenberg
can be excused because several experiments which showed how his own interpretation must be revised,
came much later.
Some not even until before the 1990s, with the development of sophisticated laser and quantum optics
optics devices.
So why the the historical context and the lack of more experimental evidence justifies Heisenberg not
so modern physicist?
Nowadays, we can no longer stick with the microscope interpretation as a correct understanding of how
the uncertainty principle works.
This is no less fundamental than the geocentric model of or flat earth theory.
We should accept that nature is telling us that we should never forget that wave particle duality.
When a particle goes through a pinhole, we must think of it as a physical process described by transverse
plana waves, which a meter wave which is refracted like any other wave and produces a spherical wavefront
not more nor less than in this figure.
Quantum mechanics, the classical understanding of particles which possess definite properties, such
a position which move along precise trajectories and possess a definite momentum, must be taken with
great care.
There are no positions or momenta which describe a particle we must seriously consider.
We must take quantum physics and nature seriously and consider consider instead that these are emergent
qualities, not intrinsic properties.
Particles do not have at all a clear and precise position and momentum as we imagine them to have at
our microscopic level.
And as our naive, intuitive, intuitive understanding wants to make us believe, quantum physics seems
to suggest that the physical objects we imagine as point like hard material, material, billiard balls
are instead entities which are intrinsically somewhat fuzzy with no sharp and well-defined boundaries,
and that travel throughout space as waves that eventually then collapse to a point somewhere, interacting
with some detectors or whatever.
This nature of particles is independent of the precision of our measurement apparatus and independent
of the fact that we interact or not by observing it, the position and velocity of particles is independent
from what we know in the classical world in which we live.
Therefore, indeterminacy is not a matter of ignorance.
Heisenberg uncertainty principle is not a principle about a lack of information.
It is not about particles, but which we cannot determine their whereabouts and speed.
It is about physical entities that simply do not have anything to do with our anthropomorphic imagination.
To sum up this lecture, we must keep in mind, therefore, the following things.
First of all, Heisenberg's uncertainty principle is not a principle about the lack of precision of
measurements.
Then Heisenberg's uncertainty principle is an intrinsic aspect and law of nature, which arises due
to the particle wave duality and finally, even an ideal measurement instrument with infinite precision
must nevertheless obey it.
These are the important aspects that distinguish classical from quantum physics.