Let us return back briefly to the Braly hypothesis here, we had to deal with an abstract object, with
a sort of conceptual synthesis that resembles us quite well, both a wave as well as the appearance
of a particle.
Every particle in quantum theory, like the electrons, protons, photons, etc., can be represented
by a wave packet that is a small, localized wave that travels throughout space and which has a frequency
or wavelength, if you prefer, and it has a maximum central value that decays quickly on both sides.
It is a way to visualize a wave that nevertheless can interact locally as a particle and fits well into
the wave particle duality where the quantum objects seem to behave as waves and yet as particles.
To recall what we found out in the lecture on the different wavelength and the concept of the wave packet,
then we have also seen that in quantum mechanics we have to deal with internal interference phenomena
which have some similarities with that of the waves of classical mechanics.
We introduced the concept of the phase between two waves or a phase relative to an origin, and we saw
how this is reflected in the formalism of quantum theory.
And there we saw that it is sometimes easier to write wave phenomena not with real numbers, but more
generally with complex numbers representing waves in space and time as complex functions with real and
imaginary part.
This week.
Make it clear, especially in the lecture of the appendix, the mathematical appendix, if you need
further insight on this, I invite you to take a look also to the appendix lecture.
Here you see an example of the simulation of an electron, one dimensional travelling wave packet,
the mathematical function which describes a wave packet or any quantum mechanical description of the
state of the system, is called the wave function.
And this is usually written with the letter C.
The wavefunction contains all the information, the information about a particle or a quantum system
in space coordinates X and in time T as C, X, T, upsy of X, T, this is, in fact the conventional
and standard mathematical descriptions, description of waves in quantum mechanics.
The red line represents the real part of the wave function, whereas the green is the imaginary part
of the recall, as we have described in the mathematical appendix, that the face of the real and imaginary
parts are shifted by 90 degrees to each other because, according to Euler's, Formula One can express
the former with a cosine function and the letter with the same function.
But we will not dwell in these mathematical details.
More relevant, irrelevant at this stage for us is to recognize the models of the wavefunction, the
blue line, which envelopes the wave packet.
It is this quantity that is of practical value, as we will see now.
But first, as you can see, with time passing by, the wave packet becomes larger due to dispersion
effects.
This is a more realistic representation of a wave function since it takes into account not only the
speed of a particle, but also that due to Heisenberg's uncertainty and the initial conditions of a
particle for particle's position and momentum are uncertain.
And then this uncertainty inevitably will grow with time, since the difference between two possible
initial conditions will reflect itself after some time, also in a difference of its whereabouts, of
the particles whereabouts which will become larger and larger with time passing by.
Letters represent this in still image.
Again, if you take a look in the mathematical appendix, you will discover that we can represent the
intensity of a wave that is a real positive number.
That is the physical quantity that we really measure, say, the number of photons we measure arriving
on a specific area, on a detection screen as being given by the squared models of the wave function
as PSI models squared equal, say, of X times of X complex conjugate, where here we consider only
the change in space variable X leaving out the change in time.
That is the variable T.
Therefore, it is conventional to depict a wave packett as in the foot in this figure.
You see the real part of a wavefunction in blue and it's squared models in red which represent the effectively
measured intensity.
The imaginary part here is not shown here just for the sake of simplicity.
The Delta X is taken as measuring the width of the Wave packett and corresponds to the uncertainty of
the position of a particle due to Heisenberg's inequality.
If you think of the density of dots, for instance, those forming the interference fringes infringes
on the screen of the Dabbous experiment, that is the number of photons hitting per unit area, the
photographic plate or a camera or whatever kind of detector, then the intensity is just proportional
to the density of dots.
Uh.
The registered number of particles on the screen per unit area, or as it is represented graphically
in this picture, like the transparency of the red particle around and origin, is what can be taken
to be proportional to the probability, to a probability to find the particle in that specific area.
Now, you might recall that while the overall disposition of many photons on the screen resembles that
of the interference fringes, it is nevertheless always a completely probabilistic process that determines
whether a single particle will hit the screen.
We have already discussed this.
The appearance of one photon as a dot on the screen is a purely statistical phenomenon.
Therefore, one can regard the intensity that is the squared models of the wavefunction model squared
of PI as something proportional to a probability per unit area and which is called simply probability
density.
This square models of the wavefunction is the master tool with which physicists describe probabilities
in quantum mechanics, that is, that which connects theory, a pure theory of pure mathematical theory
and formalism with the experiments and observations one makes in a laboratory.
It is this latter quantity that is finally what allows an abstract, complex mathematical function to
correlate with reality.
This can describe it by the measurement process and the.
Experiment physicists perform in the laboratory.
You can introduce the following interpretation then, which is due to the German physicist Max Bond
and is also called the bond rule and which tells us that the square models of the wavefunction sea is
a probability density to observe a quantum system in a specific state or a range of states.
To make it clear what this rule means, let us consider this graph, let us suppose that the curve represents
the probability density to find a particle around a Norwegian someplace, somewhere.
If the horizontal axis represents the position X where a particle can be found, the vertical axis is
a probability density P of X to find it at the position X.
You will find frequently such kind of bell shaped curve in several textbooks.
It is the so-called normal or Gaussian distribution, but probability density is still not a quantity
that can be measured, since it's since it represents only an infinitesimal quantity.
It makes no sense to ask what the probability is to find a particle in a specific position since the
in the interval on the space axis in such a case would be zero.
One can only say with what probability a particle can be localized in a specific spatial interval around
the origin, say the Delta X we worked with in Heisenberg's Uncertainty Principle.
The name density is no coincidence, just think of the density of matter, the material density function
of the body describes how the density in it varies inside a volume.
But this still isn't enough to tell us something about the amount of matter if we don't specify how
large this volume is.
Similarly, the wave function and its associated square models, that is the probability density describes
all the possible states of a system, but still does not tell us the probability to find it in a range
of possible states.
Therefore, what we need to consider is the sum of the probability density function over a specific
range that tells us something, this tells us something about the effective probability P a v capital
letters to find it in that range.
For example, for normal distributions, the X interval of plus minus sigma, this is a letter he is
Sigma is the definition, the range that determines a sixty eight point to seven percent probability
to find a particle.
Sigma is called the standard deviation and tells us something about the dispersion of a set of data
values.
The probability to find the particle far from the center drops off quickly at plus minus three times
sigma.
It is almost zero.
It might also be of interest to know that mathematically and mathematically rigorous approach to Heisenberg's
uncertainty principle holds precisely when the uncertainty range of the particles position and the momentum
is the standard deviation and therefore can be also reformulated as Sigma X times sigma p greater equal.
Each bar have in general to obtain a probability P in capital letters to distinguish it from the lowercase
P of the.
Probability density to find a to obtain the probability P to find the particle inside some spatial range
plus minus X, we must take the integral of the probability density over that entire interval.
That is the integral over the squared models of PSI of X.
So we have this one P equals the integral from minus X to plus X of the squared models of SPSSI of X,
the X where the X, the X tells us along which dimension, along which physical value we have to integrate.
And integral is the area under the graph function, which can be obtained as a sum over all the functions
values at each point along the x axis.
Even if you are not accustomed with integral calculus, it is not so difficult to visualize this.
For instance, just think of how the mass of your body is given by the integral over a mass density
function of all of its value.
Again, take a look to the appendix mathematical appendix lecture.
And of course, if you consider the probability to find a particle anywhere throughout the universe,
so to speak, the spatial range must be infinite that is taken.
You have to take X equals plus minus infinity as a domain of integration.
Then obviously you will get 100 percent probability.
That is certainty to find the particle somewhere, which mathematically translates into the integral
giving unity and which we describe in this way here.
The integral which has as integration domain from minus infinity to plus infinity, and which obviously
has to give and number one, if the wave function is normalized, so to speak, which means the wave
function must be must have values and must be rescate in such a way that if we integrate it over an
infinite range, then it must give one.
The expression in the brackets on the left hand side of the equation is just a more compact form to
express the integral.
It is a quite common shorthand in quantum theory that it will take up in more detail also later.
More generally, the wavefunction applies not only to a particle's position, but to any possible state,
it is a calculation tool with which also the probability to find a particle having a momentum or angular
momentum, the rotational speed and atom or a nucleus being in some energetic state can have, etc..
And the take away message of all of that is that quantum mechanics is a purely probabilistic theory
at bottom.
This is due to its wavy nature.
There is no way to know what the behavior of a single particle will be, even not in principle.
Except when the particle is in what is called an Afghan state, as we will see later.
That is why in quantum theory, statistical tools play such an important role, we can only compute
the probability to measure a value in some interval in quantum mechanics.
Quantum mechanics, it makes no sense to speak of a system that is in some state.
It makes only sense to say that there is a certain probability that the measurement will furnish an
outcome and that we associate with some state at the instant of measurement.
But we are not allowed to say anything on its state before and after that measurement.
The wavefunction is a state function only in the sense that it is a mathematical tool that tells us
about the statistics and probability to find a specific system in a specific state or a range of possible
states.
At this point, the question is whether the wavefunction is just an abstract mathematical description
of the statistical behavior of a system, or does it really represent a real object in the physical
world?
And if it has to be considered real, how can it be that it is something that behaves like a wave and
then turns out to describe particles?
This question poses a problem, which is the so-called measurement problem or what is more popularly
known as the problem of the wavefunction collapse.
It is one of the typical quantum ontological philosophical problems.
It is illustrated with what we already know and saw in the double slit experiment, namely that first
a plane wave is distracted by the slits and then the two expanding concerned concentric circles wavefront
emerging from each of the approaches to have towards the screen.
These wavefront can be described by the wavefunction.
See, once they interact with the screen, the interference fringes form, but as a pattern of dots,
each representing a point like interaction at some specific position, there is nothing left of any
wave.
And so we see that first we have the wave function and suddenly it seems to collapse into a point.
This suggests an interpretation that tries a bit desperately, I might say, to reconcile the two apparently
opposite points of view.
First, before the measurement, we must conceive of the single photon or electron or whatever particle
we may talk about as a wave or wave packets, which still before the measurement, that is, before
it hits the screen, continues to behave according to the diffraction and interpretive interference,
laws and principles.
There is nothing that should be conceived as a particle.
When the wavefront goes through the slits, it is still a wave and there is no particle that is supposed
to go through one or both slits, or only in the sense we might be authorized to say that quantum mechanics,
a single particle, goes through both slits and interferes with itself.
But this is a very desperate point of view, I would say, whereas at the instant of measurement or
interaction of the particle with another particle or with its surroundings, or it falls down on the
ground on and interacts with another microscopic or macroscopic object.
However, in our case, at the instant where the wave interacts with the screen, it suddenly reduces
or collapses to a point on the screen, manifesting itself again as a particle.
But before that instant, where the act of measurement, of course, or the.
Interaction, of course, you must still consider to be a wave with an extension in space, not a single
point.
From the mathematical, mathematical and formal abstract point of view, everything is clear.
You just calculate with the wave function and then take the squared models and obtain the probability,
the probability density where you will find your particle, integrate over a region of interest and
obtain a statement about the probability to observe the system in some specific region and for a specific
state here, the particle to be detected inside a spatial interval along the screen.
Therefore, the problem is not not mathematical.
We may say it is not even scientific, but it is an interpretational problem.
A question arises in the domain of the ontology of the philosophical speculation.
We might say from the ontological point of view, there is no consensus as to how we really should interpret
this collapse and what kind of objective reality quantum mechanics is describing.
After all, what kind of thing is it that behaves as a wave unless one looks at it and then it collapses
to a point instantly in an infinitesimal interval of time?
What is really out there?
We might say before the measurement, it seems that we have only a sort of ghostly entity, the way
we nature of which we will never observe directly, but we can infer from the interference phenomena.
And at the Measurement Act, it manifests nevertheless as a completely different entity, namely as
a point like particle.
And there is no way to intercept a morphing transformation from one entity to the another.
After all, we are talking about a probability wave travelling through space.
But the notion of probability is an abstract mathematical concept.
It is just a mathematical function.
Mathematicians write with a pencil on a piece of paper that we do not think of as an object, having
a concrete existing moving out there somewhere.
One can see waterways on a lake here.
Sound waves through air perceive light and sea birds flying.
But nobody has ever seen a mathematical function or the square root of minus one moving throughout space.
And yet this is what quantum physics seems to be about.
It seems that we must not only resort to very abstract notions to describe the world, but the world
itself seems to be a sort of mathematical abstraction reminiscent of a platonic region.
Is there anything physical out there that is represented by see is a collapse of see only a statistical
or is it also real physical entity occurrence?
So far, nobody has been able to furnish a really convincing and generally accepted answer to these
questions.
Most physicists simply do not bother and will tell you that they are too busy with making calculations,
are happy that the math works.
And indeed, the mathematical foundations of quantum mechanics were extremely powerful in furnishing,
furnishing predictions that could be measured and confirmed and which led to the tremendously successful
standard model of particle physics, atomic physics, solid state physics and so on.
With all their practical applications in applied physics as well.
But from the interpretational point of view, not much progress has been made, and this suggests that
we have still not gone deep enough in our understanding of the world.
For many years, physicists delighted themselves with calculations.
But recent attempts to build quantum computers, which need more or less direct answers to these questions,
and after decades of attempts without success, to discover a general theory of quantum gravity, that
kind of theory that reconciles the gravity force with electromagnetic and nuclear forces, these foundational
foundational issues have gotten more attention again.