Let us go through a brief introduction to some formal aspects of quantum mechanics.
We will keep it a non rigorous introduction in contrast to a complete course on quantum mechanics,
but it is nevertheless necessary to digest some simple but very important formalism and symbolism,
since it will continue to emerge frequently here and there.
And it is that kind of representation, mathematical representation that you will encounter throughout
all textbooks on quantum mechanics.
So let us turn our attention back to the concept of the wavefunction.
We consider it to be continuous for the position and space of a particle and its value, the density
probability or the integrated probability function of the particle in space, which gives us the total
probability that an event occurs.
This does not change abruptly from one point to another.
And for the case of the position of a particle along an x axis in space, it is a continuous function.
That is the way function of X of X, X opposite X is a continuous function in X.
Technically speaking, the system has an infinitely many degrees of freedom, one size, also infinite,
many degrees of freedom.
We saw, however, that there can be other behaviors of quantum systems, for example, that the energy
state of atoms is quantized, for instance.
Recall the optical spectral lines of hydrogen or the fun experiment where we saw that the atoms have
discrete energy levels here.
The wave function can no longer describe the behavior of continuous energy output, but the energy is
insteps.
So also the wavefunction, uh, can no longer be a continuous function, but must be represented by
a set of discrete possible states of the system.
As for instance, we have already seen the case of the hydrogen spectrum in these cases, we must ride
the wave function, the wavefunction PSI not as a continuous function in space, but as a set of signal
states, E1, E2, E3 and so on until n the end energy state, which can be represented, which can
represent the discrete energy states, capital letters, letters, E1, E2, E3 and so on, until N
or the dynamic of variables like spin or angular momentum, as we shall see later.
In the language of quantum mechanics, each of these discrete states of a quantum system are called
Igen states from the German Igen, which means self igan states are those quantum states where repeated
measurements of the system under consideration will always lead to the same result.
So, for example, if a particle is in a specific igan state energy and states, this means that I measure
its energy and always I get all this the same energy.
So then we can say that particle is or that atom or whatever that quantum system is in that ion state,
which distinguish itself from other sort of states that we will see later, because we will see that
how also quantum systems can be also in a superposition of state.
So, for example, the energy of a quantum system is the dynamic variable, the observable quantity
that can be measured and which can have several discrete igan states E1, E2, E3, but not something
in between in quantum mechanics.
These Afghan states are defined on a Hilbert space without going too much into mathematical details.
It's suffice to say that the Hilbert space is an abstract vector space that is an extension of the real
Euclidean space to a multidimensional space of complex numbers and complex vectors.
So if the Hilbert space has a finite dimension, it is the state space of a quantum system with a finite
number of island states.
Otherwise, it is infinite, as infinite is then the number of degrees of freedom.
Another important difference between the space as we conceive it in school geometry is that the elements
of the Hilbert space are no longer points and coordinates, but functions.
The wavefunction being the primary object to act on.
So instead of points, we have wavefunction, the Eigen states, E1, E2, E3 and so on form the Igen
basis, Igen basis of the Hilbert space and the over, all possible states of a quantum system are represented
by a vector defined on this basis called the state eigenvector or just eigenvector or simply the state
vector.
As in the figure, you can see a simple case for a system with three possible agnostic states.
So you see here, for example, the case of a system with three possible igan states.
Therefore, we can depicted make a graph, a picture in a three dimensional space.
If it would have more igan states, more possible states, this would be possible to make a graph of
it because then we would have a multidimensional object.
However, until one, two or three dimensional, it is still in our human understanding how to represent
this with a graph.
And it resembles in some sense, the Cartesian coordinate system.
However, instead of the X, Y and Z axis, we have the axis corresponding to the three possible states
or eigenvectors.
Whereas the length of each eigenvector take for instance, each one is given by a complex coefficient
C one the same also for the other two actors, C two and three, C three.
These are complex numbers which express how long this vector is.
Whereas here the.
Total vector, so to speak, which is a state vector in quantum mechanics, is the linear combination
of all the AGN eigenvectors.
So we see that this is given by the red vector and we see that the state vector of of the whole of the
system over all the possible states is given by BPCI equals one one plus three to two plus three easily.
We will now quickly describe also this formalism with the strange brackets.
I will come to this next.
But what is important that you understand, at least intuitively, this principle of the state vector
and how this is a linear combination of all the possible eigenvectors in what we call a Hilbert space,
in this case a three dimensional, but normally it is much bigger Hilbert space eventually also an infinite
dimensional space.
So as we see, let's recapitulate, because this is also an important point, the information with what
probability each of the Igan states will be observed after a measurement is carried by the complex coefficients
see one, two, three, and so on.
This means also that the bond rule still holds.
You remember model squared, the probability capital letter P associated to the is igan state e i is
the squared models of the E complex coefficients.
C.
E.
So as we read it here.
P of e i equal, c I times C I complex you.
Is equal, the model of square of S.I for I equal one, two and so on, depending from the dimension
of the Hilbert or if you prefer, the number of possible Igen states or to quantum system.
So let us see something about this notation, their notation.
Of this sort here and with which is pronounced cat by.
Is common notation for vectors in quantum theory, state vectors can be written according to the Dirac
notation.
Paul Dirac was a British physicist who made several contributions in quantum theory.
We already saw how he used to write the kind of integrals we encountered when we discussed the Bourne
Rule as brackets as and you pronounce this here, Brassai capsid sort of.
Each bracket bracket is a product more precisely, one should say the inner product of a better but
bracket a AROW vector, which.
Elements are the complex conjugate of a and a cat vector, B, a column vector.
As you can see, this was not like lacking a bit of weird lexical fantasy, which, however, turned
out to be extremely useful.
For example, the general bracket brought a cat B is given by this formula.
Here you see a cat B is equal.
The complex conjugate vector of a bra A and which is written horizontally as a one complex Connealy
times a too complex concept and so on, so on, until a complex conflict times the vector, that cat
B, which is a vector written vertically and in each element without a complex conjugation.
So be one P to be two and so on until the end.
And which Phanor is written as a one complex conjugate of one times B one plus complex conjugate of
A two times B two and so on.
This is just an algebraic method to define our writing.
So you see the right expression of this formula can be synthesized in this very compact form, rather
a cat B.
This means also that with Dirac's notation, a lot of calculations are made formally simpler.
For example, if you take this one here.
The bra.
Of the East Asian state, Brax, a etai equal to a vector, which is zero everywhere except at the E
coefficient, at the E coefficient, and you put there the complex conjugate coefficient corresponding
to the length of the E eigenvector.
So you have zero zero zero.
And at the IS position C, a complex conjugate Ochiai start and the others also zero.
And then you write as a CI equal, you want to see three and Sien and then the probability to find that
is agan state can be written also in that bracket notation as follows the probability p of e i that
is I can state to measure that is I can say it is given by the model, the square of Brax.
If I get PSI, which is equal, the model square of C, I think, and according to the little formula
and calculation we have done here above, it is just a symbolic formalism introduced by Dirac and later
developed further by others, such as the mathematician John Funnymen, with which one represents the
probability to observe a system with a number of possible discrete states.
It is customary also to state that it is the model square of the projection of the state vector BPCI
onto the igan basis spanned by its eigenvectors, one can interpret the dashed lines in the graph as
projections here.
This lines are the projection of what the measurement does.
When you measure a quantum system, you project its state or state vector on to one of its IDN basis.
It is a measurement act.
The project projects the state vector onto one of its possible Iten basis vectors.
This is analogous to the way function, collapse or state production we saw in the case of a continuous
wave function there.
Also, the act of measurement collapses the way function, describing the particle position in a continuous
space on one of the infinitely possible states after all.
Also, the position of a particle is a state here.
The same happens the projection of the state vector onto one of its aying basis is, mathematically
speaking, what we do in reality, doing a measurement in the laboratory with a measurement device.
We bring the quantum system from a quantum not still not defined quantum state, and then make a measurement
and only one of these possible states happens to come into being so to speak.
Moreover, once the quantum system has been placed into one of the island states in quantum mechanics
jargon, one says it has been prepared into a specific state.
And if it does not interact with the environment, then every subsequent measurement will always deliver
the same result.
Therefore, the system being in the state.
Cat.
E i.
In fact, this description of quantum measurement derives directly from experimental observation and
was first formalized by von Neumann, also known as the four nomen projection postulate or.
More recently, in modern quantum theory, you simply call it the measurement measurement postulate
of quantum mechanics, and in its modern version, it tells us the following, that for each measurement
of an observable, the probability to find it in one of its possible igan states is given by the formula
that we have discussed previously that we see more of the square of the complex coefficients.
Secondly, after the measurement, the system instantly collapses from state to state etai system to
one of the vectors.
And this is the projection.
It projects the projects, the state vector from side, from step side to one of the island states.
Ay ay ay ay ay ay.
Thirdly, from that moment on, any new measurement will always show the system to be still in the same
state.
This is an important fact, which means that say, for example, we have a particle which is in some
superposition.
For example, we don't know what kind of state it is.
It can be whatever kind of system.
But once the measurement is made on this particles, they say it's spin up.
We get spin up in the measurement.
Then if we repeat the measurement, we will always see spin up again.
The same, obviously, with spin down.
That's something we have already seen with Tangela Experiments where we saw that once we measure the
spin of a particle, then cascading the stars and galaxies devices on the same axis that's important
on the same axis, then you will always see it again in the same state.
So in short, a very important postulate of quantum mechanics and why this puzzle has always been employed
with success as a powerful predictive tool in quantum mechanics.
Later on, we will see how it leads to some still unsolved issues summarized by the so-called measurement
problem.
You go from the measurement to measurement problem and which is also famously represented by the Schrodinger's
cat experiment and paradox.
Again, with the sum of all the models squared, complex coefficients, each representing the probability
of the ice, can states to be measured.
These must obviously sum up to Surtain certainty that you must get one number one, which tells us that
this is 100 percent probability that this.
One of these must come out because there are no other left or to put it another way, the sum of the
probabilities of all possible evil even must give unity.
No.
Not how the sum of all the probabilities adding up to unity is represented in Dirac's notation neatly
as this expression here, which is rare Keat of side.
Which is the sum of all the complex coefficients squared and which must finally give the number one.
Also, keep in mind that eigenvectors are always depicted and considered as perpendicular vectors to
each other that is orthogonal or also normal vectors orthogonal means generically that they are perpendicular
and also normal means that they are perpendicular vectors.
But with unit length one, they have a length one.
But in any case, eigenvectors are orthogonal and they represent mutually exclusive measurement outcomes
such as spin up and spin down.
You, of course, the quantum state can be in a superposition before the measurement, but once you
have made the measurement, you will only see or spin up or spin down.
You cannot see in the real world spin up and spin down at the same time.
And this is translated geometrically in the fact that the eigenvectors are perpendicular to each other.
Also, remember that if.
To eigenvectors, Eisenstaedt vectors are let's let them simply cat and cat B are orthogonal, then
they are sculler product Brahe A Cat B is always equal zero.
So if you want to check if two vectors are perpendicular to each other, you just make the sculler product
of them.
And if it is zero, then this is a geometrical demonstration, proof that they are indeed perpendicular.
And this means physically in our measurement environment, in the laboratory that we are talking about,
two mutually exclusive.
Outcomes, measurement outcomes.