Now that we have seen a bit what the Schrodinger equation is about, let us briefly take a quick look
at its application to the real world.
In fact, the Schrodinger igan equation allows for the calculation of the energy spectra of atoms,
the potential energy we of X of the electrons around the nucleus depends on the number of protons that
this nuclear nucleus contains.
If one sets the particular boundary condition on the structure of this potential for, for instance,
that is spherical and that it decreases according to an inverse law and that the wavefunction must be
continuous, the Schrodinger equation becomes a solvable second order differential equation.
Which solution will furnish the energy states and the probability amplitude psi of X to find the particle
somewhere around the atomic nucleus?
But that is what we have always to keep in mind, this is only a this has been.
Must be intended only in a probabilistic sense, the igan equation formalism with its operators, eigenvectors
and aying values is a mathematical description of the probability to find a particle in a specific position
or state more generally with some specific momentum and some discrete or continuous energy states and
so on.
There's no such thing as in the balls atom or in classical physics as particles flying around a nucleus.
There are no particles at all, but only the probability density function wrapped in some form or another
around the center, the nucleus of an atom.
In the case of the simplest possible atom, only an electron which is immersed into the potential field
of a proton that is the hydrogen atom.
Will we obtain for the energy ground state away function which describes a simple, simple probability
density, just a spherical probability density distribution centred around one proton, no nucleus,
no electron is visible as a particle.
What this represents is the probability density to find the hydrogen atoms electron.
It is just a graphical but quite effective representation of so-called atomic orbitals.
Orbitals are the squared models of the way function obtained from Schrodinger's equation and the graphical
representation of which highlights the statistical probabilities probabilistic nature of the quantum
world.
You just show it with a picture.
The more intensely shaded regions here represent higher probability to find the electron in some just
that place, while when the shading is less intense, one represents this.
This represents simply a low probability density, low probability to find the electron.
Just in that place, we get some sort of cloudy and fuzzy sphere, the so-called electron cloud or electron
electron configuration, which has no longer anything left of the clear, well-defined, deterministic
and precise representation of classical mechanics.
However, this figure depicts the hydrogen atom only in its ground state, energy, ground, state.
As we know, atoms are capable to absorb in a quantized manner quanta of energy and acquire other energy
discrete levels.
If an atom absorbs a photon, the electron cloud will acquire a different configuration.
That is a different wavefunction with another probability distribution which will describe the excited
atom.
You will certainly recall how we used the one dimensional standing wave for the hydrogen atom in both
atomic model, where we used to describe the electrons orbit no longer with a particle travelling in
precise and well-defined path, but as a travelling wave around the atomic nucleus.
That is a probability wave which wavelength is given by the liberal relation, and that could be displaced
only at discrete distances from the center of the atomic nucleus to its energy levels according to its
energy levels, because otherwise it cannot build up a standing wave with constructive interference.
This idea can be generalized and extended to a circular circular two-dimensional standing with which
we could visualise here with a sort of vibrating membrane.
There are only specific vibration frequencies that are allowed in order to produce a standing wave that
does not destruct itself due to destructive interference.
But that has just that specific correct frequency that the back and forth reflect.
The waves overlap onto each others.
So to build up a constructive interference, stable, two dimensional standing wave, as in this case
here, there are two quantum quantum numbers now because there could be two frequencies, one vibration
along one dimension, say, the X direction and the other vibration along the other spatial dimension,
say the Y direction.
Therefore, one classifies all the two-dimensional standing waves with a set of two numbers zero one
one one, two, one and so on.
The same thing does the equation for a spherical, three dimensional potential here for completeness.
The hydrogen atom orbital in its ground state, which corresponds to no vibration standing probability
wave.
It is just a spherical distribution has been shown again, whereas these pictures show several atomic
orbital examples for higher energy levels of the hydrogen atom.
Well, now, since since it is difficult to visualize the internal distribution of the three dimensional
standing wave.
These are two dimensional sections, slice slices of the three dimensional probability distribution.
So you must imagine just cut it a section of it.
It is what we get when we cut the atom along as light that goes through its central nucleus, so to
speak.
Each state defines the form and structure of the orbital and the slice.
They are three dimensional standing waves, however, the kind of three dimensional analogue of the
two dimensional or one dimensional circular standing waves or that we saw also for the standing wave
in a box, if you recall, when we considered to explain the black body radiation.
The difference, however, is that an atom does not have a solid confining boundary.
As to the walls of a box or we imagine a billiard ball, but is mostly the limited by its nuclear no
nuclear electric potential.
And since we are a three dimensional space, the atoms electrons configuration can be described by three
atomic quantum numbers.
The first is the principle quantum number 10, which represents the energy level of the atom.
It is that we already encountered in the BARATTA model with Circler electronic orbits.
The second is the angular or at the quantum number labeled L. which characterizes the total angular
momentum of the electron and specifies the shape of the orbital in that specific energy level.
And this is the additional quantum number that emerges when one considers Sommerfeld some of sommerfeld
extension from circler to elliptical electron electronic orbits.
If you recall, we already saw this.
Whereas the third quantum number, the so-called magnetic momentum quantum number, no Lebert M describes
the orientation, the orientation of the orbital in energy state and an angular momentum l along a specified
direction.
From this mathematical quantization procedure we have described above and apply, applying a former
description no longer in Cartesian coordinates but in spherical coordinates.
It is possible to show how all these three numbers arise naturally and describe the different states
of an atom and nice probability density cloud is associated with every combination of these quantum
numbers.
Atomic physics is much more complicated than that.
This should be regarded, regarded only as an intuitive introduction, and we will not go deeper into
this.
It would require a much more rigorous and lengthy mathematical physical description which goes beyond
the aims of this course.
What you must, however, keep in mind is that what you are seeing here are probability distributions,
another decisive difference to the black body cavity where the standing waves are considered, where
electromagnetic waves.
This means that if we would try to detect the position of an electron inside these orbitals, the wave
function would collapse instantly at the act of measurement to a point particle.
But before that, in quantum theory, we must conceive the system and is not made of particles.
But as a single whole entity described by a fuzzy electron cloud represented by the orbitals.
It is like in the case of the double slit experiment before the photon hitting the screen, we must
conceive of a wave describing the photon at the instant of interaction.
It collapses to a point on the screen.
Not only at that instant, not before.
Here we have the same situation before any attempt to measure something.
It makes no sense to say that the electron has a specific position around the nucleus or momentum,
but only that we have a certain probability to find it there with some certain probability to have a
specific momentum.
High lightning with this, the purely wavy and probabilistic nature of the quantum world, these sorts
of calculations which all use this mathematical, mathematical formalism, the Schrodinger's equation
and Dirac's notation can, of course, be applied to much more complex atoms than the hydrogen case
and also to atomic nuclei and more like molecules.
It is almost impossible to visualize the internal structure of a three dimensional orbital for a complex
system like a molecule which has many electrons.
However, here you can get at least a glimpse of how the outer and inner electron configuration looks
like for carbon dioxide dioxide molecule.
And the lower image is that of the water molecule.
It is in this way that nuclear and atomic physics were successfully understood and exploited.
Even today, nuclear reactions, atoms, molecules and several properties of matter can be explained.
Solid-State physics is one of the most prolific sciences of modern times, Schrodinger's equation and
much more.
In general, the eigenvalue equation of Dirac's not notation, which builds upon the burning fuel,
turned out to be a powerful mathematical tool which led to the quantum revolution of the 20th century.
This allowed physicists to develop a sophisticated but consistent theory that proved to be correct over
and over again, providing also a formidable theoretical background that allowed applied physics to
build the material basis upon which the modern electronic devices in the industry was revolutionized.
If you are using your computer now, it is also because of this theoretical developments in quantum
physics, which allowed for building modern integrated circuits and chips and with which we nowadays
build our electronic devices on the theory.
On the theoretical side, adding special relativity to this non relativity with the quantum mechanics
led to the standard model of particle physics, which can be considered one of the most successful and
precise scientific theories ever.