At this point, physicist had a sufficiently large mass of experimental and conceptual understanding
of the physics of atoms to go a step further, the idea that matter emits and absorbs electromagnetic
energy in a discrete manner had become at the time and established and accepted fact.
What was missing, however, was a structural model which could at least partially explain this.
Ernest Rutherford, a physicist from New Zealand, discovered in 1911.
By performing certainly scattering experiments with radioactive particles that atoms are almost empty
objects, since more than 99 percent of the mass of an atom is concentrated inside a tiny, positively
charged nucleus.
Putting things together a couple of years later, Niels Bohr, a Danish physicist conceived of the atom
as a kind of tiny solar system with the negative electrons circling around the positively charged nucleus
made of protons.
This is the model most of you may have encountered in school.
What characterizes Borse model was that it is it still retains the idea of electrons flying along very
well defined and precise orbits.
Every orbit can be occupied by a certain number of electrons.
Moreover, every orbit corresponds to some energy level of the electrons in the atom.
And there were no intermediate orbits, only orbits corresponding to specific energy levels, which
can be labeled with progressive integer numbers and equal one to three and so on.
These numbers were called and are called so until today, principle quantum numbers, because these
define the possible discrete energy states of the atom.
This was the first atomic model that could explain partially at least, why atoms absorb and emit light.
Indiscreet quantities is the orbits are fixed.
Then also the energy levels of electrons in those orbits around the nucleus must be discrete.
The energy, absorption and recommission is conceptually visualized with the transition of an electron
from one orbit to another.
If an electron absorbs a photon coming from the outside from the environment, then it transits towards
a higher orbit, but then will quickly readmit the photon back by returning to the lower energy level
orbit.
Remission, of course, because every system will always tend to return towards the lowest energy level
possible, since there is an empty place left by the Electrum, it will reoccupy it back by emission
of electromagnetic waves.
It is not necessary that the that the that the transition be between neighbouring orbits, but could
also occur between orbits with very different quantum numbers.
The difference, however, in any case, in energy of the two orbits will be just that energy that the
electron absorbs and emits.
And this energy difference will also be that which determines the frequency or the wavelength of the
absorbed and emitted photon, according to Planck's formula.
This model could indeed explain the atomic spectra of the hydrogen atom, measured experimentally like
this one for the hydrogen atom and that we have already seen before.
For every electron transition from one orbit to the other, in each of its possible combinations, one
can calculate the the energy difference and there of the energy and wavelength of the absorbed or emitted
photon.
Yes, summarizing a qualitative picture of some of these possibilities is displayed.
For example, the transition to the ground state quantum number, an equal one.
Sometimes it's physicists use quantum number and equal zero.
As for the ground state, but in our case I put an equal one.
So corresponding to the energy e0 zero from all the above discrete electron orbits and equal to an equal
three, etc. of energy one, two, etc. emit photons of the energy each one minus zero e two minus eight
zero three minus eight zero and so on.
This is the so-called Lehman series of hydrogen, of the hydrogen spectral lines, many other possibilities
other than that, which means many other possible serious exists, each labeled with the name of its
discoverer.
In this figure, you have that Lehman series is depicted here on the left in this blue picture as a
transition which corresponds to an emission of photons.
In fact, you have the electrons falling down to the quantum, to the energy state corresponding to
the quantum number and equal one.
But this could be also an absorption not only in emission, for example, for the Bulmer serious here,
you can see that you have the same thing only in the opposite direction, but with the electrons absorbing
a quantity of energy from an energy level corresponding to the quantum number and equal to therefore
to the second orbit electron orbit up to the third, fourth, fifth and so on orbit.
On the right side, you have a similar scheme which may which is only shown graphically in energy levels
instead of using the picture of orbits.
And you can see that you have also an energy level, infinite, which means nothing else than the electron
comes from the far outside and falls into the field and domain of interaction of the nucleus of the
hydrogen atom, which is obviously the proton, which means so it comes from the infinite distance and
falls onto into this orbital.
Atomic model, which is Borse model.
And again, also for the other serious passion and bracket, serious and so on, these are the cases
where the energy friends of the emitted or absorbed photon is equal, that where you have a transition
from some orbit or from some quantum energy level or quantum that with some quantum number down to Itou
in the case of passion, serious and down to E three in case of bracket serious.
So this was, broadly speaking, the model of Atum, it might be interesting also to say to explain
as a further historical side note, uh, it might be worth to mention that both Atem atomic model was
even refined and extended by are not Sommerfeld Sommerfeld, a German physicist who considered also
elliptical electron orbits just as we know it from planetary orbits.
Planetary orbits are all elliptical.
The circular, perfectly circular orbit, impractical in practice, does not exist.
It is only an ideal.
It is idealisation and and this is an interesting historical anecdote since it shows how we as humans
are instinctively driven first by the desire to transfer our understanding of the macrocosm onto the
microcosm.
And sometimes it works.
In fact, this attempt was not without success.
Sommerfeld Sommerfeld introduced a second quantum number, the so-called Orbital or Atsumi quantum number.
Er the first was and this is L a.
Which for each principal quantum number end specifies nd allowed orbital angular momentum of the electron
around the atom atomic nucleus.
So you have that l the second quantum number that Sommerfeld introduced, equal zero one, two and so
on until N minus one.
And these levels are also designated as Espie, the EFG and so on.
Also with letters and which characterizes the ratio between the same samey, major and minor axis that
is the elongation of the corresponding electron orbit.
This more general, more sommerfeld model was able to accurately explain a number of more complex atomic
spectral spectral lines, indeed, um, it provided a partial at least an approximated explanation of
the splitting of some spectral lines that were observed due to the presence of strong external electric
fields called this is an effect called the stark effect, or of magnetic fields, which is called also
that Zeeman effect.
It was a quite exciting success at the time, since this seemed to indicate that physicists were after
something that could lead them in the right direction.
However, also many inconsistencies became clear soon the summer was able to make these predictions
of the atomic hydrogen.
And spectral lines.
But first of all, only with limited precision and and and and also, at any rate, only for the for
the hydrogen spectra, while all the other elements of the periodic table, not to say the molecular
energy levels and structure cannot be explained by such a simple theory.
Both atomic model and the more I find both some Sommerfeld atomic model was an attempt to explain atomic
behavior and energy states, and it is indeed an interesting historical remnant of the intellectual
intellectual journey of humankind.
In my opinion, it made perfect sense when viewed in that historical context, but nowadays it is no
longer tenable.
Absolutely not.
Unfortunately, it is still taught in schools as if it were the final sentence, sentence and summation
of atomic physics.
Whereas quantum mechanics will explain things much more accurately and precisely as we shall see later,
it was only with the advent of quantum physics and its application to atomic to the atomic structure
that science could correctly predict atomic spectra.
The atomic model that arises from quantum mechanics, will be completely different than that, of course,
or sommerfeld model, and which could only be considered temporary, such as finally Ossabaw himself
had to admit.