All right, in the last few videos in this series, we got a brief taste of the general environment,
an atmosphere that was in place when Ice-T made his breakthrough discovery a special relativity back
in 19 05.
What did we learn?
We learned that back in that time, we had really fleshed out the ideas of classical physics Newtonian
mechanics, but rendue mechanics, Hamiltonian mechanics, you name it.
And we were very confident but complacent.
And what we had discovered, right in terms of relativity, it was a very simple, straightforward idea
that we had worked out many, many years ago.
What we derived in the first video is the Galilean transformation, a transformation that allows us
to establish an absolute universal conception between two different perspectives or two different reference
frames, right?
We are trying to make this absolute conception so that if reference frames a observe something and reference
frame, b observe the same behavior, we can make their interpretations gel up and make sense right
to be compatible with one another, right?
We wanted this universal conception.
OK, so the Galilean transformation allowed us to do that.
But what we found when we started doing the Mikkelson morally experiment.
And when Terrance and Phillip did their experiment with the lasers when they shot out the lasers and
found that, whoa, this does not extend to electricity magnetism.
What we found is that the Galilean transformation is a limited snapshot of a bigger picture, right?
We had only understood how the how the universe behaves for a small subset of events rate events that
occur with very low velocities, very low speeds, very low situations that do not encompass everything
that could happen in the universe, OK?
So the problem that scientists were really experiencing was the fact that Maxwell, in electricity magnetism,
said light should be constant, but they did not want to believe in that because they're well-established
ideas and notions.
You know, the ideas of classical physics and the Galilean transformation insinuate that if you have
some reference for that's moving really fast, you shoot out some light.
Guess what?
The light observed by somebody stationary should be faster.
We fleshed out those ideas in the last video.
OK, now what we're going to do is we're going to take a look at why chants of fill up when they're
doing their experiment, why they ran into problems, why the Mikkelson morally experiment, why it
changes the face of physics, why it gave us the first breakthrough that had not happened for many,
many years, right?
Physics was sort of stagnant at that time.
OK, so believe it or not, what Einstein proposed and what Taz and Philip had just discovered in their
experiments is actually the backbone of special relativity.
OK?
And by accepting this discovery, that light is always constant and asserting this fact, relativistic
effects are the consequences that arise by accepting these realities, OK?
So what they had just discovered are the two postulates a special relativity, which I have written
out and documented here and again.
By accepting these possibilities for special relativity, several consequences arise which give birth
to special relativity and relativistic effects that we're going to start to discuss in this video,
right?
So this is a super exciting video.
This is going to be your first taste of special relativity.
Some of the wacky effects that are introduced as a result of it, and hopefully your mind is blown.
Hopefully, you have a lot of questions.
You should write Physics should be a discipline in which you question really, you observe you do not
prescribe.
If you learned that last week, you observe is their and then you critique.
OK, so first, let's go over the postulates that were just discovered in terrorism Phillips' experiment
or from the Mikkelson immorally experiment that Einstein extracted when he was developing his theory
is the first postulate.
Now I'm going to give the exact wording from a textbook.
It's going to be a little cryptic and I'm going to explain it.
Postulate number one states that if I reference Frame X is an inertial frame, remember we went over
inertial.
That's a frame which does not have inertial effects, no acceleration.
It's moving at a cost velocity.
So again, this is if a reference frame s is an inertial frame and if a second frame f prime moves of
a constant velocity keyword here costs velocity for special relativity relative to the original frame
s then s prime is also inertial.
What in the world does that mean you've got?
Re-align, you're like, Woo.
I had no idea what that's talking about, but if you dive a bit deeper into it, what's really exciting
is that the laws of physics are invariant between frames now and our second video, we went through
this experiment with terrorism and fill up, and I showed that gallium invariance is is a thing.
What was that?
Let's refresh your memory.
Gasoline and variant states that the laws of Newtonian mechanics are going to gel up between reference
frames.
And we proved Newton's second law.
But what this is says, is all the laws of physics are going to be constant or they're going to be arriving
in the same manner, regardless of your reference frame.
OK.
So this is a pretty cool possibility and has a lot of consequences associated with it.
One thing which I want you to think about and keep in the back of your head is that if you accept postulate
number one with the laws of physics are invalid between frames, it means that there is no absolute
reference frame you like.
Oh, wait a second, we're trying to find this absolute universal conception of physics.
What does that mean?
That basically means that if you have two reference frames, one which you think is stationary and another
one that is moving, there is absolutely no way to figure out what is the moving reference frame and
what is not.
I'm going to repeat that again.
There is no way to figure out what reference frame is moving and what is not, because this conception
of reality, the conception of a moving reference frame is relative to an observer, right?
There is no absolute conception.
So let's say we have fill up you standing on the earth and we see Terence Zoom by in a spaceship.
Philip is going to say Terence is moving, but from Terence's perspective, if he's on a ship and he
doesn't know a priori that it's moving, it may look as though the Earth is moving away from him.
Because if there's no acceleration, it may feel as if you're stationary on the ship and you will not
know that you're moving unless you had studied the stuff previously.
OK?
So I want you to keep that in the back of your head that there's this sort of symmetry, this sort of
duality perspective going on here that you cannot know absolutely who is moving right.
There is no absolute conception of the universe.
Rather, it's relative to reference frames.
OK?
OK.
So that's one big postulate that came out of the the observations that Einstein was making and also
from Tyson Phillips' experiment.
But the big one, which has passed probably the most significant consequences is postulate number two,
and this states that the speed of light in vacuum has the same that you see in every direction, in
all inertial frames.
What does that mean?
Well, this is basically the result we got from the last video where, you know, we had a chance to
fill up conducting that experiment with the spaceship through flying away from some stationary, relatively
stationary individual.
He shot a laser.
And they both observed the same speed of that light.
OK, so this is actually something we've tested again and again and again, which was shown to be true,
which is shown to be the way in which the universe really, I guess, takes the phenomenon of light
and transpires in front of us, OK?
So that's how the universe behaves.