I want to talk about one more thing, and I'm going to talk about how we actually proved this different
experiments we've done to show that, you know, this weird, wacky idea is true, that it really happens.
And what I want to say is that built into this experiment, by design, by design, there's a sort of
an asymmetry at play here.
And I did this on purpose.
So you may have heard when I was explaining this experiment outlined right here that I want you to pay
attention to the events that happen here.
What I said is that in the moving reference frame, the two events the flash of light and the detection
of light from which we're measuring time.
They are synonymous.
They happen in the same place, two events are synonymous.
However, in this reference frame.
It doesn't have the same kind of symmetry.
This guy and this guy, we need two people in different locations.
The events have to take place at different spots.
One is that x one y one, the other one is that x to y two.
And X1 and X2 do not equal each other.
This is different, this is different than this, and depending upon how you define these guys, you
is prime s that's going to give rise to this effect.
So what you need to know is that the person?
Who is moving?
Well, always has a time that's lower than the observer seeing that moving.
So in other words, this time is always going to move slower.
His clocks are going to move slower.
Then fill ups and Erick's the Persian stationery on Earth, as you can tell, that's sort of confusing
when you go through these kinds of problems.
You don't have to figure out keep track of what's going on, what is s.
What we say is that we're going to designate Terrence this time as a special time, a special time.
We're going to call it what is known as proper time.
OK.
And we're going to give it a designation which you'll see in the lot of text books as a not t not.
OK, so I'm going to write this as such Senate and explain what I'm talking about a bit more.
T not c not.
OK.
So this.
Is proper.
Time very important.
Proper time again.
That is the time in the reference frame that is moving or what is more important is the time as measured
by somebody where the two events occur in the same place.
Now the reason why we call it proper time is because.
For somebody on Earth from an everyday kind of situation when you measure something, you know, if
you're in a car and you make your trip when you start the trip and when you end the trip, it occurs
in the same place relative to your reference frame.
Right?
You're in the car when it starts and you're in the car when it ends.
That's how we time things.
OK.
That's how you time things.
So it's proper in the sense that it gels up with our intuition, what we're used to viewing times.
So again, proper time is always selected as the time where the two events occur on the same place where
they're synonymous.
OK.
And what is going to happen is that time as measured by somebody who is not moving, who is stationary,
right?
They're going to measure the two events.
Their time is going to be dilated.
It's going to be larger, which is documented in this equation here.
OK, so that in here it asymmetry is built into the problem.
And now you're thinking, Yes, I'm a master of special relativity, so I'm going to throw in something
to mix it up a bit and really make you think about this.
So I just talked about an asymmetry.
But what I'm going to say, and it's going to sound sort of contradicted.
So a lot of things will sound in special relativity.
There is actually a symmetry at play in this problem.
What what am I talking about here?
All right.
So I told you there's an asymmetry in the sense that the two events occur at the same place in here
and they don't end this reference frame.
But.
You know, in this set up, Terrance says.
Or rather, Phillips says that your clock is running slow.
That's just how it is.
That's how it's going to be.
But at the same time, we could have done this experiment in the reverse direction, which arises some
symmetric property of the experiment, right?
Parents could say, Hey, screw this clock, you guys, you have the clock on Earth.
When I fly by on, I'm going to, you know what?
I'm going, I'm going to measure it.
I'm going to see what happens.
So in that situation, if you have the clock on Earth, this is sort of reversed.
What's going to happen is they're going to measure.
The light coming up and their picture, follow ups and Eric Fisher is going to look something like this,
it's like, what will it observe on Earth?
We shoot a laser up, it comes back down and we don't have any sensibility about anything moving.
But according to parents and the first postulate, special relativity, we cannot determine that he
is moving and they're not or that they're moving and he is not.
The first process that's for all to the says that there is no absolute reference frame.
At rest.
So because of that and because we're an inertial reference frame, Terence is going to say, Hey, I'm
just standing here.
You guys are moving from his reference frame, looking out the window.
It's going to look as though Philip and Eric are moving away from him.
All right.
He doesn't know that a ship is moving.
He has no a priori knowledge.
So it may look like these guys are the ones who are removing him from his standpoint.
What Terence is actually going to see, it's going to look like this same picture.
But on Earth?
OK, so these guys are moving.
And then what he will say is, according to Esperon, we get something like this the opposite of that.
But if we account for proper time, the proper time.
Is going to be the people on Earth where it goes up and down.
And then Eric is just going to say, gets it gets diluted, dilated.
So we see here that there's an inherent contradiction, right?
According to Tarrant's, these guys are moving, but au pair according to fill up.
These guys are moving.
Who's right?
Right?
In this case and the original case?
When Terence is moving.
Philip is going to say your clock is running slow and the right.
But in the reverse case, we just discussed.
When these guys are moving, cash is going to say, wait a second.
Fill up.
Your clock is running slow.
And he's right.
Wait a second.
Doesn't that contradict what's going on here?
No, it doesn't.
It works out.
They're both right.
This is special relativity.
What you observe is relative your perspective and the phenomena that arises is relative to your experience,
to your reference frame.
OK, and that's what makes special relativity so weird.
You should be like one the world's going on here, and we're going to take a look in the next video
at something called the twin paradox, which resolves this for you and makes you feel much better.
But they're both right.
Phillip thinks his clock is running slow, but at the same time, Tarrant's thinks Philip's clock is
running slow and they're both right.
That's where relativity folks weird stuff.
All right, I'll resolve that in the next video.
I can let you think about it.
See if you can figure it out.
See if you figure it out.