All right, for the final part of this problem, in part, see what we're going to do is we're going
to consider a more challenging question because I consider the first few parts pretty straightforward.
We're just taking our ideas, taking the concepts and we're labeling things, identifying things and
then plugging and chugging.
But in this part, we're going to mix it up a bit.
I'm going to challenge you a bit and show you that, yes, relativity is weird.
It's wacky, and some challenging ideas can crop up.
There really force you to think hard about what's going on in front of you, OK?
So for this problem, which is going to be labeled part, see what it states is the phone, it says,
according to the rocket clock.
How long after it left did the signal arrive back at Earth?
Now, if you took what we did initially, you said, Oh, I know the proper time of the rocket, I know
the Earth.
I'm living going to use my delta to eagles gamma times, Delta T not equation.
And then I'm just going to calculate what I need, and that's going to give you the right answer.
And if you go down that path without paving that path to success, correctly labeling things, questioning
things, thinking before you act, you would end up with the wrong answer.
What am I talking about?
To illustrate this, what I'm going to do is I'm going to solve the problem without any governing equation.
You had an answer and then show how we can get that quicker using time dilation if if we identify things
properly, right?
So it's important to think about these things before you jump, dive straight into the problem and start
chugging along.
OK.
So what we're going to do when we read this, we know that we're in the rocket's reference frame because
we're doing this according to the rocket clock.
And what we want to try and find out is the total time again.
But with respect to the rocket, what is it?
What does it determine in order to really get the correct result?
We need to question what's happening in that reference frame.
So let's do a thought experiment just like Einstein himself.
OK.
So according to the rocket, what's going on, going for the rocket?
If you're in the rock and you're standing still, looks like you're not moving, and everything outside
of your window is moving past you.
You look back behind you and you say, Oh, look, look at the Earth, man.
The Earth are not moving because there is no acceleration that could dictate that I am moving.
Remember the first part of the special relativity?
What I see is that I'm stationary.
I've been standing in this rocket ship all my life.
But what I do observe from my vantage point is that the Earth is actually moving back at a speed the
relative equal to zero point eight C.
And if we recognize this fact in this reference frame, we will get the correct result.
OK, so let's take that and let's try and figure out what's going on with all using our time dilation
equation.
OK.
So from this vantage point, what we know is that.
I I spit out from the Earth, and after one hour, I send a signal back.
So know I know the time from launch to sending of a signal.
What I really need to figure out is how long it takes after I send the signal to get back to Earth in
order to do that.
I can use similar ideas that are used in Part B, right?
What do we do?
We used kinematics.
We said V is equal to Delta X over Delta T.
Let's use that.
But in this case, we now remember we are in the rocket frame.
We want our ex to figure out how experiences arise and transpire from our perspective.
Right.
So in order to do that, what we really have to do is we need to figure out the distance this guy has
traveled initially, right when it sends a signal.
So according to this guy, according to the rocket, we say, Oh, well.
The physical laws rise in different reference frames in the same manner, so we know that, you know,
the Earth would say the relative is equal to Delta X and we're going to call this Delta X out.
All the rocket I'll put in are here, and that's going to be all the time I measure in my reference
frame.
This is going to be at T out, according to the rocket.
And we just need to find out unknown.
We know this guy that is just this.
You know, Delta T out are one hour.
We to isolate Delta X, so Delta X.
The distance we have traveled, according to the rocket, is equal to the relative times Delta three
out, according to the rocket.
Now we need to do is plug in shock.
We put in our relative velocity.
The delta time out is one hour and again we use our new units.
So this is just an easy calculation.
This is it's almost mindless right here, right?
So this becomes zero point eight light hours or, as I just said, it's three times the units in hours.
So we got this this calculation here.
We're getting some more information.
We're getting closer to the answer.
Next, we need to figure out, OK, when I fire that signal.
How far does the light have to trap now based upon Part B?
You may want to think, Oh, well, I shoot the signal and has to go the distance that I traveled,
right?
It has to go the distance that I travel.
But experiences arise based upon your perspective, your perspective to find your experience right.
So according to the rocket, what I see is that this guy, I'm stationary and the Earth is going to
the left.
So to get back to the Earth, I need to chase the Earth, according to me and the rocket.
So what happens is we have to go the same distance belt acts that I originally traveled, but the Earth
is going to go another distance.
So the total distance I really have to travel really is going to be Delta X.
Out, according to the rocket.
Well, sadly, just as the Earth travels, right?
So that's going to be very relative.
Times Delta T back in time, it takes to get back to Earth.
As measured by the rocket, because we're in the rocket reference frame, so this is going to get me
a distance, and again, this is just the Eagles, Delta X and the Delta T multiply the depth to the
B to get Delta X.
So this should give us, well, the distance, the White House, the travel.
So if we're trying to figure out the light.
Well, that's just, you know, see times Delta T gives us the distance light travels, right?
So this is just the novelty at the same time interval.
We're trying to find relative to the rocket.
OK, so that makes sense, right?
Because from.
That reference frame the Earth is moving to the left, so has to travel an additional distance to get
back to the Earth.
OK, so.
What happens is we need to isolate this Delta T back R, and when we do that, we just plug in shocking
assets.
So in order to do that?
We bring this guy over here, and we find that Delta X out R is equal to Delta T.
Back.
Are.
Times the relative.
Or rather time, see?
Minus, this guy actually brought it over.
As such, and then we find that if we flip this guy over, I like having my very all the less, not
sure why, but it makes me feel comfortable.
We had Delta T back.
Ah, and that is equal to Delta X out.
Divided by sea minus feral and all we need to do now is literally plug and shut.
So Delta X out, ah, it's going to be zero point eight light.
Hours or see times, hours.
And then we have C minus 0.8 C, OK, well, we know right off the bat seas are going to pop out is
going to cancel.
So we're going to get to a time on the top.
This is what we're looking for.
We got what we wanted.
So it's basically like zero point eight over zero point two.
And when we do that calculation.
It's basically what is that 0.8 times five?
Which is just for.
So we get a Delta C that.
Are.
Is equal to four hours.
And again, that's the beauty of our selected unit notation and find the total time back.
This is literally just the altered T out, according to the rocket, was Delta T back.
According to the rocket, we have the Delta T out, that's one hour plus Delta T back.
That's four hours.
We end up with a total of five hours.
Now we get this and compare it.
To that on Earth, and I want you to find the glaring contradiction here.
Why should you be confused?
Because, well, wait a second.
In part a we said the rocket is the proper time based upon us analysis here.
The rock is the proper time, so the time on Earth should be dilated, which means that the time on
Earth should be larger than the time as measured by the Rock.
Oh, wait a minute.
This total time, five hours larger than that on Earth.
Did I make a mistake?
What's going on here?
Well, I want to say and why I think this problem is very good is that no, no, no, no, we did not
make a mistake.
This is what would happen according to the a reference frame.
And we accounted for all phenomena that the person on the rocket would actually measure.
So what's going on here?
What I'm going to do is I'm going to write this up really quick.
We don't lose that.
So we have total time of the rocket, five hours.
All right.
That's sort of my my box up here of the results we can keep track.
Remember, counting very important and any kind of physics discipline.
If that's true, what what in the world happened?
Were we wrong apart?
No, we were right in part A and we are right Morsi.
And this is sort of why I see the time dilation equation for the last because we're going to work through
this again, using time relation and what we want to do.
We want to do the same exact thing we were doing previously.
So previously we were looking at the time interval.
Between when the rocket goes off, shoots off and when it's sent, and in that instance, event one
and event two in the rocket's reference frame occur at the same place.
So it looks like when they occur, you're at rest, right, taking off and sending a signal.
It's not if they're in the same place, but in part, see something weird is happening.
We're not looking at the same events.
We're asking how long after it left?
The signal arrived back at Earth, so event one is again, that's leaving the Earth for.
But Event two is.
Arriving
at her.
Which is much different than what we did in part see.
So what I said is that the proper time occurs in the reference frame where the events are synonymous,
they occur in the same place.
Well, looking at these two reference frames, for part, see where does that occur?
Obviously, it occurs in the Earth.
It occurs in the Earth because when it takes off, you can stand on the the launch site.
You see it go off.
All right, you're in the the station where you're monitoring stuff and then when you receive the signal
by the same station, you're just sitting there.
So you've been at rest at these two events.
And for this question?
The proper time.
Is the Earth?
So I know what you're thinking.
Oh, wait a minute, that's confusing.
And this is why you need to build your intuition, practice some of the problems I give you and try
to use this format.
Try to keep a count of things and think about the reference frames.
Think about is my proper time changing words at the same.
If you can keep track of this and keep track of everything and then use our conventions.
That's how you pave a path for success.
OK, and this should not be surprising, because even when we run through the example, I said, you
know, the guy that's moving.
Are the people on the Earth?
I believe it was Phillip and Eric.
Their time was being dilating because proper time was the time on the rocket, but according to the
rocket, it looked like the Earth was moving.
So from his vantage point, it looked like time was dilating to him.
So we got the reverse effect and I told you there was sort of a symmetry, an asymmetry built into the
problem, right?
So this is the reverse effect.
This is the other side.
This is what arises according to the experience of somebody in the rocket.
OK, so according to this, our notion changed because we changed the events and now the proper time
is as measured on Earth.
All right.
And sort of throw a mark going to go crazy.
It's making me make me go crazy all this wacky special relativity.
So.
In order to get the right yourself, right, we could have taken our results from Part B and we could
have said, Oh, well, yeah, I'm awesome.
I could keep track of my stuff.
I'm going to write up my equation.
Delta C.
Total.
Is equal to gamma delta T, nor not total.
We say, Oh, wait a minute, I found out at the proper time is Earth.
This guy is going to be here.
This guy is going to be boom.
Seems like we're getting that result.
Rocket is dilated.
Let's see what happens.
So all we need is just one job, right, baby.
So we get our Lorentz factor, which is one of the square root of one minus B or C squared as just one
minus 0.8 C divided by C.
We square this term and we multiply by Delta T, not total.
So that's three hours there.
We do this calculation.
What you will find.
Is that?
So you get a result.
Which is the following.
Bam.
They match up.
OK, so what do we learn, what do we learn?
We learned that, yes, special relativity is weird on effects arise, but.
If you study them.
And you keep track of reference frames.
What is proper time, you think through the problem instead of rushing through and just throwing numbers
in without thinking you will pave a path towards success?
Hope you enjoyed that video.
Hope you enjoy the example.
I hope part.
See really challenged you.
Make sure you understand this.
Make sure you understand what I did.
And if you don't go back and try to work through the math.
But next, what I want you to do is run through our example problems and then I'll join you next as
we take a look at another relativistic effect or sort of popped out sort of in Part B.
So keep that in the back of your mind that you know that life, according to the rocket and the light,
the queen, the Earth, it seems like they might not match up.
Oh, what's going on there?
Stay tuned.
I'm going to answer that shortly.