In the previous video we saw
that the shallow quantum well
can be faithfully represented as
an attractive derived delta potential.
And in this video we're going to
solve the Schrödinger equation
with a delta potential in an arbitrary
dimension, one, two or three.
And we're going to use
a very powerful method,
mathematical method, that as a matter
of fact was used by Leon Cooper,
to solve the key problem in
the theory of superconductivity and
the problem of electron pairing which
brought him eventually a Nobel Prize and
now this phenomenon of pairing is
actually called Cooper pairing.
But we'll talk a little about this later,
but at this stage we're going to focus
on just a single particle Schrödinger
equation with this sort of
short-range attraction.
And so
before going through the technicalities,
I want to give you the bottom line,
the main result,
if you sort of get lost in
these technical details.
So, at least I'd like you to know the very
important outcome of this calculation
we're going to see.
And so the outcome would be the following,
so we'll see that in one and
two dimensions that measure how
weak attractive potential gives
rise to bound state of a quantum particle.
So, doesn't matter how shallow a well,
we have it always will bind the particle.
But in three dimensions, it turns out that
if you have a very weak potential, very
shallow potential, it's not enough to keep
the particle to localize the particle.
And this difference,
qualitative difference,
actually have a very important
consequences in various fields.
In physics, you may want to remember that.
But now let me go to the technical part.
Okay, so and I will start with
a certain math reminder which
basically will remind you
what a Fourier transform is.
So, we can solve the problem, but
we'll solve the problem using
only the Fourier transform.
There will be nothing else involved
essentially this solution.
Fourier transform and
inreverse Fourier transform.
So, what is a Fourier transform?
So, if you have an arbitrary function,
well reasonable function g(x),
in our case it will be a wave function and
various derivatives of it.
So the Fourier transform of this function
g(x), which we call f of g(x) or
g tilde (k) is an integral of
g(x) with this exponential.
So physically this K in our case
will represent the wave and
H x K is going to be the particles
momentum but in principle you can
view this Fourier transform
as a mathematical procedure.
And an important fact here is that if you
know the Fourier transform function you
can restore the function itself but
doing the inverse Fourier transform.
So, g (x) is equal to an integral of,
there should be a g
tilde (k) into the power minus ikx,
dk over 2 Pi.
So, I remind you or
emphasize that where to put this,
2 Pi is actually a matter of convention or
convenience, so we could have put
the 2 Pi in the [INAUDIBLE] transform or
we could have separated them.
Sort of like this, so we could have
put 1 over square root of 2 Pi here,
1 over square root of 2 Pi here or
any other combination of powers so
that the total power of 2 Pi in
the denominator is equal to 1.
And this is a metric convention
in the quantum mechanics,
the convention is that 2 Pi
appears in this inverse Fourier
transform which features the wave
reaction or the momentum.
So, I will just erase this stuff here.
So, anyways so, this is what we know and
now the simplest perhaps example of
a Fourier transform will be actually
a Fourier transform of the delta function.
So, if we want to Fourier
transform the delta function,
we know that the delta function
when integrated the value
of the function is being
integrated with at x = 0.
So and if we integrate the delta of x with
the e to par ikx from minus infinity to
plus infinity we'll simply will get
one because e exponent of zero is
equal to one.
So, therefore the Fourier image
of the delta function is one.
Just same identity in this case basically.
So, and we can also do the inverse Fourier
transform which basically gives us
our presentation of the delta function and
it's an integral for
minus infinity to plus infinity
of this exponential dk over 2.
We have seen it already actually before.
So and these identities actually will
be enough for us to solve the problem.
So, now the problem that we actually
want to solve mathematically
is the Schrödinger equation
which is presented here.
So, the left hand side of this equation
here represents the Newtonian, so
the Newtonian in this part is
the kinetic energy or the usual
kinetic energy written explicitly
in the coordinate representation.
So, this is just p squared over 2m and
this guy is our potential,
delta potential.
So, later on we're going to generalize
it to arbitrary dimension but
at this stage I'm just doing
1 dimension for simplicity.
So, of course, we're dealing now
with Schrödinger equation and
the goal of this calculation, basically,
the goal of our derivation, would be
to determine the value of the energy.
And in particular we would
want to figure out whether or
not there are bound states
with negative energy.
So, essentially if we want to
sort of draw symbolically the,
potential that we're dealing with so
it's, zero everywhere but
in the vicinity of x =0 there
is a sharp sort of well.
And the question is whether
theres a bound state or
bound states in this well
with some negative energy.
So, this is basically the question.
And so now, let me do the actual
calculation using this reminder and
Schrödinger equation.
So, what we're going to do,
we're going to represent inside facts
as free of transform of the wave
function in moment of our presentation.
So, this is going to be an integral of
dk over 2 Pi of sum psi tilde sub key,
I'm going to write it.
E to the power- ikx,
from minus infinity to positive infinity.
And just for the sake of brevity,
I'm going to call this integral and so, so
that I don't have to write the standard
factories and limits again.
So, it is identically equal
in my notations to this.
So, there are three types of theorems
that appear in this equation.
So, the wave function itself,
appears in the right hand side,
multiplied by the energy.
In the left-hand side, though,
we have, for instance, this guy,
which is the second derivative of
the delta function, psi double prime.
So, differentiate this Fourier
transform twice over the coordinant,
we're going to pull out, so the of
the exponential is the exponential itself,
but they're going to pull
out this minus i t squared.
So, therefore,
we can represent this as derivative s
psi tilde sub x (-ik)
squared e to the power- ikx.
So, this guy is the Fourier
transform of psi double prime.
And finally we also have this term,
so delta(x) psi(x).
But since delta (x) is a sharply
peaked function that x = 0,
so it essentially pulls out only
the value of the wave function of x = 0.
So, all other values of this
wave function, in this product,
basically don't matter.
So, this term is going to be identically
equal to psi (0), delta (x).
Okay?
And delta (x), we know that delta (x),
before you even measure
the delta (x) we discussed in the previous
slide, is simply equal to one.
So, we can represent this as a side
of zero and integral over k again,
it's implied that it's minus infinity to
the plus infinity either from minus ikx.
That's it.
So, this is basically the way we
can write this in this situation.
And so,
if you can put everything together, so
we're going to have in the left-hand side,
we're going to have- h squared over
2m side tilde psi tilde sub k- ik
squared either to power- ikx.
So this term,
the second term is going to be minus alpha
psi (0) which here is simply a constant.
So, we have pulled out the value of
the wave function (x) = 0 just a constant.
And here we have this
integral e to par- ikx.
In the right hand side, we're going to
have simply energy times the wave function
coming from here k psi
tilde e to the par- ikx.
So, we see that in all three terms,
we have these integrals and
we have these exponentials.
So, we can simply focus on the overall
coefficients that multiplies
all these exponentials and
essentially get what we can call it and
shorten your equation in momentum space.
So in some sense, we can just
get rid of these integrals, and
let me have some space here.
Let me erase most of this stuff.
So as a result, if we basically look at
this equation without the integrals for
a particular key.
So, this term, the first term on
the left-hand side is going to give us
plus each squared over 2m
k squared psi tilde (k).
The second term is going to give
us minus alpha times psi 0.
So, this psi zero is
elevated real space though.
And at the right-hand side is going to
be the energy that we're looking for
so this is our unknown.
This is what we're looking for.
Psi tilde (k).
So, we see that instead of solving the
complicated differential equation as it
looked in the beginning we're now, reduced
the problem to solving essentially.
A linear equation that we know
how to do from high school math.
So, we simply can put this psi tilde,
in the left-hand side of this guy,
in the right-hand side is
we going to have h squared,
k squared over 2m- energy x psi tilde.
So these two guys.
And in the right-hand side we're
going to have + alpha psi (0).
So, the wave function,
the another unknown,
the wave function therefore is
simply equal to alpha psi (0).
Wave function in real space divided by h
squared p squared over 2m minus energy.
And, in some sense this is already
a partially solution to our problem.
It's a solution in the sense that it
determines the wave function in momentum
space and if we want for instance to
find the wave function in real space.
All we have to do is just inverse
Fourier transform it back to x.
But our main interest again is to
answer the question of whether or
not there are bounds
states in this potential.
So this, I just copied here the same
equation we derived previously.
So, it emphasize that this is
really what we're after here.
So, the question is are there
any available energy levels,
level in this shallow quantum well
which responds to particle beam
localized in the vicinity of the works.
So, it turns out that this question
can be answered from this equation,
in just two simple steps.
And those of you who like mathematical
puzzles, sort of aficionados of these
puzzles may want to just stop the
presentation and stare at this equation.
And try to come up with a trick that will
allow you to figure out this energy.
But if you just want to know the trick,
let me show you how it works.
And it's actually very neat.
It doesn't require any super
complicated calculations.
So this stage, let me recall that psi
of x basically, can be represented as
the inverse Fourier transform of
psi tilde of k either from- iks.
So therefore, psi 0 which appears on
the right-hand side of this equation,
psi 0 corresponds simply to
setting f to 0 in this equation.
So it's going to be an integral
of all over all k over 2 pi
of this side tilde (k).
So, let me elevate this integral
in both sides of this equation.
So, we have an equation, I can take
integral of both sides of this equation.
And if I do so in the left-hand side,
I'm going to have side tilde of
k which for
this relation gives me simply psi (0).
While in the right-hand
side I will have this
coefficient which is
simply constant alpha psi
(0) an integral over key 1 over h squared,
k squared over 2 m minus epsilon.
And so, the neat thing that
happens here is that this,
we see that there is a psi zero that
we don't really know at this stage but
the psi zero appears on both sides of
this equation so we can simply cancel it.
So, we end up with an equation that
doesn't have the function anymore.
So, it has only one unknown.
And this unknown is exactly
the energy we are after.
So, if we can solve our equation and
find the value of the energy,
this would imply that there exists
a bond state in our potential.
And remember that the bond
state has negative energy, so
it must be below the continuum.
And this would correspond sort
of to localized particles, so
we can simply put the same models here and
the plus sign.
So, this would correspond to
our energy we are looking for.
And also if we want sort of to
restore normal form of the integral.
So, we can recall that
my notation was simply
to save some space so
this is really what we have.
So, let me skip the remaining technical
step which essentially boils down just to
calculating this integral,
which is an elementary integral, and
just present the result.
And here,
I sort of re-written this equation,
in the sort of slight a different form,
and this is a result of the calculation.
So, if you double the integral you
will see, that there exist one and
only one solution for the energy.
And the energy is equal to minus m
alpha squared over two h squared,
so remember alpha here is
the parameter which multiplies
the delta potentials since sometimes Alpha
controls the strength of this potentials.
This more of the Alpha the weaker
the potentials that X of the particle.
And the result here is that, in the
shallow quantum well in one dimension or
in the corresponding Delta potential well,
there exists one and only one
bound state with this energy, which scales
as so with the strength of the potential.
So, in the second part of this video
we're going to discuss how this result is
modified in a very essential way if we go
to more physical dimensions, to two and
three dimensions.