So now we're going to address the same
question addressed in the previous video,
namely the question about the existence
of a bound state in an arbitrarily
weak shallow potential well, but now we'll
do so in more than one demonstration.
I should mention that there are actually
very few problems in quantum mechanics in
2D and 3D which allow relatively
simple analytical solution.
Most often, in these cases, we have to
resort to either numerical analysis or
a rather technically complicated
mathematical calculations.
Well, the solution I'm going to
present is not exactly trivial.
It will require a lot of thinking.
But otherwise it will follow almost
one to one the steps that we
used in the solution of
the one-dimensional delta-potential.
However, very importantly the result of
these steps is going to be quite different
in 2D and 3D.
So namely, for those of you who
want to skip the technical part and
just to get through the bottom line, so I
will just tell you the result right away.
So unlike in one dimension where the
energy of, first of all the bound state
always exist and the energy of the bound
state in the weak potential scale is
sort of as a power loses as a second
power low of strength of the potential.
In two dimensions it turns out
that the level also always exists,
but the energy of the level is extremely,
extremely small.
So the level is very shallow and the
energy of the level scales exponentially
in a very unusual form with
the strength of the production.
And this actually has very important
consequences in many cases
in particular and it relates to a certain
calculation we're going to discuss
in the theory of super
conductivity a little later.
And also, in three dimension, it turns
out that there is no level at all.
So if you have a very weak
attraction between particles.
So for example, a very weak potential.
Well there is, so this attraction,
attraction is not going to
induce a bound state and
this fact is also very important.
Now let me prove the statements I just
made and prove the solution is going to
follow very closely as already mentioned
the solution that we had in one dimension,
we started from the stranger equation for
the delta potential.
So now of course we have to
deal with this regular equation
in our dimension where wave function
now is a function of a vector r and
the kinetic energy now involved
is in contrast to this over x.
And finally the delta function
is the delta function is
sort of a sharp peaking function
in the D dimensional space.
So let's say in 3D so,
this delta far is simply the product
of the delta function of x, delta
function of y and delta function of z.
So, the first step in
the solution just like in 1D
involves a free transforming our equation.
So essentially we go from
the wave function, real space to
the image of the wave function memento
space or more criticize the wave vector.
So the only difference in time dimension
is that we have transform is slightly more
complicated so it transforms along
each of the directions, x, y, z, etc.
So if we were in higher dimensions.
And so if we perform this slightly
more complicated transform.
So the kinetic energy which is basically
this derivative becomes minus k squared.
The delta function,
the free image of delta function just
like the one I mentioned is simply one.
And so
we get to the following equation which
is just the linear equation for
the image of the [INAUDIBLE] function.
And this you see there is essentially no
difference between the one dimensional
case and the [INAUDIBLE] dimensional
case apart from the fact that this guy
now is a vector.
And while this guy was just a one
dimensional component of the wave vector.
So again we can of course solve
this equation for side tilde to k.
So we're going to have the same
side of zero divided by h squared
K squared over 2m and I will write it
as plus absolute value of the energy.
Again, we are looking for bound state and
we know that the bound state must
be negative if it exists at all.
And using exactly
the same trick as before,
we're going to integrate this
equation both sides of this equation.
Now over the entire three
dimensional space of this.
So and if we do so,
we come up with self consistency
equation which again in 1D in higher
dimensions look almost the same.
So the only difference
is that the integral
here is going to over to
a higher dimensional space.
So it turns out that this difference,
the fact that we are now integrating over
high dimensional space leads to
very important consequences for
the actual solution of this equation.
Here we knew that doesn't matter how
small alpha is as long as it's non 0,
we can always find an energy that
would satisfy this equation.
So now it turns out that for
high dimensions,
it's not going to happen necessarily.
Let's say for D greater than 2,
there will be no solution so and
to see this, we actually have to calculate
this integral that appears in this
consistency equation
that was just derived.
So to do so, we should first notice
that the function that we're actually
integrating does not depend on
the directions of the wave.
It only depends on this absolute value.
So let's say in two dimensions,
we can write d2k as a dk
times k which is essentially
corresponds to an integrating
over the absolute value of k
times d five of k which is
the angle that the vector k
forms with the x directions.
So let's say this is our
three dimensional k space,
this would be k of y,
this would be k of x and so
this is our vector k so
this would be the angle five of k.
So, what I'm saying here
is that the equation,
this equation that we're looking at, so
it can be written as alpha D2k,
in this case, over 2 pi squared.
So this function, and we can write it as
simply, well, alpha over 2 pi squared.
Oops, squared is here so
dk times k over this function
are from 0 to infinity.
So, we integrate overall
possible lectures.
And an integral over the angles but
nothing depend on the angles.
So this integral will simply give us 2 pi.
And, so in 3D we can do the same thing so
in the dimension we can do this procedure,
we can sort of integrate
over the angles and
just separate the integral
over the magnitude of k.
So let me write therefore my self
consistency equation in these four.
I'll write it in any dimensions.
Alpha s sub d minus 1,
which I will explain what I mean by that.
2 pi to the power of D,
so in here I'm going
to write it as dk k to
the power of D minus
one a squared k squared over 2m plus ie so
this s of d minus one is the integral
that comes out of the end though.
So let's say in two dimensions
it will be simply two pi, okay?
So I wrote it in this form because
it actually corresponds sort of to
a d minus 1 dimensional sphere.
So in this case, in two dimensions,
it would be basically integrating
over the circle, in three dimensions,
we'll be integrating over the solid
angles that cover the entire sphere so
let's say s1 is equal to 2 phi which we
found out so s2 is going to be equal to 4
phi, well we can formally introduce
as 0 which is just 2 etc.
So in any dimension,
you can principle calculate it.
But for practical purposes, we don't
really need to know anything about
these three numbers because in real life,
we don't deal with anything
about three dimensions,
two dimensions or one dimension.
Now, the problem that we have is that the
theory here is already in two dimensions,
when we integrate,
let's say from 0 to infinity, so
the integral was actually
divergent at large keys.
So let's say if d is equal to 2 and
especially d is equal to 3.
So the higher we go, the more divergent
it becomes as we go to larger key.
So this integral is
actually equal to infinity.
So if we look at it, without thinking.
And well, when there is an infinity, so
we have to think about why it appears.
So remember that actually
this constant alpha came out.
Well, we're solving essentially
the problem for a delta potential.
So our V of R is alpha
times delta of r and
delta function, the delta function
is a very artificial function.
Was basically introduced to model a show
of potential, a physical potential that
has, so
it has a certain width which equals a and
it has a certain depth, so
which means which will equal you know it.
So and alpha is of the order of
u naught e to the power of d or
d is the dimensionality of our space.
But in any case, so this delta
function potential is introduced to
represent real physical potential
that exists in reality,
which has actually a finite width and
finite depth.
So when we go to large wave vectors,
actually the large wave vectors
respond to small distances.
And if we consider, and if we encounter
a divergence at large K, which we do here.
So it means that something bad
happens at small distances.
And so this something bad means that well,
there are no real delta
potentials in nature.
Okay, so,
all potentials that have a finite radius.
And so we can cutoff this, in some sense,
in physical diversions by
introducing a parameter 1 / E.
Where E is the radius of far of real
physical potential that we model with
the delta potential.
So this is actually a solution
to this otherwise puzzle.
Otherwise we will get an infinity.
We shouldn't get an infinity.
So, basically what I'm saying here is
that, even if we were to put a real
potential in the very beginning and
do everything properly,
then this cutoff would appear actually
naturally in our calculation.
So, but here we just introduce it by hand.
So now we're entering a final
part of our derivation where
we will rely on the integral
we just derived.
So here there are no more angular
components of the wave vector,
there is just one integral involved.
And we cut it off at the 1 over E.
So and also, modified it a little bit so
there's 1 over alpha,
it's not a, it's alpha.
It's the strength of the potential
in the left hand side.
So again, the main question we've been
actually asking is whether there is
a bound state in a weak potential.
That is the potential
where alpha goes to 0, and
therefore, if alpha goes to 0, one,
1 over alpha goes to infinity.
And so the question that we
are now asking is whether we can
find a solution to this equation when
the left hand side is very large.
So you may ask me, you just got three
in infinity so, what are you doing?
This is really would be reasonable
question to say from a mathematician.
But, this calculation actually
illustrates, in a very nice way,
the difference between doing mathematical
calculations in physics and math.
So, the definition I just got in
read off was an unphysical infinity.
It's not real.
It was sort of an artifact of our modem.
And also this infinity was not
dependent on the energy so whether or
not we put energy to 0 or
to or something finite, this so-called
ultraviolet divergence would have existed.
And so we got it off,
we remembered where things came from and
are got rid of this divergence.
Now the question is whether we can have
an arbitrarily large integral by adjusting
the value of the energy, okay?
And so here is basically this integral so
I don't write here,
this overall coefficient
because it's just a number.
It cannot be made large or
small it's just a number.
2D is 1 over 2 phi and 3D is 1 over 2pi
squared so it has, it's not important.
So, how do I answer this question?
So if we look at it, we see that
the absolute value of energy appears in
the denominator, so the larger
the energy the smaller this integral.
It's a very clear-cut tendency.
So, the integral is the largest
when energy is equal to 0.
So therefore, the question we're
really asking is whether we can,
if we set this energy to 0 and
the remainder integral would be a key to
D minus 1 divided by E squared,
or simply this.
So the question we're asking whether
the integral below can diverge.
So we got rid of diversions
in the previous slide.
In this slide,
we're asking whether we can get it back.
But the important thing here is we want to
get it back not from a large momenta but
from a small momenta,
the latter is called infrared diversions.
And in physics, for
those of you will be thinking about
becoming theoretical physicists,
you may remember that infrared divergence
is if you find something like that, well,
either you made the mistake or if it's
new, you should think about Nobel Prize.
So it's very important.
Infrared divergences are real
unlike ultraviolet divergence
which are sort of artificial.
And this boils down
basically to this question.
Now clearly, if let's say,
D is equal to 3,
so the dimension of space is equal to 3,
the space in which we live, so
then we simply have integral from 0
to 1/a or in this case It's finite.
There's no diversions.
And therefore, the answer to the question
is the question of existence of
the bound state is that in 3D,
there is no bound state, okay?
So if alpha is sufficiently small,
the right-hand side cannot possibly
compete with the large value
in the left-hand side.
But if we go to lower dimension and
among the reasonable dimensions,
two comes to mind.
So, unless we consider some fractals or
whatever,
so that's the only thing we can have,
1 and 2.
So in two dimensions, this integral
becomes an integral from 0 to 1/a, dk / k.
And we get a very weak sort
of logarithmic divergence so
the lower limit we're going to get 1
over 0 and it's equal to infinity.
So the integral divergence.
Which is great,
which means we have a bound state.
So this is really the summary
of what we learn from simply
considering this integral to
which we simplify our problem.
So, if our dimensionality is smaller or
equal to 2, so the integral diversion
are physically it means that there
exist always exist a bound state.
Does metric how we could traction this.
So, otherwise the integral is finite and
their no bound state.
So, even though there is a well,
there's nothing in there.
There's nothing in this well.
So the last thing I'm going to do is that,
I will estimate the value of the energy or
the bounds State in two dimensions.
So we just found there is one.
So let's estimate this energy.
And of course for this I have to solve
this equation specifically into g.
So let me do so.
Let me just calculate this integral,
actually estimate this integral.
I can of course calculate exactly but
let me estimate it.
It's easier, so in the first thing I'm
going to do I'm going to factor out this
coefficient here in front of the integral.
I'm going to have m over pi h squared.
So I will get an integral
from 0 to 1 over a and
let me write it in this form,
dk times k and
so here I'm going to have k squared plus
square root of 2me over each squared.
So just throw it in this form
you will understand why.
So if I set energy to zero I have
the logarithmic diversions which
as we know allows me,
allows the existence of the bound state.
Now but if it's finite, so
this divergence disappears so
the smaller it is
the larger the divergence.
Now to estimate the value of the integral
I can simply move this sort of cut off
of this divergence from the denominator
to the lower limit of the degree.
This method is called, well a symptomatic
method is called a very big accuracy.
So if we have integrals of this type
with divergence if we don't want to
perform exact calculations
sometimes it's not possible.
So one can just do this trick and
this provides a reasonable estimate.
So if we do that, so
what we're going to get is approximately,
let me write it this way,
approximately m over pi e squared
integral now from this 2 me,
a squared 1 over e.
And so here I will have simply dk over k
and so this, of course, is lower, and so
the result is that m over pi H squared,
log of 1 over e,
the upper limit times h over 2m(e),
the lower limit.
And so now I'm in a position to find
the energy, so I can simply solve
this equation for e by exponentiating
both sides of these equation,
which gets it free of the logarithm.
And so the result is going to be, so the
energy of the absolute value of the energy
is going to be, let me write of
the order of a squared over ma squared,
exponential of 2 pi h squared
divided by alpha with a minus a sign.
So this is really the final result and
the result is very interesting.
So for a theoretical physicist at least,
because the function that we
got is a very strange function.
So remember that this parameter alpha
controls the strength of the potential.
And, we consider the case
when it's very small.
So, e to the power minus 1 over
alpha is really exponentially small,
very shallow level in
already a shallow potential.
But the function is strange because,
well if you write it, e to the power minus
something over alpha, so this function
does not have a Taylor expansion.
So remember that if we have a function,
if an alpha normally, it's small alpha,
we can approximate it by f
of 0 plus f prime of 0 times
alpha plus f 2 prime sub 0
over 2 of a squared, etc.
So this is a regular Taylor
expansion of a function.
So in this case, all of the derivatives,
all the terms in this Taylor
expansion are equal to zero.
And this actually would have posed
a problem if we had tried to solve this
problem using so-called preservation
theory which physicists love because
oftentimes gives us access to solutions
that are otherwise impossible to get.
So we start with a known solution,
then do a Taylor expansion in
the vicinity of the solution.
So here it wouldn't have been possible,
exactly because of these weird properties.
The function exists, we can plot it,
we can look at it, but
there is no Taylor expansion at all.
So and it turns out that in
the second lecture this week we're
going to study some basics about
the theory of superconductivity and
there's a classic formula in these Nobel
Prize winning Bardeen-Cooper-Schrieffer
theory of superconductivity which features
this function, this sort of function.
Actually, the reason it took people, as I
will talk about it in the next lecture,
the reason it took people almost 50 years
to come up with a solution to the problem
superconductivity is partially
because of this circumstance.
That the result actually is something that
can only be obtained by an exact
nonperturbative calculation.
But it couldn't be obtained
using the perturbation theory.