All right.
Sort of finish the construction of this bridge and rectify their varying conceptions of time.
What we're going to do is we're going to take another look at the same experiment, but it's going to
be slightly different such that we can massage the right result out of it.
What's going to happen is we're still going to have terrorists speeding away to the right in a train
and fill up observing it from the ground.
But the event we're going to take a look at is not a firework in Terrence's train, but rather a firework
that fill up shoots against a wall that Terence has passed.
So it blows up and makes a mark on that wall because you know what builds over here?
He's that he's bored is like, what the hell I want?
Have some fun too.
So he shoots the firework and blows up on the wall and makes a mark.
And now we're going to use this to take a look at both of their conceptions of time and see how, ah,
the the time of which this arises, how it's going to differ between the two.
And then, you know, where is the gap between there can set the pace.
The way in which we do that is similar to what we did with the Galilean transformation.
What we're trying to figure out how they're there, lengths are going to vary.
And what's important to note is that from Philip, when he's trying to figure out whether or not are
you versus the opposite direction when Terence is trying to figure out Philip's time and length, his
measurements are going to use time in his reference frame to prime and also explain prime in his reference
frame.
He's going to use that to try and predict what Philip Philip will use to account for the length from
his reference point all the way to event number two, where the firework blowing up on the wall somewhere.
Well, if she does, that is, you know, it's simple geometric ideas here.
What you can do is he knows that he has traveled around a Philip has moved away from him from his point
of view, from his point of view, a distance of v t prime that he measures with the time on his train.
And remember, time is going to flow differently on his train because the experience transpires differently
based upon his reference frame.
So it's going to say Viti Prime MP subtracts where he thinks the event occurs ex-prime from that guy.
Or rather add them all right, because this is negative.
He's going to get X.
In other words, you have X plus x prime y is equal to V T Prime take over.
That guy?
And you would get get the same exact result, right?
Using geometric constraints here, so what he says is he's trying to figure out X, he's like, he says,
Oh, well, that's just equal to.
ex-Prime.
Los.
The ETF, right again, Ron Run plans tried to get you X, but this is the important thing to remember
this guy.
And this guy.
These are measurements in a reference frame s.
OK, let's write that down measured.
In as prime, not us, as we did previously.
So.
His conception of Philip's length of X might be a little different.
Let's take a step back.
What we know is that from Phillip's standpoint, and this is where it's going to differ from the last
experiment, we just take this from him to this mark.
Going to because it's going to be the length at rest.
Nothing is moving.
There's no moving body, right?
Right.
So we would mark this length as the proper length right because a moving body as is observed to be contracted.
But the proper length is always the length in the reference frame where the distance is at rest.
So this is the rest, this is the proper length.
So to Terence, from his standpoint, this distance here as he moves looks like suit.
It's gone to the left and his vantage point.
So this length is a moving body and it's going to be observed to be contracted.
So his measurements are not going to give you simply x what Philip measures.
It's going to give his measurement his conception of this length x, which means that he's going to
see a moving body.
It has to be contracted.
So this guy is his conception of the length again, emphasis on that point.
So we take the X divided by gamma again, length contraction, and we end up with the following.
So it looks pretty similar to what we just found what we could do if we get X equal to gamma.
Science X Prime Plus V.
He prime.
And we want to do is we want to isolate one of the times to prime so we can define it in terms of the
parameters of the other guy because we want, let's say, s prime.
Philip, we want him to say, OK, I've got my time.
I got my life.
Let's use that to switch over to Terrence this time.
So we need to get rid of this prime somehow.
How do we do that?
Well, we've already derived a map, a bridge between their conceptions, which was this guy, right?
So we could take that was thrown into the equation and see what we end up with.
So if we do that?
We get our Lawrence Potter gamma expert is no more than an X minus the tea, not a prime plus v tip,
right?
OK, so we're making some headway here.
I'm just going to grab my notebook here, and that's what we need to do.
And again, I missed a little parameter here because remember, this is this is actually I wrote this
up incorrectly, so this should be again as we found.
Sorry about like us.
So this becomes a gamma.
And we just need to distribute the terms and see what we end up with.
Well.
Jonathan Sgamma let's go to square.
X.
Minus.
Ghana squared the tea.
Plus, Gamma V, right?
All right, we're making headway here.
So now we want to do is we want a group like terms and then isolate the term we're interested in finding,
remember, we want to express pride in terms of the parameters from the other records so they can switch
between each other.
It's a map.
Remember a way to translate.
So what we could do is we could take this x.
We see common terms.
We could take out a squared move that over.
And what we end up with is a one minus gamma squared.
Multiply by acts, we could pull this guy over to the gamma square feet.
So we just add.
Gamma squared.
Viti.
And that leads are gonna be prime on the right side, so we're making headway, we're getting close.
What we need to do is we need to isolate this guy.
So what I'm going to do is honor the vibe by Gamma B and flip the equation.
So it's more in line with what we're looking for.
We're looking for trouble.
I like it on the left side.
That's wrong to you.
So we take T Prime.
We say that is equal to this guy, all this stuff.
What am I gonna be?
OK.
So we take one minus gamma squared.
Provided by Gamma V..
And that is multiply by X.
And then this guy got squared being divided by Gallup is no different than times team.
So we need to add on that gamma.
Times key component at this point, you're like, whoa, wait a second.
That does not look very nice.
We didn't make much headway here.
That looks pretty complicated.
So what we want to do is we want to make board space.
And then we're going to try and massage this little guy right here so we can groove terms and get this
nice expression that we can use for describing to you front.
OK.
That's going to be our map, right?
We want to be simple.
All right.
When you translate stuff, you don't want it to be too complicated.
You want it to be very quick and efficient.
So we take this guy here and we could say, Hey, wait a second.
If we take one minus gamma squared, we cannot be.
We know gamma is a function of the four, so maybe we can throw that in there.
Somehow we get this nice, elegant gamma to pull that out front and we can group terms and it looks
much nicer.
Okay, so we take one.
Minus gamma squared.
Over again, maybe this guy right here and we say, oh, wait, a second, that's.
Well, we could take the one hour we we could pull that guy out.
And then we end up with one over Karma.
Minus Myanmar, right?
Right.
And also, we know that Gamma, as I was just saying, gamma is nothing more than one of the square
root of one minus v over C.
So if we plug that in, maybe we can incorporate that v inside, right?
That's the name again.
That's the name again, maybe.
So we set that equal to one over B.
If those brackets flip that that guy up.
We take the square root of one minus v over C that guy squared.
And then we have a minus one over root one minus three over C, and I promise we're painful a lot of
algebra.
But when we're done, it's going to look nice.
I promise you can hold me accountable.
So we get this and we say, OK, let's make the same denominator for both of these terms, and maybe
we can group them together.
So what we want to do is we want to multiply this guy by the square root of one line is B or C squared,
divided by the square root of one minus VRC squared.
In essence, we're just multiplying it by one.
You know what I mean?
So this guy just becomes nothing more than o one, minus the R C quantity squared.
Because remember, if I'm multiplying by this, the term here divided by the same term?
Square over town, square root is nothing more than that quantity to the one and basically that some
gripping the term.
So that's this guy.
Then this term here minus one, we divide that guy by the square root one minus v over C squared.
And when we get this, we see, oh, wait, a second, that just cancels that and we get this nice time
here, which is no different than.
Backing up and putting the correct term for.
Right.
We don't want to mislead you guys.
So I forgot that one of your and it has to carry along for the ride.
Right?
We don't just kick him off.
He's not smelly enough to kick him out.
So what we end up with is negative the quantity of oversee this guy squared.
That's going to be over.
That square root one minus VRC squared, but we know that this guy is no different than just so we can
multiply that by gamma.
And we have the one over be right in front.
OK, so we end up with that.
And what happens is.
Well, you divide by that guy at the and we get a B over C squared.
Times Sgamma oh, look at that is much nicer than this monstrosity right there.
We want to get rid of that guy.
So when we take this guy, this this negative term, I want to forget the negative.
And we make some board space to get rid of all that work.
We don't like it anyway, we won't get rid of that algebra.
So we say that this guy coming up here, this this is no different than.
This guy basically up here.
Te Prime.
It's no different than.
This guy becomes negative B over C squared times are gonna on X plus Yamauchi, and now you have a we
have a common term, we can factor that baby out and it's going to look much nicer and much more manageable.
So we do that, we get the gamma, so we pop that out.
I'm going to use the tea first and then I'm going to subtract.
The.
Overseas squared and multiply by X.
And if we did all that correctly, the results should agree with my notes, which it does because you're
awesome.
You did the math correctly with me.
It was your presence that helped us get the right result.
So we got this guy right here.
And we find that.
Philip can figure out Terrence, this time by taking his calculations and multiplying all this junk
in front of it.
OK.
But.
What's important is.
We've accounted for space.
We've accounted for the correct conception of time.
And now the last ingredient, remember what I said, this should agree with what we find here.
That's pretty complicated.
So we're going to have to spend a bit more time on that.
What we want to do is make some more board space and then say what happens if we is much less sea or
in other words?
We're going to say.
If V is much left to see, we know again the Lorentz factor as we found this guy just becomes approximately
one, because remember, viewers see that's approximately zero.
And then one minus zero, that's one on the bottom, one of our one, it's pretty much one.
So again, gamma is still approximately one.
But when that happens, we find that S. Prime is equal to one.
Signs T, oh, look at that we got we oversee what is this, what is this term for an ex?
This is b over three times one, obviously.
Oh, wait a minute.
We oversee is very small and only divide by three times 10 to the eight meters per second.
That's extremely small, which means that this guy is essentially zero in front of the X.
Doesn't matter how big access this guy is infinitely small compared to the T. It's going to have no
effect.
That's like saying, Oh, we got T.
Maybe T is ten plus point zero zero zero zero zero b you want.
When you add that together, you get like it's at 10.
That's in essence what we're doing.
So this is the simplification that the Gaussian transformation and that are concessions of time are
basically making every day when we observe events, right?
It's sort of like our minds can't keep up with what's going on in a sense.
So you assert that this is minus zero and prime is essentially equal to T band that mass that we had
in the galley and transformation, we got our conception of life.
We've got our conception of time and all that's left is our conception of Y and Z.
Well, it's we could do that pretty easily because we know that relativistic effects only arise in the
direction of which they're being applied.
So if you're basing your velocities in the X direction, the effect is in the X direction, in the Y
and Z direction, there is no effect.
There is no implied effect because that's right.
If you cruise along in this direction, your y conception, right?
Shares of Philip are not going to disagree about what that is going to end up being.
So we are in a good position right now.
We're in an excellent position because what we can say is.
We can erase all this stuff and we can say, Oh, Galilean transformation, you do not converge upon
every situation that can arise in the universe.
I'm going to take you through, are you in the wastebasket?
And I will replace you with something that's superior better and basically an all inclusive conception
of the universe.
So if we erase this, make that board space, bam, we put down racer and what we say.
Is the following, OK, so we get.
We get X.
For a time so mean that the relativistic effect that he's traveling in, the direction we get prime
is equal to gamma times x minus v t.
Or rather.
We only did this part here, so I'm going to put it over here.
We're going to say ex-Prime.
Is equal to gamma times x minus v t.
We're going to have why prime is equal to y z, prime is equal to Z, and then we're going to have our
conception of time.
C Prime is equal to gamma T minus v over C squared.
Times X.
OK, I'm going to make this little gap.
Sort of.
Put a little x on this guy because this guy is not proper anymore.
And what I've just done for you is derived.
What is known as?
The Lorenz transformation.
And it is named as such because both Einstein and Lorenz did derive this result right here, but.
Einstein was the individual who correctly interpreted it, so sometimes it is it has a group name,
I believe it's the Lorenz Einstein transformation.
But what is important is that our initial goal that we set out to conceive of and derive, which is
coming up with a universal conception of the universe, something which bridges the gap between an infinite
set of perceptions of events rising around us is nothing more than this guy right here.
We have erected that bridge using the foundational supports of time dilation and length contraction.
His is this beautiful result, this beautiful map the look or parents could use.
To translate their experiences into somebody else's experiences and their predictions, their results,
their conceptions can line up so they can they can actually have a conversation about it and have this
nice universal conception of the interest.
Hope you enjoy that derivation.
I hope you enjoyed us wrapping up the portion of this course for a lot of the kinematic ideas and special
relativity.
Next, what I want to do is I want to show you the power of the less Lawrence transformation and show
you how can help better explain very convoluted situations that arise in special relativity.
And we're going to do that by taking another look at the Einstein train paradox that we resolve previously.
And I'm going to show you how this map, which translates all this information very quickly, easily
and effortlessly, could help us reconcile what's going on and get to the correct conclusion quickly
and have proof of what's going on.
Stay tuned.