The quantum harmonic
oscillates the problem.
And its solution go far beyond the simple
generalization of the particle and
is bringing problem on classical physics.
And they appear in a variety of context
in quantum physics as already mentioned.
For example, electromagnetic radiation
can be thought of as a collection of
harmonic oscillators, the phonons.
And much more generally,
various complex structures in quantum
mechanics oftentimes can be thought of
as being built of this small building
blocks being quantum harmonic oscillators.
But in each particular piece,
the meaning of this individual
oscillators is different.
And today I'm going to show you
the appearance of this quantum harmonic
oscillators in the context of
a very interesting problem.
That is sort of underlies solid state
physics, or condensed metrophysics.
And this is a problem of
excitations in crystals,
which are collections of many,
many ions that form a periodic structure.
And these ions can oscillate, and
these oscillations, quantum oscillations,
are called phonons.
And we will see how these phonons appear.
And we'll see also that they can be
described in terms of the creation and
oscillation operators that have been
introduced in the first lecture this week.
To understand the concept of a collective
mode such as a phonon for example.
In a complex quantum system, we first
can go back to classical physics and
remind ourselves the notion
of a normal mode which
is equivalent to the quantum
collective mode.
And this normal modes appear
in complex classical systems.
So here I have a primitive
classical system.
If you want this is a simple
harmonic oscillator.
And in this case, as we know,
the frequency of the oscillation
is equal to the square root of
the stiffness of this spring
divided by the mass of this object.
Now if we made the system
a little more complicated,
and instead of just one oscillator,
consider,
let's say two masses attached to
let's say three springs in this case.
So we have a system here with
two degrees of freedom and
this system will have two
different oscillation frequencies.
Responding to different times
of oscillation motions.
So, for instance, this type of motion.
When the two masses sort of
oscillate in phase with one another.
So this let’s say first type
of motion is described by
the frequency which is exactly 2 to omega.
There is also second type of motion that
we can imagine in this slightly more
complicated system.
In which case let’s say,
these guys oscillate out of phase,
in this fashion sort of.
And this oscillation frequency,
people two in this case,
is equal to square root of times
the basic frequency of these guys.
So let's assume they all
had the same stiffness.
And we can make things more and
more complicated, and
let's say in this case have a six.
This six masses a dash, at the springs,
and in which case we will have six
different degrees of freedom, and
six different oscillation frequencies.
And this oscillation frequency's so
called normal moles in classical physics,
they have an analog
[INAUDIBLE] in quantum physics.
In particular, let's say in this
example of two harmonic oscillators,
just by knowing the results
of the classical calculation.
We can write down, as a matter of fact,
the spectrum of the corresponding
quantum problem.
And the spectrum of the corresponding
quantum problem will be simply.
The energy's going to
be equal to h omega 1
(n1+1/2) + h omega 2 (2+1/1).
And it's going to depend on
two quantum numbers, n1 and
n2 corresponding to two
harmonic oscillators.
But these are going to be directly
the harmonic oscillators built out of
let's say the coordinates and
momentum of the two particles.
So these oscillators, so the corresponding
creation and operations, there's going to
be a certain non-linear combination
of these x1's and P1's, x2, and P2.
Which sort of describe
the generalization of this in phase and
out of phase motions to quantum physics.
And in general, now we have a classical
system with some normal modes,
there's a corresponding quantum
system with the actual,
with the spectrum associated
with these normal modes.
A very interesting example of a complex
many particle quantum system is a crystal.
We know that crystalline
structures of various types
appear in a variety of
solid state materials.
And in this structure.
So what happens is that ions or atoms of
which this solid state material is sort of
built, they arrange themselves
into a unique order and pattern.
And so here, for instance,
I'm showing a fragment of
a so-called simple cubic lattice.
And these blue balls in this
picture respond to atoms sitting
on their equilibrium position
on their lattice sides.
But this picture is a bit deceptive,
actually it's probably better to
say incorrect,
in that the atoms here in are not static.
So then indeed have some
preferential positions,
some equilibrium positions, but
they move around all the time.
So this position that they occupy
responds to a minimum in some effect,
the potential the fuel.
But they can oscillate near the minimal
of this potential, and these oscillations
are basically described locally as
essentially harmonic oscillator motion.
So a better illustration
of what a crystal is.
So that I put together, well, for
simplicity, for two dimensional case.
So it is presented here.
So instead of thinking about atoms,
which are sort of tied together in this
crystalline structure
by some rigid objects.
We should think about
atoms being tied together
by some elastic springs with some
stiffness, which is fine, all right?
And so when we look at this system,
so by analogy to what I just
discussed in the previous slide.
We can think about this system
as a many-oscillator system
with a lot of degrees of freedom.
So in reality, in this material,
so there are not two or three or
six atoms like in the previous lab.
But there are billions and
billions of atoms.
And therefore, there are many frequencies,
eigenfrequencies and
normal MOOS, classical normal MOOS.
And they can respond to various kinds of
complicated oscillations in this system.
And in the limit of an infinite number,
basically so
called thermodynamic limit when we
consider essentially an infinite crystal.
So this creates normal MOOS
that merge into continuum
curves which essentially corresponded to
elastic waves running through this system.
And mathematically, these waves
are described by a familiar expression.
So if we think, let's say,
about the displacement of an atom
with regards to its equilibrium position,
some delta r.
As a function of time for
a particular atom, let's say nth atom.
So it's proportional to
the familiar exponential of chi.r,
so where this atom is located,
minus omega t.
But this omega is itself
a function of key.
And so to find this so called photon
dispersion is the main question that
appears in the context of this problem,
and this is what is going to
be of interest to us.
Of particular interest is the question of
what are the low energy
MOOS of this system.
So what it actually
means is the following.
Suppose we have a completely
static crystal.
So.
Well, as static as it gets.
In quantum mechanics,
there is always zero point motion but
we can consider a classical system.
Let's say we just physically built
this model by attaching a bunch
of masses to the springs and
arranging them.
In the equilibrium pattern, and let's
see with touch this system a little bit.
We apply very weak perturbation.
So, the question I'm asking
about the low energy modes is,
are we going to excite any
oscillation in this crystal, or
this weak perturbation is not
going to have any effect.
In other words, do we have to overcome
any threshold or gap as condensed metric
people call it, in order to excite
the minimal perturbation in the crystal.
And as we will see in a later,
in today's lecture, so
the answer will be that it doesn't
matter how weak the perturbation is.
There's always a very low energy mode,
which corresponds to a long wavelength or
a small k wave running through
the sample through this crystal.
And this type of an excitation
is called an acoustic mode or
it corresponds to sound modes
running through this crystal.
And it turns out that appearance
of this acoustic sound modes,
has a very profound explanation which
goes as far as relativistic quantum
physics actually where there is
a theorem called gold stone theorem,
which guarantees the appearance
of certain low energy moles.
And even though I'm talking
now about a classical system,
let me nevertheless try to
connect it to this therm.
But I will present sort of a poor's
man's version of this Goldstone
theory which is relevant to our problem.
And then hopefully we will be able to
understand how they are connected.
So this is going to be
a little bit of detail work.
So the poor man's version of the Goldstone
theorem that I'm presenting is related
to the notion of symmetry in quantum
physics that we already discussed.
So suppose we have a quantum
system which is invariant or
symmetric with respect to a certain
class of transformations.
What it means is that there exist
transformations, let me call them u, and
this operator commutes with the Hamil
20 which describes this system.
So this is what it means.
Or in other words,
UHU minus 1 is equal to H itself.
And let me consider the situation
when there is not just one or
two symmetry operations that exist,
but as a matter of fact we can have
a whole family of such operations.
Let's say labeled by some parameter,
let me call it alpha.
So an example of such symmetry for
instance could be symmetry
with respect to translation.
So let's see if our Hamiltonian is
symmetric with respect to translating
everything, every single particle in
space, let's say by a certain distance.
So it could be a distance of one meter,
or one centimeter, or one kilometer.
So there's a whole
continuum of distances and
directions in which we
can translate our system,
in which case this alpha actually is a
three dimensional vector of translations.
Well, another example could be
symmetry with respect to rotation.
In which case,
alpha could represent an angle that we can
choose by which we can rotate our system.
But in principle, can be anything.
So we just basically postulate
the existence of some symmetry,
what is called symmetry group, but
I'm not going to go into these details
with respect to which the felmonian
of the system is invariant.
But a very interesting fact
is that even though the model
itself can be invariant under
certain symmetry operations.
The quantum states, the, for instance,
lowest energy state of the ground
state does not necessarily,
have to be invariant,
under this same symmetry, U.
So what it means is that the system,
we find itself in a state,
let's see, let me call it such that U,
acting on this is not equal to.
So by translating, let's say,
our system in space,
we do not necessarily
represent the same state.
And in this case, we say that the symmetry
is broken, or spontaneously broken.
But the key statement, which is also
the statement of this Goldstone
theorem in this context is the following.
If once again we have a situation
where the Hamiltonian is a variant
under a certain continuum of symmetries,
but some or
all of these symmetries are broken.
In this state in which the system finds
itself in this state, let's say sine r.
Then to each broken continuum symmetry,
their response low energy mode,
sound like mode.
If you wanted, we just discuss.
And well, this statement,
this correspondence is again,
the statement of its goals down here.
So I realize that there have been
a lot of words that I've said,
but perhaps the best way to understand
the actual meaning of these words
would be to provide an example.
Which also will explain why this
discussion is relevant to what we
talked about before in the previous slides
about crystals, and all these things.
Now let us look at a crystal
structure once again.
So we have here a periodic
arrangement of atoms, but
nobody puts this crystal
structure by hand.
Right?
So if we have a piece of some sort
of material.
Let's say a piece of copper.
So nobody builds it by hand,
like atom by atom.
We don't have to do it.
So the nature does it itself.
So this structure, so
they form spontaneously.
And there is some wave
function if you want.
We described, well,
very complicated wave functions.
We described this atom.
So how do this atom
form in such a pattern?
So I know it is a solution to a certain
Hamiltonian that describes those atoms,
and this Hamiltonian,
it has a kinetic energy of all
the particles involved in the problem,
all these atoms.
Plus, an energy describing
its interaction.
And very importantly here.
Well, it depends only on
the distance between the atoms.
So here n and
then they labelled various atoms.
Now if you look at this Hamiltonian, so
you see that if we translated
the whole thing, if we let's say,
change r to r plus some constant distance,
let me call it d.
Then the Hamiltonian is not going to
change since we have here only
the distance between particles which
is the position of a nth particle minus
the position of nth particle,
if we translate both of
them by the same distance.
The distance between them is
not going to change right.
So therefore, in other words,
what I'm saying here is that here
the Hamiltonian is inverted under
a translations in real space.
But an arbitrary, it's very important,
but an arbitrary distance.
So, but if you look at
the crystalline arrangement here, so
it is no longer in variant
under an arbitrary translation.
So if I remove my particles, let's say
by a fraction of this lattice constant.
Another reproduce the crystal.
So the crystal is till symmetric but
it has a symmetry which is sort of lower.
It has only decreased symmetry.
While the original symmetry of
the problem was a continuum symmetry.
And that's the crucial difference.
And therefore here we have broken
spontaneously broken if you want.
Three continual symmetries in the x,
y and z directions.
And therefore there must exist three
modes or three fold generic mode or
at least three low energy
modes in this state.
And this modes are exactly
the performance that we're going to find.
Of course now our solution is,
we will see them automatically.
And they're not going to be related to
a spontaneous symmetry breaking itself,
but it's very interesting.
This connection is very
interesting because you can sort
of predict the existence
of such low energy modes.
Just by the fact that certain types of
structures form out of symmetric systems.
So in the rest of the lectures
today I'm not going to alluding
to this Goldstone theorem.
So this was just a remark for those
of you who are interested in advanced
understanding or advanced subjects.
But I just wanted to make
this remark because I find it
quite illuminating because
you can see the appearance of
the application of this very powerful
theorem in the very simple example.