Here, a very important chapter of our little and fast overview of the mathematical.
Basics that we need.
In this cause and this are the trigonometric functions and waves, so let us briefly take a look to
the formalism that describes waves and is used extensively in quantum mechanics.
If you are already acquainted with trigonometry and complex numbers, you can, of course, skip all
this section as all of this appendix.
However, I think it is important to agree, at least on some basic notions and conventions on the symbolism
that will be used throughout this course here will lay the foundations for the most basic and elementary
descriptions of the wave and intemperance phenomena which are ubiquitous in quantum physics.
And this will also open for us the way on the concept to the concept of the wavefunction and notion
of paramount importance in all quantum physics discussions.
You may recall from your school math classes, some to grant trigonometry and how the cosine and sine
functions resemble, well, a periodic oscillation that is, so to speak, a wavy movement.
Be it an electromagnetic wave, a sound wave, a water wave or any wave motions or perturbations, they
can easily be described by sine cosine functions.
There are, however, notable exceptions, for example.
Waves in shallow water and so on, which are not cosine functions, but however and for most applications,
the so-called cosine function that is to trigonometric functions serve well, that to the default for
our description of the real world, the red curve shows the sine function where the blue one is the
cosine function.
Both have the same domain.
That is, they are both traced along the X axis.
This x axis could represent a spatial, temporal or angular or any other kind of physical magnitude.
For example, just think of time passing by along the X axis where you put seconds or minutes or hours
in this figure.
Instead, the x axis represents the angular radiance value radians take take the value from zero to
two pi instead of the angles in degrees from zero to 360 degrees and has been here subdivided in steps
of PI force.
The head of the wave at the specific value for X SCIEX is plotted on the vertical axis and is simply
called the magnitude magnitude of a wave.
The choice of the Greek letter BPCI is not a coincidence, it is the famous and most used letter in
all textbooks on quantum mechanics.
The maximum and minimum hate for sine and cosine functions are plus and minus one, respectively.
Now, what distinguishes the two waves or the two functions is that they are shifted relative to each
other along the horizontal x axis, as you can see.
Otherwise, they are perfectly the same object, how much a wave is shifted relative to the other?
Is that what determines their relative phase?
That's a notion of phase.
That's how two waves are displaced or shifted relative to each other.
The sine function, if nothing else, then the cosine function shifted by a phase difference of minus
P half or vice versa.
The cosine is sine shifted by plus behav.
Notice that the concept of face is a relative notion, not an absolute one, the face of a wave must
be determined relative to another wave or against a fixed reference.
For example, this reference can be another wave or as it is done, usually relative to an origin.
The intersection between between the two axis at X equals zero.
Moreover, an important aspect that differs the two functions and will turn out to be useful throughout
this course is that the cosine is a symmetric function.
That is, it is symmetric with respect to the reflection along the Y axis or its values are equal on
the right and left hand side to the to the origin, whereas the sine function is a. symmetric.
Which means that it has a point symmetry with respect to the origin.
Or its values are opposite on the right and left hand side with respect to the origin.
And this figure, we can see a wave that is described by cosine function with the x axis no longer an
angle in radians, but having the dimension of a spatial quantity.
The x axis in meters is now meters, centimeters, etc., and with a phase shift relative to the spatial
origin that is with the same phase angle, V added.
This space dependent function traces a graph of a wave along the space of the x axis and oscillating
a certain number of times per space unit.
This letter, this letter aspect is accounted by the so-called wave number or wave vector, which is
given by the letter K equal to PI over Lambda.
Therefore, the quantity.
K times X is proportional, proportional to a number that tells us how many times a wave of wave length
wave length lambda can be arranged into a space interval X.
Times two by The Factor two, PI service serves a purpose to obtain an expression given in radians.
Then the graph of a wave moving along an x axis in space was initial phase five.
And with no Kay is given by this little expression, CI of X equals zero times cosine function of K,
X plus five where size zero represents the maximum value of the oscillator oscillatory movement.
It is the the amplitude that we expressed previously.
We I spoke about previously, it is the amplitude of the wave, no longer unity.
As for the side and cosine function, but any possible value notice that a positive value for the Phase
V shift the cosine function backwards from the right to the left, whereas a negative value from the
left to the right.
Hmm.
So that's the plus or minus sine determines in which direction the.
This mathematical wave moves.
However, real waves are not just frozen grass.
They move with time passing by to account for the temporal evolution of a travelling wave.
Another non-negative face term, which changes with time, is added to the description of a wave making
the graph move towards the right direction.
Just like here, you see that the blue dot oscillating up and down and the peaks moving from the left
to the right with time passing by.
To every periodically oscillating phenomenon, we associate a frequency, the number of oscillations
time unit.
The international unit standard for the frequency is the Hertz.
That is written in shorthand as a Unit H said, which is the number of oscillations per second.
And is labeled with a Greek letter, no, for example, no equal 50 hertz means 50 oscillations per
second.
One then defines as Omega, this Greek letter here, equal to PI, no, as as the angular frequency,
the frequency times two pi with which the wave oscillates.
The quantity of Omega times t is proportional to a number that tells us how many times a wave of frequency,
new oscillates and terror in the time interval, 30 times to PI, as usual.
One might consider it also a temporary phase shift.
As the wave no accounts for the spatial coordinates.
OK, times X, the angular frequency accounts for the temporal displacement olmeda times to a real wave
of amplitude zero wave number K and initial phase V can therefore be represented by a two valued function
CI of X T equal size, zero times cosine.
OK, X minus Omega, T plus five.
And which depends both from a space coronate X at a time Paramatta T.
The negative sign in front of the angular frequency.
Assures that the wave moves from the left to the right.
Hmm.
With this general expression for a wave, one can describe any physical wave movement phenomenon in
physics.
This equation is the most common mathematical description of oscillatory phenomena.
Let us now go over to another very important chapter of the mathematical description of quantum mechanics,
which is the.
That of complex numbers, complex numbers are and complex, complex functions are used everywhere in
quantum mechanics.
Why complex numbers?
Well, for the simple reason that they are nowadays used everywhere in science where waves come into
play.
Moreover, as we shall see, the concept of the wavefunction is a complex, valued function.
So let us see first where the where the idea of complex numbers comes from.
Historically, it was because mathematicians tried to solve equations where the square root of a negative
number could furnish a solution.
For example, this one.
Alpha squared plus one equals zero.
This can be solved only if we admit the existence of a number called the the imaginary number I and
which is the square root of minus one.
Here, alpha equals I equals square root of minus one.
Inserted and you see, obviously, that it is a solution, but also other equations, for example,
the cubic cubic polynomial equation like this one eight times cubic ULFA plus B.
Alpha squared, plus see Alpha plus the equals zero with A, B, C, the some real coefficients, this
equation requests a solution that is given by a more general, complex number which usually is labeled
with the number that in general, any complex number that is the sum of a conventional real part X and
written as real of Z plus another imaginary part erm offset and which is the imaginary number times
another real value y that is that is equal X plus ie times Y.
Where X and Y are just real numbers.
But why is multiplied by the imaginary number, which is the square root of minus one?
This means that we can represent any complex number also graphically on a Cartesian x y plane.
That is the so-called complex plane.
In this complex plane, the real part of any complex numbers given on the horizontal x axis, while
the imaginary part on the Y axis.
Notice that instead of using the Cartesian x y coordinate axis, it is also possible to represent the
same complex number with Ray Vector R capital letters R and its corresponding angle teta teta, the
Greek letter teta as shown by the upper red vector.
And this figure here, which means that we can represent any complex number resorting to trigonometric
functions, the sign and cosine functions.
So we recovered something that we use later, because any complex numbers, real parts value along the
X axis can be represented by the X equal real part of that, which is nothing else.
There are times cosine of theta.
While it's in the imaginary part, value along the Y axis is y equal.
Imaginary part of that equal ah times sent a sign of data.
Putting this together and a complex number can be represented, as said.
Equal X plus Y equals the Rivette, there are times.
The square back in square brackets.
Cosine of Theta plus I sign Detta.
It is customary among physicists and mathematicians to write this in an equivalent, but more compact
form by using the exponential function that is the so-called oilor number and which has a precise value
equal to point seven, one, eight and so on.
It is an irrational number.
It has an infinite number of delegates and the expression.
E to the power I take to represent the unitary circle in the complex plane.
That is the circle of radius are equal one and which crosses the x axis at plus minus one and the Y
axis at the imaginary numbers plus minus I, that is when one sets are equal one and theta equal plus
minus by half.
Then one obtains the so-called oilor formula discovered by the famous Swiss mathematician Leonid Euler
in the 16th century and which reads E to the power I theta equal.
Because cosine of Theta plus I sign Detta.
The important numbers to keep in mind are especially e to the power.
Zero equals one E to the power plus minus I pay half equals plus minus I e to the power plus minus I
p equals minus one.
Therefore, any complex number can be represented also by set equal R times E to the power Eita and
from.
That follows.
X equal real part of our times, E to the power eita equal R Times commentator Y equal imaginary part
all of our times e to the power I teta equal air are sign detta.
Another concept you will frequently find in news in the complex, no formalism is a complex conjugate.
The complex conjugate is that of that.
Equal X plus I y is nothing else than this number here reflected across the X axis.
The Red River below the x axis, it is obtained only by changing the sign on the imaginary part on the
angle theta, as said Star Star stands for the complex conjugate said star equals X minus eye times
Y, and which is equal are the vector times oil and number to the power minus I.
TimeStep.
The complex conjugate that is usually written with a star or bar symbol of a satellite that starts at
Spart will use the star here.
This is usually very useful to obtain the the absolute value of any complex number.
Therefore, we have to distinguish between the absolute values of real numbers that we have seen.
You take just a square root of the or the number square instead.
It's a little bit more tricky.
An easy and quick way to remember and to imagine the absolute value of a complex number is just think
at the rate vector are capital letter are, which is nothing less than the length of this vector.
This is the absolute value in the complex plane.
If we define as the squared modulus of a complex number as model of squared of Z equals, said Times,
said Star.
And that is the complex number of times its own complex conjugate, and if you want to buy yourself
a quick calculation, you will realize that the model A squared offset equals said times.
That star equals are times e to the power I teta times are times e power minus I teta to equal.
X plus I Y times X minus I Y, and this gives X squared plus plus Y squared and which is R-squared,
Kazantsev squared plus sine squared as shown here, and which finally gives the square of the array
vector.
And the last step, because of the turmoil in the square brackets being Alwis unit.
This means also that the rave act or are is the models of the complex number are equal said.
Absolute value, some of you may have noticed that this is the good old Pythagorean theorem, X and
Y are the legs and R is the hypotenuse of a right triangle.
We shall see why the concept of the square models of a complex number is so important in quantum mechanics,
it turns out it will turn out to be the measure for the probability that an event in the quantum world
occurs.
Complex numbers are well suited to represent functions of waves.
This is not surprising when we think how the complex Reflektor of length our are spending with some
angular speed.
The complex circle can represent an oscillatory movement if we if we project.
Are on the x axis, just like we did on the y axis with a blue dot of the previous figure oscillating
up and down.
From this equation, which represents just the projection of the array or are on the x axis.
And recalling how the travelling wavefunction was constructed.
We show it here again and we will place the Ray Rector are with the amplitude of the waves side zero.
This one, while it's oilor angle, theta, is replaced by the spatial and temporal evolution and the
and the initial phase of the wave function.
This part here and insert it in the.
Formula in this formula, then the real part of the complex ray vector gives this as a result where
we have expressed the mathematical formulation of the traveling wave we have seen before.
With the oil afunction.
For compactness, however, physicists and mathematicians used to describe waves or any oscillatory
and periodic phenomenon that can be described by sign of cosine function as complex numbers without
taking the real part simply as this one with a pure expression or where the oil function comes in.
This makes calculations easier, and once a result is obtained, one takes the real path to get an expression
in real numbers.
The point in using complex numbers to describe waves, therefore, is that they can retain a phase in
space and time with some formal advantages over the real trigger on a trigonometric functions.