Hi everybody welcome to my class on DC circuits by DC circuits I simply mean that means direct current
circuits and that basically means that the direction of the current eye the direction doesn't change.
So the direction let me just write that down.
Direction is constant.
Now the magnitude of the current can change but the direction doesn't change.
So you can go from zero to a maximum value or it can change from some maximum value to zero but the
direction doesn't change.
If you want circuits where the direction changes they refer to those as AC circuits.
All right here's kind of a list of topics that I cover in this class we're going to start with current
and the motion of charges when you place an electric field in a wire from a microscopic viewpoint.
What does that look like.
Once we have those kind of concepts nailed down we're going to introduce the concept of resistance something
that resists the flow of charges moving and the concept of resistivity where they are going to link
everything together the resistance the current and something called ohms law.
We introduced the concept of potential difference and earmuffs.
After that we're going to look at energy when it relates to electric circuits and by energy are typically
looking at how much power is being supplied by these power supplies by the batteries in the circuit
and how much energy is being used and what is the rate at which energy is being used in some of these
resistors.
Sections 4 and 5.
So Section 4 is combinations of resistors in many circuits that you see although they might look complicated
there are techniques that can reduce the circuit that something that looks really really complicated
the something that's much simpler.
So we're going to learn different methods to simplify circuits whether you have some resistors in series
in parallel we have techniques that we can use in order to simplify them and we'll practice a whole
bunch of problems together.
Section 5 is really the bulk and it's really applying to rules Kirchoff's rules in order to analyze
any circuit.
For example analyzing the circuit on the right hand side by the end of this section would be very very
easy and by analyzing I mean are you able to find the current through every single resistor.
Are you able to find that potential difference across every resistor.
Can you then use that information to look at the power being supplied by every battery in the circuit
and the power being dissipated by every resistor in your circuit.
The last section then we're going to introduce a new component to our circuits we're going to plug in
capacitors into our circuits like the circuit shown down below.
So that is what happens what changes are you able to analyze then the current the charge and the voltage
across the capacitor or across any other point in the circuit.
Well look at different methods to analyze what happens when you first close a switch versus what happens
over a longer period of time.
So by the end of this class you're going to look at circuits on the right hand side and say yeah those
are pretty easy now.
And that's the overall goal of my class so let's get started.
I have some fun at the end there is over 50 problems that you can practice by yourself with detailed
solutions worked out the best part is.
Message me any time and I'll get back to you.
OK.
Let's do this.