Hello everybody,
my name is Ian Applebaum and
I'm an associate professor of physics
at the University of Maryland.
Today I'll be giving a guest lecture in
this exciting online course exploring
quantum physics.
I'm thrilled to be delivering this topic,
in part because my own research
deals with experimental aspects
of spin polarized electron transport
in semiconductor materials.
And I feel strongly that understanding
the historical background
I'm going to tell you
about today is absolutely
essential in making future
progress in this modern field.
I want to start our discussion of the
discovery of electrons spin, by reminding
you of what was known around the turn of
the 19th century about atomic spectra.
High voltage across a discharge tube
filled with low pressure hydrogen
causes the emission of
electromagnetic radiation.
Optical photons and
a spectrometer can be used to disperse the
different wavelengths across a detector.
The discrete wavelength seen were
known long before quantum theory
to satisfy Rydberg's formula which
told us that the photon energy Is
proportional to the difference between the
reciprocals of two squares of integers.
Bohr's theory which included quantization
of angular momentum in classical electron
orbits captured this famous result but
it was wrong for many reasons we now know
such as failure to predict the ground
state absence of angular momentum and
importantly the degeneracy of
each principal electronic level.
From the solution of Shrodinger's equation
in spherical metrical potentials, we know
not only that has the ground stayed zero
angular momentum but also that the excited
levels were the principal quantum levels
not one, we're actually degenerate.
Meaning that several states
have same iogin energy g.
This follows from the multiple
spherical harmonics,
labeled by the polar quantum number l,
and as quantum number m.
A spectroscopic notation is
to label l equals zero as s,
l equals one, p, l equals two,
d, and so forth each level of
principle quantum number n has
a maximum l equal to n minus 1 and
states with a given value for l,
have values of m given by minus l,
minus l plus 1, in integer steps through
zero and up to l minus one and l.
This gives a total
degeneracy of 2l plus one.
Therefore each set labeled by a given
principle quantum number n
has degeneracy of n squared.
A natural question to ask then is how can
we observe this degeneracy experimentally?
We need to break the degeneracy,
split the levels and
alter the photon emission spectrum.
We can do this with a magnetic field.
Here's how.
Let's imagine that we have a classical
electron orbit with total angular momentum
given by this expression.
Now, this circulating charge
particle comprises a current,
and so, the orbit has,
necessarily, a magnetic moment.
Classically we know that
the magnetic moment that
absolute value of that magnetic
moment is given by just the current
times the area that it circulates around.
Now the current in this
case is one electron
circulating around in a given period.
So this is the charge of the electron
minus e times the frequency of it's orbit.
And the area off course for circular orbit
is just PI times the radius squared.
Now the frequency of the orbit is
just given by the velocity divided by
the circumference two PI R.
And that gives rise to a simple
expression for the magnetic moment.
But here, we're going to play a little
bit of a trick and multiply and
divide by the electron mass,
and also Planck's constant.
And the reason why we do this
Is that we can see m, v, r.
[NOISE] here, is the absolute value
of the total angular momentum.
Which has the same units
as the action h bar.
That means that
this fraction of out front carries all
of the units of the magnetic moment.
In fact, it has a special name.
It's called the Bohr magneton.
So with this magnetic moment we
know that in a magnetic field,
each state is going to acquire
an energy due to the interaction.
Now if the magnetic field
is along the z axis,
then we can simply write this
interaction energy as minus the z
component of the magnetic moment
times the magnetic field along z.
So, if different states with the same
principle quantum number n have different
values for the z component of the magnetic
moment, their energy eigenvalues
will shift differently in a magnetic
field, and the degeneracy will be broken.
So we need to calculate the magnetic
moment associated with each orbital.
From the preceding discussion, we know the
relationship between angular momentum and
magnetic moment.
And if the field is aligned to the z-axis,
we only need to calculate
the vector component along z.
But this means we need to know
the angular momentum vector along z.
So we need to calculate is
expectation value, and for
that we need an operator representation.
We know that the linear momentum
operators are h bar over i,
times the derivative with respect to
the conjugate real space variable.
So it's easy to see, that the angular
momentum along z takes this form.
Because phi, the azimuthal angle,
is its conjugate variable.
The expectation value then
is this matrix element,
the operator sandwiched by the state.
The only part of the way
function that matters here
is the phi dependents which we
know from the spherical harmonics.
The derivative brings down
a factor if i x m and
what's left is the original
normalized state.
We see then that our answer
is integer units of h bar
determined by the azimuthal
quantum number m.
This is why m is commonly called
the magnetic quantum number.
Now we can complete our calculation.
The energy added due to the interaction of
the orbit's magnetic moment with magnetic
field along z is simply the Bohr magneton
times the magnetic field strength times
the magnetic quantum number.
This result is pleasing enough but
some understanding of the scale
of the effect is helpful.
The Bohr magneton is small,
about 60 micro electron volts per Tesla.
And a Tesla is a huge magnetic field,
about 20,000 times the strength
of the Earth's geomagnetic field.
The largest fields in the lab,
created with superconducting coils,
are several tens of Tesla.
The energies are then small in comparison
to the electronic transitions.
So any observed shifts
of the spectral lines,
are going to be proportionately small.
So here's what happens.
A non zero magnetic field induces
a splitting between degenerate states,
adding energy to states with
positive magnetic quantum number m,
and subtracting from
states with negative m.
All states with m equal zero
Including this all ground state
level are unaffected.
The splitting energy is
name after Pieter Zeeman
who want to now bill price in 1902 for
observing this Petron line splitting when
gas discharge tubes were
placing in the negative field.
Now we have to remember that this
energy spectrum we calculate
is not the same as the optical
spectrum of emitted photons,
which are only due to
transitions between the levels.
And not all transitions are allowed.
The expressions which determine
when the transitions are allowed
are known as selection rules.
We're going to calculate them next.
During an electronic transition electron
wave function forms a super position
of the initial state and
the final state with lower energy.
Each component evolves
differently in time so
the electron probability distribution
center of mass can move.
This oscillating dipole is what
radiates electromagnetic energy.
A simple calculation of the expectation
value of position yields this expression.
Where we can see the first two direct
terms from the inner product of the wave
function are symmetric, whereas r,
the radial variable, is antisymmetric.
So integration over them vanishes.
The cross terms, which oscillate at
the frequency determined by the energy
difference of initial and
final states, may survive.
Now, those away functions have previously
been writing in spherical coordinates.
We want to convert interval into
cartesian coordinates so we can see
along which axis we might get a charge
oscillation and electromagnetic radiation.
Here's the transformation we
need in terms of the polar and
azimuthal angles veta and phi.
It allows us to split the vector integral
from the previous slide into individual
cartesian components.
First, let's consider the x and
y components of the integral over angle.
We'll have to evaluate
something like this,
two complex exponents containing phi and
sin of cosine over phi.
Using the Euler formulas,
we see that this will involve integrals
over integer periods of
the oscillating complex exponential.
Which is identically equal to 0
except when the exponent is 0.
Since the z component
does not depend on phi,
it's even easier to see that in this
case the integral will be equal to 0.
Only if the magnetic quantum numbers for
initial and final states are the same.
Taking together, we see that there is no
dipole transition and no corresponding
emission of photons unless the change
in magnetic quantum number is plus or
minus one or zero.
This is our selection rule.
By considering these
kinds of arguments about
periodic symmetry of the integrand and
the integral over the polar angle theta,
we can likewise derive another
selection rule for transitions,
such that the change in orbital
quantum number must be + or -1.
So which transitions are allowed?
l must change by 1 and
m can change at most by 1.
The 2 piece stage can decay to the 1s
ground stage and in a magnetic field all 3
of these transitions from m equals 1 zero
minus 1 have different energies giving
different emitted photon wave lengths that
we can analyze with the spectrometer.
The 3s state.
Decays only to the three 2p states.
And 3p decays to 2s, also with
three distinct transition energies.
For higher values of principle quantum
number n, we can have transitions from
the l = 2 d states with
a broken degeneracy of 5,
which can transitions
to the lower p states.
This involves many possible transitions
that satisfy the selection rules.
However, there are always only three
different transition energies,
delta m equals minus one,
zero and plus one.
So each spectral line splits into
a triplet in a magnetic field.
Now I want to point out
something extremely important in
atomic spectroscopy.
Recall the energy time
uncertainty principle.
It says that there's a reciprocal
relationship between the lifetime of
a state and
the resulting spectral line width,
which limits resolution of
high precision measurements.
If a transition is forbidden by selection
rules, other processes maybe allowed, but
typically far less efficient and
result in exceptionally long life times.
Here, we see that the transition to
the bound state from the 2s state,
is forbidden by the selection rule.
And other processes yield a lifetime
of over a hundred milliseconds in
comparison to the nearly equal transition
from 2p to 1s in about one nano second.
The line went through this transition,
is therefore extremely narrow.
Allowing very high-precision measurements
of exquisite quantum effects such as
the Lamb shift.
Due to small corrections of energy levels
from quantum electrodynamical effects
of the electron interacting with short
lived excitations in the vacuum.
In addition to the selection rules, we
can use the different forms of the dipole
vector components to explain another
feature of zamon splits electrical lines.
They're optical polarization and
directional dependants.
For instance, we know that the transition
corresponding to delta m equal to 0,
no change in the magnetic quantum number
during the transition is caused by
a dipole along the magnetic field axis, z.
However, we also know from classical
electrodynamics that an oscillating dipole
does not radiate along its axis.
Therefore, this spectral line is absent
when observed along this orientation.
The other two are present, and
due to dipoles oscillating 90 degrees out
of phase along x and y, yielding right and
left handed circularly polarized light.
If we observe from a direction
perpendicular to the magnetic field
access, then the delta m equal to zero
line in the middle can be seen and
has a linear polarization along c.
The other two are polarized
perpendicular to the field axis.
Because they are again due to dipole x and
y.
Hendrik Lorentz win the Nobel Prize
in 1902 along with [INAUDIBLE].
For explaining this
polarization dependence.
He used only classical physics,
a theory which we now know is wrong.
Despite this perceived success
in explaining the Zeeman effect,
a serious problem remained.
Some spectral lines split into
triplets as predicted but
others split into multiplets of four,
six, etc.
Here's a few examples.
Now, we haven't made a silly mistake,
we just need to re-examine
the ingredients of our theory,
namely the equation.
Converting the classical kinetic
energy into an operator is correct in
the absolutely non-relativistic case as
we've done here with the construction of
the Schroedinger equation, but we're
clearly leaving out an essential piece of
physics by not even using
a relativistically invariant expression.
Now, can we fix the problem
by starting from scratch,
constructing a wave equation by starting
with the relativistic expression for
kinetic energy that's given here?
That's what we're going to
see in the next slides.
By the way, those of you who haven't seen
this expression before might want to see
that It's asymptotically equivalent
to the classical expression,
in the limit that the momentum p is small.
Then we can expand the square root and
it's Taylor series, and
see that the dominant terms are the
familiar mc2, rest-mass energy, and
the classical kinetic energy.
Everything else is small,
all though not negligible, as we will see.
If we take a relativistic expression and
try to use it as
an operator on a wave function,
we immediately encounter a problem.
Our momentum operators
are within the square root.
And it's not clear at all whether
this makes any mathematical sense.
The problem disappears if
the expression inside the square root
is itself a perfect square.
If we write the rest mass energy and
kinetic energy components in x, y, and
z here, 1, 2, and
3 with arbitrary coefficients,
then we can make this a perfect square if
these coefficients satisfy what appears,
at first, to be an unusual constraint.
It give unity when squared, but
they anti commute with each other.
These coefficients clearly
are not scaler values.
However, this fact didn't
frighten Paul Dirac
from writing down this relativistically
invariant equation in 1928.
The alpha coefficients
are clearly not scaler values.
But matrices, which satisfy the anti
commutation relations, and form a so
called Clifford algebra.
Now we can write down many matrices which
satisfy the algebra, but it makes sense to
first look at the simplest case,
with the smallest dimension matrices.
It turns out, this can be done with
matrices as small as four by four.
Here's one choice of basis.
I two is the two by two identity and
o two is a two by two matrix of all zeros.
The two by two poly matrices,
the sigmas form the off diagonal
blocks of the alpha one two and
three four by four matrices.
Now importantly, this converts
the wave equation into a four-by-four
matrix equation and the wave function
into a four-component vector.
Two of these correspond to arrest
mass energy of mc squared,
when the momentum p is equal to zero,
as we expect for an electron.
But a natural question to
ask is why two values?
Degeneracies like this are a signature
of symmetry, but which one?
Which degree of freedom do
these two values correspond to?
We're going to look at an experiment for
a clue.