All right concept check nine.
We have two light bulbs that are connected to a wall socket bulb.
Number one they're connected in series as shown here bulb number one is a 100 watt bulb Number two is
40 watt which statement is true.
OK.
Well the wall socket is 120 volts.
These are 100 watt bulb.
Here's a 40 watt bulb.
All right.
Now both light bulbs are at their normal brightness 100 watt bulb is brighter than the 40 watt bulb.
40 watt bulb is brighter than 100 watt equal brightness or can't determine how you might be.
Just try to answer this quickly.
Say oh the wattage of a 100 watt bulb it's it's got a bigger power rating it must be brighter than the
40 watt bulb.
Now you've got to be just a little bit careful when you make that argument because now we have two of
them that are connected in series with each other.
So if you wanted to calculate the power dissipated by a 100 watt bulb Well what you would do is there's
different ways to rate this power equation but one way we saw would be the resistance of the 100 watt
bulb.
Let's call it R1 and multiply by the current flowing through it squared right.
And we know since there are going to be in series the current is going to be the same flowing through
both of them.
So we'll just call that.
I know the power being dissipated by the 40 watt bulb you say it's 40 resistance R2.
OK.
And multiplied by the same current.
All right.
So whichever one dissipates more power should be the brightest light bulb however.
So they both have the same current.
Now we have to determine what is the resistance.
Right.
If we know the resistance are one and our two we'll be able to determine which power is actually bigger.
Now you have to be a little bit careful.
Now we're going to use this information when they kind of rate light bulbs like this.
This is when it's plugged into 120 volts all by itself.
So let's consider a simple circuit where we have just the 100 watt bulb.
Let me just represented by a resistor here.
Here's our resistance one here is 120 volts.
That way you would find the power dissipated here well you can simply write the power being dissipated.
Now the voltage is going to be the same in both cases.
It's going to be 120 an that's divided by the resistance.
This was another way we wrote down the power equation.
So when they write down 100 watts like this that's the power dissipated again V is 120.
So what does that mean.
I means that the resistance is going to be the voltage squared divided by that power rating.
So what does that tell you about the resistance.
It tells you that for 100 watt bulb the resistance again the voltage square divided by the value of
the wattage tells you automatically that the resistance of this guy is actually less than the resistance
of the 40 watt bulb.
Are two.
So that's very important.
Resistance a 40 watt bulb resistance is bigger.
Now we go back to the original statement over here our original equations.
Now it's different in this case because the same current now flows through them.
When you plug them in differently.
Right just like in this little circuit over here if plug in a 100 watt bulb.
And then I substituted for a 40 watt bulb.
You're going to have a different amount of current flowing through it.
But when they're in series with each other the same current flows through them.
So these are my power expressions over here and we just argued that the resistance are two is actually
bigger than the distance are one which means that the power is dissipated by the by that the watt bulb
is going to be bigger in this case than 100 watt bulb when they're in series
OK.
So actually the 40 watt bulb and then the situation is he going to be brighter than 100 watt bulb kind
of counter-intuitive.