All right here's our first RC circuit concept check question it says consider this circuit over here.
We have power supply to them resistors capacitors switch.
Consider the circuit below the switch S is close that time equals to zero so close that up over here.
Boehme What is the voltage across this capacitor over here.
Just after you close the switch and you get all these choices.
0 9 volt none of the above are impossible to determine.
Well the key to this problem here.
Again if they don't tell you that what the charges I guess maybe should have put that in there but you
can probably safely assume that the initial charge on the capacitor most capacitors if it does grab
them you put them in a circuit they're probably uncharged.
OK.
So if it's on charge remember the relationship between the charge and the voltage across the plates
is simply given by this expression over here.
So if initially there is no charge.
Again it's going to take a bit of time before a charge starts accumulating on there.
Right it doesn't go from zero charge to its maximum value instantaneously.
So since the charge is zero that means that the only way the charge is zero is if the potential across
the plates is zero.
So this is kind of just they just a quick check see if you remember stuff about capacitors.