All right here is concept check number three 3 consider this following circuit here a power supply.
We have three resistors and capacitors initially on charge when the switch is close that time goes to
zero right close that guy up.
Which circuit is equivalent to this circuit.
The instant immediately after the switch is close.
So remember all we do again in a short time limit what you can do is you replace the capacitor basically
just with a wire right.
And that's a basically short a capacitor and that's how it behaves.
In the short time limit now you don't eliminate any of the resistors anywhere.
Right.
That's not what happens.
OK.
So all the resistors still have to be there.
The only thing you do is you simplify any branch with a capacitor.
So right away you should be able to answer that choice.
Number three is the same office you don't get rid of any of the power supply.
They don't need to go anywhere.
So choice 3 is really the best answer for this case.