Art here's RC circuit cons object number four because consider the following circuit here on the right
hand side looking a little bit more complicated.
The switch is close and close that up here.
Time equals zero.
They ask What is the voltage across the capacitor just after you close the switch and 0 through 9 volts.
Missin a few here.
None of the above are impossible to determine.
All right.
The key to this problem again is just after you close the switch Well you know initially it's uncharged.
So the initial charge is zero.
We always have to have this relationship for any capacitor you have that the charge is directly proportional
to the voltage.
If the charge initially is zero that means that the voltage initially has to be zero across those plates.
OK.
So that's it.
Zero is the correct answer for this guy.