All right here is content check five for RC circuits again same circuit as before or we're going to
do now is what does the current through the capacitor.
Well through the capacitor is it a little bit of kind of maybe not the best term to use here.
Well we're asking for is it what is the the rate of change of the charger and what's the current in
kind of this section over here.
Just after you close the switch again the key to all these problems here is in the short time limit
what you do is you just short off the capacitor or you just replace it with a wire.
And now if you want to determine the current out here what we could do now is basically this outer branch
has a resistance of zero.
This other branches middle branch here has a resistance of two homes.
So what happens when you kind of group them up had these basically behave like an effective resistance.
And what's the value if there's two of them right the equivalent resistance if there's two you end up
multiplying so you get two times zero divided by the sum two plus zero equals zero.
Right.
Basically all the current that comes into this junction Well it's going to go through the path of least
resistance.
It's going to go toward the capacitor initially.
Why would it want to go through the two home.
Right.
That's more resistance initially going out in this outer branch.
So all we have to do now is if we can determine how much current flows through the battery and across
the 1 ohm resistor all that current initially is going to go toward this outer branch.
OK.
In order to do that all you have to do is apply Ohm's Law use LOOP rule and let's go around this outer
branch.
So the first thing I encounter is a 6 volt battery.
The next thing I encounter now is a 1 ohm resistor and I'm going to get a voltage drop across that resistor
and that's going to be equal to our I.
So the resistance is one and the current is I and that's it.
Now I'm at this point and now I keep going all the way around this outer branch but there's no resistance
here initially.
And then I go back to where I started.
That's it.
So the current at the end of the day six stamps is the correct answer.
Again this is in the short time limit here where the capacitor behaves like a just resistance with or
no resistance.
Right.
It shorted.