All writers problem three says consider this Surtur below which resistor has the largest power consumption
so which one dissipates the most amount of power.
This is kind of a good problem here.
So if we're talking about a power dissipated by resistance again power equation you can write three
different ways right.
That was a one way we can write it as our squared was also another way and we can also write it as V
squared over r.
So let's start comparing them so we got to compare the three.
I don't want to do I don't want to solve for the entire circuit.
All we have to do is determine which one has the largest We don't actually have to do any math.
We don't want to know the actual value of it.
We just want to know which one is the biggest.
So let's first compare 10 to 1000.
Right.
One thing we know is that the voltage between points B and D right the voltage between the Point B and
D should be the same as the voltage between Point B and C because both of these are in parallel with
each other.
So that must be equal to the voltage between Point B and C..
So actually if you use now this for Use the third equation that I wrote I.
At this equation over here remember V here is the voltage across that resistor R is the value of the
resistance.
So if you compare the power across the 10 arm resistance what you would do is you would say all the
power.
You're right the power dissipated in this 10 arm resistance is equal to the voltage across that 10 ohm
resistance.
That's what we called VBIED.
You've got to square that value.
And now you divide it by 10 if you'd compare it now to the power dissipated by the thousand ohm resistor
Well you'd get the voltage across a thousand.
It's actually the same as this one so the voltage B.C which is the same divided now by not 10 is divided
by a thousand.
So you automatically see that the 10 ohm definitely dissipates more energy than a thousand on me because
I'm dividing by a much smaller number here.
OK.
So we've got this guy is the winner between both of those.
Now we have to compare the power dissipated between the 50 and the 10.
So what's the best way of looking at this.
Well you know the current is going to be different.
Right.
So you have current that's going to flow in here it's call it current AI and then we have a junction
over here.
So what happens to that current.
Well part of the current is going to flow down here.
Let's call that one and part of the current is going to flow through the thousand.
Let's call this Aitu.
Now you should know from that junction rule that whatever flows into the junction has to be what's flowing
out.
Therefore from that I think you should conclude that the current.
I must be bigger than the current one right because we know that I have to be equal to I one plus I
had to write and since there's only a single power is applied you know the current is going to flow
in this direction here and then go back.
All right.
So if you can understand this part I think now we just go back to our power equations now for this problem
here it's probably a little bit easier to use this equation over here.
Again it doesn't matter which one you use there I'll give you the same answer.
However now we're going to compare the value of the resistance and the current flowing through it.
So let's compare the fifth wheel versus the 10 ohm So the power dissipated in the 50 ohm resistor you
would read like this it's 50 multiplied by the current How much current is flowing through it.
I label that.
And that's squared.
Now when I compare this to the 10 ohm resistance.
So what do we get we get 10.
Now it's the current going through it is I.
So let's compare both of these things.
Well the resistance is bigger here.
It's bigger than 10 so that number is bigger.
And we also know from what we have over here about our current that the current eye is also bigger.
So if I square it it's certainly going to be in the B.
Ok so the largest power consumption then certainly has to be the 50 ohm has the largest value of the
resistance between the 50 and then in the tank.
And we know that the currents are also going to be bigger.
And so 50 is the biggest or the most power dissipated in that 50 ohm resistance so choice number one
is the correct answer for this one.