A writer's concept check for the same circuit as before but the question is a little bit different says
consider the circuit here which statement is correct.
So there's three statements that says that the current in the segment A B is equal to the current in
B and B c.
So here's the segment ab so we can call this current over here.
Let's call it I A B and then we're going to call this current down over here in this branch.
Here's the current IBD and here's the current and this branch through the thousand ohm resistor.
This here's the current b c OK and we know here we have a junction rule.
And the other two statements simply tell you that they compare the currents that compare the current
through the 10 home and then compare it to the current in 1000 ohm resistor.
So which statement is correct.
Well again you would probably start by writing the junction rule and you could see that statement 1.
It really is the junction.
All right that's Kirchoff's current law right.
The junction will whatever curve flows into the junction has to be the current flowing out of the junction.
So definitely one.
All right so we can actually eliminate some choices right to only Knobe three only.
So one has to be in there.
So it's either one by itself or it's one in one of these other two choices.
So let's compare these other two choices compare the current through the 10 ohm and the current through
the thousand ohm.
Now the one thing we should know is that the voltage between points again voltage between points Biondi
must be equal to the voltage between Point B and C and that is because they are in parallel with each
other.
If you have two resistors in parallel the voltage across each one must be the same.
So now let's just carry this out.
The voltage across the resistor simply 10 multiplied by the current going through it.
BD and this here must be equal to the voltage across the thousand ohm resistor Well that's the value
of the resistance multiplied by the current flowing through it.
B C So automatically you see that the current.
Now if you look at the statements over here they say one is bigger than the other.
Well think about it if you're current over here there's going to be way more current flowing through
the 10 ohm resistor than the thousand ohm resistor.
There's a little less resistance over here right.
And that's what this equation tells us it tells us that the current B-D if you bring the 10 on the other
side it's going to be a hundred times the current through B C.
So the real statement here is the current here must be bigger than the current b c.
So there are two statements that are correct.
The first one in question to you over here or sorry statement number two over here is also correct.
So one and two are correct.
Three is incorrect.