All right.
Here's the last problem here we have a uniform electric field which exist between two parallel plates.
We have an electron here that's released from arrest from the surface of the negative plate and then
it strikes a positive plate which is a distance of three point six centimeters from the first.
And it gives us how much time it takes.
OK.
So let me go ahead first and just kind of fill this in.
This is zero point zero three six meters and the amount of time it takes delta t is small because it's
a tiny little electron.
So two point zero times ten to the negative eight seconds.
Okay.
For a first question fine the acceleration of the electron.
All right.
So acceleration when I would think about that I would probably think about the word force.
Right.
So I'd say there's probably a force acting on the electron and the force is usually given by the charge
multiplied by the electric field.
And if this is the only force acting on this electron I can go ahead and kind of draw.
Right here there has to be a force acting on it like this.
Right.
If this is the only force that should be equal to the mass times the acceleration.
Oh.
So my acceleration then must be QE over m.
So let's think about this for a minute do I know the charge of the electron Yep.
Do I know the mass.
You might not know the mass but here let me go ahead and give it to you the mass of the electron is
nine point one times 10 to the negative 31 KG something you can look up in a book.
However do I know the electric field.
There's no mention here of the electric field so I'm kind of stuck.
If I if I wrote this down there's nothing wrong with this but I wouldn't be able to take it further.
So one thing I could do now is maybe use some of this information right here because I know it accelerates
because there is an electric field.
So what I'm going to do here is I'm going to use some of the Kitimat X in order to analyze this motion.
So one of the kinetic equations says if an object is accelerating and it starts from rest well it could
look something like this plus one half the acceleration multiplied by T.
Now if I start from rest it means that this first term is zero because there's no initial velocity.
So this is another equation that I have at my disposal that lets me solve for acceleration.
So now I have to do a little bit of algebra because I know it goes you know three point six centimeters
in this amount of time.
So right away I should be on the right that the acceleration if I'm a little bit careful two times delta
x divided by T squared and I know everything now in this problem.
So I can write this down.
So two multiplied by zero point zero three six meters I want to have it in s I units at the end and
two times ten to the negative eight.
And you have to square that time.
All right you put that number in the calculate you're going to get a kind of a ginormous number one
point eight times ten to the 14 and that is in meters per second squared.
OK.
So that's kind of my answer for chart choice A.
All right read.
Question B.
Question.
B now says what is the electric field.
Oh well this is now I can go back to this other problem which I was kind of started off with.
All right except now I'm asking for the electric field e so I really want an equation in terms of E
so I can put the charge down here at the bottom so I kind of look like this just rearranging that equation.
And now again I know everything here.
So guess what I can just go ahead and substitute that again nine point one times ten to the negative
thirty one for an electron the acceleration we just calculated one point eight times ten to the 14 a
lot of different orders of magnitude here you have to deal with and the charge of the electron I know
is one point six times tend to the negative 19 this is a good exercise to use your calculator and hopefully
you get it right.
I think I got 1024 and I would write that a nuance for cool on all right.
So this is the question.
B In the last one now find the speed.
OK so how fast is it moving now once it hits the other side.
It started from rest right.
So v zero is equal to zero but it's been accelerating now for a long time.
So for part c again I'm gonna go back to my good old faithful Kitimat ex because I know basically everything
about it.
One other key nomadic equation which you might know is this one the square that gives me the speed.
V not squared plus two times the acceleration multiplied by the displacement.
OK so I guess what I'm gonna do here.
This initial velocity is zero.
So all you have to do here at the end is simply take the square root of both sides and you're gonna
get an expression for the final speed.
All right going to put everything in the calculator again.
Let me make this kind of big so I have to.
This is one point eight times 10 to the 14 the large acceleration and the displacement is zero point
zero three six.
Don't forget to take the square root of this number at the end.
So the final speed of this electron just before it hits the plate.
I think I got three point six times tend to the six and that would be in meters per second.
OK so this is a problem see right here.
All right kind of a nice little cinematics problem just to end the exam.