Here's multiple choice one we have two uncharged metal spheres one and two they're mounted on insulating
supporting rods.
So maybe let me go ahead and kind of troll this kind of sphere number one and fear number two.
OK.
And now a third metal sphere carrying POSITIVE CHARGE IS THEN PLACE Mir number two.
So we better label these here.
So let me say this here is number one and this here's number two.
Now we bring a third one close to number two.
So I mean actually bring this one a different color here okay.
And they also say that number three is a positively charged.
So through some process it was positively has a net positive charge a copper wire is momentarily connected
between one and two.
So here's our wire and then it's removed.
Finally sphere three is removed.
So let's first take this into the situation to consideration.
So I bring this positively charged object.
Well what is that going to do.
All right.
It's going to attract some of the negative charges from sphere one.
Also the negative charges from sphere to right and that there is going to leave sphere one with a positive
net charge because some of its electrons were attracted to the sphere number three which was positive
and then what do you do well then you remove this guy whoops and then you remove the wire.
Let me go ahead and remove the wire here.
Color it in.
So if I then remove the wire I just cut it.
What's gonna happen after that.
Well this is what's going to be left over.
And again don't forget we're also going to remove this guy.
Right.
So once we remove sphere number three this is what we're left with.
Okay so let's have a look at these choices now.
That's kind of the underlying physics behind it.
So sphere one in sphere two are still uncharged No that's not what we have here guys sphere one carries
a positive charge and Sphere two carries a negative charge that one seems ok to me a circle outward
sphere one carries negative nope that's not what's going to happen.
Sphere one both carry positive charge note both negative charge so the correct answer for this one is
B Ok so it kind of helps to kind of draw each one of these in to consider that what is going to move
and again it's only the negative charges that can move OK on the conductor's album to an outer space
we have a positive charge q is release near a fixed charge so this big charge q cannot move as Q moves
away so let me kind of to draw when it's a little bit farther away this is a little cute still positive
what is true about the motion of this charge here and again there could be more than one correct choice
so it's be a little bit careful so let's go through them in detail it will move will with decreasing
speed well imagine here it's released right.
So here it's released so its velocity was zero and what's going to happen.
Well if you think about it what's going to be the force acting on the positive charge q right.
There is a repulsive force which is given by cool Holmes law.
And that force depends on the distance Ah well what happens as there is a force it's going to start
to accelerate it's going to start speeding up well what happens when it's farther away right when it's
all the way down over here again the ah gets smaller but the force is still going to be in the same
direction it's still being repelled by this positive charge it's only moving like this.
OK so at the end it's always going to be speeding up it's just speeding up at a slower rate it's certainly
not going to move with decreasing speed is it going to move with constant acceleration.
Well I think what happens to the force remember our force for cool Ohm's Law will be k uppercase Q It's
the charge of this sphere a little Q and divided by the distance squared the direction we know is always
in the same direction in this case to the right.
So as the distance gets bigger the force gets smaller and noon second losses force is equal to mass
times acceleration.
So over here my acceleration down over here is going to be small as it gets farther away.
Over here the acceleration is bigger but it's always in the same direction.
The force and the acceleration are always in the same direction so it's definitely not constant because
the force changes.
What else do we have it will move with increasing acceleration.
One that we just talked about that case okay.
It's certainly not going to move like that.
It will move with decreasing acceleration yes.
Right.
This is what we just mentioned right here because the force gets smaller.
It will move with increasing speed.
Okay.
Remember our definition of acceleration.
Definition of acceleration is the change of velocity with relative to the change in time.
Okay so my change of velocity is the acceleration multiplied by the change in time.
Well the acceleration is always in this same position.
Sorry same direction.
Therefore the change of velocity which is a final minus initial over here.
This is always going to be speeding up because the acceleration is always in the same direction this
number gets smaller but it never changes directions.
So the speed is also always going to increase.
All right.
So in this case extremely choice D and choice E are the two correct answers all right.
Question 3 two point charges Q1 and Q2 they're separated by distance.
Are if the magnitudes of both charges are halved and their separation is also half what's gonna happen
to the electrical force.
OK.
So let's imagine here's our Q1 here's the Q2.
We also said they are separated by some distance.
Ah okay.
So in this case here.
Well what would be the force of force acting on this I'll just call this case 1 would be k Q1 Q2 and
divided by our square that would be the magnitude of the force.
Okay.
So what happens now.
Well let's compare it to force number 2.
This is when I make the changes.
Okay.
So the first thing I notice is that both charges are halved.
So we're gonna have q 1 over 2 and we're going to have Q2 over 2.
What else.
Their separation is also halved.
Okay.
So that means that the distance between them now is going to be R over 2.
So let's substitute everything in here and see what happens.
We're going to have q 1 over 2.
We're going to have Q2 over 2 and we're going to have the distance.
Now is not r it's R over 2 squared.
Now you've got to take care of all these factors.
So you're going to have a factor of four in the denominator over here and you've got to be careful with
this one right.
Because after you evaluate that one you're going to have K Q1 Q2.
There's gonna be the one factor of one over 4 from both of those twos but here when you evaluate this
it's going to look something like this so these fours are actually going to cancel out and you could
see what we're left with right here is this term is the exact same as that one.
So at the end f 2 is going to be f 1.
So even though we've made these changes to both charges and also change the distance at the end we get
the same expression for the force which means that E here has to be the correct answer it doesn't increase
by any factor.
Okay.
So you're gonna be a little bit careful with these all right.
Let's read problem for here we have four point charges.
They have various magnitudes and they're arranged in this square configuration here.
The length of the side is deep well which of the errors represents the net force acting on this point
charge here in the corner.
Let me just go ahead and kind of draw that point charge it has a magnitude of positive Q All right.
What you have to do is consider the interaction between this charge and the three other charges so you
can consider them one at a time.
So let's first consider both of those both positive point charge.
So on charge q you should have a force like this.
Call it f 1.
What about the fourth down here between this guy and this guy.
Again they're both positive.
Therefore the force should be in this direction.
What else.
Now you have the corner one and the bottom corner one one of them's positive the other one's negative.
So the forests should be attractive.
So it should be in this direction.
It's called this F 3.
All right.
What you have to do now is you have to add all these as vectors.
If you add EF 1 and EF 2 together you're going to get a vector that is like this both EF 1 and EF 2
they have the same magnitude.
Right.
They have to have the same magnitude because you have positive two QS interacting with a positive Q
charge.
So at the end we have to find what is this guy here.
This is EF 1 plus EF 2 as a vector.
Again you know this angle here should be forty five degrees because these are the same magnitude of
vectors.
All right.
So now we have to actually write down some of the magnitudes.
First of all you can't have a vector that's going to be along B or D because we know it has to be along
this line.
Right.
So we're really comparing what is which vector is bigger this purple one or this green one.
If we know which one is bigger than that'll be the direction of the net force.
So it certainly can't be B or D.
All right.
We're left with either choice a choice c.
So now we have to look at the magnitudes.
Well one thing that's easy to write is the magnitude of EF 1 the magnitude of EF 1 is simply k.
We have positive q.
We have two Q and they're separated by distance.
Dean you have to square that thing.
So let me just put the two in the front.
Q squared over d squared.
This is EF 1.
Well what about the magnitude of this guy.
Here you can use some trigonometry because the magnitude of EF 1 plus EF 2 is going to be you can write
that as again do some trigonometry right sine of forty five or close of forty five is equal to EF 1
divided by the magnitude of the hypotenuse here.
All right.
So really EF 1 should be something like this.
This should be close of 45.
And this here should be equal to the magnitude of EF 1.
This is just using some trigonometry right here.
OK.
So at the end the magnitude of EF 1 plus EF 2 as a vector it's a little bit longer than what I thought
it was going to be but a Coast of forty five is square root of two divided by two.
So at the end we should have something like this.
It's right to OK Q squared divided by D squared and now I have to divide by two root to square root
of two and divided by 2.
So at the end we get four square root of two K Q squared over d squared.
All right.
Anyway this number here is going to be this is like one point four.
You can get a number in the front.
Let's look at the magnitude of this vector or the magnitude of F 3.
Okay.
So F 3 again is going to be equal to k.
The magnitude is the charge.
Q The other charge is also has a magnitude.
Q It ought to put the negative sign that just tells me the direction and now divided by what is this
distance here it's the distance squared so it's gonna be this squared plus of this squared that gives
me 2 D squared.
That is the distance squared.
Okay.
Here you have to use kind of Pythagorean Theorem in order to find what this distances.
All right.
So at the end if you compare both of those you should find that this force here is bigger than this
force.
So that means that the net force is going to be along misdirection here.
Okay.
So a is actually the correct answer for this one.
All right.
Let's go onto the next one.