Here we have a uniform electric fuel with magnitude given by this six times ten of the six newtons per
Coolum is directed along the x axis a cube having an edge of zero point one metres is oriented as shown
in the figure.
WHAT IS THE ELECTRIC FLUX passing through the shaded area right here.
ALL RIGHT.
SO HOW DO WE FIND THE ELECTRIC FLUX here.
Just going through this area right here.
Given the dimensions of everything and the electric field.
So again if you consider the electric field here is in the positive x axis or fields should be going
directly like this.
We also would have liked the area the normal to the area the vector that's perpendicular IS ALSO LIKE
THIS.
ALL RIGHT.
SO IF YOU REMEMBER THE DEFINITION OF THE ELECTRIC FLUX it would be the for a constant field anyway it's
the magnitude of the field the magnitude of the area and coast of the angle between the electric field
and the vector that's perpendicular to the area.
In this case here the theta is equal to zero degrees so coast of zero equals to one.
So we don't have to worry about this.
So our electric flux reduces the simply the field magnitude multiplied by the area.
So this is pretty easy.
Field MAGNITUDE IS SIX TIMES 10 TO THE 6 in the area.
Again it's a square and the side is zero point one so you have to square that thing.
So again six times tend to the six I don't even need a calculator for this one this is zero point zero
one at the annual SHOULD GET SIX TIMES 10 TO THE FOUR.
OKAY SO THE CORRECT ANSWER FOR THIS ONE LOOKS LIKE IT'S GOING TO BE choice B.
So nothing too difficult about this problem.
Hopefully you got that one all right.
Question 10 says we have two tiny particles having these charges over here they're separated by 20 centimeters.
What are the magnitudes and direction of the electric field midway between the charges.
All right so let's go ahead and draw them out.
So we have a 20 micro Coolum charge 20 micro cool on and then we're going to have a negative 8 micro
Coolum.
Put this one here and this is negative 8 micro cool.
And what we want to know is at the midway between them they're separated by 20 centimeters.
So that's this distance right here I'm going to put that right in meters right away that zero point
two meters.
What we want to know here is right here at the midpoint what is the electric field right here at this
point.
So first thing we have to figure out is where there's going to be two contributions to the electric
field.
There is the electric field produced by the positive one which is like this.
This here has a magnitude let's call it E E 1 and the negative charge also produces an electric field.
And again we're going to call it's magnitude E 2.
At the end we have to add them up as vectors since they're in the same direction we simply have to add
them up.
One thing we could do right away is that if you look at all these choices some of them say it's directed
toward the positive charge so it can't be anything directed toward the positive charge.
It has to be directed toward the negative charge.
All right.
So let's eliminate choice to be in choice D right away.
And now we're left with different magnitude.
So now we have to be a little bit more careful rights either tend to the fourth end of the five or ten
to the six.
So let's go ahead and look at the magnitudes of each one of those things.
All right.
So E one right here is going to be k q and divided by the distance.
Now the distance is zero point one squared.
All right.
And e to is going to be k its charge here is going to be so let's just call it Q2 and again the distance
is still zero point one squared.
Let's go ahead and substitute in all our numbers here nine times 10 to the nine is for the K value.
This charge is 20 micro cooldown times tend to the negative 6.
And all of this divided by zero point one squared.
All right so be a little bit careful when you plug that in your calculator for the negative charge you
have.
Whoops just said Let's substitute our numbers so we get nine times ten to the nine for our constant
k.
The magnitude of this charge is eight times tend to the negative six.
And now how far is it away from that charge the point where we're evaluating the field is zero point
one meter.
All right.
At the end what you have to do here is you have to add both of those up.
So we have to take calculate those numbers and add them up.
All right.
Now I'm going to let you kind of go ahead and do that at the end.
If you do it correctly.
Let me check my answers right here.
I think I obtain an answer which was a 10 to the six.
All right it's over 10 if you do careful here at the end e total is equal to the magnitude of each one
plus the magnitude of E two.
OK.
Which gives me twenty five point two times ten of the six.
And that's measured and nuanced per Pakula that's our magnitude.
All right.
But those are the basic steps into getting to that answer all right.
Here's number 11.
The end of the electrical potential in this case OK electrical potential a distance of 4 meters from
a certain point charges to 200 volts.
What is the potential at a distance of two meters from the same charge.
All right.
So let me kind of draw this one out here.
So we have oh let's get rid of that maybe use this.
All right let's draw a positive chart.
I know it's positive because it's 200 volts and I'm going to be a certain distance of four meters away.
So let me draw kind of point over here that's four meters away.
I don't know exactly where that is.
So really could be kind of anywhere on this sphere that is four meters away.
Right.
That the potential everywhere here is two hundred volts and the formula you would use to calculate this
would be that the potential V from the point charge it would be k q divided by the distance in this
case it's the distance are so hours for what is the potential now if you're only two meters away.
So what if you cut that distance in half what happens okay.
Well if you think about it now.
So when you're four right here.
So if I make the distance smaller I should have a higher electrical potential.
Okay.
And again if the distance now is two instead of keeping everything else the same which you would have
is the potential would be k q the same K the same Q And the distance now is are over two.
So it really be two times k q over R and this guy here in the bracket is what we call two hundred volts.
So in this case here you'd have to have four hundred volts so the potential gets bigger as I go closer.
Okay.
And for this case here going from two meters to four meters I doubling the distance in this case the
potential goes down by a factor of two.
So we have to have 400 volts.
I would have probably eliminated choice B right away and a whole so choice D I would have probably also
eliminated choice a the potential is not going to stay the same because it's produced by a point charge
and it's not going to get smaller because I'm getting closer to that charge.
So I would have been left with only two choices and then doing a little bit of math would have got me
to the right answer.
So sees the right answer here.
All right.
So let's have a look in number 12.
We have two protons are fired toward each other in a particle accelerator with only the electrostatic
force acting which of the following statements must be true as they move closer together.
OK.
There could be more than one answer.
So let's kind of draw it out here.
Imagine when they're really far away.
So there's a force acting on them it's repulsive right the force might look something like this might
look something like this.
That's the force.
What else.
They're probably moving at a certain speed.
All right.
So what's happening to that speed as they get closer as they get closer and maybe eventually they might
be something like this.
How would you draw the force in this case.
I think I would draw a bigger right because the distance is smaller.
They're probably slowing down so I don't know maybe make the velocity a little bit smaller.
There might be a point where they get close.
They don't quite touch.
They get to zero and then they start going back.
All right.
So let's have a look at some of these choices here.
There are electrical potential energy Kipps keeps increasing.
So do we have more potential energy over here.
Well think about it in terms of kinetic and electrical potential.
OK.
So this is really the two forms of energy that we have.
We have kinetic plus potential right over here and the first step.
We have a lot of kinetic energy.
So we have a small potential energy.
So what happens as they get closer the kinetic energy gets smaller.
So the potential energy has to go up because the total energy is conserved.
So yeah that wouldn't make sense to me.
What else.
Their kinetic energy keeps increasing.
Well no that's not true right.
Because they're slowing down.
Right.
Because there's a force acting in the opposite direction.
There are electrical potential energy keeps decreasing on No.
That can't be because we just said the kinetic energy gets smaller.
So that has to come at the expense of the electrostatic potential energy their kinetic energy keeps
decreasing.
Yes.
This one here makes sense.
So we have a That's good we have d That's good.
Their acceleration keeps decreasing.
OK.
Why when I read the word acceleration I immediately think about the force is the force getting smaller
or is the force getting bigger.
All right.
We just said here force gets bigger.
And the way we argue that is just by using cool Ohm's law it's the same charges but the distance between
them is getting smaller.
So if I divide by a small number I'm going to get a larger force larger force means larger acceleration.
All right.
So a India the correct answers for this one.