We have two three micro cooling charges they lie on the x axis ones at the origin the others at the
2 meter mark.
What is the potential due to these charges at a point six meters from the axis.
Well I suggest we kind of draw something here going on.
So let me draw the origin right here and we have another one that is two meters away.
Let me draw those charges so too so they both have the same charge.
Right.
So one of them is here.
That's three micro cooling.
And the other one is here and it's also three micro Coolum.
And now we want to go six meters away.
So the point is really somewhere down over here.
Right.
So the point is here.
So it's it's four meters away from this guy and it's going to be six meters away from this guy.
OK.
And what we're looking for here is what is the potential.
So we have two point charges which you have to do is find the total potential.
So it's going to be the potential due to let's call this Q one charge number one to call this one Q2
again of the same magnitude but they're different distances.
So it's the potential due to one plus the potential due to the other.
Now we just use our equation for point charges.
So it's K again Q And now divided by the distance for Q1 I'm going to call this R one plus K Q2 divided
by R2.
Let's go ahead and substitute everything in here first and foremost.
This numerator is going to be the same for both because we have the same charge right.
So really you could factor that out.
You could write k q and now just have the distances here are one plus one over R2.
All right now I'm in a better position to substitute the numbers.
So the total potential now would be k is nine times 10 to the nine.
Let's fix that the charges three micro times 10 to the negative six.
OK.
And then we have this term here.
So it's one over six meters plus one over four meters.
OK.
I think if you put everything on the calculator be a little bit careful when you do that you should
get eleven thousand volts.
All right so choice a is the right answer again just using superposition if you have more than one point
charge you add the potential due to each one the problem 18 in a region where the electric field is
uniform and points in the positive x direction the electrical potential is negative two thousand volts
at X equals the eight and plus 400 volts at X equals to two meters.
What's the magnitude of the field.
Again I would kind of like to draw this one.
So let's just kind of make a line here at X equals to 2 and the voltage over here is 400 volts and then
we have a line at X equals to eight meters.
X equals the eight meters and the voltage over here is negative two thousand volts.
Okay.
So the electric field is uniform and points in the positive x direction where you would plot the electric
field here would be something like this
all right it's kind of like a parallel plate capacitor right where this plate is positive.
This plate here is negative.
Then we have an electric field like this.
So what is just the magnitude of e again the equation that we have over here is that the change in voltage
is equal to negative e multiplied by Delta X that the voltage varies linearly from one plate to the
other see the voltage is getting smaller as I go in the positive x displacement here over six meters.
All right.
So again this is a final value minus an initial value equals to minus E..
And again this is X final minus X initial.
So imagine here this is my initial and this is my final.
Again we're just worried about the magnitude here.
But let's look at this side.
What we get.
All right.
The final voltage here is negative two thousand minus the initial voltage which is 400 equals to negative
e and the final position is eight and minus two.
OK.
So we get minus twenty four hundred is the difference in the voltage and you get minus E multiplied
by six.
OK.
So we could do one last step that the voltage here can get rid of those negative signs.
It's going to be equal to twenty four hundred divided by six.
OK.
So the final answer here at the end should be equal to 400 volts per meter.
The fact that it's positive means that it's pointing in this direction over here.
Again if we're just worried about the magnitude it could have done this a little bit quicker but just
show you how to use that equation right there.
So C is the correct answer for this one
problem 19 now the equal potential surfaces of two point charges are shown find the value of the potential
market on the line for each surface.
Oh the values are listed over here for each surface.
What is the potential difference V G minus VDI.
All right.
So let's go look where we are.
So G is over here and D is right here.
This is easy all you have to do is just simply substitute the values.
Right.
So V G minus V D is the potential on this equity potential.
So I just read it could be anywhere on this point right here.
This is negative 160 and minus well v DVD is zero.
So I get negative 160 volts OK.
Pretty straightforward.
You just reading the values off the chart right there.
So A's the correct answer.
All right.
So here is our final multiple choice problem.
We have a potential difference between plates in an airfield parallel plate capacitor.
The separation is six and the voltage difference is 60 volts.
What's the strength of the magnitude of the electric field between those plates.
All right.
Well this is kind of straightforward.
I think you just draw some parallel plates.
Again we know the separation is six centimeters so just be careful and are right that in meters 0 6
meters and the voltage here between those plates is 60 volts.
All right.
So that's it.
All we have to do is find what is the electric field here between these plates.
Again the electric field is the change of the potential with distance.
OK.
And we're going over a distance of zero point zero six.
Again I don't have to worry about this negative side I'm not worried about the direction here.
I just want to know the magnitude.
So this here is 60 volts divided by zero point zero six.
Well I can even do that math in my head.
This is six over a hundred.
Me bring one hundred over here left with one ten times 100 is a thousand.
A thousand volts per meter.
OK.
That is the strength of the electric field.
So for this one the correct answer is C hopefully you got that one.