All right here we have an electric dipole it consists of two charges of six micro cool on one's positive
ones negative they're 10 centimeters apart.
We want to find the magnitude and the direction of the electric field that it produces over here.
All right.
So let me just kind of draw this one red and the negative one blue.
So we have to do is consider the superposition.
Right.
So the positive one produces an electric field in this direction.
OK.
Can I call that a e positive and the negative one produces an electric feel that points toward it.
It should have the same magnitude.
And that is going to be a negative.
Well you want to do now as you want to add both of those as vectors.
If I put the blue one over here this is e minus the total electric field should look like a vector that
points like this to the left.
All right.
So that's the total electric field so we could start off first of all by finding a couple of things
first of all.
What about this angle here I'm gonna need this angle because at the end I want to break this down in
two components.
OK.
The angle.
Well one thing you should notice is that if I know this distance of the hypotenuse and let's imagine
I break this down into two equal triangles.
I know the length of the hypotenuse and I know the length of the adjacent side so I can use coasts.
All right so coasts of theta should be like seven over.
Sorry FIVE OVER SEVEN.
LET'S TRY THAT AGAIN.
ALL RIGHT FIVE OVER SEVEN.
Something like that so you can find with the angle theta is here and you should get theta that's forty
four point four degrees I think I got.
OK.
So that's gonna be important later on.
And then at the end if we're looking for the total field you notice that the total field only has a
component like this it has no vertical component.
So really what we're doing here is at the end we're going to break it down into components if I think
about that red vector there that red vector I can break down into two components I could break down
into a vertical component.
This is E plus sign of the angle theta and a horizontal component.
This guy here is E plus coasts of the angle theta.
So my total field really at the end should boil down to this.
I'm gonna have two of those because the negative one the magnitude is the same.
So it should end up being simply two times the magnitude of the field produced by one of those charges
multiplied by coast of the angle theta.
All right.
So we still have to do this work right here what is the field produced by one of those point charges
right here.
So I need to find what this is.
I'm going to do this right here over here.
So the field produced by this positive charge right here at Point P.
OK.
Again it's the value K it's going to be the magnitude of the charge which I'm just going to call Q for
now and divided by the distance squared.
So let's substitute all our values and find with this magnitude of that red vector is this is nine times
10 to the nine the charge that's producing it is six micro Coolum and the distance is seven centimeters
and so far it is from the point so it's zero point zero seven meters.
And you have to square that.
All right.
If I did this correctly I would get a field of one point one times tend to the seven Newton's preschool
on.
So now you've got to substitute everything back over here.
Yeah.
So I would get the same magnitude for the field produced by the negative charge.
Right.
I still get one point one times 10 to seven Newtons per call only it would just be in a different direction
but at the end I'm only interested in picking off both of those horizontal components.
We're gonna go back and just substitute everything here.
So you total it put in all the numbers now it's two multiplied by one point one times 10 to the seven
and multiplied by Kosovo 44.
I wanted to I could also just write five over seven right here.
That's the same thing.
So e total at the end of the day the magnitude one point six times tend to the seven Newtons curriculum
the direction again the direction is like this right.
I would say to the left I've defined the total vector now of this electric field produced by the dipole.