Hi everybody, and
welcome to the first lecture in our
course Exploring Quantum Physics.
Today, I will introduce the main
formulation of Quantum Theory,
Uta Schrödinger, and
I'll also tell you a little bit about
the fascinating history of the subject.
But before going to this main part,
I would like to talk about the process
of learning quantum physics.
And about why I think so many people
find it difficult and frustrating.
And I hope that this brief discussion
will help you avoid this frustration.
And make the process of learning
quantum physics here more effective.
Richard Feynman really
doesn't need an introduction.
He was one of the heroes and
legends in physics universally
recognized as a genius.
He was also a great speaker and
enthusiastic popularizer of physics.
In 1979, he gave a series of very
interesting lectures on quantum physics
at the University of
Auckland in New Zealand.
They're actually available
on YouTube online, and
I would encourage you to listen to them.
If you do so,
you will see that Feynman spends 30 or so
minutes in the beginning of his first
lecture to prepare the audience for
what they were going to hear next.
And one of the main messages in this
introductory part was that no matter
what Feynman were to do,
the audience wouldn't really be able
to understand quantum mechanics anyway.
Then he talks about physics students and
physics professors and their level
of understanding of Quantum Physics.
Let's listen to what Feynman
had to say in this regard.
>> If I'm going to explain this to you,
the question is,
are you going to understand it?
Will you understand the theory when
I tell you first, that the first
time we really thoroughly explain it to
our own physics students is when they're
in the third year graduate physics, then
you think the answer's going to be no.
And that's correct.
You will not understand it.
>> [LAUGH]
>> But
this business about not understanding
is a very serious one that we have
between a scientist and an audience.
And I want to work with you because
I want to tell you something.
The students do not understand it either.
>> [LAUGH]
>> And that's because
the professor doesn't understand-
>> [LAUGH]
>> Which is not a joke.
But very interesting.
>> So what Feynman seems to be saying
is that nobody, not even professional
physicists, other then himself perhaps,
really understands quantum physics.
Well, this is probably the last thing you
want to hear before starting this course.
But this is strictly not my intention to
give you the impression that you should
give up without even trying.
On the contrary, I'd like to
speculate what I think Feynman might
have meant there about why I think so
many people
find it difficult to study Quantum Physics
and other advanced physics subjects.
And I hope that this discussion
will help us further
down the road when we encounter unusual
counter intuitive quantum phenomenon.
Let us look at quantum mechanics
from the perspective of
all major physics theories out there.
In this slide I attempt to present all
these theories in a single diagram,
which of course is an unrealistic
sort of silly task and so
the result I came up with
shouldn't be taken to seriously.
What we have here are three axes
labeling fundamental physics constants.
So here I have the inverse speed of light.
This constant g is the gravity constant
which appears in the Newtonian gravity.
And along with the horizontal axis
I have the Planck constant, which,
as we shall see, is the most important
fundamental constant that appears in
quantum mechanics in that it relays
the particle and wave properties.
Now, the red dots in this
diagram represent symbolically
major fields of physics.
For example,
on this line I have two red dots.
So the one which has all, corresponds
to all physical constants being zero
is just kinematics or classical mechanics,
essentially 17th century physics.
So this dot here with
a finite gravity constant but
all other constants zero
is the Newtonian gravity.
Now moving up the vertical axis to
a finite speed of light brings us
to a theory which takes into account this
finite speed with which interactions
propagate, and this is the celebrated
special relativity theory of Einstein.
Combining it with gravity
results in general relativity,
another celebrated, another very
famous geometric theory of Einstein.
Finally moving along
the horizontal axis to a finite
Planck constant brings us to
actually the subject of our course.
Non relativistic quantum mechanics.
So there is also this part, which we're
not going to discuss too much in this
course combines the relativistic effects
and the quantum mechanical effects.
And this is the so called Quantum Field
Theory of quantum electric dynamics,
a more complicated theory.
Actually I could have other theory,
another dot which has all
fundamental physics constants.
This would be theory of everything.
It doesn't really exist yet
but everybody wants to get it,
so this has been one of the holy
grails of physics for many years.
Now, going back to the reigning
quantum physics and
what does it all have to do with it.
So, let us discuss what theory
governs our everyday lives.
What is sort of our comfort zone?
And I would claim that we're at
somewhere here in this area.
Certainly the length scales
that we encounter in our
every day lives are much
larger than atomic.
The velocities are certainly much
smaller than the speed of light.
And, well, we do experience gravity on
a daily basis, so we're somewhere here.
And here is also where
our intuition works.
And if we say you understand something,
what we usually mean by that is that we
can relate a phenomenon to another
phenomenon that occurs here in this area.
So for example, if we were to
say that we really understand
the quantum mechanical affect,
it would oftentimes imply that we
have found a way to relate it by
something we already know here.
But the problem with all these advanced
physics subjects, especially with
Quantum Physics, is that such mapping,
such a relation, is not always possible.
In other words, it's not always
possible to meaningfully project
quantum mechanical phenomenon
on this classical axis.
And if no classical analog exists,
this is what we call strange.
And this is what we find difficult.
But on the other hand, if we were to
imagine if a fictitious civilization of
tiny species that lived on atomic
scales somewhere in this area, so
these guys would have had really a lot of
problems understanding our classical work.
So the problem is not really with
the quantum physics itself, but
with our centristic position on
how we want to understand it.
But now how do we learn Quantum Physics
if we can't really readily understand it
at a intuitive level?
Fortunately, there is a way to do so.
By speaking a common language of all
physics theories that is not rooted in,
and is independent of,
our classical world.
And this is of course Mathematical
Formalism that needs to be developed.
And it may be true now that two
seemingly unrelated phenomena,
let's say on the classical side and
on the quantum side,
may be explained by similar differential
equations or something like that.
And by studying those we
can develop intuition about
something which is otherwise
inaccessible to us.
But after this discussion you may ask,
why bother studying Quantum Physics
if it's not really relevant
to our everyday lives?
So the motivation comes from experiments.
And more recently also from technological
advances that create systems and
devices which operate further
on the right on this axis.
The take home message here is that
when you study Quantum Physics or
any other advanced physics subject for
this matter, you should actually
be prepared to encounter phenomena that
may appear bizarre at the first sight, and
that you may find difficult to understand.
When it does happen, don't panic and
certainly don't drop the course
because of that, and don't assume that
others find these things obvious.
It's certainly not the case.
So I think the best way to
understand such new concepts
is first understand experimental
data that support them.
And then develop or
understand the mathematical formalism, and
the proper theory that
describes this phenomena.
So when you use this theory again and
again, you will develop
your own intuition.
And get the feeling about it deeper
understanding of the subject.
So speaking about the mathematical side,
so I should mention, of course,
quantum mechanics is a demanding subject.
And we will have to use certain
advanced mathematical techniques, but
there will be lectures with different sort
of levels of mathematical sophistication.
Some of them will be pretty advanced,
some of them actually won't
use much math at all.
And so I hope that all of you
with different backgrounds, and
different levels of
mathematical preparation will
find something that is useful and
interesting.