Nowadays we don't really
have to search too hard for
a motivation to study quantum physics.
There are plenty of experiments happening
around the world every day which exhibit
quantum effects.
But the situation of course was quite
different about 100 years ago or so
when quantum physics was born.
When people couldn't rely on such
sophisticated techniques and
methods, and manifestations of quantum
physics were very, very subtle.
In this video, I'm going to discuss
two such pioneering experiments.
But before going to this part, let me
tell you a little bit about the mood of
the scientists back then on the eve
of the discovery of quantum physics,
which in fact was very pessimistic.
In that people believed that there was
nothing else but classical science and
Maxwell's equations and
Newton's equations and Newtonian gravity.
So to illustrate this, I here present two
quotes by very influential scientists,
Albert Michelson and Lord Kelvin.
For example, Albert Michelson in
1894 at the dedication ceremony for
a physical laboratory at the University
of Chicago said the following.
The more important fundamental laws and
facts of physical science have all been
discovered, and these are now so firmly
established that the possibility of their
ever being supplanted in consequence of
new discoveries, is exceedingly remote.
A little later Lord Kelvin says literally,
there is nothing new to be
discovered in physics now.
All that remains is more and
more precise measurement.
So you can see that even the most famous
and the most influential physicists didn't
believe that there was anything new there,
and they didn't expect anything new.
As a side comment here,
let me mention that Michelson actually
received the 1907 Nobel Prize in physics
for his groundbreaking experiments on
the measurement of the speed of light,
which laid the foundation
of the relativity theory.
So he obviously was proven
by wrong himself actually,
but back in the end of the 19th century,
he and
Lord Kelvin where not the only one
thinking in this pessimistic way.
So the reason for
this was a lack of obvious experiments
available at the time that couldn't
be explained by the classical theory.
So in some sense you may say,
that the situation was similar to what's
going on now actually with
the large Hadron Collider at CERN.
Where all experimental data,
including the discovery of the God
particle, or Higgs Boson last year
are actually consistent with
the so-called standard model.
So hopefully the situation
will change soon and
there will be some
exciting new discoveries.
Just like it did change
back 100 years ago or
so when a few elephants sort
of entered the classical room.
By which I mean, experimental data that
couldn't be explained by classical theory.
So here I present a list
of a few such experiments.
And two of them we're going to
discuss later in this segment, but
among them is black-body radiation,
quantization of atomic spectra,
which we'll talk about
later in the course.
The photoelectric effect, which showed
that under certain circumstances
light can behave as a beam of particles.
And also there was another very curious
and interesting in its history experiment,
which I refer as accident in Bell Labs,
shows electrons behave like waves,
which normally goes under
the name of electron defraction.
So I will now discuss in
detail these two experiments.
Philipp Lenard was a German physicist and
the winner of the 1905 Nobel Prize in
physics for his work on cathode rays.
But back in the beginning of the 20th
century, he was studying how
ultraviolet light interacts with metal
by knocking off electrons from it.
This effect originally was discovered
actually by Hertz in 1887.
It's now called the photoelectric effect,
but
originally it was actually
called the Hertz effect.
So here I present a schematic of Lenard's
experiment copied from his original paper
published back in 1902,
that is the year here.
In this experiment,
he had two metal plates.
Here is the left plate and the right
plate connected by an electric circuit,
so we should imagine having
an electric circuit here.
And one could adjust
voltage across the plates.
So in the photoelectric effect,
light comes in from
a source somewhere here and
illuminates a metallic plate.
So under certain conditions
that we'll discuss in a second,
electrons are emitted from the metal.
And if their energy is large enough to
overcome the potential difference here,
they reach the right plate,
which effectively closes the circuit and
results in a measurable electric current.
So by adjusting the voltage
across the plates,
one can measure the energy of
the immediate electrons this way.
So what's very important is that if we
rely on the classical theory of light,
which views it as an electromagnetic wave
of this sort, here's an expression for
the electromagnetic wave, which we will
see actually pretty often in this course.
So the classical theory
would clearly predict,
and this is very important,
that increasing the intensity of the light
should lead to more
energetic photoelectrons.
So the more intense the light,
the higher the voltage that
the electrons would be able to overcome.
Also the classical theory would
predict that intense light of
any frequency should be able to kick
some electrons off of the metal plate.
So these are very clear cut predictions,
and
there was no way around them and
the framework of classical physics.
However, this was not all what Lenard
observed actually in his experiment.
As a matter of fact, his experiment
observed exactly the opposite.
So first of all the energy of the emitted
electrons didn't depend at all on
the intensity of the light,
which he was in sharp contradiction
with the classical physics.
And also very importantly,
no photoelectrons were produced if
the frequency was smaller than
a certain critical value.
So the frequency of the light was
smaller than some omega critical,
there was nothing.
No effect whatsoever, the electrons
didn't reach the right plate.
And so
this was a major mystery at the time, and
got actually Albert Einstein
thinking about it.
So it's probably not very surprising
that this mystery attracted Einstein's
attention, as he was obviously thinking
about the properties of light at the time,
as we know.
So, three years after Lenard's
paper in the year of 1905,
which is often called the miracle year,
because in 1905 Einstein wrote
four amazing papers that have completely
redefined the foundations of physics.
And one of these papers is this paper
that we're now discussing concerning
an heuristic point of view toward
the emission and transformation of light.
So in this paper, Einstein basically
introduced the notion of a photon,
which resolved the mystery
of Lenard's experiment.
So here I have a long quote
from Einstein's paper.
These are Einstein's words in the paper.
So let me read it.
The usual conception that the energy of
light is continuously distributed over
the space through which it
propagates encounters very
serious difficulties when one attempts
to explain the photoelectric phenomena.
As has been pointed out in
Herr Lenard's pioneering paper,
the one we discussed
in the previous slide.
And then he goes on to the main
concept of the photon.
So according to the concept that the
incident light consists of energy quanta,
however one can conceive of
the ejection of electrons by
light in the following way.
Energy quanta penetrate into the surface
layer of the body, and their
energy's transformed, at least in part
into kinetic energy of electrons, etc.
Notice that Einstein didn't really
call his proposal a theory,
but rather an heuristic point of a view,
which it was.
It was more a quantitative picture, but
a very important one because it introduced
the notion of photon, a particle of
light carrying a quantized energy.
And so here is, I show a little animation
which illustrates sort of Einstein's
view of what might be happening
in the photoelectric effect.
In this picture, we have this particle.
So let me play it once again.
We have these particles which
essentially represent light, and
each particle of light, each photon,
interacts individually with electrons.
And therefore, only if the energy of a
single photon exceeds a certain threshold,
photoelectric effect would occur.
And also, this picture explained
why the effect was not dependent on
the intensity of light, or in other words,
on the number of photons heating
this surface for a unit of time.
So another important element of the theory
was the assumption that the frequency
of the light, lambda here,
was proportional to the energy.
And the coefficient of proportionality
become the energy, and
omega we now know is a blank constant.
So there's actually going to be
two notations for Planck constant.
We use h and h bar.
So h bar we're going to use
a little more often, and
the relation between them is just
this numerical factor of 2 pi.
So in this picture,
basically it was clear why
the frequency of the light was the key.
So the frequency of the light was related
one to one to the energy of these photons,
and electrons would either be able
to overcome the voltage here or
not, depending on whether or
not the frequency was high enough.
And this essentially resolved the mystery
behind the photoelectric effect.
So an interesting comment here is that
Einstein received his 1921 Nobel Prize in
physics mostly for
his work on the photoelectric effect.
Here is actually a citation for
the Nobel Prize.
Actually, I think it's fair to say that
for as important as this insight turned
out to be, the theory of photoelectric
effect, his other achievements
in developing special and general
relativity are even more impressive.
So finally,
let me mention here that ironically,
Einstein being one of the pioneers
of quantum theory, actually remained
skeptical of quantum mechanics throughout
his life and never fully accepted it.