Now we're going to rely on
wave particle duality to use
the form of the main equation of quantum
physics, the Schrödinger equation.
But before going into this main part,
let me ask the following question,
which picture is more fundamental?
The particle based picture,
or the wave based picture?
So here I have an example of what
we usually mean by particle.
In this case, here's a baseball, and
this is an object which has a well defined
velocity and position at any given time.
We can identify it's position simply just
by looking at it and measure its velocity.
In contrast,
when we're talking about waves,
it doesn't really make sense to ask
the question where the wave is located.
So here in this example,
I'm showing the wave which is
generated using a rope and just by
looking at it you realize that there
is no well-defined position of a wave.
However, what we can do, we can define
the wave velocity and wave vector,
and also we can describe a wave
using this mathematical expression.
So in this expression,
u is the displacement.
So in this particular example,
u is the vertical displacement which is
a function of the coordinate and time.
And the x coordinate is
this horizontal direction.
And for a simple sinusoidal wave, this is
a kind of expression we're going to get.
Now, the relation between the wavelength
and the wave vector is lambda,
the wavelength,
is equal to 2 pi over the wave vector key.
And the relation between the frequency,
omega, and
the velocity of the wave, so the velocity
is essentially the coefficient of
proportionality between omega and
the wave vector key.
There are actually two types of
commonly used expressions to describe
a simple sinusoidal wave such as this one.
So the one I just described and
also the one using this
exponential of a complex argument.
So i here is the square root of minus one.
And they are equivalent to one another.
So here, the balance is established
by simply remembering that
exponential of i times some
real constant let's say x,
is equal to cosine of x, plus i sine of x.
So this is, this equivalence in
this case is simply an identity.
In the future we mostly will be dealing
with this description of a wave,
in terms of the exponential
of a complex number, and
often times, we're not going to
actually see this imaginary part.
The real part, we're simply
going to be describing a plane wave
in terms of this exponential.
So don't be surprised to see that.
Now going back to the question about which
feature is more fundamental, particles or
waves.
I'm going to make
a statement that the latter,
the waves are more
fundamental than particles.
Because we cannot represent
the wave in terms of a particle but
we certainly can represent
a particle in terms of waves and
this representation in the mathematical
language is called Fourier transform.
So Fourier transform, so
here is a generic mathematical
example of a Fourier transform for
some arbitrary function f(x).
And in this case, so
this ace of k represents so
called free harmonics or
amplitudes of this function f of x and
this guy's for ikx, in some sense,
responds to a snap shot of
a wave at any given time.
So by decomposing an arbitrary reasonable
function into this Fourier harmonics,
we essentially are representing
as a linear combination of waves.
In particular what we can do,
we can consider, let's say in this case,
function f(x) which has a very sharp
peak with some spread-out narrow width
around this location, let's say delta x.
And so if this is our f(x), so
we can represent this f(x)
in terms of these waves.
And this would be a decomposition of
a particle like amplitude in the waves.
Now going back to quantum mechanics
we can resolve a dilemma that was
presented by the experiments which
revealed wave particle duality.
The dilemma being of how we want to
describe our quantum mechanical objects
either as particles or waves.
And according to the discussion in the
previous slides, it seems reasonable to
try describe quantum mechanical objects
in a more general form as waves.
And what I have in mind here are the
experiments of the type by Davidson and
Germer who saw that electrons when
being reflected from a crystalline
structure, they exhibit interference
like patterns just like light would do.
If we wanted to describe
interference of light,
we actually know how to do it because we
know how to solve Maxwell's equations.
So the solution of Maxwell's
equations in vacuum
are called electro magnetic waves and in
the case of free electro-magnetic wave we
would simply have written a plane wave
just like in the previous slide, and so
this indeed would describe the data
in terms of interference of light.
Now, having in mind these experiments,
we established sort of
one to one correspondence between
the interference of light and
interference of quantum electrons.
We are forced to write a plane wave
to describe these quantum electrons.
So we're going to write, let's say for
electron, free electron
moving in the x direction,
we're going to write this exponential
to the power i kx minus omega t.
But without the left-hand side or
right-hand side, this is not
a legitimate mathematical expression.
To make it such, we introduce
essentially new mathematical object,
the wave function psi (xt).
And we, in some sense,
postulate that free electrons,
I describe by this plane wave with some
coefficient it's not very important.
Now, and k is the wave vector for
an electron and
wt is the frequency of the electron.
Now, to relate k and
omega to more familiar
physical properties such as momentum and
energy,
recall the Duvall relations between them,
between p and k and omega and energy.
And those relations are the full lengths,
so
p is equal to the plane
constant h bar times k and
energy is equal to h bar times w.
So, we may as well try this
wave function for the electron
with now with momentum p as some
coefficient e to the power i over h bar
p times x minus energy times t.
So we sort of postulated a solution
to our quantum mechanical problem but
we don't have a problem yet
we don't have a fundamental equation
that our wave functions electronic
wave functions are going to satisfy.
So in order to figure out this equation we
can recall the following simple equation,
namely the equation for the energy,
the kinetic energy of a free particle, and
as most of you know, this kinetic
energy is equal to m v squared over 2.
Or if we want to write
it in terms of momentum,
momentum is mass times velocity so
we can write it as p squared over 2m.
And now comes the main
trick in figuring out or
guessing measure to c fundamental
equation of quantum physics.
So first of all, we're going to
demand that whatever equation we're
going to guess must give this
plane wave as its solution.
And also we're going to demand that the
energy which appears in this plane wave
must be related to momentum
after this relation.
Basically, you must enforce that
free electrons indeed have so
called free particle dispersion or
free particle spectrum.
mv squared over 2 or p squared over 2m.
So this also must be satisfied.
Well, a reasonable naive guess, and it
turns out to be incorrect let me just say,
would be to assume that the electron
wave function satisfies
the usual wave equation.
So let's say in the one-dimensional
case we would write
simply (d2) over (dx) squared minus
one over the velocity of our wave,
(d2) over (dt) squared, psi equals to 0.
Now, if we plug either of these
expressions in this equation and
you can check it as an exercise,
we're going to get the familiar relation
between the frequency and the wave vector
that I wrote in the previous slide or
the analogous expression for
the energy and momentum.
But, it would work actually for
electromagnetic waves.
It would work for photons which
are quantum electromagnetic waves.
But, it does not manifestly work for
electrons because this
linear relations between the energy and
momentum is not the kind
of relation we are looking for, so,
we must construct some other equation.
And the simplest such
equation can be constructed,
let me just erase this part here.
So the simplest such
equation can be constructed
if we notice that the derivative,
if we apply let's say the time derivative
to this plane wave wave function side.
It's going to give us
the same wave function but
multiplied with minus i over
h bar times E, times psi.
So this is essentially the result of
the action of this time derivative and
for the spatial derivative,
we're going to get plus
i over h bar p times psi.
So this is the action of the x derivative.
And so we find here a clear correspondence
between the energy and the derivative.
i h bar d / dt.
The momentum, in this case one-dimensional
momentum and -i h bar d / dx.
And of course, if we were to have
a three-dimensional momentum,
momentum vector, we would need to write,
-i h bar gradient.
Let me write it like this.
So this is called radiant,
which is if we have a function,
let's say f is by definition df / dx.
The unit vector in the x direction,
df over dy.
The unit vector in the y direction plus df
over dz, unit vector in the z direction.
So, if we want to enforce the constraint
that the energy of the particle,
E, is equal to p squared over 2m.
So we sort of forced
to construct the simplest equation that
would do it in the following form.
So, let's say in the left hand side
we're going to write our energy and
E i h bar d over dt acting
on the wave function side,
and in the right-hand side we're going to
write this so-called momentum operator.
Let me put the hat here.
P squared over 2 m.
Also acting on psi.
Now if we write it explicitly as
a mathematical differential equation, i h
bar d over dt,
p squared over 2m will follow from here.
So i squared gives us minus one,
h squared is h squared and
this gradient squared is called LaPlacian.
So it's just the usual notation for
this LaPlacian is either these gradient
squared explicitly or this triangle.
So moving this p squared over 2 m to
the left hand side I can write it as
plus h squared, the LaPlacian divided
by two m and this whole thing acts on
the wave function which in the three
dimensional case is a function of the
three dimensional position r and times t.
And this equation is the free
Schroedinger equation
which we sort of derived, but of course
we should use the word derived in quotes
because there is no way we can derive
a fundamental law of physics and
Schroedinger equation is
an example of such a law.
So our derivation is nothing but a guess,
but it's a very convenient guess.
Because it allows us to
generalize this equation
to a very important class of problems.
Namely to the problems where
the electrons are not free electrons but
move in the presence of a potential.
So to see how this happens let me
sort of identify the right-hand
side of this equation in this
form with an energy operator,
which in quantum mechanics
is called Hamiltonian.
So this operator H hat is a very
important object in quantum mechanics,
let me actually write it, Hamiltonian.
And in the case of the free particle,
it is simply this kinetic energy,
but, it's very natural to generalize it
to the case of an interacting particle or
particle in the potential in which
case I will write p squared over 2m,
the kinetic energy,
plus the potential energy V of r.
And if I do so, and
if I write the resulting equation
as i h bar d psi over dt
on the left hand side and
in the right hand side this h hat psi.
So this actually becomes
the fundamental equation of quantum
physics that actually appears
on the logo of our course, and
which quite amazingly contains just
about all of non-relativistic,
well, single particle physics and
it can be generalized also to
describe many particle physics.
So, the theory of Methos, the super
conductors, pretty much everything we can
imagine that doesn't involve relativistic
effects, is contained in this equation.