Hi everybody.
A physics ninja here what we're gonna do in this section over here is what I've done is I recently gave
a final exam to my students in my introductory physics class at the college that I teach so that the
exam was covered a lot of topics but three of the questions dealt with material in this class.
So I don't want to do now is kind of let you give those problems a try.
And then you can look at the video solutions but let's just look at them together.
OK I see if they make sense to you.
First problem I gave them was this 1 3 1 gram spheres of small balls.
What we're going to do is we're going to release them from rest and they're allowed to move away from
each other.
First of all if you look at them they all have the same amount of charge and they're all positively
charged with 10 nano columns.
They're separated at initially with 1 centimeter separation and they want to know the first one what
is the speed of each sphere when they're far apart.
Now there's three of them.
So you've got to think about what's going to happen in this problem and the next one is find the acceleration
of only one of those charge when it's a certain distance after move 30 centimetres.
Okay so that's kind of a nice electrostatic problem dealing with point charges dealing with energy dealing
with forces.
Okay.
So give that problem a try again the PD f for this.
These three questions is attached to this video.
Let's scroll down a bit.
The second question was a capacitor question and I had this network of capacitors looks rather complicated.
We have five capacitors in what I have it are connected to a 10 volt battery.
What I want to do now is what is the potential VAB now.
If you look at the diagram the point is here the point B is here.
So what would be the voltage across one capacitor.
In this case at the 5 micro Feride capacitor how would you find just that voltage the voltage across
the battery is 10.
But it's not gonna be 10 across that one.
All right.
How would you solve that problem.
And the last one is probably the easiest problem from my exam is we consider a 3D point charges that
are spread out on this two dimensional grid.
I've given you the magnitude of all of these three charges.
OK.
Some of them are positive.
Two of them are negative and they want to say which first question is which are the following vectors
represents the direction of the force on the charge.
Q 3 so we're really looking at this charge.
What's the best one that describes the direction of the force.
If it's interacting with those two other point charges the second part is pretty straightforward.
Let's calculate how big that force is what is the magnitude of that vector of the force acting on Q3.
All right.
So 3 kind of problems.
They're not super short but given the try.
See if you can apply what you learned in order to get to the final answer.
Watch the video see if you've got a right.