All right.
So what I first do is consider this arrangement.
Our first question here says Let's try to find the speed when there are very very far away of each one.
So let's imagine what's going to happen over.
So three positive spheres.
Imagine we were just looking at this one so there'd be a force here between Q2 and Q3.
There's also be a force between Q1 and Q3.
Right.
So cue 3 is going to move to the right.
So after a long period of time this is going to be Q3 here.
It's going to be really really far away.
What about on Q1.
Q1 is kind of the exact opposite.
There is a repulsive force between Q1 and Q3.
So maybe draw a vector like this.
And there's also a repulsive force between Q3 and Q1.
I would move that way.
So after a long period of time I don't know how long but it would kind of be really really far away.
This would be Q1.
Ah what about the middle one what happens.
Well there's an interaction between Q2 and Q3 just draw like this.
And then there's also an interaction like this.
So what's going to happen to Q2.
All the charges are 10 nano Coolum.
So these forces are the same.
So what's going to happen to that charge.
This is the really key to this problem.
This one will remain stationary.
OK.
Because again these move out at the same rate Q1 and Q3 but Q2 will remain at the same position.
All right.
Now a little tip if they're asking you to solve for this speed right here.
OK.
The speed is a scalar quantity it's usually best to try to use energy in order to solve that.
So when you read a question they say speed.
The first thing that comes to mind is a scalar Maybe I use an energy method or conservation of energy
to solve this problem.
So what type of energy is involved.
Well again let's not worry about the forces for now we kind of argued what's going to happen to each
one but this is how I would kind of do it right.
Initially what we have is some potential energy we have some potential energy here let's call it you
want to we have some potential energy here between both of those this would be say two and three and
then we also have some potential energy between Q1 and Q3.
So there's really three terms to the potential energy.
So and initially they're stationary.
So initially the kinetic energy of the total system initially has to be equal to zero.
Nothing is moving.
So what happens when they're far away.
Again this guy here is moving like this at some speed.
This guy here is gonna be moving like this at some speed.
And this guy's gonna be zero.
So my final condition here is that you're going to have a whole bunch of
kinetic energy and you're gonna have very little potential energy.
So we're gonna set this up using conservation of energy and then we're gonna solve for the speeds.
Okay.
So let's kind of go to a fresh page and write down our expressions for the total potential energy the
total kinetic energy.
All right and see how it changes from potential to kinetic in the system.
All right.
So this is kind of what it looks like.
This is how I would write it.
So I'll do kind of initial over here.
What is the total energy initial.
So again we have all of these different potential energy terms
and initially I'll just write it like this.
Initial of the system.
But again I'm an across that out because this here has to be equal to zero.
Nothing's moving.
All right.
That has to be equal to.
Again what is the energy when it's out here.
Well so you have to kind of think about is there any potential energy when these charges are very very
far apart.
For that you have to remember what the formula for potential energy between two charges it's always
going to be the charge a charge B and divided by the distance.
This is the equation for the potential energy between two charges a and b.
OK.
Again if the distance is very very far away there's not going to be any potential energy.
So kind of you final of the system.
I'll just write it like this
this guy here has to be equal to zero because they're very very far away.
So at the end all we're left with is the final kinetic energy.
So how did we write the final kinetic energy.
Well we have this charge that's moving so it's going to have one half mass m they're all the same mass
I could just write it as M and V squared plus one half.
Again this term for charged Q3 V squared notice I have the same speed here and again I'm going to have
the same speed because they're identical charges they were released from ress and I have the same forces
acting on each one but the forces are in the different direction.
So at the end this final energy right here on this side of the equation is simply C add one half to
one half.
You're going to get M V squared and that's it.
All right.
So now we have to work over here on these three terms.
Let's work on these three terms right here.
Let's kind of write them out separately.
OK.
What you can do is this is the initial POTENTIAL ENERGY OF so let's do this one first one too what does
that term look like.
What's going to be my constant k.
It's going to be the charge Q1.
The charge Q2 and divided by what is the distance I'm going to call one centimeter the distance are
again I'll convert that into meters when I substituted over here.
All right.
What other term do I have.
I've got the interaction between 2 and 3.
Notice that one's going to be the same because I have the same charges as 1 and 2.
And I also have the same separation.
So really those two terms are going to be the same.
And what about the last one.
Now I have at the interaction between 1 and 3 between 1 and 3 this is what I have I'm going to have
k q one Q three this time and divided by what's the distance.
Now if r is 1 centimeters of the initial distance here is going to be 2 centimeters.
All right.
Let me just kind of get rid of this two centimeters.
So that's actually two are because I've called R is equal to one centimeter.
All right.
So now we've got to put it all together this is pretty straightforward.
The total term here that I've highlighted in the blue simply looks like this.
So there's two of those terms.
So two of these terms I would write it as two K Q1 Q2 divided by R and then plus this potential energy
k q one Q three divided by two are in all of this has to be equal to the final kinetic energy of the
system.
Again the two halves ended up can't adding up to give me one in the front.
So let's scroll down here.
Let's keep moving.
All right.
So this is simply a fraction over here I could kind of combine some of the terms remember all the charges
are the same.
So I can really factor that out.
So you simply have K Q squared because Q1 Q2 and Q3 are all the same.
Then they open up a bracket.
I would be left with two over par for the first term.
Right.
This and this.
And plus one over two are in this case.
Again I kind of prefer to do the problem algebraic Lee again if I want to put things on a common denominator
the common denominator is two are.
So I would do this is to this you would turn into a four.
All right now you could see I can add those pretty straightforward.
It becomes five over two are guy.
So we have five K Q squared over to r equals M B squared.
All right let's go over here.
I'll write down the expression for V squared and then I'm going to substitute in all the values.
So I have five over to K Q squared and divided by now.
Again I'm gonna have the M HERE I HAVE TO BRING THE M at the bottom are m all right so let's substitute
in all our values I made that kind of large so 5 and 2 that stays the same our constant K is nine times
10 to the nine.
Now the charges were 10 nano Coolum.
That's 10 times ten to the negative nine and you have to square every.
Don't forget.
Now make sure everything is in the proper units so the distance are was we define it as one centimeter.
So this is going to be zero point zero one meters and then the mass.
We kind of go back up to the question here.
The mass here was one gram.
All right so one gram would be zero point zero zero one kg.
All right.
So now you've got a plug in this whole thing into the calculator so let me go ahead and do that nine.
Let's go.
5 1/2 is 2.5 times 9.
Each of the nine times ten either than negative nine squared and now divided by all those terms and
I have to also divide by the mass at the end.
Don't forget to take the square root of all of those terms.
All right.
And I do that and I get a number that is approximately zero point for seven meters per second.
OK.
So that is the first part of this problem.
That would be the speed of each one of those again.
This is only four charges 1 and 3 the charge 2 is speed of 2 would have to be 0 meters per second.
OK.
Because we said the force's balance for that one.
All right.
Part B says fine the acceleration of this charge after it moved a distance of 30 centimetres.
OK.
So and it's only the charge Q1 and again acceleration.
So again this word is a vector accelerations of vector so it would probably use forces probably the
easiest way to find it.
OK.
And I've sketched it out here so it started over here Q1 and then it moved 30 centimeters.
But again at the same time Q3 moved 30 centimeters.
So if you were going to do a free body diagram on Q1.
All right.
This is Q1 there's gonna be an interaction with Q2.
Right.
So there's gonna be a force acting on it.
This will be the force of Q2 on Q1.
What else.
There should be another force there should be an interaction between Q3 and Q1.
Now this force is going to be a little bit smaller because it's far away.
This is Q3.
I'll just call it three on one like this.
So we have two forces there in the same direction.
So they're going to add as vectors.
So what I want to do is I really want to find the net force acting on Q1.
For that I have to add both of those and I'm going to add them both as vectors.
So at the end my net force has to be a vector like this.
So let's add them both up.
So this would simply be f of two on one plus F of three on one.
Again this one's expected to be smaller but let's calculate it anyway just because the distance is going
to be so much bigger.
All right.
So how would we substitute this.
So this would be again using cool Ohm's law for this one.
Again all of these terms are the same so Q2 Q1 this is the same charge.
Now what is the distance now between Q2 and Q1.
I said Q1 move 30 centimeters.
That means it's going to be a distance of 31 centimeters.
So right here right away I'm just going to substitute this 31 squared.
I wrote it in meters right here plus K. Q3 Q1 now what is this distance.
Well it's simply going to be double that distance right.
If you have a look at it if this is 31 that means this other one is going to be 31.
So this is simply going to be all right 62 centimeters away and you have to square that term.
All right.
So at the end we got a substitute in all our numbers and get one final answer.
So let's go ahead and keep chugging along.
Here let me substitute in all the values I'm going to factor out the top term because it's the same
so K Q squared and then this term here simply becomes thirty one plus one over zero point sixty two
squared.
All right and then I got to substitute the values.
So this is nine times 10 of the nine for my k constant Q again was 10 nano Coolum ten times ten of the
negative nine.
Oh don't forget to square that term and then multiply by this whole term here zero point thirty one
squared plus one over zero point sixty two squared.
All right the last thing we have to do then define the total force and again once you know the net force
you should be able to find the acceleration because it's the mass of that charge multiplied by the acceleration.
All right and the mass I know is one gram.
So again we're going to have one last step at the end to get the acceleration really all I have to do
is divide this whole thing by the mass.
All right.
So let's go ahead and write down my final expression.
So nine times ten to the nine 10 nano columns time to tend to the negative nine squared term in the
bracket.
Zero point thirty one kind of lengthy isn't it but it's lengthy but it's doable.
And now don't forget I have to divide by the mass if what I'm looking for is the acceleration and the
mass of that charge was 1 grams I would write it like this.
All right.
So now you gotta plug everything in the calculator.
I'll let you do that.
And at the end this is what you should get.
All right assuming I did things correctly I get that this term here in the brackets should be approximately
13.
So then I want to multiply that by nine either the nine.
Multiply that by my ten nano columns ten either the negative nine squared equals and last term is divided
by zero point zero zero one.
Ha.
My final answer I promise is the final answer is zero point zero kind of 1 2 and this would be in meters
per second squared.
All right so that would be the acceleration of that one charge.
Yeah not bad.