All right.
Problem two is A CAPACITOR PROBLEM.
So again we want to know the potential difference between those two points.
And again if this is the kind of combinations of capacitors and parallel and some in series.
But if this is a and b again a can move anywhere here.
This is also point A and B it's going to be the same potential difference across the five versus across
both of those in Part B we want to know what is the total energy stored in all capacitors.
So that one's actually a little bit easier to do I think because what you can do is just replace the
entire network by an equivalent capacitor.
So let's kind of start by simplifying this a little bit.
All right.
So I'm going to take everything here let's take these both of those and combine them and form one equivalent
capacitor C equivalent one.
So these are in series.
All right.
If I have two of them that are in series if you remember the formula and series it was like this C equivalent
one would be one over two I'll just write it in micro Faraday that's fine.
My final answer will be a micro Farad.
So this is one.
So that means that C equivalent one in that blue box is equivalent to one micro Feride capacitor OK.
Now what do I have.
Well can I simplify this any further.
What if I do this.
What if I combine the blue box with the five that's out here.
What we have here now I'm going to call this C equivalent to this are in parallel.
Right.
So if they're in parallel it's very easy All you have to do is add them up.
So make sure you understand this part C equivalent to is equal to C equivalent one which is in parallel
with this 5 micro add capacitor.
Again everything here is in micro fair and so you get one plus five.
So everything in my red dash box is simply equal to six micro Fred C equivalent to.
All right what I'm going to do now is I'm going to redraw this circuit for a second.
So let me just redraw this battery and now all I have I'm going to have a one micro Feride what happens
to everything over here.
Again I've just replaced that by an equivalent six micro Feride capacitor.
So this is six micro Feride.
This here is one micro Fair at and at the bottom I still have my three I haven't touched that.
So is there a way to replace these three into one.
Again what we have here are three capacitors that are forgot the drop capacitor that are in series.
So the final step is really one divided by C total is going to be equal to one over one plus one over
three plus one over six.
Right that is the rule for combining these three.
And if I do that what I'm left with at the end is a 10 volt battery
with just one single capacitor and the value of that total capacitance right here is going to be C total.
All right so I've got to do a bit of math over here what I would do is maybe put things on a common
denominator so let's maybe choose six so one over one would be six over six.
And this guy here would be two over six.
So this is easy to combine.
I just add up all of these I get nine to nine over six which is kind of the same thing as three over
two.
Again at the end no I got to flip it around because this is one divided by C total.
So my total capacitance at the end would be two thirds.
And this here is in my girlfriends.
Don't forget.
So this is the equivalent capacitance of the entire network.
All right.
Let me just kind of draw an arrow right here.
So let's kind of start with B and then we'll work back to a it really doesn't matter but I kind of like
this approach a little bit.
So what is the total energy stored in a capacitor.
Well if you remember the total energy stored if I only have this simple circuit over here the potential
energy stored I can write it as 1 1/2 Q V.
There's three different ways of writing this Formula One way it was like this CV squared.
I know the value of c I know the value of V has to be ten.
This is probably the best way of doing it.
All right.
So the potential energy so for Part B I would write the potential energy is 1 1/2 C total and V squared.
You don't have to find the energy stored in each capacitor that would be a little bit more work.
I'd have to find the capacitance of each one and the voltage across each one.
All right.
But right now this is it.
Now again I want to get a number in jewel so this is going to be two thirds two thirds zero point six
six times 10 to the negative six because it's in micro Fred and then multiplied by right here 10.
And I have to square it.
All right.
So you're going to get 100 here 100 times this will take two exponents away so this will be times 10
to the negative four.
And it will be zero point three three times 10 to the negative four that will be measured in Joules.
All right.
So that is that part.
So now let's go back and find the voltage here between points A and B how do we do that now.
Well again I think it's kind of useful to use one of these intermediate steps.
We first started by finding the blue value which was one micro Feride.
However the voltage A and B is going to be the same across both of those we said.
It's also going to be the same voltage across the equivalent capacitor of this network.
So A and B is really right here.
All right.
Make sure you understand that part because we've combined everything here therefore the potential that
we're looking for is really what would be the electrical potential across an equivalent six microfiber
add capacitor.
So for this simplified circuit here we have three capacitors in series if they are in series remember
that the charge is the same on each plate
and that is really the important thing.
So if you know the charge on the one micro Feride capacitor I would read it like this.
Q One is equal to well one micro Feride.
Let's just call it C one multiplied by the voltage across that well let's call it V 1.
What else the charge on the six micro Feride capacitor has to be the same.
This here would have to be the capacitance C6 6 micro faired capacitor in the voltage across the voltage
across is really what I'm trying to find here.
This is really VAB and it has to be the same thing the same charge on the three micro Feride capacitor.
So it's the value of the capacitance multiplied by the voltage across the three micro Farad capacitor
All right.
So that gives us relationships here between these voltages right.
For example the voltage V1 is you simply related to the voltage a B so use the first two part.
So it'd be C6 that's 6 micro Feride capacitor.
And here I have to divide by 1.
Okay so the voltage v 1 is 6 times VAB.
So that's kind of a useful relationship.
Oh how else.
What about V3.
The voltage across the three micro Feride capacitor.
Again if I just use the last two parts here I could write an expression and related to the voltage across
the six.
So that's what it would look like.
It would be C6 which is 6 divided by three and the voltage a B.
So this here would simply be 2 2 times the voltage across a B all right.
And the last thing we do now is we simply do a loop rule.
If you do a complete loop the voltages must sum to zero.
So you have ten here you're going to have a voltage drop a voltage drop and another voltage drop.
And this is what it looks like here.
So the final expression here if I do a loop again this is the circuit.
We have ten.
First thing we encounter is that one micro add six and three
all right use cure coughs voltage law magic.
I was going to start right here at this point and I do a complete loop around.
First thing I would do is I would get a increase of voltage of 10 volts when I cross the battery.
And then I would get a voltage drop across here we're gonna gonna call that v 1.
Gonna get a voltage drop across the six micro Feride capacitor actually instead of V six where we've
been calling that VAB.
That's what I'm trying to find.
And mine is v 3 and that there has to be equal to zero.
All right we want to solve for VAB so the next thing you want to do is just use my two relationships
here that I found to get rid of both of those unknowns.
So that's what you have ten minus.
This here is going to be instead of v 1 I'm gonna write it as six times VAB
minus VAB and the last one is minus V Three V Three was two times VAB and that there has to be equal
to zero.
All right straight forward VAB is the only unknown here.
So we have ten has to be equal to six two and one that gives me nine.
All right.
And my last expression the voltage between points A and B is going to be ten over nine.
Okay.
And that is the voltage right here if this is point A and this is point B the voltage across that capacitor
the six micro Feride capacitor is ten divided by nine.
If you want to get a number for that ten divided by nine gives you like one point one 1 and that's a.