All right.
So here's problem three we have a grid with three point charges here giving you the magnitude the grid
is one centimeter by one centimeter.
So that means that this is three centimeters apart and those are two centimeters apart.
And what else.
So which of the following vectors we have five choices here best illustrates the direction of the total
force on charge q three.
All right.
So here's charge q three how would be the force on charge.
Q3 charge Q3 is positive and let's look at the different interactions.
So we have interaction between Q2 and Q3 Q2 is negative.
So that means on this one Q3 would be attracted to this one.
I'm going to call this f 2 3.
What else do we have.
Q3 is also attracted to Q1 because Q1 is negative.
So that would produce a force like this I'm going to call that f 1 3.
Now if you would add both of those as vectors again if you'd add both of them as vectors you'd have
to kind of go something like this.
And then at the end the resulting vector would be this one this one here would be the total force on
charge 3.
Let's just write it as F 3 total.
That would be kind of the general direction I would depend on how big each one of those.
But the only one that kind of has that angle over here is kind of figure B.
Mean scroll down a little bit.
The last one says Just calculate how big this forces right.
What is the magnitude of this.
Well if you think about it for just a second so let me go kind of go back up if we know the magnitude
of each of these components we should be able to find the total.
Right.
Because that's just Pythagorean.
So F 3 total again would simply be Pythagorean theorem.
All right.
You find the magnitude of each one of those.
So it'd be f one three squared plus F two three squared.
So we have to find both of those.
So let's start by finding both of those terms.
So what is f 1 3 as a magnitude.
Again it's k q one.
Q 3 and what is the distance now between 1 and 3.
What's this distance here which is 2 centimeters so zero point zero two And don't forget the square
that's cool Ohm's Law.
All right.
So let me.
Again I'm not going to worry about the positives and negatives for these charges because they only tell
me the magnitude.
So we have nine times 10 to the nine q 1 The magnitude is 1 nano Coolum 1 times ten to the negative
nine.
Q Three is for nano Coolum and all of this gets divided by that distance squared.
Okay so let me do that my calculator quickly here.
So this nine either the nine times one either the negative nine times for either the negative nine and
divided by that distance.
And don't forget to square that distance.
All right at the end here I get a value that is nine times ten to the negative five.
So this is a Newton's All right how about the next one.
F two three so it's gonna be similar it's gonna be k and Q2 Q3 and the distance is now different.
Right.
Because the distance is the distance between this charge and that top charge which is now three centimeters.
So this is zero point zero three squared.
Okay.
Again we've got a substitute an all the values nine times 10 to the nine.
Q2 again the magnitude is three times 10 to the negative nine.
Q3 is still four times ten to the negative nine.
And all of this gets divided by distance squared three centimeters and square that term.
All right let me do this one in the calculator nine either nine times three e of the negative nine times
for either the negative nine in all of this.
Now divided by zero point zero three squared equals.
Now this guy here I get one point two times ten to the negative four Newtons.
So actually this force is bigger although the distance is bigger the charges more than make up for it.
So at the end what you have to do now is substitute everything into the final expression.
Right.
Because we got EF 3 total.
The magnitude is all we're interested in for this part so let's do this.
So the first force we found was nine times ten to the negative five.
And I have to square that term this is just Pythagorean theorem and one point two times 10 to the negative
four and I have to square that term.
So let me do that one in the calculator in the last part here.
Either the negative five squared in all of this.
Then take the square root.
All right at the end of the day I get one point five times 10 to the negative four.
Then that is measured in Newtons and that is the length of this total force.
This problem is pretty straightforward I think.
Hopefully we're able to get that one.