Hello everyone.
Welcome back to exploring Quantum Physics,
I'm Charles Clark.
This week, we're going to look at solving
some of the practical problems of quantum
mechanics using the vehicle of the theory
of atomic structure and spectra.
We'll start with an overview
of optical spectrosopy,
it's a subject with great scientific and
technological importance.
In some sense it's responsible for
modern telecommunications infrastructure,
the knowledge that we have about
the properties of the sun and stars.
And it's one that provided really
compelling evidence, a very
deep quantitative evidence, for
the existence of quantum mechanics.
Now from the course homepage you can get
to this section, Additional Materials.
And within it you'll find a section
called, Original scientific literature.
And we will be using two of
the papers here in the homework.
Bohr model of the atom, and, The
photoelectric affect, a paper by Einstein.
You'll really need to look at these in
order to answer some of the homework
questions.
It does not require the reading of
the full paper, but I hope you will get
some enjoyment out of having read original
work by Niels Boor and Albert Einstein.
You're all familiar with
a beautiful rainbow.
An effect seen when sunlight
is scattered in a certain way.
And it seems that all the colors that we
can perceive are found within the rainbow.
Now here's an important tool for
spectroscopy.
We have white light entering
into this prism here.
And then you see output of a band
of colors running from red to blue.
This technique, this is basically what you
might call a deep multiplexing system.
The pure white light comes in and
what comes out is a spread
out mixture of colors.
This is the technique used by
Isaac Newton to demonstrate
that white light of the sun was
indeed a mixture of colors.
Because what he did was pick
off a particular color,
let's say the blue, and
put it through a second prism
to find that no further
separation of the color occurred.
So, from the modern perspective,
color is a proxy for
the wavelength or
the frequency of the light,
which are related by this characteristic,
wave equation.
The frequency of a wave motion is equal
to its speed divided by its wavelength.
Now here's a rather clever
demonstration of the inverse action of
the separation light.
This is a multiplexing effect,
where one combines a violet,
a green, and
a red light by the following way.
There's a laser, you can't really see it.
These are cylinders of water
with a hole poured into it.
And when they're illuminated
from behind the laser light is
entrained in the stream of water
that's falling into a dish.
And what you see coming out of
the dish is scattered light.
It's just a random mixture of the violet,
the green, and the red colors, so
it looks white.
So in other words,
this shows the combination of
these three different colors.
It gives apparent white light.
Now I use this illustration
in part to introduce
the three reference lasers that we'll
use for discussions during the course.
These are three commonly used laser
lights that you've seen in practice.
For example, the red laser pointer
with a wavelength of 650 nm is widely
used in lectures and presentations,
as is the green laser pointer.
The diode pumped solid state green laser
pointer with the wavelength of 532 nm.
And then the Blu-Ray laser
player utilizes a violet
laser with a wavelength of 405 nm.
These spread the range of
human vision as we'll see, and
so they provide a good set of basic tools.
If you want to remember
properties of light,
it's nice to have some specific examples.
So we'll use these the number of points
in the lectures and the homework.
Okay, now we'll just have the first and
only inline quiz of this introductory
lecture to give you some practice in
thinking about the properties of light.
So, the main message of the inline
quiz was that when you combine
two photons to produce a third,
you add the energies of the two photons
to get the energy of the third.
So that the light from
the green laser pointer is made
my combining the energy
of two infrared photons.
Now the rainbow is a very smooth
appearing object, and those colors that
you saw dispersed by the prism also
seem to form a relatively smooth band.
But about almost exactly 200 years ago,
Joseph Fraunhofer,
looking at the spectrum of
sun with high resolution,
found that it exhibited a number of rather
sharp features of a mysterious type.
And here is a modern study
of the spectrum of the sun.
The rainbow has been sort of
spread out here, and stretched, so
that you can see very narrow
regions of wavelength
where there are dark spots
in the structure of the sun.
Here are reference lasers laid out
roughly where their wavelengths lie.
And this notch here is going to be
of great interest to us later on.
So when this phenomena was discovered
it was not understood at all.
And there was no physical theory
that suggested why the smooth
light of the sun should be disrupted by so
many apparent imperfections.