Hello everyone, welcome back.
So now we're going to go and
solve the problem for
the classical motion of the hydrogen atom.
Now some of you may have done this before,
but we're going to do it in a way that
leads to some of the material that's
essential for the development of quantum
mechanics, particularly understanding
the angle momentum operator and
some other symmetry operators that
are very important in quantum theory and
give us the actual insight into
how to solve equations in general.
So to return where we left off last time,
we have these first-order
equations of motion.
Now let's try to make some progress in
solving them by isolating invariant
quantities, that is, constants of the
motions, things that don't change in time.
I mean, you know what some of these are,
for example, the total energy.
So now,
since we're given equations of motion for
these two vector quantities,
it makes sense to try to find constants of
the motion by looking at
various other products.
So here is the kinetic
energy of the system,
something of which you're familiar with.
Write it as p squared/2 mu, it's
the same as one half mu r dot squared.
And now, just as a check to see
how well you're following things,
here's a little online quiz on the actual
meaning of this T, the kinetic energy.
So I hope it's clear that
the kinetic energy is expressed here
is in the frame in which
the center of mass is at rest.
Because it just deals,
this p has to do with the motion
of the relative coordinate.
So the electron and
the nucleus together could be
moving as a million miles an hour with
respect to your frame of reference, but
it's in the frame of the center mass that
the expressions become most economical.
And then here is a,
this is actually something that happens
quite generally in any system of
particles interacting by pairwise forces.
You can see that the time derivative,
the kinetic energy,
just following the Newtonian force laws,
is minus the timed derivative
of this quantity minus the timed
derivative of the potential energy.
So, the potential energy here,
when added to the kinetic energy, gives a
constant of motion, meaning that when you
start the system with an arbitrary
configuration of the two particles,
that is the positions and the velocities
are what they are at some initial time.
Then at any later time, you then
compute the total energy in terms of
the sum of the kinetic and
potential energies.
And at any later time, that sum
adds up to exactly the same thing.
Now I'll have a quick check to see
about your understanding of this point.
So I hope it was clear that from
the construction, the potential
energy depending upon the relative
coordinate, it actually doesn't matter,
at least in non-relativistic mechanics,
whether that's in
the frame at rest or in the frame moving
with the center of mass, it's the same.
Okay, so the result of that is
we found one constant of motion,
meaning this helps reduce
the complexity of the system since that
we know that however the particles may
evolve from their initial configuration,
it's always the case that their
energy has the same value.
So they can't move all
over configuration space.
You might say that this defines a sort
of a surface in the multi-dimensional
space on which the particles
are constrained to move.
Not to belabor the point, but
why don't we have another quick check to
see how well you're following things?
So I hope the results of that last
quiz were pretty transparent.
I mean, once again,
the energy is the energy in
the frame that's fixed
on the center of mass.
Okay, so we had a process of starting
with a product of variables and
finding a sort of a conservation
law that related its time
derivatives to another
function of position.
So why not proceed systematically
on those lines and
see if there are other products that
have a fairly simple tiny dilution?
So to put it another way, this,
the kinetic energy is
proportional to p dot p.
So then there are two other scalar
products of these two vectors,
r dot r and r dot p.
And I think you will find that
there's nothing simple about the time
evolution of either of those.
So how do we proceed in
some systematic fashion?
Well there are three possible scalar
products of the vectors r and
p, and then there's one vector product.
Because r cross r as 0 as p cross p.
Now here I am assuming,
Basic knowledge, Of vector algebra.
So I mean, I hope you do understand.
If you don't understand what the vector
cross product and dot product are,
this would be a good time to pause and
take a refresher.
But the basic idea is that things
like the dot product is something
that's invariant under rotation
of all the coordinates in
the system, that's a so
called scalar on the rotation.
The vector product is sort of
the next degree of complexity.
It acts like a vector under rotation.
So, a vector, when you rotate it,
assumes a different orientation.
In general, a rotation changes
a vector into another vector.
The dot product is proportional of the
cosine of the angle between two vectors.
And if you rotate the system,
that clearly stays the same.
So here is this, Quantity, the cross
product of the position momentum.
What is its equation of motion?
Well, it's straightforward to
compute the time derivative of that,
L dot by definition is r dot
cross p + r cross p dot.
Okay, so now, what about that?
Well r dot, Is
just proportional to p, so
that means that this is equal to 0.
Now, what about the second term?
Well, p dot is proportional
to the vector r,
not as a complicated coefficient,
but in terms of the cross product,
this becomes proportional r dot r,
so also equal to 0.
So here's the second constant of motion,
the angular momentum r cross p.
So, let me say two things about this.
And that is this result
that the angular momentum
is a constant of motion is generic for
systems in which the force is
the gradient of a radial function.
There's no dependence of the force on the
relative angle between the two particles.
And the second is,
this puts a very strong constraint
on the possible motions that can occur
from given initial conditions, and we'll
review that in the next online quiz, which
is going to be the last for this part.
So I hope it was clear to you in
thinking about that, that for example,
here's the defining,
here's the definition of angular momentum.
And so
this means that r dot L is equal to 0.
Let's see, how do we see that?
Well, we know that r cross p
is perpendicular to r and p,
very simple result of vector algebra.
So that means that L, which is, we've
determined is fixed in space for all time.
So let's say at any given time,
we have a value of the position and
the value of the momentum.
From those, we determine the value
of the angular momentum just by
taking the cross product, very simple.
And then forever after, the value of
the angular momentum stays the same,
so that r is always perpendicular to L.
Well that means it lies, I mean,
if you draw, let's orient L, so
it's sort of standing up straight.
That means that r is moving in the plane
that must always be in the two dimensional
plane that's perpendicular to L and
that the same thing is true with p.
So in other words,
the conservation of angular momentum takes
us from a problem, which is sort of three
dimensional in its formulation and
reduces it to motion in two dimensions.
That's a huge reduction in complexity.
So we now know that all we have to do
is to enumerate the allowed values of
angular momentum and
then to solve the equations of motion for
the particular values of
the angle of momentum.
And that is going to pass through into
quantum mechanics in a very important way.