All right here's a three branch circuit this time kind of complicated looking right.
It's got five resistors to batteries.
So again we want to find the current everywhere.
Now I haven't given you any choices here and we also want to find the potential at all these points
given that the potential points see zero volts so that could be the grounding over here.
All right.
So first thing we want to do is we want to pick directions for the currents.
Call this I again it doesn't matter whether you're right or wrong the physics will work its way out.
So I'm going to kind of pick kind of stuff I usually do.
I go on this way I was going down to going to the right through the battery and then maybe two more
down here.
So there's another junction over here.
So some current going up here I three and then maybe some other current going down here I-4.
All right so we've got all these branches here.
We've got five different currents we have to determine.
Let's go ahead and maybe write some junction rules.
If junction at point B if at the current going in has to be equal to the current going out.
So it has to be one plus to call this equation one.
What other ones we have we have another junction down over here said I to do this one at the end.
Two has to be equal to three plus four.
All right.
There's another equation equation too.
One thing I can also do is I can simplify both of these right the three in the six Let me shade that
area a little bit here just so we know we're talking about both of those.
You can simplify it because there's two resistors that are certainly in parallel with each other.
So what you have to do is you simply multiply divided by the sum you multiply and you get 18 18 divided
by nine.
This is equivalent to a 2 ohm resistor.
Actually what I'm going to do is I'm actually going to forget about this entire part for now.
I'm just going to replace everything here by two ohm resistor between point D and point B at the and
I'll come back and solve for this.
But let's just for now just replace it with a 2 ohm and then it looks really really similar to a previous
problem I did.
All right.
Next we want to do now is we don't have enough information and we really need to write down some loop
rules.
So let's go ahead and write those.
I'm going to start at point F and I'm going to go on this interior or this loop here that's on the left
most side.
So the first thing I do is going to be equivalent three going across a battery and I'm crossing a battery
in this direction so I get plus 18 volts.
Now I'm going to get a drop right.
I get a voltage drop across that resistor which is minus 12 multiplied by the current flowing through
it.
Now I'm going to go down the center branch again I'm going to have a voltage drop given by six multiplied
by the current flowing through it.
In this case I won and then I'm going to go back to everywhere where I started to point.
So I get zero for that one.
Now the other thing I can do is I can do a big loop around the entire thing.
So let's do that.
Call this equation for and I'll have enough information at least to get started.
So first thing I have again these first two terms are going to be the same they're exactly the same
as this so it's 18 because I go over the battery across that resistor.
Now I'm at point B and next thing I do now I'm going to cross a three ohm resistor so I get a voltage
drop given by three how careful here is multiplied by different current.
I do all right now at Point C I'm going to go here and I'm going to cross a battery battery and I'm
crossing it from the lower to the higher.
So I get plus 21.
Now on that point Dean I want to get the point.
And instead of introducing kind of two new variables here I'm just going to replace this by an equivalent
resistor and now I'm going to go across it that equivalent resistor which just to say I get a voltage
drop given by two and multiplied by two and that's it.
I go back to where I started and I've done actually these three equations here allow me to solve for
I 1 and 2 because they don't really introduce 3 or 4 because they don't because that kind of simplified
it by using this equivalent resistance.
So now I can proceed and I can actually solve for these three currents here just using equation 1 3
and 4 am going to do it the exact same way I previously did.
So using equation 3 let's call it three prime.
I'm going to start by isolating and by using either one or isolating I one and writing it in terms of
the current.
So if you do that I bring that on the other side I get six times I one has to be equal to 18 minus 12
times I.
So I get that I won.
If I divide through by six I'm going to get three for that one minus two times.
All right so that's my equation 3 pry my equation for prime do a similar thing.
18 plus 21 gives me 39.
And this one three two and two I will give me five.
So I get five Aitu.
I bring that on the other side.
I'll isolate that.
Now I get thirty nine.
And what else do I have I still have the minus 12.
OK.
Now you can isolate what I two is.
Thirty nine is looks like a messy fraction.
Thirty nine over five minus 12 over five multiplied by.
OK so now I have expressions for I want an I'D to and I'm going to go back to Equation 1 and let's substitute
everything and Equation 1.
Let's call this equation 1 prime.
So you get i equals three minus two I Plus thirty nine over five minus 12 over five times.
All right the only unknown in this equation over here is the letter I.
So you just have to group all the terms together.
Bring this on the other side bring this on the other side.
So what do you end up getting in the getting I mean plus two I if I bring it on the other side and plus
12 over five I on this side here I get thirty nine over five plus three.
OK.
Now I'm going to put things on a common denominator of five.
I think that's going to help me.
So this is going to be five over five plus ten over five.
This is still 12.
And on the side too if I put everything on a common denominator of five I think that's going to help
me.
This is still 39.
If I put this over five that means I have to multiply by five.
All right.
Now this simplifies nicely what just about done.
So are about all the algebra but that's life.
All right so what do we get over here we get 15 plus 12 27 and here we get oh 54 Well that's easy.
So I simply going to be 54 divided by 27 and we've seen that before.
There's two imps.
Boy that was a lot of work to get to that answer.
But here we have two aims in this section over here.
Two aims are now part of that Currence going to go down here part of it's going to go over here.
So let's go ahead and look at that.
So look at I won I won we have an expression for Iowa and it's three minus two times.
The letter I wrote two times two.
What happens here if three minus four minus one.
What does that mean is the first time we've seen this in this group.
So remember whenever you end up getting a negative sign.
The only thing it tells me is that my initial guess was wrong.
Instead of having a current flowing down in that branch really what we have is a current flowing up
in that branch.
OK.
So switch the direction.
And now you're going to find that one is actually here.
So it's one app and it's flowing up so that they'll be scared by this.
OK so just be a little bit careful with that one.
I too on the other hand too we have our expression down over here.
This looks like it's a bit of a mess.
But let's try it out.
Thirty nine over five minus.
This will be 24 over five.
Oh that looks like 15 over five which gives me three.
All right.
So does that make sense.
Says this guy here's three.
Here we have one going in.
We have two going in.
Oh yeah.
You have to have three going that way.
Perfect.
All right so now we've got three going into the junction.
Now how do we solve for the two currents down over here.
Three and Four.
Let's go ahead maybe do that over here in the box.
So we've already got one equation that relates both of those.
What else can I do while I can do.
You know that the voltage across each one has to be the same.
Or you can do a little loop rule right around here if you want to.
Let's do that let's go around counter-clockwise around this small loop.
What does that look like well when you cross a resistor like this I get a voltage drop given by three
times three and then I'm going to go cross a six ohm resistor but I'm crossing it in the opposite direction
of the current.
So I get a voltage gain of six times I4 then I go back to where I start.
And I get zero.
Maybe I can simplify this a little bit.
So what would you get used.
Right I three must be equal to two I4 from this equation and then can go ahead and substitute that over
here.
And what do you get.
Because you know what I do is we solved I tune the previous problem we said it was three amps.
So now what do you get I three wants do that.
So you get to I4 plus I4 gives me three.
So what is I forgive you for then must be equal to 1.
And I've got three going in.
I've got one going downstairs.
How many do I have over here.
I have to have two.
This here has to be two minutes and you're going to get that just for manipulating these two equations
a junction rule.
And also my basically my loop rule just rearranged.
You could solve for those two unknowns.
This is what you'll find.
All right.
Pretty good so far.
Now all we have to do is look at all the voltages.
Now we've solved all the currents.
Let's look at all the voltages except they're telling us that this voltage up here is equal to zero.
Well that's pretty easy.
So let's go around now.
Let's go around the loop here and write down all these voltages everywhere.
So if I go to D.
Well that should be 21 volts above point C right.
So VD should be 21 volts
BD.
OK.
Now what else oh how can I get the Wii.
Well there's a couple different paths I can do now right.
How do I get over here across.
I can either go through the three Omaar I can go through the six it doesn't matter which one I do.
Both of these are in parallel there's the same voltage drop across each one.
So let's just go down here through the six.
So I get to get a voltage drop equal to six multiplied by the current going through it.
That's six six volts across this one and I'm at 21 and if I go down six volts that means that the voltage
right over here has to be 15 volts.
How about now if I go to point f Why do I cross any resistors here.
If I don't then there's no voltage drop across anything here.
So that means at this point here should also be at 15 volts.
All right.
How do I work my way today.
Well if I work my way to a I get 15 here and then what do I do I gain how many I gain 18.
So that means that the voltage over here up Point A has to be 15 plus 18.
It gives me 33.
All right what else can I do on how I can go through the 12 ohm resistor right.
If I go through the 12 Omers this there are a lot of different ways to get to be.
I can either go over here I can go from E to be I can go from C to be it doesn't matter.
Actually it's pretty easy even just to go from C to be because you know there's a voltage drop here
and the voltage drop across this three ohm resistor is the value of the resistance multiplied by the
current.
So that gives me nine.
So that means that this point here should be at 9 volts because I know that I have to drop down 9 volts
if I'm going to be at zero over here.
Point C.
All right.
So actually determining the voltages around it's pretty straightforward especially if they give you
a starting point.
Once you know the currents and you know the values of everything the voltages of the batteries you know
the values of currents everywhere.
You know the resistor is everywhere or you can easily calculate what the voltage gains are the drops
are at every point in the circuit.
So it's pretty easy to fill out the rest of the blanks.
Hopefully you understand this by now.
This should be starting to get a little bit easier for you.