All right here's our first problem here that kind of involves a whole series of questions related to
kind of a full circuit which involves parallel and series combinations.
So the first question is well first it says that the switch one is open.
So there's going to be no current up here and then switch to is close so let me go ahead and draw wire
here that connects both of those.
OK.
First thing is what is the equivalent resistance of this circuit.
Well the first thing we're going to do is first we're going to combine both of those are there in parallel
with each other.
If I combine both of those.
Maybe you just write it up over here.
I'm just going to use my trick because there's only two of them.
And all you have to do for that is you multiply them and you divide it by the sum.
And what you find over here again 18 goes into six three times and 12 goes and three four times.
We have basically an equivalent resistance here of four ohms that's everything here in the orange box.
Now the other thing we need is we need to combine this four ohm resistor with a two old resistor and
those are in series with each other.
So our total is the equivalent to simply two plus four which gives me six ohms.
OK.
What's the current Now in this MF effort through the earmuffs source again what we've done now is we
simply simplify this circuit over here.
Into something like this.
This is still an 18 volt power supply and this is my equivalent what I've called our total here which
is 6 ohms.
So automatically you can write down ohms law for this simple circuit in the current simply 18 over 6
which should give me 3 amps.
So that means you have 3 amps over here you have three amps over in this section you have three amps
flowing through this tube and resistor.
OK so we've got both of those.
What's the potential drop now across each resistor.
Well that's basically just applying ohms law to each resistor.
Right.
So for Part C we can do that immediately for this to ohm resistor because the potential drop across
the resistor is simply going to be the value of the resistance times the current which is two times
it's going ahead of myself two times three three was the current flowing through it.
That gives me six volts.
So there's six volts between this point and that point.
Now what about both of those.
Now since these are in parallel we should know that the voltage across both of those have to be the
same.
So how do we get the value.
Well again now if you look at this branch over on the left hand side if I could look at between this
point and this point and I compare that to what's going on between this point and that point we basically
have two branches here that are in parallel with each other.
And one day we should know about that is that the voltage across both of those branches have to be the
same OK.
So let's just find with the voltages across both of these points.
Well if we start down here at the bottom what do we do we first gain 18 when we crossed the battery
and then what happens.
We just said there's a voltage drop now of six volts.
So the voltage difference between points A and Point B has to be 12 volts.
And that also must be the voltage difference between Point C and point D.
That just comes from the loop rule.
So the voltage difference
just call it.
I don't know which we should call here.
Again let's just apply the loop rule here.
So what we would get is 18.
Then we get minus 6 when we go across that resistor.
And then that there has to be equal to VB.
So you see that VB right away I can write the VB.
Mine is V-A has to be equal to 12 volts.
So that means that you have to have 12 volts across both of those across points C and point the point
C is at a higher voltage than point D.
So this here must also equal divisi mine VD must also be equal to 12 volts.
OK.
Here you gain 12 volts.
Here you go down 12 volts.
OK.
Because the sum has to be equal to zero Appian.
So what does that mean.
So let's just write it all out then.
I mean that the voltage is now across this 12 Olmer this there has to be 12 volts and it's also the
voltage across the six ohm resistor.
All right that's question see.
Now what is the current through each resistor.
We already know the current through the tube resistor that has to be 3 amps.
How do you now get the current here across the 12 ohm and across the 6 ohm.
Call that question D.
Well if you automatically know what the voltage is we just said it's 12 volts across each one you can
automatically just apply ohms law and find what is the current through each one.
So for the 12 ohm resistor we have basically 12 equals to the value of the resistance times the current
flowing through the 12 alarm resistor.
So the current flowing through the 12 ohm resistor has to be one what else.
Well we can also write a student a different color here.
We also write that the voltage across the six ohm resistor is also 12.
That must be equal to the value of the resistance multiplied by the current flowing through the 6 ohm
resistor.
So the current flowing through the six ohm resistor has to be equal to 12 over 6 which gives me two
amps.
You could have also used a junction rule over here because you know you have three going in you're going
to have one going on this side you're going to have two going on this side.
They have to sum up whatever current flows into the junction.
Must be the current flowing out of the junction.
All right good.
We've got the first four parts going.
Now let's switch it up a little bit.
All right.
For part e and f.
Now it's going to switch the current a little bit or switch the circuit rather.
So let me go ahead and just kind of make some room over here maybe remove some of these parts.
The nice thing about the videos is you can always go back in to see what I did before.
OK.
I think this should give me enough space.
So now we say that switch one is now closed.
Let me go ahead and close this.
All right.
What is going to be the current now through this two ohm resistor.
When the switch was open we said there was three amps.
What happens now that it's closed.
Well you can imagine over here let's kind of redraw what's going on over here.
So we've got our resistor 2 ohm resistor and now there's another path.
So we kind of have something like this.
So what would happen now if you have two Ohmes.
But now the current whatever current is going to enter over here it now has a choice.
Is it going to go through the path on the kind of along this path or is it mainly going to go through
the tools resistor while the two ohm resistor offers some resistance.
What about this path over here on the right hand side.
It offers no resistance and whenever that happens basically all the currents are going to decide to
go along this path.
And none of the currents going to decide to go through this two ohm resistor.
Now if you want to kind of show why that is.
Again if you look at the right basically we have two past that are in parallel with each other and if
two paths are in parallel with each other the voltage across has to be the same regardless of the path
that you take.
So the voltage across these two ohm resistor is simply the value of the resistance multiplied by the
current flowing through the tumor's asthore.
That has to be equal to the voltage.
If I go across this side the right hand side.
So what's the voltage between this point over here.
Call it point and point B if I'm going just along the wire against these wires are basically ideal conductors
right.
That's how we've simplified circuits when we've drawn them out and if they're ideal conductors they
basically don't have any resistance whatsoever.
So the voltage drop across something that doesn't have a resistance is zero.
And the only way you can have that now is if the voltage drop across this two ohm resistor is also zero.
And the only way you can have that is if you have zero because you have the resistance is two.
So the current must be zero.
This is basically creating a short so all the currents basically are going to go through here because
it's the path of least resistance OK so that one's kind of a trick.
But make sure you understand why that is are in the last part is question.
AF So now we're going to open switch to switch one is going to remain closed.
So let's go ahead and clean this up a little bit.
So do this clean up the diagram an open switch too.
OK.
So this is what we have now is not the three amps anymore you got to be careful with this.
But we have something like that.
All right so a switch is opened find the potential drop now across the six ohm resistor and across the
switch.
So what is the potential drop now across the 6 ohm resistor and also across the switch.
Well again if this is OPEN basically the resistance here right there should not be any current flowing
through that other branch.
Basically all the currents going to go through the battery.
It's going to go where the switch S1 was going to go down here and it has a path to go through the 12
ohm resistor and then go back.
So there is no more current because this is basically an infinite resistance.
If I open it up if you have infinite resistance I don't care what the voltages you're going to get.
Zero current.
So this current here is going to be zero which means now that the potential drop across the six ohm
resistor.
Well the value of the resistance multiplied by the current going through it.
This here has to be zero volts OK.
So now the next part is what is the voltage across the switch.
If you took a volt meter and you put one in here one end over here which value would I measure.
So in order to find out well you kind of have to do a loop.
So let's call this maybe point no which we call this let's call this maybe point C and let's call that
point D.
Let's find the voltage across.
So that means you have to start at point D and then end up going all the way to the other point.
We can't really go right across the gap.
We can go somewhere else I can start over here at Point D.
I can go around here.
I can go around here go through the battery and end up that point.
So that's what I'm going to do.
So we're going to start at point D which I'm at some particular potential I go through the resistor.
However we just said there is no current over here.
If there's no current that I don't have to do anything with Kirchhoff's loop rule I'm going to go over
here.
I'm going to go over here again there's no current here.
Flowing through that tumor's this is set off to do anything.
Now I'm going across a battery and I'm going to go from the high potential to the lower potential.
So I get a voltage drop of 18 and then I go all the way up to point C V c.
So at the end the difference of potential between both of those sides is v D minus v c is going to be
18 volts.
So you use a volt meter you plug a volt meter in here kind of look in something like this.
You're going to measure 18 volts OK.
Kind of a tricky problem and I think both of these were a little bit tricky.
I think the first four are more straightforward but you know make sure you understand the solution that
I provided here.