Example eight let's find the currents.
So between points.
B We have a 12 volt potential difference.
Find the current in each one of these resistors or start with case over here.
If you have 12 volts across that means you have 12 volts across each one of those resistors right.
Even if these are in parallel.
That's what it means.
So if you have 12 volts across this forum resistor that means you apply Ohm's law to each one of those
you have to get four in the current flowing through that.
That resistor.
So you get the current flowing through this forum resistor has to be three amps automatically should
be able to write this down the current flowing through the three ohm resistor is 12 over 3 4 amps and
the current flowing through the 6 ohm resistor is the potential difference divided by the resistance
which gives me 2 x I could have asked you what is the current flowing through point a major in the current
flowing like this.
Again this is kind of a junction over here and you know you've got current flowing through each one
of those resistors we just calculated.
We have three amps here you've got four amps here you've got two amps here.
All right and you've multiply each one of those values you have to get 12.
That means that the current kind of going into that junction has to be 9 amps.
It also has to be 9 amps leaving the junction.
We need to conserve the charge.
OK so next part case be.
I think the first thing I would probably do is try to simplify this a little bit.
Let's maybe try to simplify the parallel combination over here.
The way I would do that our equivalent one there's only two of them.
I always liked the multiply divided by the sum divided by eight.
You can divide through by four on each term.
You are left with three over 2 ohms.
And now if I combine the three ohms with the three over to the total are equivalent for this or between
points and point B call that are equivalent total is three plus 1.5 is me 4.5 ohms.
Let me just write that as 9 over to help a little bit with the math after I just kind of like to have
things in fractions most of the time.
All right.
So we now we have to find the current was the whole point is simplifying all of this so we know we have
12 volts between points and points B.
So that means that the current now simply going to be 12 divided by the value of the resistance which
is nine over two we can factor out at three.
And at the end we're left with eight over 3 amps.
So that is the value of the current flowing through this equivalent resistance.
But it's also going to be the value of the current flowing through the three ohm resistor so I can automatically
right.
This is the current flowing through the 3 ohm resistor.
Now what happens here is there's a junction.
So part of that current is going to flow here.
Part of that current is going to flow here.
The two old resistor is going to see less.
It's going to see more current rather than the six ohm resistor because it has a smaller value of the
resistance that's where most of the current prefers to go are in order to find how much current flows
here.
Well if we know the voltage drop across each branch we can find it using ohms law again.
But what we can do we could first find what is the voltage across this point
match and we know the voltage drop across is 3 ohm resistor because I know the voltage drop from 8 a
B.
I know that 12.
So it's the voltage drop across the three ohm resistor.
Well it's three multiplied by the current flowing through it.
We just calculated that it has to be 8 volts so you have 12 from a to b.
You have eight right here that means you're left with four.
Two there has to be four volts across both of those resistors they are in parallel with each other.
So each one of them has a four volt drop across it which means you can calculate what the current is
now.
Pretty straightforward.
So the current flowing through the six ohm resistor and the current flowing through the three ohm resistor
adds two ohm resistor Ratta it's going to be the voltage across each one of those we just said it's
4 divided by the value of the resistance in this case it's six.
In this case it's to see you get two amps going down here and you get to over three amps flowing through
the top one.
Now you can check both of that out.
Both of these out.
Now if I add both of those if I add two thirds plus two on that's six thirds I get eight thirds or that's
my junction rle whatever current flows into the junction has to be the current that flows out of the
junction.
And I had a third flowing in I have to have a third flowing out kind of a good problem here.
Hopefully you got that one.