OK I now want to just compare the previous case now to spend a little bit more time on a long time limit.
So the switch has been closed now for a longer period of time so my current We said DKs because of the
build up of charge and the field produced by the capacitor inside the wire offsets the electric fuel
produced by the battery inside the wire.
All right.
So we're down over here we know the current eventually gets to zero current eventually gets to zero.
I've placed a maximum amount of charge here.
Let's call a final charge on this capacitor QF.
So there's plus QF on one charge on one plate.
There is negative QF on the other plate.
And let's go back to my loop rule.
What would the Luper look like now in the long time limit.
That was my equation 1.
So in the long time limit Well let's rewrite it except this time I no longer have to worry about the
current term because I remember I just said that the current goes to zero when the current goes to zero
after a long time.
It means there is no more voltage drop across this resistor so we can eliminate this term in the long
time limit and that means we're immediately left with that the voltage.
There's only two terms left here.
You see that the voltage across the capacitor ends up being equal to the EMR for the battery and that
is kind of this point over here that's when equilibrium is kind of set.
Now if I use my capacitor equation Well the capacitor equation I know that the voltage across the capacitor
is equal to and this time limit it's going to be the final charge divided by the capacitance which equals
to the E-Myth of the battery.
So lastly I just want to isolate for what the final charges the final charge on those plates is actually
simply equal to the capacitance multiplied by the EMR of the battery.
This is an important equation right here.
One thing that we notice here is that it doesn't depend on our let's write that down.
So regardless of what the resistances the final charge you get on the plates is independent of our does
not depend on the value of the resistance.
That's kind of interesting.
Now if to this plot I'm going to add now what the charge looks like I'm going to plot it on the same
y axis except the green line will represent the charge.
The blackline will represent the current as I have it here.
So initially what we had here is zero charge.
So the charge actually started like this.
And now we know that after a long period of time I'm going to reach some final value in the way it kind
of does that.
It looks like a opposite of an exponential decay like an exponentially kind of saturated value and this
value here is simply QF which is equal to the capacitance multiplied by the EMI.
OK so that's kind of just a qualitative look at what's going on in the short and the long time limit
what we're going to do now is we're going to actually derive values.
Now we're going to do a bit of calculus in the next video if you want to skip the calculus you can but
it's not that bad.
So we're going to actually look at these relationships and calculated the other thing you can see from
both of these plots.
Remember the connection here between the current and the charge the definition of the current tells
you how does the charge change instantaneously right.
It's the slope of the graph and that also makes sense from this plot.
Let me plot the slope here in purple.
If you look at the slope of the Green Line Well initially the slope is something like this.
Right.
It's large and it's positive and that's exactly what the current says right here.
And then what happens to the slope.
It still remains positive but it's not as steep.
And once you get out over here it's not the best picture of the slope here but the slope tends towards
zero once you get into the very long time limit because my current tends towards zero.
OK so these pictures here are complimentary to one another.
Recalling that my current is the instantaneous change of the charge with respect to time.