OK there are a few important things I want to highlight about our equation here for the charge on the
plates as a function of time.
This is what we have.
First of all in our limits in the limit that time equals to zero which you see if you substitute zero
in here.
What do you get.
Well you get zero over here and you get one minus exponential of zero is one.
Therefore you're going to get one minus one so you're going to get zero.
And that's what we had.
Right we initially had an uncharged capacitor at the other limit.
You can do is when.
Time tends toward infinity.
Now we know what that case when we analyzed it we got towards some final charge and that's what you're
going to get here in the second term here if you substitute time to be a very big number since it's
negative over here.
This term ends up tending towards zero.
And then you're left with the charge when time is very very big.
It tends toward this value here.
See a capacitance multiplied by the MF of the battery.
So we're OK in those two limits.
At any other time now the benefit of having an equation like this is you are able to calculate for any
now any time if you're given a MF a capacitance any the value of the resistance.
You can actually go ahead and calculate the exact charge.
For example at time t one you can go ahead and calculate how many Coombe's would you have on these plates
as a function of time.
So a couple other important things about this equation.
Number one if we know the charge on the plates remember our capacitor equation right there is our fundamental
kind of capacitor equation that says the charge on the plates is always proportional to the voltage
on the plates.
So imagine you substituted that over here.
Right.
This is the charge as a function of time must be equal to the capacitance as a function of time multiplied
by the voltage is a function of time.
The same equation we just substitute our expression for charge and it's always proportional to the voltage.
So that automatically tells me that the voltage on the plates now is a function of time.
Also has the exact same shape as the charge.
Right.
It just has to have a different unit at the end of the day so you can see on both sides here and cancel
allow the capacitance and I'm left with an expression for voltage as a function of time.
Let me just kind of just erase that.
There you go.
So there's the expression for voltage as a function of time.
It also looks exactly like this.
So the voltage starts at zero when the charge is zero.
And then it tends toward the MFA the battery at time when time is very very long.
Another important fact about this equation here is you notice that this guy here in the denominator
of the exponential function first of all if you look at the units of it you have time in the numerator
that means that the denominator term must also be in units of time because the argument for an exponent
can't have any units.
So actually this value is what you call the RC time constant.
So the RC time constant
sometimes you define it as the letter tau and that's defined simply by the resistance multiplied by
the capacitance.
So what does that mean in terms of kind of this picture over here.
So this shape here would have a particular time constant and it would be equal to the resistance multiplied
by the capacitance.
It kind of tells you how long does it take for you to reach saturation.
I imagine I had a different set up here with a different resistor and a different capacitor.
So I may have a different time constant.
Well you may have a shape that looks like this.
Again you would reach the same saturation value because it's the same potential in the battery but this
one here might have a slightly different time constant let's call it our two C-2 it could also maybe
have a different case something that takes a lot longer to reach saturation.
And this guy here might have a different time constant call it Tao 3 so he'd be a completely different
circuit with a different value of the resistance and a different value of the capacitance.
So this time constant is really a measure of how quickly let's write this down.
So how quickly a capacitor will either charge or discharge quickly see charges.
Let's just do it like this.
So in this case if I have three different time constants tau to be the purple one which would have a
resistance R to in C you see this one here charges pretty fast.
Where is the green one charges a little bit slower.
Any orange one takes the longest amount of time to charge.
So if you were going to rank these time constants you would say that Tau 2 would be the smallest one.
Let's call this one here Tau one or just simply Tau given the given by R C and the last one the biggest
time constant here would be my time constant Tau 3.
So the question is since it's simply just the resistance multiplied by the capacitance you can see there's
only two ways you can make the time constant.
Big or small.
Right.
If I want to make the time constant as small as possible.
Well I either make the resistance very small.
So if you make the resistance very small this is going to charge up really fast if you also make the
capacitance very small.
It's also going to charge up really fast.
If I make the resistance very very big again that initial current ends up being so small that it takes
a longer time for the charge to settle on those plates.
So the next question is how do we actually calculate the current again.
Our equation up here is the equation for the charge as a function of time is very important.
If you take the derivative of this equation with respect to time we can obtain an expression for the
current.
So let's go ahead on the next slide and do that and look at the properties of the current as a function
of time.