A couple of things that I want to also mention about both of these charging and discharging cases here.
So in the charging case again we're putting charges on these plates.
Basically what we're doing is we're creating an electric field here and whenever you create an electric
field you end up storing energy.
So think about that.
So we end up storing energy here in that electric field or the capacitor stores energy.
There's all kind of different ways of looking at the exact same problem in the other case.
What we have is we initially have some energy stored in our capacitor and then that energy once you
start having that current flowing.
When I close a switch Well that energy gets dissipated in this resistor.
So if you wanted to look at this are these problems from an energy perspective here.
It's kind of different ways you can look at it.
But if I could I can always write the energy stored in a capacitor.
The different ways of doing this here let me just to kind of this way here is one half multiplied by
the charge on the capacitor multiplied by the voltage across the capacitor.
Now if I use my capacitor equation remember here we had the charge was always proportional to the voltage
across the plates.
So there's different ways of writing this formula if you either want to eliminate the charge I can using
this equation so you can write this as one half C-v square depending on what kind of information you
know and if you don't know the voltage across the capacitor.
But you know the charge and the capacitance You can also write it like this.
So just to eliminate voltage from this expression using a simple equation here you get one half Q square
to receive the exact same expression just written in three different forms so make sure you remember
that guy.
Now everything that we've seen so far for example we've seen that in this case over here let's just
take this one or even and this one we've seen that in both cases we were able to calculate that these
were time dependent quantities right.
These were.
We had functions that describe them and we can calculate the voltage at any time.
So our expression is now for the potential energy stored as a function of time.
They also become time dependent equations.
Right.
So in reality when you're writing them down now for RC circuits all of these quantities here become
time dependent quantities.
So you can get this in and get another expression here.
If I substitute depending on which case I'm looking at the charging vs. versus discharging you can get
an expression of the potential energy stored in that capacitor as a function of time.
And again I can use either of the other equations as well but just keep in mind this here becomes a
time dependent quantity.
The other thing we looked at before when we looked at circuits was power.
All right power was the rate at which either energy was being dissipated or the rate at which energy
was being supplied to the circuit.
So for power what we had we also had different expressions like power being delivered to the circuit
was the IMF multiplied by the current.
Now this becomes a time dependent equation because our current changes with time so keep that in mind
whenever you are solving problems for RC circuits and then looking at the power we have to use our expressions.
Now we might look at power in the short time versus the long time limit then we're just taking specific
cases here for this function.
But otherwise you're going to be a little bit careful.
Also if you're looking at the power being dissipated in the resistance again our expression expressions
before our eyes squared was one which was also equal to the squared over our again.
All of these now would become time dependent equations.
So all of those exponential factors I want to say one more thing.
All of these exponential factors that we had for our time dependent equations.
They all look something like this.
When you square all those terms that's what's going to happen here and all of these expressions we're
going to end up squaring all those terms.
So they all become when you square an exponential you're not going to change the sign but you're going
to get a two in the front.
Exponential of minus T divided by R C squared.
Member the laws of the exponents here you end up getting a minus two.
They're all right I let you practice that.
I think I've got a couple of problem and the problems that that look at.
Energy and Power.
So it will look more specifically at problems but I just wanted to highlight this that.
OK.
It's the same expressions as what you previously used in static cases.
Just now we have to use the time dependent expressions.