Are is probably nine are asking you to calculate what the resistance is.
It's this circuit here shown this MF equals to 50 volts and the capacitance down over here to micro
Feraud.
OK the switch now is opened after having been closed for a long time.
So when it's closed for a long time basically he simply does have current that's going to flow around
the closed wire.
This just acts like an open an open circuit so no current's going to flow over here.
OK.
So that means initially the voltage drop across this resistance is 50 volts because if add 50 you'll
lose 50 and then there's no other voltage drops when that switch is close.
OK.
And the voltage across the capacitor then initially has to be zero.
So let's write that down.
So the voltage across the capacitor at time zero must be equal to zero.
And what else.
Well now they say and four seconds later the voltage drop across the resistor.
Which was initially 50 right.
The voltage drop across the resistor at times zero had to be equal to 50 volts.
However at four seconds now they're telling us that the voltage drop across the resistor at time equals
the four has to be equal to 20 volts.
So we know then that the voltage across the capacitor at time equals to four seconds must be 30 volts
because if you do a complete loop at time equals to four.
Remember the switch is open.
So you have plus 50 you're going to have minus 20 volts across this resistor.
You have to have 30 volts across this capacitor here at Time equals the four.
All right so these are all the voltages now are asked to find what is the value of the resistance.
So again basically what happens now is that the capacitor is starting to charge.
And it's not fully charged because we didn't wait long enough.
So the voltage as a function of time across this capacitor is well are going to be our final voltage
which is going to be let's just call it V.F..
And again it's a charging so the equation looks like this it's one minus exponential of minus the time
divided by our time constant which is R C and in this case our final voltage.
Again that's a time equals to infinity that's going to be equal to the voltage of the battery.
So my final value here is really going to be 50.
And I do know the voltage at time Eagles the four seconds right at four seconds what I have is I have
3000 volts.
So one minus exponential of minus four seconds that's when I have 30 volts over here divided by our
AC.
All right.
The only equation in sort of the only unknown in this equation here is the value of the resistance.
We know that capacitance is to microflora And so at the end all we have to do here is do 30 over 50
must be equal to 1 minus exponential.
And all of this minus for over R C R it all you have to do now is kind of simplify this expression.
So let me just continued on this side of myself a bit of space here.
So I'm going to have one minus this will be three over five which is 0.6 and that's going to be equal
to the exponential of minus 4 divided by RC.
All right.
So to simplify this now all you need to do is take the natural log on both sides so you take natural
log of 0.4 and that's going to be equal to if you take natural log of the exponential you simply get
the argument which is minus 4 over R C and the last thing I'll just isolate for the unknown resistance
in this case which is our.
So it's minus 4 divided by the value of the capacitance multiplied by the natural log of 0.4.
We know the value of the capacitance.
Pretty straightforward as is two times ten of the minus six and multiplied by the natural log of zero
point four.
All right.
Put everything in a calculator.
I think I got a pretty large resistance of 2.2 times tended to the six ohms
and that's the value of the resistance here given all of this information and the problem.
All right so this is just the problem of basically writing down what you know what you don't know realizing
that this is a charging of a capacitor problem or it's kind of disguised with the switch but that's
all it is.
You just have to be able to identify that.
And then at the end you simply have one equation in one unknown.
Just do a little bit of math in order to get to the final answer.