All right so here's example too.
So we've got a surrogate with a 1 micro ferrite capacitor and a resistance of 10 Kila ohms at time T
equals to zero we're given there's an initial charge on those plates of two micro Coolum.
They're telling us now or asking us what is the charge on the capacitor when time equals the five milli
seconds.
So again this is just the standard discharge circuit.
Right.
So it's one resistor.
Very easy one capacitor very easy.
And that's it.
And the reason we're going to have some where we have initially charged it here right so we have some
initial charge let's just put it on this plate here.
So positive two times ten to the minus 6.
Cool ohms is my initial charge.
This capacitor or sorry this resistor over here is 10 Keela ohms That's 10000 ohms.
That's our value are.
Now that said we know it's discharging so the charge is a function of time on these plates is given
by Qs 0.
Same as last time.
Exponential of minus the time divided by the time constant which is R C for this case.
That's all there is to it.
So it's kind of the opposite of example one example one we were told what the final charge is you are
asked to calculate the time in this case it's more straightforward because they tell you the time.
All you have to do is calculate what this final charges.
So this is two times tend to the negative six multiplied by exponential of minus.
Now five seconds that's five times ten to the minus three seconds.
Divided by are 10000
multiplied by the capacitance one times ten to the negative six.
All right.
Substitute everything into the calculator.
You get the charge.
Q Should give you about one point two one times ten to the negative six Coolum which is the same thing
as 1.2 1 micro Coolum That's how much charge there is left on the plates after five milliseconds.
OK.
Pretty straightforward application of our equation here for discharging a capacitor.