All right here is example six us finding the initial current is a good surrogate here with a bunch of
resistor and a whole series of capacitors and one battery and it's switched a named meter.
So here is the problem it goes to zero.
All capacitors are discharge.
So the voltage across each one is zero.
And then that switches move from the open to the close.
Let's go ahead and close that up.
OK.
And what's the current now through this branch through the e-meter just after Segal's to zero.
All right.
So what does that mean.
Well how do we analyze circuits like this.
The first thing you have to realize is that in this time limit at T equals to zero we have a rule right
at Teagle zero just after T equals to zero.
What happens is the way you deal with capacitors is you basically just short them.
So it's as though you connect wire right here and you connect them.
So let's go through all our capacitors and kind of just do this.
That's what it looks like.
Time equals to zero.
Now you have to think about it.
So now you imagine there's current currents flowing here it's going to hit a junction.
So what happens now when you have a path here with zero resistance and then you have a path with 25
ohms up here whereas the current going to go where the current is going to go through the path of least
resistance.
It also means that any branch that's in parallel with something that's shorted is not going to have
any current.
So you can forget about that.
Where else do we have a situation.
Well we also have this one this 25 here is also in parallel with this 10 micro Feraud capacitor which
means that if the current is given a choice once it gets to that junction it's basically just going
to go through that branch.
All right the next thing we want to do now.
OK.
Now we have to analyze this circuit a little bit.
So we're first going to do now that we've eliminated two of those resistors.
But let's have a look at what's going on now.
If we draw a loop so where is the current going to go it's going to go like this.
It's going to go through here.
It could go all the way out here could come back here could flow through here like that part of the
current now could also once it gets over here that we still have a junction here there's still this
path that it can go through.
You just don't have access to this 25 ohm resistor because it just prefers to go through the path of
least resistance which is out here.
All right.
So that means we have the green branch and then we have this orange one well basically both of those
are if you look at this here the outer branch has a resistance of 25 ohms.
The middle branch has a resistance of 50 ohms.
So what you can do is you can kind of group both of those and these are in parallel with each other.
So you can replace both of these resistors with an equivalent resistor and the equivalent resistor.
If there's only two of them you simply multiply them and you divide it by the sum.
So if you do that you can cross out 25 out of each one you're going to be left with three.
So the equivalent resistor for those two outer branches is 50 over three.
OK so now let's have a look at what we got.
So now we've got a battery we've got to 75 ohm resistance.
I've combined everything here in this purple circle and that's an equivalent resistance of 50 over three.
And then there's also this 15 Omers distance down here.
So basically all you have now is three resistors that are in series with each other.
So the total equivalent resistance for this circuit at time equals to zero.
Pretty straightforward.
You just got to add them up.
So it's 75 plus 50 over three plus 15 ohms.
OK.
Punch that in the calculator where do you get.
One hundred six point seven.
Little bit bigger than 100.
So now what have we done.
We've simplified this entire network into something that simply looks like this.
And again we're only looking at the time equals the zero limit or very short after that time.
And this is my our equivalent This here is 100 volts so guess what the current flowing through this
through this section over here is the current flowing through my equivalent resistance which is basically
just the voltage of the battery which is 100 divided by my equivalent resistance which is 1 0 6.7.
That gives me approximately 0.9 for amps.
So a correct answer for this one is choice D.
And that's how you solve problems at least in this time limit.
You forget about anything that's in parallel with a capacitor.
And again it's only because the capacitor here doesn't have a resistance right.
If there was a resistance you've got to be a bit more careful but you simply short that capacitor.
If there's any resistance in parallel with it all the current is going to go through the shorted bit.
None of the current is going to flow through that more resistive path.