All right here is example seven entitled energy dissipated or in this example says the switch in the
circuit below is in position A.
So if it's in position it's really only this first part of the circuit here at the beginning and it's
there for a long time.
OK the switches then move to position B but only for a second and then it's return back to position
A.
So while the switch is in position B how much energy is dissipated here in this.
Fifty five hundred ohm resistor.
All right.
So let's have a look at this problem.
So the first thing we got to notice is its first in position A for a long time.
Well what does that mean.
That means that after a long time there's going to be no more current in this section because there's
a single branch and there is a capacitor.
There's no more current After a while because the capacitor the voltage across the capacitor ends up
being 50 volts.
Once you achieve that you're done charging the capacitor.
So we know that after a long time I have 50 volts across this capacitor which has a value of 200 micro
Fred.
All right.
So we actually can also calculate how much charge there is but doesn't really matter for now.
OK.
So what we've done now is we've stored potential energy in this capacitor the potential energy stored
in the capacitor initially
it's going to be what.
Well let's call it you.
Now there is you can read it as this is cue times V.
I kind of like the other formula again and you can manipulate this kind of three ways to write this.
I kind of like to write it like this because I know what the value of the capacitance is.
I know what the voltage across the plates.
Therefore I can calculate this.
This is a 1 1/2 C would be 200 times tend to the minus 6 and then the voltage is 50.
Don't forget the square.
So you calculate this and you get zero point two five Joule.
That's how much energy you stored in this capacitor.
So now what happens.
Well now you're going to flip the switch so you fully charged this capacitor.
You've put a whole bunch of charge you put a voltage on it and now I'm going to switch into position
B.
Now once it's in position B guess what happens.
It's going to start to discharge.
However I'm not going to let it fully discharge I'm not going to let all of this energy dissipated because
I'm only doing this for one second.
So what we really have to do of this problem is calculate what is really the final voltage after one
second.
All you have to remember here is that you are discharging.
So let's calculate what the final voltages across and then we can also look at the final potential energy.
So the final voltage or the voltage after and any time is given by some initial voltage which is 50
in this case.
And again it's exponentially decaying function minus T divided by my time constant which is our c time
constant for this cases.
Pretty straightforward 200 micro Feraud multiplied by 50 volts and the time.
Now the time is going to be one second.
That's also pretty straightforward.
OK so let's substitute everything in here.
So we get 50 volts exponential of minus 1 divided by the value of the resistance.
Now look at it's fifty five hundred fifty five hundred.
Multiplied by the value of the capacitance 200 times ten to the minus 6.
That's the RC time constant.
Substitute everything into my equation here.
Actually really what we're finding here is the voltage at time equals to 1 second.
We've substituted one into that equation.
All right.
So that gives me a voltage of approximately twenty point one volts.
That's the voltage at one second.
So that means how much potential energy is stored in this capacitor here.
After that time equals the 1 second.
So over here you simply have to look at the final potential energy was one half multiplied by the capacitance
that hasn't change and it's whatever the final voltages across the plates.
So in this case it's the one half multiplied by two hundred times ten to the minus 6 and multiplied
by twenty point one and square that value which you get here zero point zero for as you will.
That's my final potential energy.
I started out with Point two five and now I've only got point zero for what what does that mean.
That means that some of that energy was dissipated and the energy dissipated.
Where did it go.
Well it actually was dissipated into heat through this resistor.
So the energy dissipated
you simply take the difference between my initial energy dissipated and try that again is simply going
to be 0.25 minus zero point zero four.
So most of that energy was dissipated through that resistor.
So that's how much energy is dissipated in a resistor that's kind of I think the easiest way to solve
this problem.
It's pretty straightforward.
Calculate the initial potential energy calculate the final potential energy that energy had to go somewhere.
It was dissipated.