All right here's an example.
We have an RC circuit problem says the capacitor in the circuit shown is initially charged as the six
micro ferrett capacitor find the current through the four ohm resistor and through the 8 ohm resistor
in these different time limits.
So immediately after you close the switch and then after a long time when the switch has been closed
and then also find the charge on the capacitor after a long time after you've closed the switch.
OK so let's first look at kind of right after T goes to zero.
Let me just call it the zero here.
Remember what happens that goes to zero and you first close the switch.
The trick now is you can redraw the circuit.
It basically behaves.
This forum is still going to be there.
The switch is closed.
The Forum lets also draw the aid on that one still there.
We close this branch.
Here's the 8 ohm.
And remember immediately after you close the switch the capacitor behaves as though it's shorted.
So that basically means like you have this additional branch here where there's nothing there.
It basically means that the resistance of this branch here is effectively zero.
So if it's zero it means that if you go from point B all the way to point B.
Well if you go through this outer branch there is no voltage drop across this outer branch because the
resistance is zero.
And that means if this 8 ohm branch is in parallel with this one there is no voltage drop across this
8 ohm resistor.
So that automatically tells you that the current through this middle section through that 8 ohm at least
in the short time limit this current here has to be equal to zero because all the current is basically
going to just go in the outside of whatever current flowing through this 4 ohm resistor is basically
going to continue along this branch and no current is going to go through the center.
So this problem becomes very very simple with just a single branch and the resistance is four ohms.
The total resistance of that single branch in the short time limit the voltage of the battery is 12
volts.
You automatically know then that the current initially has to be three amps and you get that from the
12 divided by for 12 volts divided by forums gives you three amps.
OK so we know that one.
And also Well we know that was the current through the four ohm resistor.
The current through the 8 ohm resistor is zero.
All right.
What about now in the limit where time is long Let's just call it infinity and it's really long with
respect to the time constant of this particular circuit.
All right.
So in that long time limit.
Remember what happens now.
Well you get a voltage across this capacitor and after a long time there is no current flowing through
a branch where there is a capacitor.
So that means if there's no current basically it's basically an open circuit over there.
So you still have this forum resistor.
The switch is closed now.
We still have our 8 ohm resistor.
Let's finish off this branch and now you basically have an open circuit over here so there is no current
flowing through this outer branch.
I must be equal to zero.
If it's open the resistance basically is infinite.
So here you still have the 8 ohm here you still have the forum.
And here we still have a 12 volt battery.
So now you could see that the branch that we're interested in it's really again just a single loop circuit
the total equivalent resistance is 12 ohms.
The voltage of the battery is 12.
You automatically can right that the current through the forum resistor has to be equal to the current
through the 8 ohm resistor and must be equal to 12 divided by 12 which gives me 1 amp.
So that's the current After a long time.
Now find the charge.
So he said you're going to eventually charge up this capacitor and there's going to be no current.
So what is the actual voltage now across from point C to point B.
So in order to answer that one I'm going to do now is I'm simply going to choose a loop and when to
choose a loop that kind of goes around here remember that switch is closed.
I want to introduce what I want to introduce the voltage across that capacitor so I'm going to choose
this exterior loop here and let's use Kirchhoff's loop rule here.
So if I start at point f the first thing I encounter is a 12 volt battery so I get plus 12.
Now I'm going across the four ohm resistor and I know there's a current of one amp so I get minus four
volts across this resistor.
Four times one.
And then I go all the way to point seen on going across the capacitors.
I'm going to get a voltage across the capacitor and go back to point f I get zero.
So automatically burn VC on the other side.
You left that the voltage across the capacitor gives me 8 volts.
Right it's not equal to 12 volts in this case because there's also a voltage drop across this forum
resistor and you also know that the voltage drop across this capacitor has to be the voltage drop across
the 8 ohm resistor.
Both of those branches are in parallel.
I could have done that the voltage drop across the 8 ohm resistor is simply eight times the current
which gives me 8 volts.
All right.
Now I'm asking for what is the charge after a long time.
If you know the voltage you know the value of the capacitance you automatically know that the charge
is simply a capacitance multiplied by the voltage.
In this case it's six times ten to the minus six multiplied by eight.
This gives me 48 charges 48 times ten to the minus six which gives me 48 micro Koolau so that the final
charge on this capacitor.
OK.
Kind of a simple problem but it's important to understand these two time limits and how to calculate
things.