Hi everyone today I want to look at a an equivalent resistance problem.
So here's the problem here I have those two points A and B denoted here and in between those two points
and b I have a network of twelve resistors now the resistors are combinations of resistors in parallel
and in series.
So we're gonna apply the tools in order to simplify these 12 resistors into one equivalent resistor.
All right let's go see how we set this problem up.
Again I'm going to assume that all the resistance values are going to be the same thing and they're
all going to be just the value are and I'll be able to simplify this network into one equivalent resistor.
All right let's set it up.
All right I want to first look at this problem here look at the overall symmetry of this problem because
if you look at what I've highlighted here in this dashed box you're going to notice that this pattern
over here kind of repeats itself.
I mean it's kind of rotated a little bit but really whatever whatever is in this dash box is kind of
the same thing is as this part over here.
And it's also the same part as what's down over here.
It's just rotated but it's the same overall component.
Right.
So if we're able to simplify what's in that dash box we can also simplify what's in those other circled
areas.
So let's go and just look at this area over here which I've represented here on the right hand side.
OK.
So this is what we have down over here we have a point over here and a point over here.
I want you to first look at this top branch over here.
Imagine there is a current here flowing in this direction that current I would have to flow through
this resistor.
And then once it reaches the top it really is going to continue and flow through the second resistor.
So that means that we have over here is that both of these resistors here have to be in series with
each other.
So I can simply Simplify both of those.
That means that the equivalent resistance of this upper branch over here has to be simply R plus R because
they are in series with each other.
Therefore you left with two are now if you go back and we redraw this picture over here.
This is what we have we now have a resistance and I'm going to plot the two our resistance.
Let me just plot it over here.
Something like this little sloppy but that's OK.
And then here I'm going to have this other point which is all the way down over here and I still have
my blue resistance which is kind of on this diagonal over here so let's go ahead and redraw this one
OK.
So I've done quite a lot of work already and I know that this one here is to are I've simplified this
bit and the first one I haven't changed this is still an equivalent resistance.
So now if you look at this what you have now are two resistors that are in parallel with each other.
Right these resistance says to R and R are simply in parallel with one another.
So in order to simplify this into one equivalent resistance between these points all you simply have
to do is apply the formula which simply says that one divided by my equivalent resistance let's call
this equivalent resistance one is going to be one divided by two R plus one divided by R.
So this is pretty simple to simplify you simply have to put things on a common denominator which we
could choose as one over two are in order to do this I simply have to multiply by two for each side.
And what you're left with is three over to r except that's one divided by the equivalent resistance.
So at the end of the day you simply have to take the reciprocal of this.
So you get that are equivalent one is simply equals the two are divided by three.
All right.
So that means that everything here in this dash box can be simply represented by two are divided by
three.
So now we're going to use this in order to simplify the rest of the network because that means everything
over here can be simplified with a resistance which is equivalent to a two hour over three resistor.
Everything down here in this lower triangle and in this other triangle can also be replaced by this
value of equivalent resistance so let's keep this value in mind to are over three and let's go to the
next page and see how we further simplify this network.
So this is what we first found we found that everything here in this dash box was equivalent to a resistor
which was equal to two are divided by the value three.
That also means that while this is the same thing right.
It's a combination of series that is then in parallel with this one resistor are.
So if we redid the same type of analysis we would get to our over three for this one we would get two
are over three for this one and we would get two are over three for this one.
So now we simply have to combine all of these new resistance values which are all to our over three
into one equivalent network.
So I've redrawn my original circuit now and instead of drawing all of those triangles with those each
one having three resistance values I'm simply now replacing those values with their equivalent resistance
values and now all we have to do is simply look at this simplified network what we have here are two
resistors.
Let's look at this top portion over here.
Both of these are simply in series with each other.
All right.
So this is pretty simple to simplify.
That means the equivalent resistance inside my red box over here I simply have to add those values together
so you get to are over three plus two are over three which gives me four are over three.
Well guess what.
I'm gonna have the exact same value down over here I'm going to get an hour equivalent for that lower
segment which is also equal to for our over 3 All right.
We're down to one last step.
Now all we have to do is simply combine both of these guys.
Remember both of these resistance values are now in parallel with each other so since they're in parallel
we should simply apply our formula for parallel resistors and get one total equivalent Resistance for
this problem last step in our problem now is simply to combine both of these equivalent resistors for
the complete upper branch here which was for our over three and the lower branch which was ended up
being the same just from the symmetry of the problem.
And now all we have is one over our equivalent and really total now right.
This is the last step is going to be one over let's just write it out first one over our equivalent
for this top branch and again plus one over our equivalent from the bottom branch.
But keep in mind these are the exact same values right.
So therefore it's really simply two times whatever are equivalent from one of those branches.
Right.
Since they're the exact same value.
So we simply going to get two divided by four are instead of dividing by three I'm just going to multiply
by three and this is one over our equivalent just right total like this okay.
So the last step now you could simplify this a little bit.
I can factor out too when I'm left with a two.
So the last step here is simply take the inverse of this.
So we get that my equivalent our equivalent called our equivalent total at the end of the day simply
going to be two are divided by three.
Okay.
So that was kind of a nice problem that you have to combine resistors in series and parallel and at
the end we should get to our divided by three.
If the value of the resistance was example 10.
Well we can easily calculate that it would be twenty over three.
All right very very straightforward.