All right.
So here's our kind of important summary here.
Definition of the current flow of charge the rate at which charge moves or flows past some point per
unit time.
OK current is measured in cool ohms per second.
We refer that as being an ampere an amp.
Sometimes you just use the letter A.
So one cool on per second is equivalent to 1 amp and looking at the microscopic.
If we're looking at electrons moving in a conductor the definition of the current If you look at all
the charges that could move through this conductor you can write it in terms of different properties.
You can read it in terms of a charge density how many electrons are free to move per unit volume of
the conductor multiplied by the charge of each electron multiplied by the cross-section of my wire.
Typically these are circles so typically have like a PI are squared for the area.
You can calculate that in the last term here is this drift velocity.
OK.
How fast are those electrons moving in this conductor.
Now there's drif velocity again if I go back to my back to basics slide right how fast the electrons
moving it really depends on how big that electric field is.
All right Ed we'll see in a minute.
When we look at what's going on it also depends on other aspects because these electrons although they
accelerate a little bit they will and they will encounter other electrons.
They'll also encounter positive ions and they're basically going to collide.
So they don't just accelerate forever and then this term just gets bigger and bigger.
So let's have a look.
Let's zoom into a wire and see what it looks like.