All right.
So remember we had we had our electrons here that were in this copper wire.
So I want to see a few things about another term that I think comes up here is current density.
So again these were kind of drifting along.
And that means if I have electrons flowing from the left to the right I have a positive current flowing
in the opposite direction that was the convention.
I often define a term called the current density.
The letter used for current density is J.
So it's called this the current density.
And for the purposes of this class we are just going to consider kind of simple cases where we have
a constant density Throughout the same.
So there's the same number of charges kind of going from or crossing near the top of the wires the bottom.
OK.
And the definition of the current density if this density is constant is simply the total current
divided by the total area.
So that's the definition of the current density.
So for this particular case again total current is usually just written as I.
The total area here we're looking at the cross-sectional area that we're looking at the charges moving
through.
So in this case it was simply a.
So for our case here the current density for this particular case you just bring on the other side what
you're left with is this charge density the charge of each electron multiplied by the philosophy.
Right.
That is simply the current divided by the units now of current density.
Pretty straightforward have to be measured in units of amps per the units of the area or meters squared
if you want to work in Esai units.
And conversely if somebody gives you the current density J and you want it to find what the total current
is.
Well again if you know a as you can find the total current simply by multiplying the current density
multiplied by the area.
OK.
Now I think we get a little bit more complicated if the current density is not constant.
This is true if it's constant and the area is kind of perpendicular to the flow of the current density
it could get more complicated more advanced books.
Sometimes you might see that the current density you'd have to if the current density wasn't constant
you'd actually have to integrate over something like this.
But this is more advanced topic.
OK.
We basically just consider cases where there's the same number of same current density everywhere throughout
this cross-section here and also the cross-sections always kind of perpendicular to our current density.
OK so let's keep things simple and just takes a very simple definition.