As do a simple example here of finding the draft philosophy.
So why are used in experiments is typically made of copper and this radius here is approximately 0.7
millimeters take the density of copper it's the density the material is eight point nine grams per centimeter
cube and the molar mass of copper is approximately 63 three and a half grams per mole.
All right so estimate the total charge of free electrons in each meter of this wire.
If you have a current of one ampere.
OK.
So let's kind of just draw it out for a second here.
Remember we have our equation here an equation that relates the current the drift velocity and everything
else.
Let's just examine what's going on here.
So first we're going to have a length of copper that is 1 meter.
So the first thing we have to do we know the density we have to figure out how many electrons are located
in this one.
What is the total charge.
Q inside.
Well let's think about our equation for a second.
So if we have one meter I know that density of copper is this.
Let me try to figure out how many actual copper atoms are located in this one meter.
Right.
What is the number of atoms.
And I know each one here gives me approximately 1 free electron.
So if I can figure out what is the number of copper atoms in per meter I know the volume because I know
the cross-sectional area here I know the radius.
So I could probably calculate what the cross-sectional area is.
I know the length is 1 meter.
So lets start thinking about this.
So first you consider the volume What is the total volume while its going to be the length multiplied
by the area in that area.
So let's just do the length is one.
Actually I don't even need to write that.
And it's a one multiplied by the cross section which is going to be pi the circle an R squared in radius
here is 0.7 times ten to the minus three and I'll square that value.
OK so that's the total volume and that's measured in meters cube.
So I have a number for that.
Our next thing we have to do now is figure out how many atoms do I have here how many copper atoms do
I have per meter cube.
So let's think about this just from the dimensions.
So if you're given the density our density here is in grams per centimeter cube.
All right.
And I know that the molar mass is in grams per mole.
So actually if I wanted to get rid of grams here I could do is I could do something like this I could
do grams per mole and you'll see that here I got grams in the numerator here I have it in the denominator.
So at the end here I'm going to get the number of miles per centimeter cube and I can do one more thing
I want to really know where it is the number of atoms.
Right.
The overall goal number of atoms copper atoms per meter cube while we could first start by calculating
per centimeter cube then I can convert it.
So this first term here is the density This is eight point nine.
Now this second term over here in grams per mole the second bracket over here if you wish is this smaller
mass you got to be careful this is sixty three point five grams per mole.
All right.
And that takes care of these grams.
Now I'm not quite there at the end I wanted to know how many atoms there are.
Now all I know is how many moles per centimeter cube.
But if I use Avogadro's number I think I can do that right because Avogadro's number is measured in
the number of atoms we want to get rid of moles.
So we have to have it like this.
You introduce another bracket here.
This here is simply Avogadro's number which is six point zero two times ten of the 23 atoms primal.
And now you see the moles are going to cancel out.
Moles are going to cancel out.
And if I evaluate these three thing these three terms just multiply through well here you got to divide
but at the end what you are going to get is the number of atoms percentage meter cube.
I did this correctly it should get eight point four seven multiplied by 10 of the 22.
And again this is an atoms per centimeter cube you can convert that right away to meter's cube.
Let you do that again.
Pretty straightforward.
Eight point seven times ten to the twenty eight atoms per metre cube.
All right.
So now that we know that we know that each one now each of those Adam gives you one electron.
So we now really have our charge density.
All right.
Let's write that out.
So the charge density of the free electrons again charge density will be measured in cool ohms per metre
cube.
So what you need to do now is if I have something in atoms per metre cube I would need to multiply that
by cool ohms per atom in order to get rid of that and that I know right because I know each atom gives
me one electron.
So you have to have 1.6 times tend the negative 19 cool ohms per annum.
Thats the number of free electrons multiplied by the total number of atoms so this is going to be eight
point four seven multiplied by 10 of the 28
atoms per meter cube.
All right you see that the atoms cancel out.
And at the end my total kind of charge density for these free electrons I right is f e over here.
If I did this correctly should give me one point three six times ten to the ten.
Cool ohms perimeter cube.
All right.
So you want to know now is the total charge.
Well again we know what our total volume is.
All right.
Because the length is one in our cross-sectional area was here.
So what you can do now is if you want to determine what the total charges.
Q Is you simply multiply this density that we just got the density of the free electrons multiplied
by the volume.
All right I'll let you carry that out.
I did it and I found 2.8 multiplied by 10 of the four cool ohms perimeter.
Again it's cool almost because we're really just looking at one meter here of wire.
So on one meter of wire there's quite a bit of charge 2.8 times 10 of the four coulombs 28000 cool homes.
All right.
So this is these kind of the problems kind of come up pretty often.
Again if you're given some information about the density typically just do some dimensional analysis
to figure out how many kind of atoms do you actually have in a block of material.
Now each atom has a lot more electrons but only some of them will contribute to the current.
For copper it's typically one free electron per atom for silver for other materials it might be a slightly
different number but it's not all of these electrons that contribute right.
Not all of the copper electrons that are going to contribute to the current And I think that's the important
point here.
OK.
So for Part B we're just asked to calculate what the drift philosophy is in the equations up here so
let's just start with that and maybe just rearrange the equation a little bit so you can right that
the drift velocity if you know the current.
I know got to be a little bit careful how we have still our number density number of free electrons
meters.
Q multiplied by the charge of each one multiply by that cross-section which we know what this expression
simplifies a little bit.
Remember what this is a number of electrons per meter.
Q And if you multiplied by the charge of each electron This basically is given me in the number of charges
right the total charge and cool ohms per meter cube.
Well I had that value right.
I mean this is basically the total charge.
Q divided by the volume which is the area multiplied by the length the length is 1 meter.
OK.
So let's just go ahead and just replace this right that's what any is any is basically the total charge
divided by the total volume that I'm looking at.
So all you have to do here is just multiply or just right.
I say that if this guy were going to raise the total charge here and that 1 meter length of wire divided
by a and multiply by 1 here I still have that definition which includes another area term over here.
So you could see this simplifies a little bit those area terms cancel out.
The length is one so you don't really have to worry about that.
So all we're left with here is what is the current divided by basically the charge per unit length here
the current for this problem here was 1 amp.
So you get 1 divided by 2.8 times ten to the four.
And this is going to be giving me my drift velocity so the drift velocity put that in the calculator
which you get at the end is approximately 3.6 times ten of the minus 5.
And since I've kept everything in S-I units I should get meters per second.
At the end.
OK.
A lot of times you write these philosophies in millimeters per second just kind of get rid of some of
those terms.
So that's 3.6 times ten to the minus two that's in millimeters per second.
So you can see that the drift velocity in kind of typical copper is extremely small.
Right.