All right let's kind of look at the units of everything involved here just to kind of start making sense
of everything.
So we had I k Iowas simply current and that was measured in amps and one amp was one cool on per second.
All right what else.
We had a current density.
This was a simple formula was total current divided by total area.
So this was measured in amps per meter squared.
Put a square bracket whenever I'm kind of discussing the units about about a quantity.
Well what else do we have.
We have electric field field.
The electric field is measured in units of volts per meter.
What else I introduce that quantity called
resistivity resistivity.
Well what is the simple equation for a resistivity its was the constant of proportionality between the
electric field strength and our current density.
So that means that our equation for Roe must be equal the E divided by the current density.
All right so now let's simplify this.
So the units for e are volt meter
and the units of J were current which was amps per meter squared.
All right we can cross out one of these meters here.
So we're left with this guy here in the square bracket of volt per amp multiplied by a meter.
Actually this guy here can simplify and let's go to the definition of resistance resistance the equation
that we had was that the voltage or the difference of potential was equal to the resistance multiplied
by the current.
Right.
These were two forms of Ohms law.
So if I isolate for resistance.
So I say equal but I really mean a little arrow there.
So the value of the resistance can be written as V divided by.
So if you look at this guy now looks pretty similar to one of those terms.
This is voltage divided by amperes by amps group actually we define this as being an olm.
We call this an ohm and the symbol we use for that.
You've probably seen this kind of this symbol over here than upper case omega that's the symbol we give
for resistance.
So now if I go back to my resistivity.
So that's what you call one ohm is 1 volt per ampere So you see both of those are kind of linked together.
So actually the more common unit we see for resistivity is then simply written as an old.
That's the volt per ampere multiplied by a meter.
So resistivity is often written only in terms of 0 meters like this which are the quantities that we
have.
I think we've pretty much have everything here.
Now let me just also mention something so I said everything here.
Both of these equations were versions of Ohm's law the value Roe.
This is a material property.
So you can look it up different materials will have different values of resistivity.
Now you might have heard of something called the conductivity.
Right.
Let me just right ro here is just reminding you this is resistivity
you might have heard about something called the conductivity.
When you're talking about conductors you'd expect the resistivity to be pretty small because conductors
tend to be pretty good at conducting electrons.
But there's something called conductivity.
And usually they use the letters Sigma for that last letter over here actually and it's pretty straightforward.
It's related to the resistivity and it's just the reciprocal of the resists devotee.
So that means if you know the reason civets you automatically know the kind activity.
And there is I just want to mention this is because sometimes Ohm's law here is written kind of like
this.
Most of the time as we are going to apply it like this.
But if you use the definition of the conductivity every now and then instead of writing it like the
first form what we're going to do is you're going to replace the resistivity by one divided by the conductivity.
And some people like to write it like this and then just to get rid of the term in the denominator here.
You're right that the current density is equal to the conductivity multiplied by the electric field.
The Joe equation I like to call it.
All right.
So we have pretty much everything here I think.
Other quantities Well there was also the was the voltage right.
You can break down a Volt and two more fundamental units if you want it to one volt is a jewel per Coolum
was a definition of a volt if you go back to electrostatics and you can break the jewel down into more
fundamental units as well.
At the end of the day everything can be broken down into kilograms meters seconds coulombs.
So these are just some of the important relations that kind of link all of these things together.
So ohms law there's really three different ways to write it for the rest of this course we're really
going to mainly focus on this guy right here.
But just be aware that other things exist out there.