Art I mentioned before that for Olmec resistors you can write the total resistance as the material property
the resistivity multiplied by the length divided by the area.
And this first term the resistivity was really a property of materials.
So what I've got here a resistivity values resistivity values are usually quartered at some temperature.
They were the units in meters and on the left hand side here we have the resistivity for conductors.
Again for conductors you'd expect it to be pretty small down over here on the right hand side have got
different materials Semiconductor.
And let's just compare it to insulators for now for example.
Compare copper to wood.
All right wood doesn't do well if you put it into a circuit.
It's resistivity is these values here tend to the eight to 10 to 14 depending on which kind of wood
you're looking at.
Compare that to copper copper is a very good conductor its value of the resistivity is extremely low
compared to would tend to the minus 8 0 meters.
You can compare copper now to some of the other more common used conductors.
Silver is a pretty good conductor.
Resistivity is a little bit lower than that of copper.
They also have aluminum a little bit higher but still pretty low.
Again they're all in the range of 10 of the negative 8 here whereas the insulators are very very high.
Rubber tended at 16 right.
There is no charge conduction.
Right very very little because the resistance is so high.
So the current would be very very small.
Or if you think about Ohm's law now you rearrange Ohm's law.
You start with vehicles that are I.
However if you think about it now the amount of current that you get for a potential difference is going
to be divided by our.
So if I make the resistance very very big Clearly I'm going to get very small current right so he'd
get very small current with any of these insulators compared to the conductor elements.
Now I just want to say one more thing here about this quantity over here.
We notice the value here is listed at 20 degrees Celsius.
In reality you can change that value add value depends on temperature.
And for most of the materials if you plot the resistivity versus the absolute temperature you kind of
get a value where even at absolute zero you're going to get some resistivity because you will have some
of those collisions between the electrons and the ions.
But generally what tends to happen at least for conductors is it's pretty linear relationship over a
broad range of temperatures.
So B is kind of proportional to T after a while.
Anyway that's one way you can actually increase the resistance of the material is to make it hotter.
All right if the temperature gets hotter the resistivity goes up the length in the area.
Don't change a little bit there I mean there might be a little bit of thermal expansion.
But the main impact will probably be on the resistivity and that's how you can change the electrical
properties of resistors.