Now you walk into any Home Depot over the weekend and you go try to buy some copper wire go into the
electrical section and the copper wire that you're looking for has a certain size that's recommended
by your electrician.
Typically if you have a bigger cross-section you can have more current flowing through it.
However again now you have to worry about how much resistance there is.
Right.
The bigger the cross-section the smaller the overall resistance of that will be a determination for
your house into what kind of wire you're looking for wires in those common hardware stores are listed
in kind of these units over here this is AWG which refers to the American wire gauge
and it's simply a standardized method of calculating the diameters in cross-sectional areas of wires.
So American wire gauge is listed using these integer numbers.
There might be other ones here.
Number four refers to a wire that has a diameter of a little bit over five millimeters.
If you know the diameter you can calculate the cross-section as you increase the wire gauge number.
Look what happens to the diameter.
So a wire gauge that has a 20 listed under the American wire gauge is very very small compared to a
wire that has a 4.
So for a four you can handle a lot more amperage much higher values of the currents can go through the
four rather than 20 for example.
Again the resistance of any wire depends on what it's made from.
This will be copper for all of these different wires.
Depends on the length.
Well that'll depend on whatever application you need but it also depends on that cross-sectional area
and that's where this comes from.
OK.
So then the formula that links this number here for the wire gauge number that's the number and to the
actual diameter and millimeters is given by this equation actually I found this on the web.
I don't know exactly what the history is behind this.
It's kind of interesting I thought I'd write it down and I checked it out and it works for a lot of
those.
So anyway just a little bit of background that if you go into a hardware store typically the wires are
listed with this number this AWG number and that's all that it means it just refers to a particular
diameter.
And this is the relationship that links them together.