In this video,
we are going to use the creation and
amulation operator introduced
in the previous segment
to generate the energy spectrum
of the harmonic oscillator.
And this calculation as we
discussed is going to involve in
very important way calculating
various commutators of the operators.
So what we just proved in the previous
video was that the harmonic
oscillator Hamiltonian can be represented
as so, as the sum of two terms.
The first term is a dagger a, where
a dagger is this creation operator and
a is this an elation operator.
And also, there was a second
term which is proportional to
the commutator x of x and
p position and momentum.
And by the way, this commutator of x and
p is one of the so
called canonical commutation
relations in quantum mechanics.
And we actually should have discussed it
in more details earlier in the course but
better later than never.
So let me just first give you
this result for this commutator.
This commutator, in fact, is proportional
just to so called c number or
in the early quantum mechanical jargon or
in other words to the identity.
So in other words this commutator
effects and p is not an operator at all.
It's actually just a constant and
to see this we can go to
the position representation and
let see in position representation x times
p on the wave function side of x is
equal to x which is just
multiplication of greater followed by
minus i h bar over the x.
And so what we're going to
have is minus ih bar sin x.
Sin prime.
So this is the result of the action of
these two operators in this order.
Now if we consider a different order
of the operators, if we first put you
know x is going to act first and
then we're going to have the momentum.
So in this case we can write it as full,
it's going to be minus i h
bar g over the x times sum.
So in this case we have to use
the general to calculate the derivative
of both terms in this problems.
So it's going to involve
therefore minus i h bar
derivative of x is just one side
minus i h bar x sin prime and
now if we put everything together and
apply this commutator into
an arbitrary function psi of x,
so let me actually write it in red
if we now have commutator of x and
p sort of acting on a wave function sin.
So what it means is that we want to act by
the following operator
x p minus p x on psi.
And so we essentially have to
subtract result from this result and
so these two guys are going to
cancel each other out, and
the only thing which is going
to remain is plus i h bar si.
So action of the commutator of position
momentum on an arbiter function
psi of x is equivalent of multiplying
this function by i h bar.
Which is exactly the result that I
advertised in the beginning, and
this is again perhaps most of,
many of you already knew it so this is
again one of the canonical commutation
relations in quantum mechanics.
Now to continue this algebraic exercise
in calculating commutators, let me now
calculate a very useful commutator for the
namely the commutator of a and a dagger.
And this is another sub-canonical
commutation relation.
Let me write the result first.
I'm going to prove it and
we will see that the commutator of a and
a dagger is that is it
going to be equal to one.
So to prove this we use the definition of
a and a dagger from the previous video and
this permutation relation of position and
momentum.
So if we calculate a and a dagger,
the commutator of a and a dagger.
So we will have basically
two types of terms.
So here we're going to have m omega
2 h bar x plus ip 2m omega h bar,
and the second term in this
commutator is going to be
the same thing but
with a minus sign in front of the i.
So here it is.
And we'll see that we have
commutator of x and x.
We have commutator of p and p.
But of course the commutator of
an operator with itself is equal to zero
because of course for example x,
x minus xx is equal to zero, right.
So any operator can be used with itself.
So the only commutators
that are going to be non
trivial are going to be these cross
commutator of x and p and p and f.
And you can convince yourself
that the commutator of x and
p is of course equal to the minus
of the commutator of p and x.
Because we simply switched the order
in which the operators appear.
So therefore we can write it so
this result, so
we just go back to the blue fonts.
So it's going to be twice let's say
the commutator of this guy and this guy.
So m omega over 2h bar
from this term minus i 2m
omega h bar from this guy and
here we're going to have x and p.
But this is something we know,
we just calculated it.
So this is just commutation
relation position of momentum,
and it's equal to i a h bar.
And so indeed, if we put everything
together, we will see that m and
omega cancel here, so h bar and
h bar under the square root cancels here.
So, i times minus i gives us 1 and
2 over 2 is equal to 1.
So, all in all,
it's equal to 1 as advertised.
So, and this completes
a very important derivation,
namely the derivation of the following
identity and it's an operator identity.
It doesn't really matter
what representation we use,
what kind of methods we want to solve.
We have proven that the harmonic
oscillator Hamiltonian, so
I can actually switch to red, the harmonic
oscillator Hamiltonian as written here
can be represented as H omega a dagger a,
plus one half.
So this is from this
commutator where the a and
a dagger commute to one.
Or in other words when we see the so
this creation operators satisfy
the canonical commutation relations.
So the second term in this expression for
the Hamiltonian as we discussed
is just proportional to a number.
So it's not, it cannot possibly affect
the solution of the eigan value problem
namely if we want to solve the equation
h of si is equal to e of of si and
if si happens to be an eigan
function of a dagger a so
it would indeed be eigan function
of the whole Hamiltonian h.
With this slightly shifted energy,
because the identity operator
just reproduces the function.
So and therefore in order for
us to find the spectrum of
the operator h in order for
us to solve this eigenvalue problem and
find the eigen functions and eigen values
we have to focus on the eigan value
problem for this operator a dagger a.
And now comes a very important part
where we're going to generate the entire
energy spectrum of the Hamiltonian from
just a single eigen state of it or
more precisely from an eigen
state of this guy, a dagger a.
And to generate the spectrum, we would
need just two pieces of information.
The fact that we can represent
the Hamiltonian as so and
the commutation relations between the and
creation operators that we just derived.
So at this stage, let me assume that
I know an eigan state of this guy,
of a dagger a, and
let me call this eigan state,
lowercase n and the corresponding
eigan value will also be n.
So this would also, of course, imply
that the state n is also a solution to
the timing depend on showing your equation
for harmonic oscillator Hamiltonian, or
in other words it's an also an eigan
state of the Hamiltonian with the energy
omega n plus one half so
this is the energy of this state.
Now let us examine what happens
with this state we assumed
exists under the action of this
radiation and ventilation operators.
And of course we're very interested in,
is whether or not we can construct
new eigan states out of
an existing eigan state.
So first let me ast on this end by
the operator a dagger and let's see.
How this operator behaves with
regards to this guy, a dagger a.
So and, what we can do here,
we can take advantage of the economical
computation relations that we
derived in the previous slide.
And using this commutation relations
we can write a dagger, a a dagger
as one plus a dagger a.
So here we're going to have, so
basically we changed the order of
this to operators, so we're going to
have instead of a dagger a a dagger,
we're going to have a dagger one,
plus a dagger a.
[INAUDIBLE] n.
But, so this is just a number, and this
guy, we already know how it acts on n.
So by assumption,
this is an eigen state of a dagger a.
So therefore we can
write it as a dagger and
plus one and since this is an operator and
this is just a number,
we can exchange the order and
so we have n+1, a dagger n.
Which is exactly the same function
as in the left hand side.
So what we have proven
is that if n is an eigan
function of the operator, a dagger a and
consequently, if it's an eigan function
of the operator h, of the Hamiltonian,
then a dagger a is also an eigan function
but with an eigan value n plus 1.
So it traces the energy
off of the oscillator
by 1 energy quantum if
you want of h omega.
In a very similar way what we
can prove is the following.
So we can prove that if n is indeed
an eigan function of the Hamiltonian.
Then the action of
the amulation operator of n so
this function is also an eigan
function of the Hamiltonian.
But it is negative function with
smaller energy which sort of justifies
the terminology of this being
called an amulation operator.
So, while if were to repeat this
exercise that we just did for a dagger.
And if we were to apply a dagger a on this
function, we would see, and I'll leave
it for you as an exercise, that this guy
is also an eigen state of a dagger a.
But now with the smaller eigen value n-1.
And here I will have the same function.
So, by knowing an arbitrary Eigan
function of the Hamiltonian,
I can construct an infinite number,
what seems like an infinite number of
other Eigan functions with different
Eigan values by applying this creation and
annulation operation.
And so, we can also construct the spectrum
of the Hamiltonian, but we haven't yet
mastered the question of what n would be.
But, with a little bit of thinking,
we can convince ourselves that
n here must be an integer going
from zero up to infinity.
Zero, one, two, three, etc.
And a way to see this is essentially
via a sanity check if you want,
going back to the physical
problem we're trying to solve.
So remember that what we're doing here,
we're trying to find the energy levels
in this harmonic oscillator potential,
which is simply the parabolic
potential proportional to x squared.
So this v of x proportional to x squared.
Now, if we assume that we know in
certain Eigan function with an energy e
sub m as so, and this is let's say,
this corresponds to the state n then
by applying the creation operator,
a dagger, we can construct
a series of higher energy states.
So n+ 1, n + 2, n + 3, etc., and
there is no problem with that.
But also by applying e we
can lower the energy and
we can do so seemingly indefinitely.
But clearly this procedure has to stop
somewhere because we cannot go below 0.
So in other words,
we cannot go below the minimum
of the potential which
in this case is 0 and
this also implies that therefore,
this procedure of generating new eigen
functions using this annihilation
operator must terminate.
And so there must exist, therefore,
basically the ground state for
which the action of the annihilation
operator simply is equal to zero okay.
Or in other words so
this guy the vacuum state is the eigan
state of this guy 8 eigan b
with the eigan value being 0.
Or using this a result so
the energy of the ground state,
therefore, is equal to h
omega over 2 which is the so
called vacuum energy of
the harmonic pulsalator.
But this is really important and
this tells us that this is really
the property of the ground state okay.
And this is by the way the simplest way
to find an analytical expression for
the ground state.
We simply have to find the function
that is amulated by this operator.
And finding this function is
really the only remaining step
in completing the derivation.
Because here we have simply done
everything which needs to be done.
We found a series of energy levels.
So let me just write it again.
So E sub n, the energy levels of
the harmonic oscillators is equal to
h omega n+1/2 where n is equal to zero,
one, two, etc.
And this was constructed under
the assumption that a state exists.
But we haven't yet
shown that it is indeed so.
We haven't yet
constructed explicitly the eigenstate.
And this is really the last piece
of the puzzle that we will put
together in the next video,
where we also will summarize all the
findings about the harmonic oscillator.
And go a little closer to physical reality
from this abstract algebraic derivation
which, however, I hope shows
the power of this algebraic method.
So here again, we are solving initially
what looks like a differential equation.
But we get the results and
the quantization of the energies
without even calculating [INAUDIBLE].
It's all based on this
computation relations.
And, well, I find it very elegant.
And I hope that some of you
also enjoyed this derivation.
But there is more to do.