So in this last video of this lecture, I'm
going to derive the harmonic oscillator
wave functions, but I will do so without
writing down the Schrödinger Equation.
We will rely entirely on the solution that
algebraic solution I presented that took
advantage of the creation and annihilation
operator, it turns out that they are very
helpful in determining the explicit form
of the oscillator wave functions, si of x.
So before we write down these wave
functions we derive these wave functions
let me summarize what we know so
far which is actually a lot so
first of all we found a way to represent
the harmonic oscillator Hamiltonian
in this compact form in terms of
this creation and operators here.
And using the algebra or the computation
relations of these harmonic oscillator
operators, we derived the energy spectrum
of the oscillator, which has this form.
H omega n + one half.
Where n = zero, one, two, etc.
And again, I reiterate that this spectrum
is special in that the level spacing
between the neighboring
levels is always the same, so
it doesn't change as we
go higher up in energy.
So another thing we derived, and so
here I'm being a little more specific.
Is that given an arbitrary icon
state of the Hamiltonian with
a quantum number n as here,
so we can generate the entire
spectrum by applying the creation
operations and alienation
operators praise the energy
of the system by h omega.
So we go from n to n + 1.
And in the case of normalized
eigenfunctions there appears this
coefficient.
I haven't derived it in
the previous video, but
this is rather straightforward to do so
using the same methods.
And it's not in many textbooks so
I'm not going to spend time on that.
And likewise, given the same eigenstate n.
We can find the state
corresponding to a lower energy
with the one less quantum of h omega
by applying this alienation operators.
But what we don't know at this stage,
we don't know an example of any wave
function explicit wave-function.
So.
And
preferably we would like to see
a wave function that's in real space,
which is more intuitive that
other sort of, let's say
abstract spaces that we have been
operating with so far in this problem.
So in order to find the explicit form
of an eigenfunction, let me actually
focus on the ground state that is
the lowest energy state in our problem.
And this eigen state as we just discussed
in the previous video is characterized by
the fact that the action of this
a dagger e on it gives simply zero.
Gives us it's an eigen state
with an eigen value zero.
Or the eigen energy of this
state is equal to him over two.
So in other words, so
the angulation operator
acting on this state Must produce zero and
we can write this operator
explicitly in real space.
So we use the definition if
we want of this a as so and
here what I'm going to do is
I'm going to just write down
explicitly the form of the momentum
operator and position operator.
In real space the position
operator is really simple.
It's just a multiplication operator,
while the momentum operator as we know,
is just minus i h bar d over dx.
So therefore here I will just simply
remove the measuring constant.
So, all in all the.
Equation, so I should have written
perhaps here psi0 because I'm
specifically talking about the ground
state of the harmonic oscillator,
so explicitly the equation for this psi0,
therefore, becomes the following.
So we'll have this square root
of m omega over two h bar
x plus h over two
m omega h bar in the denominator d
over d x so which is coming
from this momentum operator.
And this acts on si not and
this whole thing must be equal to 0.
So here what I'm going to do, I'm going to
simplify this thing a little bit so
I'm going to put the square
root here on top.
I'm going to get rid of the factor two so
what I see here is that I can
introduce a new parameter.
But we call it x naught, which is
the square root of H divided by m omega.
And it appears both here and here.
And so this you can check that
the physical dimension
of the square root of H.
Over m Amanda is a length scale.
So it has a physical dimension of length.
So this in some sense a natural length
scale for the harmonic oscillator problem.
And so it is convenient therefore for
me to rewrite my equation as
above in the full length form.
I will write it as X over x not
plus x not times d over dx.
And this whole thing acts
on the wave function.
So it effects and we want to produce 0.
So now,
let me just rewrite this equation
in a slighty different form.
So I'm going to write dx
over dx sine prime, so
this is going to be sine prime and
put this guy in the left hand side.
So I'm going to have
minus x over x 0 squared
times sine and so I just want to
show this differential equation.
You can check, you can solve it formally
or you can just convince yourself
that the solution to this equation is Is
an exponential, it's Gaussian, basically.
Minus x squared over 2 x not squared.
So, and this is,
let me just put 0's in, in
here which correspond again to the ground
state and this is pretty much the result.
So, C here is a coefficient which
is determined by the normalization
of this wave function.
So again, this wave function describes
a particle in the ground state of
the harmonic oscillator and so
therefore, the total probability for
me of finding a particle somewhere
in space must be equal to one.
So therefore,
this integral from minus infinity
to plus infinity of sine r squared.
So I don't bother here with the complex
sines because everything is real so far.
So this must be equal to one.
And this gives me the value of the wave of
this coefficient that
multiplies this ground state.
A wave function so
let me just write it down.
So the C is equal to m omega over two,
I'm sorry,
pi that is pi h bar to the power 1/4th.
So this is the normalization coefficient.
But notice that we have found the ground
state wave function without actually
solving the Schroedinger equation.
We actually solved
a much simpler equation.
This first order differential equation
just by requiring that our wave
function is in state with
an value zero of this operator.
Okay, so this is great.
So we can now work with this
wave function if we want, but
what about the higher energy states?
So what we have just done
was we determined this guy,
the lowest energy state, so here what
I'm showing, let me just write down.
So this is, first of all, the potential
of this v of x if this is x, and
this levels here correspond to the energy
levels of the harmonic oscillator and
the lowest energy has the wave function
as so which is usual Gaussian.
So this is a typical Gaussian.
And high energy states have a more
complicated sort of texture.
So how do we get these eigan states?
Well, so here, we can take advantage
again of the creation operators now.
So as we discussed In the first
slide in this video so
the relationship between
the low energy states and
high energy states, so let's say
go from m to m + 1, we can simply
apply the creation
operator divided by n + 1.
Square root of n+1.
So if we apply it to our in state n,
we're going to get,
oops there's no square root here,
there's just n+1,
a normalized state that
corresponds to high energy.
And so what we can do,
we can apply this operators.
let's say to our ground state.
So we can apply this guy.
As many times as we want
to the ground state.
For instance,
we can generate this wave function So
by just applying this derivative
essentially to the Gaussian.
And this will produce certain coefficients
in front of the Gaussian and this,
well not coefficients, better to say
polynomials which are functions of x and
these guys, these polynomials they
are called Hermite Polynomials
which are special functions and
you can Google them or
you can look them up in Wikipedia and
in many books.
So this sort of, this solution using
the explicit form of the wave functions.
And the explicit form of
the Hermite polynomials appears in
pretty much any book on quantum physics.
And I'm not going to spend time
on discussing these details.
I will simply notice that you can
actually solve the Schrödinger equation
starting from this spectrum,
up to the ground state and
up to the excited state, using only
the creation and annihilation operators.
So there's very little inside that is
actually needed from the equation.
Which is in fact quite remarkable.
So in your homework, you will need to play
around a little bit with this equation.
And with this grounded state function and
I hope that you found this solution
illuminating and of course I encourage
you to look into the literature
to see more about this very important
problem of quantum physics.