In this introductory lecture, let me.
Set the stage, so to speak.
Let me give you an understanding of what the spirit is of this cause, and that stands behind my effort
to build a larger and more comprehensive introduction to quantum physics, because the problem is that
nowadays there are many there are already many popular books, textbooks and online courses teaching
your quantum physics for undergraduates and graduates.
There are many well written textbooks that elucidate every conceivable aspect of quantum mechanics.
Additionally, at the popular science level, a lot of books are no longer missing either.
So that's not a problem.
The point is, however, that on one side, they are treatises that require the reader to have a quite
good background in mathematics.
One cannot go very far with university level textbooks if the basics of at least calculus and linear
algebra, as well as many concepts from classical mechanics, are not reasonably grasped by the student.
Moreover, most of these sources are mainly concerned with the calculations and the purely technical
aspects of quantum mechanics.
While a deeper understanding of the more foundational implications are given on these kinds of tensions,
they usually tend to believe it is a waste of time.
He instead I will.
Proceed in this course in a very technical manner, but at the same time giving also a lot of attention
to more conceptual understanding of the philosophical implications of the nature of reality, so to
speak.
Contrary to popular belief, most physicists are not at all concerned with philosophical foundations
of quantum theory, but are much more focused on doing calculations, the process of which can obscure
and hide the deeper meaning and nature of the physical phenomenon.
The math describes there's somehow this misunderstanding that if you understand the math, the mathematical
concepts that describe reality, you have the most profound understanding of social reality.
And that's only partially true.
This is only one phase of the reality if you don't.
Dig deeper in the foundations of the things you are studying.
You still lack something on the other side.
That's also another point that of those who are looking for an introductory introduction, more at the
popular level.
There is nowadays also an extensive body of literature and online videos for the audience that does
not have the authentic background and does not intend to become a professional physicist.
However, unfortunately and here this is the other side of the coin.
Unfortunately, most of this popular science dwells on a surface or worse, falls into pseudoscientific
ruminations where the author wants to impress the audience with extravagant and misleading theories
or even false statements.
All of this is especially true when it comes to some of the philosophical aspects of quantum mechanics.
Most of these books, some written even by qualified and well-known physicist, reduce the concepts
to such a low level that paradoxically, they become unclear and difficult to understand just because
they treat their readers like babies.
Moreover, lots of bestselling books or science documentaries promote, so to speak.
To put it mildly, a highly dubious ideas and speculations that are backed by no evidence, sometimes
coming out with theories and ideas, selling them as verified scientific truths which are not and which
can't be verified experimentally, not even in principle.
And and also they try to sell you theories that already have not worked out.
This seemingly pedagogical approach of many popular vulgarised versions of quantum mechanics, in my
opinion, has done more harm than good and ended up in misleading the audience regarding the real nature
of the quantum world.
Therefore, there is a missing link between, on one side, the professional, fully mathematics, the
exposition of the principles of quantum mechanics, and that which is accessible to a broader audience,
but ends up leaving them with doubtful insights.
The net result is that nowadays we have a scientific community on one side that is busy with a plethora
of calculations, but has lost contact with a more profound understanding of its own foundations.
I that's what I say here.
Even physicists are too lost in their business in doing business as usual on the other side.
The public has in its mind a cartoon version of one of the most fascinating subjects of modern science.
But it is a cartoon version.
It is something that does not exist in reality.
Whereas with this course, I would like to bridge this gap between a merely mathematical exposition
and a too simplistic popular version of quantum physics by presenting an overview of the basic concepts
that stand behind non relativistic quantum theory, with an emphasis on experimental and technical facts
that should prepare you to correctly understand, first and foremost, its foundations with particular
attention paid to its philosophical implications.
However, this led me also to a dilemma.
Just because there are so many possible interpretations, it is impossible to create a full fledged
course and to write a book on quantum physics, taking a perfectly objective and agnostic stance, a
sort of agnostic in the sense of the interpretation of quantum physics interpretations I mean stance
while not letting one's own point of view, subjective preferences and interpretations slip through.
It's impossible.
The quantum world is so weird that everyone sees something different in it.
I will therefore not hide my preference for a quantum theory that is interpreted as a non-deterministic
theory without hidden variables, and that does not admit counterfactual definiteness as a logical inference
tool.
OK, if this statement has confused you, don't worry.
We will discuss this in detail during the lectures.
This might not satisfy those who support the opposite point of view, where quantum mechanics is envisaged
as a deterministic theory with hidden variables, especially those who defend the so-called liberally
born pilot wave theory or the many, many world interpretations interpretation of quantum physics of
huge Everet.
Yeah, those who know a bit of quantum physics know what I'm talking about.
If you don't understand it again, don't panic.
We will discuss this.
However, even though I will look upon the facts from the perspective of an non-deterministic, just
as every other physicist does from his or her own perspective, based on their subjective preferences
as well.
Whether they want to admit it or not, it's useless.
We all have our subjective approach.
This should not be of concern here, since what we will first and foremost lay out here are just the
facts, facts, the empirical and experimental phenomena.
Therefore, you won't lose anything because as I already said, it is just because you will learn these
basics that then.
You can take your own personal standpoint and embrace the interpretation you like.
So let us briefly now take a look at the main topics that will be covered in this course.
First of all, we will discuss the birth of quantum mechanics with a historical overview from the very
first conceptual foundation.
It begins with the all the controversy regarding whether light is a wave or if it is made of particles.
Is is it a wave or is it made of particles or are these waves made of particles or whatever?
This question seemed to receive a definite answer with Yang's double slit experiment and yet had to
be reviewed later when quantum physics was born.
Historically, the birth of quantum mechanics is identified with the intuition of Max Planck that explains
the so-called black body radiation by postulating that energy exists only in quantized forms.
Well, not every physicist, not every historian of science would agree with this, but that's what
the majority thinks.
And it is quite a bit arbitrary, a fixation point where to place the beginning of the history of something.
Normally it is done with the black body radiation, the discovery and the explanation of the black body
radiation curve by Max Planck.
This will be connected to the description of that unexpected phenomenon.
The photoelectric effect which led Einstein to introduce the notion of the photo that is the photon
as a light particle.
Then something will be said about Borse Atum, the famous principle of uncertainty of Heisenberg and
the even more famous wave particle duality and other notions which will follow us as necessary ingredients
to understand the basis of modern quantum theory, especially some emphasis will be given to the uncertainty
principle of Eisenbach.
The following chapters will address some important technicalities that are nonetheless interesting.
First, the quantum world of spinning particles is a short but intense description of the notion's,
like the spin of particles with a special emphasis on the stand stand Galla experiments what the spin
of a particle is.
Well, that will remain forever.
Probably a mystery because you should not imagine something spinning.
And yet it is the only way, as with which we, our human brain, our human mind can understand things
also in the microscopic world where we will discuss why this is not very good understanding of things
here.
We will focus on the aspects of quantum theory which sparked so many discussions and speculations among
science scientists and philosophers in the last decades.
The typical example of which is a famous thought experiment of Shogunate, Schrodinger said much more
will follow, such as the meaning of quantum superposition.
And yes, of course, we will speak a lot about the famous quantum entanglement and also whether empty
space is really empty.
According to quantum physics at zero point energy, the time and energy, uncertainty, relation and
other quantum effects like tunnel effect and so on.
I hope this video may become soon outdated because maybe at the time you are seeing this video or other
lectures that I did not mention here might have been added.
I will send to all the students, of course, and alert through and an announcement.
So check your settings to get the announcements eventually.
So this is enough as introduction, I would say.
Now it is time to go to the real stuff of this course.