So first question.
It looks like that we have a conceptual question and it says when a ball is thrown vertically upward,
it continues upward until it reaches a certain position and then it falls downward at the highest point.
What is the ball's velocity?
What is its acceleration?
OK, so can we just describe it for if we take an object, a ball, toss it upwards, it goes up, up,
up, up, up, up, up and then down, down, down, down, down, down, down, right.
So it goes up, pauses for a brief moment and then comes back down.
Right.
So what is the velocity.
At the highest point.
Zero meters per second.
And what is its acceleration?
Well.
For all freephone problems, including when you're throwing a ball up in the air, it's going to be
acted on by gravity.
So we're going to have the acceleration due to gravity acting on the object in all of its trajectory.
So at all points in its trajectory, it's going to be acting.
The force, acting on it will be the force to gravity, so therefore will have to accelerate acceleration
due to gravity acting on the object, which is negative nine point eight meters per second squared.
Well, wait a minute.
Wouldn't it be zero at this point?
Acceleration?
No, no, it won't be.
If it's got zero acceleration here, then and well, it wouldn't be falling back down because if it
goes up, up, up, up, up, and then there's no acceleration, no change over a certain amount of
time when just like, hover right there.
Would just stop and it would just hover, the reason why it comes back down is because of the acceleration
due to gravity at all points in the objects trajectory, it will be acted on by the acceleration due
to gravity, which is negative nine point eight meters per second squared.
OK, so for question to suppose you throw a ball straight up into the air at 20 meters per second,
describe the changes in velocity of the ball.
Describe the changes, that acceleration of the ball between which two seconds does the ball reach the
max height and hit the ground?
OK, so we know that initially.
What's the ball's velocity?
20 meters per second.
What's its acceleration, negative, nine point eight.
The acceleration throughout the entire bus trajectory will be negative, nine point eight, so the Hayden
what we're just going to throw this out, bam, all the way down, negative nine point eight.
So for every one second, the ball's velocity will change by negative nine point eight meters per second.
That's what this means again.
So after one second, we have what's the velocity?
It would just be 20 minus the nine point eight, which gives us ten point two.
OK, so after two seconds, what's the ball's velocity?
Well, ten point two minus nine point eight, which gives us zero point for.
OK, and after three seconds, well, we have zero point for my nine point eight, which gives us negative
nine point four minus another nine point eight negative nineteen point two, minus another nine point
eight.
Negative twenty nine minus.
And negative minus nine point eight will give us a negative thirty eight point eight.
OK, I noticed that these numbers are a little bit they're not as nice looking or as friendly looking
as what we had before when I was describing the objects trajectory.
So.
OK, it kind of looks like nice, the idea that, you know what, we must nine point eight and we got
myself another nine point eight over here.
We got nine point eight.
There must be another nine point eight.
We got zero.
And it looks a lot more symmetric over here.
Right, versus this.
It's not as like nice and friendly is walking, right?
Well, there's a reason for that.
I did hear when I started it, when I set up this problem, all I did here was I took nine point eight,
multiplied it by three and it got twenty nine point four.
I know that when I subtract nine point eight and I'll get nineteen point six and then subtract another
nine point eight, yet nine point eight and subtract another nine point eight had zero.
I can't multiply this by four or five or whatever the case is and I just made the numbers.
So it's super simple to actually see for a introduction.
I purposely did that, but so that was specifically for twenty nine point four.
Yes.
So that was specific for this number of twenty nine point four.
I said that this is our initial velocity and that's the logic behind it.
But now we're given an initial velocity of 20 meters per second.
OK, so this is just our situation right now.
We're just given this and now it's just a little bit messier looking.
But two questions.
Between, what, two seconds does Ball reach the max hype?
Well, what do we know about the max height?
Isn't the velocity just going to be zero, so between which two seconds?
Well, it reached Mexi.
Doesn't it make sense?
I would be between these two seconds max height, because this is in between, well, zero will be in
between here.
Maybe it's a little bit closer to two and then it will be two to three.
OK.
And between which two seconds does the ball hit the ground?
OK, maybe that's a little bit trickier, but don't we know that we see before that this is very symmetric?
So if I toss it up at twenty nine point four meters per second, once again, I'll hit the ground when
it's going to hit the ground at twenty nine point four meters per second, that's the velocity because
it's very symmetric path that takes so.
We know that the ball goes up at 20 meters per second.
You know what, it's going to come down and hit the ground at negative 20 meters per second, so it's
going to hit the ground between the fourth and the second.
Well, wait a minute.
How is it possible that actually reaches negative 29 and negative thirty thirty eight point eight meters
per second?
Well.
Maybe this is the situation for this problem, maybe we didn't actually toss it up and have it come
straight up and straight down, maybe what we did here was we were on a cliff and we tossed maybe we
were at the edge of a cliff and we decided to toss our object straight up.
And it comes down now that this is the level of the ground over here.
So it might have had not it reached the point of the velocity over here and zero meters per second and
then down over here, actually, I guess if this is the height that we're throwing it at now makes more
sense that it would be.
Negative 20 meters per second here and then over here, maybe we'll actually see that this is when it
reaches the 29 or negative 29 meters per second over here.
So and what it's just one of those situations where maybe we toss it up and it came down farther, we're
not really going to see that too much in this course.
Maybe your professor or your teacher, Mike Trickey, a little bit on something like that.
But just know the idea that the objects trajectory is very symmetric.
What you toss it at the initial velocity over here, it's going to equal to the the same velocity at
the same height.