So attached to this video is worksheet number three, print this out, download this and print it out,
and these are going to be your practice problems.
So also attached to this video will be an answer key.
Look at the answer key only after you're done trying some of these problems out.
So the first set of problems will be when the object is being dropped and we come down over here.
You know what it looks like that there's one where the object is being thrown downwards.
OK, so we are giving an initial velocity.
And then there is situations where we're throwing that object upwards.
And there you go.
So there's a there's a good chunk of problems in here for you to try out.
Like I said before, if you're stumbling on these at all whatsoever, just know that there's the answer
key for you.
So, yeah, good luck on this.
And yeah, I wish you the best of luck.