So from number one, keep in mind that these are all going to be problems where the object is being
dropped.
Notice how I said that they're being dropped, they're not being thrown upwards, not they're not being
thrown downwards.
And we'll actually see that these these problems over here.
So problem number one, your sister drops your house keys down to you from the second floor window if
you catch them four point three meters from where your sister dropped them.
What is the velocity of the case when you catch them?
OK, so it's describing here that your sister is dropping keys out of a window and they're dropping
for a total of four point three meters.
And you're being asked what is the velocity when you catch them?
Well, I'm just going to do here is I'm just gonna draw a picture.
Does it really matter that they're being dropped out of a window?
Does it really matter that they're being caught and not actually hitting the ground?
No, we just know that they're dropping for a total of four point three meters.
So essentially, what do we have here?
We have an object.
It's going to be dropping for a total of four point three meters.
I know that was shown here that's hitting the ground, but it doesn't matter if they're being caught
or if they're hitting the ground.
We know that they're dropping for a total of four point three meters and that's what matters.
OK, so this being the case.
Just think about the situation, your sister, what is she doing?
She's dropping keys and they're dropping for a total of four point three meters.
We're trying to find out the velocity of the keys.
When you catch them, they're going to hit your hand or hit the ground at a certain velocity.
That's the velocity that we're trying to calculate here.
So let's pull out some given information.
What would you say is the initial height of the object?
Well, we're given that that's given information here.
It's four point three.
And what would you say is the final height of the object?
Well, it's being called it's hitting the ground, so it's dropping for a total of four point three
metres, we could say that the final height is zero.
Let's come over here.
Let's just start writing this in.
What is the initial velocity, am I throwing this case up and my throwing them down, or am I just letting
go in them and letting them drop?
Initial velocity is zero meters per second.
What's the final velocity?
Oh, isn't that what we're trying to find?
What is the acceleration of the object once again, four objects are in freefall.
It's going to be a negative nine point eight meters per second squared.
That's acceleration due to gravity.
And are we given anything about time?
Are we being told anything about time?
No.
Right.
Oh, so we're going to treat this just like we actually treat the previous problems.
So we're going to say, what do I not care about time?
I'm just going to come back over here and let's look through this.
I'm going to tell you right off the bat, I don't think that I actually have any problems for Free-Fall
that actually have to do with average velocity.
So I'm just going to erase these two equations right here.
It's going to be these four equations that were going to be mainly dealing with now what's in what I
say, the variable that we simply just don't care about is going to be our time.
Let's come through here.
Let's find all the equations I have to do with time and exclude them.
So we have time right here.
OK, that's an equation that we're not interested in coming over here.
Oh, we have time right there.
OK, so I'm not interested in this one.
What about this one?
We have time here and we have time there.
So definitely not going to be using this one.
And do we have time in this equation?
Nope.
OK, so we're going to be using the equation number six.
Make sure that you write it out correctly.
And did I do that correct?
Let's just double check here.
And that was good.
OK, so now let's plug in our information so we have V F squared is equal to V.I. squared, which is
zero squared, 020 is zero zero zero.
So that's not going to have any sort of impact two times our negative nine point eight.
And we have our final height, which is zero minus our initial height, which is four point three.
OK, so this is zero squared, zero two zero zero zero.
So that's not going to have any sort of impact on our equation.
We have this zero over here and zero minus four point three.
Or we could actually just call this a minus four point three and negative four point three.
They're the same thing.
It doesn't really matter.
So let's just get rid of this zero over here and notice here that what we have is two times well, it's
a positive two times, nine point eight times a negative four point three.
So we have a positive times, a negative times, a negative.
This should result in a positive answer in the calculator right now.
And we get eighty four point two eight.
That's equal to the F squared.
I don't care what V of squared is equal to.
I want to know what our final velocity is equal to.
So how do we get rid of the squared, take the square root of both sides of the equation and we get
the F is equal to nine point two metres per second.
Hey, wait a minute.
The answer over here is telling us it's negative nine point two meters per second.
The calculator, when you take the square root of this, it will not give you a negative answer.
It's going to give you the positive version.
So make sure that you do include the negative to account for the direction.