But let's hop into problem number two, one of the rides at an amusement park falls freely for one point
five seconds after starting from rest a what does its velocity at the end of the one point five seconds
be?
How far does it fall?
OK, so let's just reread this.
We have a amusement park ride.
It's fun freely for one point five seconds after starting from rest.
Oh, wow, that's the only information we have right now, so let's do our diagram so we have an object.
What does it do?
It's falling to the ground.
I can actually just do this tick marks right here that indicate that that's the ground.
And what is it doing, this is the objects trajectory and it is just falling.
We're not given the initial height of this object and we don't even know that the final height is zero,
huh?
OK, so it doesn't say that the object hits the ground, right?
Oh, boy.
OK, so what we can actually say here is this.
Perspective number two, we could say that the initial height.
Is zero.
And it's asking, how far does it fall?
So once again, I looked at like looked at this like this is perspective one where you are given a initial
perspective to where you're not given an initial height.
You could just actually define that the initial size zero and come fall for a certain amount.
This will now be a negative number.
OK, so our initial height is going to be zero.
Finally, is what we're trying to find initial velocity, hey, are we throwing this object up or are
we throwing it down?
No, it's saying that's freely going to be falling.
So the initial velocity is going to be zero meters per second.
First question asks, what is its velocity at the end of the one point five seconds?
So we're actually going to be finding not just one thing, but we're going to be finding two.
And once again, what is the acceleration of this freely falling object, negative, nine point eight
meters per second squared, that's acceleration due to gravity.
And our time here is one point five seconds.
OK, so once again, we're going to be finding two things.
So let's find the final velocity first.
So if we're trying to find this, what we're going to do here is say, hey, Noah, I don't care what
our final height is.
So this is going to be the thing that we don't care about first.
And then when we're trying to find out the final height, what we're going to say is, hey, and what
I don't care about what this is equal to.
And that's the way that we're going to be determining which equations to be using.
So to find our final velocity, we're going to say to ourselves, I don't care what the final height
is of the object, I'm just going to race this diagram.
OK, so coming over here, OK, so where do we have a final.
Oh, so do we have final height over here.
Wyeth now.
OK, we have Wyeth over here.
So I'm going to say I don't care about this one.
We have Wyeth right over here.
And we have Wyeth right here, so these ones won't help us out finding our final velocity.
But this one, well, so let's write that down.
OK, so that will help us finding out our final velocity, so let's do that first, let's just plug
this in and go from there.
OK, so Veth is equal to V.I., which is zero plus our negative nine point eight times our time, which
is one point five.
And when we play this into our calculator, we see that this zero provides no value.
So we could get rid of this.
We have a positive, we have a negative nine point eight times a positive one point five.
Would that result in a negative answer?
And when we play this in the calculator, we will get our answer of fourteen point seven metres per
second.
What does that negative represent, the idea that the object is being dropped and we know that velocities
are vectors, so therefore it does have to do with both a magnitude and our direction.
OK, well, that's for VCF, so we just did the problem is done.
What about Palm Bay?
How far does it fall?
OK, so we want to find out what our final height is going to be.
So therefore, let's not include this answer.
When we're trying to check this out, we're going to say that we don't care about this right now.
We could use this answer.
But the thing is, though, is that I don't want to use something that we calculated in order to calculate
out the next step.
I'd rather just use our given information if we got this wrong, if we actually did anything wrong here,
if we forgot to include our negative here, we will get this answer wrong right here.
So therefore, I don't want to use this value.
So coming into here.
OK, so we're going to go through this right now and say the values that we don't care about is Veth.
So coming through here we have the effort there.
That's not going to help us find our final height.
This over here.
We have the math right there.
Don't care about this one.
Yes.
Oh, we don't have the ethen here, but we do have VCF over here.
Process of elimination is great and there we go.
So we're just going to use equation number five, make sure that you actually write this all correct,
some mistake.
I do see what this this equation is for getting this squared right here.
OK, so we have a formula once again, just double double check to see that you have the formula right
now.
Correct.
And I believe that we do.
So once again, we're trying to find out what our our life is equal to.
One thing that's great is that it's very soldat for Wyeth.
So once we actually plug in these numbers right here, we could just toss this in the calculator and
get our answer.
OK, so we have this zero over here that's not going to provide any sort of value and we have zero times
one point five a no, that's not going to provide any value whatsoever.
So we have this positive one 1/2 times in negative nine point eight times, one point five squared Hazlitt's
negative times.
The positives will actually result in a negative answer.
So we have our Wyeth tossing this in the calculator.
We will get our answer of eleven point zero three meters.
And we should be including the negative here being that that's how much it drops, so I should really
just include that in there as well.
So that's how that's how far this object drops.
We do.
So think about this once again.
We have an amusement park ride that's really falling for one point five seconds.
How far does it fall?
It falls eleven point three meters.