So let's get into problem number for a student drops a ball from a window three point five meters above
the sidewalk, how fast and how fast is it moving when it hits the sidewalk?
OK, you could you could feel free to pause this video, try this problem on your own.
Don't worry if you feel like, hey, and what we're down to the last problem, this is all the practice
you're give me now.
I have more practice problems for you.
So don't think that you're being cheated out on any sort of practice.
I will have that for yourself.
All right.
So post this video, try it on your own, unpause the video and let's do it together, OK?
So once again, that student is dropping a ball from a window three point five meters high.
How fast is it moving?
OK, so where the ball?
When it hits the sidewalk.
OK, so our indicator that it's actually going to be hitting the ground, good.
OK, so what's our initial height of the object?
What's the final flight?
What's this right this in?
What's our initial velocity?
Are we throwing the ball up or we throw it down or are we just letting go?
Are we trying to find out how fast is the ball moving when it hits the sidewalk?
OK, so this is what we're going to be looking for and what is our acceleration due to gravity?
And does it say anything about time?
Nope, and it's not I mean, asking about time.
So this is going to be the variable that we don't care about.
So when we come over here, we're going to be looking for our Delta T. and saying, hey, look, I don't
care about you coming over here.
There it is right there.
I don't care about you.
What's your skin?
We got Delta T. right there.
And we have Delta T over here as well.
So we don't care about you.
And we don't have Delta team this formula, so we could actually be using this to find our final velocity
and which is nice is once again final velocity is on the left hand side of the equation by itself already.
So that's going to be super simple for us to calculate the S1.
OK, once again, make sure that you wrote down the formula correct, and I think that we got that looking
good.
OK, so let's plug in right now.
OK, this isn't going to do anything for us, this isn't going to be F squared is equal to.
So we have a positive two times and negative nine point eight times, a negative three point five.
So we have these two negatives.
They're being multiplied to each other.
So we're going to expect a positive value right now, OK?
And that's what the F squared is equal to.
We don't care what the F squared is equal to.
We want.
So how do we get rid of the square?
Do we take the square root of both sides of the equation?
Yeah.
Eight point two eight.
I'm just going to say eight point to eight.
Meters per second.
Oh, wait a minute, though, what is the object doing?
It's falling.
Downwards, right, so let's indicate that with a negative sign right there, and that is our final
answer.