Hello everyone,
welcome back to Exploring Quantum Physics.
I'm Charles Clark.
And in this part of the lecture, we're
going to take a venture into the realm of
perturbation theory, very powerful tool.
And particularly,
we're going to look at it in
the context of understanding electrical
properties of neutral matter.
Okay, just to remind you,
we're looking at the properties of
a sort of a test case potassium rubidium
molecule, which is of interest in
multiple common [INAUDIBLE] of physics.
And at the end of the previous part,
we got to the realization that,
no, the ground rotational
state of the molecule,
its dipole moment, is oriented randomly.
And so there's no net dipole moment,
we want to orient it.
And how do we do that?
Well, we're going to apply
an electric field to the system and
see what changes that causes according
to the picture of quantum mechanics.
The tool we're going to use is
called perturbation theory.
It's a very powerful tool.
Actually, in the form that we use it now,
it was original developed by Schrodinger.
At least, it was used in almost the very
same form that we use it today in his
early papers on the hydrogen atom, in
which he deduces not just the spectrum of
a hydrogen atom, but the response of
that spectrum to an electric field.
It's a very versatile and
powerful tool, of quantum theory, and
also if you do a search on the phrase
perturbation theory, you'll find that
is a very powerful to applied mathematical
analysis in a more general context.
So I think the lessons that you learn from
working examples in perturbation theory
are widely useful no matter what
your analytical interests are,
because here's the basic idea.
Let's suppose that we're
solving an equation
of promotion of a very complex form
perhaps is given by a Hamiltonian
which has a lot of complexity and
we don’t know how to solve the equation.
So the idea of perturbation theory is,
that you try to find
an approximation to that
real Hamiltonian in terms of a Hamiltonian
whose properties you know how to solve.
And where the equations
of motion that you're really
interested in can be reached
To some degree by an expansion
in a small parameter.
And so the idea is that you
take a known Hamiltonian and its spectrum.
And then you seek to develop,
in a systematic way, the description
of the new equations of motion.
In terms of the power series
in a set of functions that
can be computed iteratively.
I should say that very often it is,
it's not necessary
to go much higher than 1 or
2 in this series in order to.
Actually learn very useful things.
So we're going to work a couple examples.
Here's the basic formulas, and as I showed
you before, we say, well, the Hamiltonian
consists of the two part,
the known one and then something else.
We're now going to focus on solving
the time-independent Schrodinger
equation by this technique.
So we want to find the energy associated
with this composite Hamiltonian.
Now we do that by expanding both
the wave function psi here and
the energy E in terms of
a formal power series in lambda.
And then we just plug these two
expressions back into the equation and
we match the power supply
in a setting order.
So again I hope you can see that, so
we have H naught plus lambda v naught
times psi naught plus
lambda psi 1 plus etc etc,
equals E naught, plus lambda E 1 plus
etc psi 0 plus lambda psi 1 etc.
So let's match the powers
of lambda to the 0.
So that means we take h0
times psi 0 from here.
There's no other match and then on
the other side we have E on sign on there.
So let's just run a reality check and
see if that makes sense to you.
So I hope your persuaded by
looking at it that at least this
first equation makes a lot
of sense because it just
gives one back the spectrum which
one presumably knows how to control.
Well now, let's see, how do we go up?
Let's go to the next order.
So, we're just taking powers of
lambda through the 1 on each side.
Lambda the 1, so from the left hand side,
that's h0 times psi 1 + V
times psi 0 = E0 times psi 1 and
then E1 times psi 0.
Okay, well, so far there's not much,
not much going on just it's symbolism so
now let's,
what we do now is we
take the matrix element,
the bra of size zero with
respect of this equation.
So zero on this, on both sides.
And so we now get this expression here and
I hope it's clear to you that
when we look at this term here.
That's exactly equal to this term by
the formation conjugation process.
So, we can drop these two terms.
And then we get this simple equation for
the first order energy correction.
It's just the expectation value of
the potential over the 0 wave function.
My good friend and colleague,
Mark Edwards, call this
the most used equation in quantum theory
which I think very well may be right.
It's not the most written
equation quantum theory,
which is the Schrodinger equation,
but this is one which is probably
solved more often than anything
else because it really gives one
a very good guidance at an early
stage on what you have to do.
And it really just requires taking
an integral of something rather
than solving a spectral problem.
So we're going to do some
of that solving ourselves.
Okay, so I guess you can see that there's
some sense that you get in making some,
looking at simple considerations
of standard problems when,
the trivial sort of attempts that we
apply we see the perturbation theory.
Describes that case well.
Okay, so now, we're going to go to
the real problem, which is to try and
understand the properties of
a rotating polar molecule
in the presence of an electric field.
So here's our Hamiltonian you see.
It's the original rotational
Hamiltonian with another term which
is the interaction of an electric dipole
moment, d, with the electric field.
This is the interaction from
classical electrostatics and so
we can write this in simply in
polar coordinates in this way.
And now I'm using these temperature
equivalents just for convenience.
So there's a sort of, keep in mind this is
just a temperature equivalent saying well,
you have an energy and
you divide it by both cost and
that gives a temperature but it does
describe the scale in a useful way.
As you may recall, this equivalent
temperature of the rotational motion in
the ground state is something like
55 millielectron, millikelvin.
And now with using a sort of
a dimensionalist parameter which
is a field strength of 1 volt per meter,
then there's an equivalent electrical
energy, which it turns out is very small
compared to the rotational energy.
So this is a sign that
a perturbation theoretic approach
will be useful in this problem because we
are using it to treat something that's
small compared to the underlying
rotational motion, the molecule.
And you might well imagine
from a physical standpoint.
If you have a molecule that's
freely rotating and you're just,
you just have a small break to
apply to try to slow it down.
That when that break is weak,
it's not going to be that effective.
So here we go on our way
to solving this problem.
We have the E0 vanishes,
here's the 0th order.
Wave function sign on, it's just
the ground state of rotating molecule.
So now we're going to evaluate the most
used equation in quantum physics,
the first order energy It's
the expectation value potential over
the ground state wave function.
And now you see this is just,
the potential is just the cosine of
the angle with respect to the axes.
So our expectation value takes this form.
Now, I hope that through the exercises
that you've done throughout this course,
you've learned that sometimes,
you don't actually need to go through
the mechanics of evaluating integral.
It vanishes because of symmetry reason,
and this equals 0 for
a very simple reason and that is, it's
an integral over all space of the cosine
of an angle with respect to some axis.
The cosine of this angle here and
well obviously the cosine
of that angle whatever point you
have here there's another point
where the cosine has it an ultimate
sign so this vanishes by symmetry
Which is quite a common
occurrence when evaluating first
order energy corrections of this type,
as we'll see.