Hello everyone.
Welcome back to Exploring Quantum Physics.
I'm Charles Clark.
In this final part of the lecture we're
going to look at the polarizability of
the hydrogen atom.
A system in which electron and
an ion move freely,
according to their own equations of
motion in three dimensional space,
much richer system you might think
than the diatomic polar molecule
which can be effectively treated as
a rigid rotator, but as we'll see,
the concepts that were developed
in of course the molecule,
apply as well to the richer
case of the atom.
I might just mention, parenthetically,
I eluded to some of my own scientific
work in a previous lecture.
I am very interested in the effects of
electric and magnetic fields on matter.
This type of approach,
as applied to the hydrogen atom,
is very similar to research
grade work that is
done in computing the black body radiation
shifts of optical atomic clocks.
So we're going to go
through a calculation which
has to do with finding the response
of an atom to an electric field.
It's convenient in these cases
to the work in the CGS units,
just because as you'll see, there's a lot
of complicated factors floating around and
that simplifies the book keeping.
We're going to look at the general
problem of a hydrogen-like ion,
which might involve an electron and
a nucleus, it might involve
an antiproton and a nucleus, it might
involve an electron and a positron.
The nucleus has a charge of Z times Z,
which Z is conventionally
the atomic number.
The electron nucleus
distance is given by r.
We retain the reduced mass so
that this formula can be used
to describe species other than
electrons found in nuclei.
And we're going to do perturbation theory,
just of the very same type that we
applied in the diatomic polar molecule.
Slight difference here for
notational convenience, I'm writing this,
the typical conventionally,
is H naught plus lambda V for
the Hamiltonian, it's what's being solved.
So I'm just going to use F,
as the field strength,
is equivalent to lambda, and
that means that the perturbation
here is just given in
terms of the unit vector,
the scale of the product of the unit
vector with the radius times the charge.
That half means unit vector now.
So here is the Hamiltonian for
the hydrogen atom that
we've talked about before.
Here is an expression for
the ground state energy,
E naught which is just
the Rydberg formula,
but with finite mass and
the square of a nuclear charge.
And then here is a wave function that
was introduced in a previous lecture.
This time it's correctly normalized.
I don't know why I had the wrong
expression before, but
this is the normalized ground state
wave function of a hydrogenic ion.
Where this length scale,
this, it's very close.
If mu were the electron mass and
Z would equal the one,
this would be the vor radius, a naught.
But now,
we'd retain it as general form so that we
can deal with particles of arbitrary
mass and of arbitrary nuclear charge.
So there's a lot of symbols
floating around here and
the mathematics does get fairly involved.
But we're going to take a fairly high
level view, and I'll show you what you
need to do to actually perform
the calculations in detail, should you so
choose.
Now as usual, the very first thing we do,
because all of the ingredients are laid
out, so
we calculate the first order energy.
I always love doing this because usually
it's the easiest step in the problem and
leads to useful results.
So here, I've written it out in its full
glory, the first order energy which is
just the expectation value
of the perturbing potential
over the square density
of the wave function.
Now I would like you to look at that and
see if you come up with any easy
ways of performing that integral.
Okay, I hope that you saw that.
Again, this is an interval
that vanishes by symmetry.
If you started to write this out and
try to evaluate it by long
hand without noticing
the essential symmetry property,
it could be laborious.
And I'd just emphasize that many of them,
basically,
all of the electrical field problems that
one encounters in quantum mechanics,
tend to have this generic feature.
In other words,
if you have this is potential,
this interaction potential, v,
is odd under parity.
If you invert the coordinates,
the potential changes sign, and so
that if you're integrating that
over a symmetric density,
the integral necessarily vanishes.
Okay, well, we got that easy part
of the calculation out of the way,
the determination of
the first order energy.
So now we come to what is really
the most difficult and that is
the solution of this equation, the first
order equation for the wave function.
This is more complicated than the one
that we had for the diatomic molecule.
Because, see here is
the usual left-hand side,
which has a Hamiltonian operator
that's got Laplacian and
coordinate function in it.
And then on the right-hand side, I guess
you can see the crux of the issue now, is
that we have two variables,
the radius and the angle.
In the diatomic molecule,
we didn't have the degree of freedom and
radial coordinate.
This makes the equation much more complex,
but there is a saving factor, again,
associated with the angular momentum.
So recall that one again, the H naught is
the Hamiltonian for the hydrogen atom.
It's completely, spherically symmetric and
it is being applied to thus psi 1,
and the result is something
that's asymmetric, so
I emphasize that means that
the asymmetry is present in psi 1.
It's revealed by the action of h naught,
but it is not created by it.
So that means we know that psi
1 has to have this particular,
again this is a y 1,
0 harmonic embedded in it,
and if you go back and
look at the Hamiltonian,
you'll see that there's
a del squared function
of which the cosine
theta is an Eigenvalue,
and then also this part here.
The fact that the cosine theta is
accompanied by a single power of r,
guarantees that the behavior
of this function near
the origin will be consistent
with this powerful property,
the angular momentum operator in that
the angular momentum completely dominates
the motion of the particle at very small
distances from the coordinate of origin.
So whenever you see
the cosine theta at small r,
this, what's called characteristic value
of the radius, must also be present.
Now this is more like a matter
of experience because
of the long range profile
of an exponential decay,
you need to have that present
in the envelope of psi 1,
and then the remaining part is
a radial function in order to keep
the angular character
consistent with the cosine.
So this is the description
of the analytical steps
that are needed to get
an appropriate form of the solution.
Now the determination
of f is another matter,
which we'll discuss on the next slide.
So again, here's the analytic
supposition that we wrote down for
the first order wave function and
with this in hand,
it's not difficult to show
that f must satisfy, but
is proportional to this rather
simple linear function.
Again, I think those of you
who like working out real
quantum mechanics problems,
this is perhaps the most
involved one that has been
offered during this course.
And perhaps you can get a glimpse of
that from this crazy looking solution.
Yes, that is a power of h bar
to the 6th and the 6th power of
the electric charge and
the third power of the reduced mass.
I think that's probably more analytically
interesting than many of the results
that you've seen so far.
This does have a dimension of volume.
Welcome to check that,
keeping mind that e is in the CGS system.
So in other words e squared over
r has the dimensions of energy.
Now there is something I want
to draw your attention to.
It's the behavior of the polarizability of
hydrogen as the plot constant goes to 0.
I mean, as if we could set
the plot at constant 0, but
this is the limit of classical mechanics.
And so what you see is that, in this
limit, the polarizability goes to 0.
So in other words in a classical world,
the hydrogen atom would not
respond to an electric field at all,
it'd just be too tightly bound.
And this is consistent, I think,
with the idea that you'd have in
the Bohr model that if the quantum of
action plots constant were smaller,
the radius of the atom would shrink and
shrink and shrink and
the electron would become so tight,
would become ever more tightly bound,
the polarizability would go to 0.
So this shows, really, the opposite effect
in the transition of the classical limit
that we saw for the polar molecule.
And one of the home work problems this
week, which was actually suggested by one
of the students, or at least I interpreted
their remarks as a suggestion,
shows, well I don't want to reveal the
answer, but just say, the behavior of that
problem, which is relevant to trapping of
atoms in the Earth's gravitational field
is, I'll just say, not exactly
the same as either of these two cases.
Okay, so that's a good introduction
to perturbation theory.
I realize it's brief and
of an overview nature, but
we've used it to attack some real
problems of atomic and molecular physics.
I hope that gives you
the confidence that you can go and
use it on the homework problem and
in other things that you're interested in.