Attached to this video, there is a document and that document is basically just this worksheet over
here, I cannot stress enough that the person who will practice these problems and actually do these
problems as opposed to just watching the video, that person will actually see it a lot more than if
you're just watching these videos.
So I highly encourage you to actually just practice these.
And kind of if you're not able to do this on your own, that's OK.
As a matter of fact, these first four you might be able to do on your own.
But then once you actually scroll down a little bit more, we actually do have these more complex problems,
these multisite problems over here.
And then it comes down and we actually get into a lot more complex problems.
So these first four problems you might be able to do on your own.
If not, that's OK.
We're actually just going to go through these.
But once again, I highly suggest that you download this document, print it out and try it with me,
OK?
And I will give you time to try out some of these problems on your own.
So don't worry about that.
I fully consider the idea that you need to practice this on your own, so I will give you enough practice
to do that.