OK, so now we're ready for these multistep problems once again, I'm actually going give you the opportunity
to do these problems on your own.
But for right now, ideally, you're actually going to be writing these notes with me and we're just
going to be doing them together.
So once again, these do we actually get a little bit more complex?
But hopefully they won't be complicated because I'm going to be explaining them to you as efficiently
and as clearly as possible.
So let's get to the first one.
And I think that the first one over here is actually probably like the nicest being that we are going
from days to minutes.
And these are like units that you're probably comfortable with.
OK, so let's get into this.
So we have three days and once again, we're going to convert converting our units.
So we already know that, hey, what we are going to be canceling our units.
So we have days on the top and we have days on the bottom over here.
And so we're just going to be even though these problems are multistep, we're just going to be using
the same exact principles as we were using before.
So let's keep in mind that we're going from days to minutes.
Let's look at these over here.
Obviously, we don't want to use any of these because these are dealing with length and not time.
And down here, we actually do have our units of that deal with time.
So I'm actually just noticing right now I'm missing the idea that there are three hundred sixty five
point two five days.
Is equal to one year, I'm sorry about that, but either way, though, we do see that we have days
over here and we have days over here.
So which one of these actually does it make more sense to go to, considering the idea that we're going
from days to minutes?
Does it make sense for us to go from these two years or does it make sense for us to go from days to
hours?
And let's think about this.
So obviously this if we go to hours, we're getting smaller and closer to minutes rather than years,
which is actually getting bigger and farther away from Mezze.
So let's just, I guess, trust me on this and we're going get closer to our minutes by going to hours.
So how many days is it?
Oh, it's just the one day and I know I have plural all over here, but whatever that doesn't really
matter is equal to what.
Oh, that's equal to 24.
Oh.
Yes.
24 hours, OK, so once again, our units do cancel out, so our days will cancel out, leaving us with
hours, but we don't want ours, we want minutes.
So this is where the multistep actually comes in.
What we're going to do here is actually multiply this by another conversion unit so we have ours and
we won't get to minutes.
So which one of these actually does have to do with both hours and minutes or election gets closer to
minutes?
So we have here oh, we have ours right here and we have ours right here.
So these two both have to do with ours.
But we are used this one over here.
And it wouldn't really make sense for us to actually use that again, because we would go from hours
to days.
That really doesn't make much sense.
So we do have hours and minutes over here and our goal is to actually get to a number of minutes.
So it does make sense that we that we would use up once again.
We do want our units to cancel out.
So we have ours up here on the top and our numerator.
So therefore we want ours in the bottom, in our denominator for them to be able to cancel out.
So how many hours is it?
Oh, it's one hour is equal to what?
It's equal to 60 Minutes.
OK, so our hours cancel out, leaving us with minutes, oh, wait a minute, look at this.
We want minutes over here and we have minutes over here.
That's once again our indicator to us, the idea that we're actually dealing with this problem.
So we plug this into the calculator and we get our answer.
So we just multiply our numerators once again.
That would actually just be our three times 24 times 60.
Those are all the numerators.
Divide that by all of our denominators, which is one times, one times at one.
And once we play this in the calculator, we'll get the answer of four thousand three hundred twenty
and the units that we have.
Is minutes.
OK, so just basically saying that three days is equal to four thousand three hundred twenty minutes,
and that's the way that we do that problem.
OK, so let's go on to the next one.
You know what?
Let's go into problem number.
Seven.
So we have ten point five miles.
To number of kilometres or kilometers, however, you can't pronounce it, so we have ten point five
miles.
Once again, Miles is just am I and not am.
So we're not going to be confusing em with my.
All right, so we have our miles on the top, so therefore right off the bat we are in now because we're
doing the calculation now, we want miles in the bottom.
And where do we actually have our miles?
Oh, once again, we actually do have it over here.
And that's the only spot where we actually do have our miles.
So it's one mile is equal to 4000, 280 feet.
And we're basically being out there.
That's the only one that has to do with Miles, where we're we're stuck with actually using this fact
over here.
So that's what we're going to use.
Once again, our units you can't cancel out and we're left with feet.
The only thing is, though, is that we don't want that.
We want our kilometres.
So we're going to have to do another conversion factor and for the time, draw our fashion line.
We're going to have our feet down here.
And what makes the most sense now?
So we have feet over here.
We have feet.
We have the this one doesn't make sense the speed that we just use that one.
So we could cross that one out already.
And we have feet over here.
Those are the only ones that have to do with feet.
Let's keep in mind once again, we want to get to kilometres.
Does it make sense that for us to go from feet to inches, feet to yards or feet to meters, once again,
we want to get to Kyllo meters?
So hopefully you're saying to yourself, well, maybe it makes sense for us to go from feet two meters
and use this one over here, and that's what we'll do.
So we have how many feet?
Oh, it's three point twenty eight feet is equal to, what, one meter?
Once again, our feet will cancel out.
OK, let's once again our feet will cancel out, leaving us with meters.
The only thing is though is that we don't want meters.
We won't kill meters.
So that's our indicator to us that we are still not done with this problem.
So what do we do?
We do another conversion factor.
What do we have in the bottom over here meters?
Because we know that the two of them will cancel each other out.
We're going to come back over here and look for meters.
Where do we have meters?
Once again, Emmet's miles.
So that's not what we're dealing with.
We have meters over here, but we just use this conversion factor so it doesn't make sense for us to
be using it.
Let's continue down.
Oh, look at this.
We have meters over here.
We have meters over here and we have meters over here.
So consider that we want to get to kilometers.
Which one of these doesn't make sense that we use.
Hopefully you're saying to yourself, let's use the first one.
We have meters over here, kilometers over here.
That makes sense to me.
So how many meters is it?
Oh, it's a thousand meters is equal to what?
It's equal to one kilometre are units cancel out, leaving us with kilometres on the top over here.
And we have kilometres on top of.
That's what we're trying to get to.
That's our goal.
So therefore, we know that we're done with this problem.
OK, this is going to get a little bit more complicated.
Put us in the calculator.
But we've been practicing this.
So I think that you're going to be able to do this.
So we have in our calculator, we type it in just like this are open parentheses and we have our ten
point five just multiplying our numerators times five thousand two hundred eighty times, one times
one.
And what that's going to change the values that we really don't need to be plugged in the calculator
divide that by one times, one times three point twenty eight times a thousand.
And when we plug this in, we will get sixteen point nine.
And wait a minute, let's look at this.
What are the units that we have?
Well, on the top, we don't have meters.
And I'm sorry, Miles, anymore.
We don't have feet anymore.
We don't have that.
We don't have this in the bomb.
We only had that in the bomb.
We don't have this.
The only units that we do have remaining are the kilometers, which is in the numerator.
So therefore, we know it's sixteen point nine kilometres and that's done with that one.
So I'm going to invite you to try out problems six and eight plus the video right now.
Try those out and hopefully you get the answer.
OK, so now we're going to get back into this.
Let's if you didn't pause the video yet to try this out once again, how to encourage that, that's
only going to be the way that you get that you're not going to get better at this by watching me do
this and actually doing this together.
You're just going to get better at this by doing this on your own.
So once again, if you have impressive video, I highly suggest that you do that.
And assuming that you did, let's get into it.
OK, I said problem number six, we have nineteen yards and we're going to get to number of meters.
So once again, right off the bat, I do know that the yards should be the first thing that we cancel
out.
So looking over here, we do see that we have yards over here and we have that's the only spot where
we do have yards.
So let's just go from there.
So we have one yard is equal to three feet.
Our yards cancel out, but we're not happy with it.
We want to get to meters, so let's actually just do another conversion factor looking through here.
We have feet here.
Oh, well, we just use that one.
So that doesn't really count.
We're not going to be concerned about that one.
We have feet over here, feet over here.
Once again, we have feet and miles and feet and meters over here.
Considering the idea that we're going to get to our meters, hopefully you're saying to yourself that
we're going to be using this conversion factor so we have feet in the top.
So therefore, we want the bomb in the denominator.
How many feet is it?
It's three point twenty eight feet is equal to what?
It's equal to one meter.
And hopefully by now you're saying to yourself, hey, we want meters and we have meters over here are
indicated to us that we're done with this problem.
And I'm sorry we're supposed to cancel these out guys.
So we just plug this in.
The calculator we do are nine times three and then divide that by our three point twenty eight.
And we got our answer of seventeen point four.
And the only units that we do have remaining here are our meters.
So that's going to be the answer there.
And once again, this is actually to the idea that nine yards is equal to seventeen point four meters.
I do at this point.
I want to stress again the idea that we are not changing the value of the 19 yards.
We're not changing any of these values.
We're simply converting the units.
OK, so and this bottom from over here, let's get our 15 kilometres to number miles.
OK, so we have our 15 kilometres over there.
We're going to put kilometres down over here that we're going to have our cancelation going on.
And which one of these bags has to do with kilometres?
Hopefully by now you're saying to yourself, let's look over here.
We have kilometres over there.
And that's the only one that we have to take us from kilometres to meters, not kilometres to miles.
So we do not know that there's going to be a multiple step in here.
So how many kilometres is it?
It's one kilometre.
And that's equal to what a thousand meters are.
Units will cancel out once again, leaving us with meters when we do want our units to be miles.
So we know that we're not done here and we're just going to have to do another conversion unit leaving
us with meters on the bottom.
Over here.
Now, coming through here, let's look at this.
We have meters over here.
We have meters, meters, meters.
Once again, we're not going to be using this one because we just use that because it makes sense for
us.
Now, this is where you really have to think about this if we want to go from meters to miles.
Do we want to go from meters to centimeters, meters to millimeters or meters to feet?
This is a little tricky, but hopefully you're saying to yourself it makes sense to go from meters to
feet because Miles is the standard unit.
It's the United States unit.
So if we want to go to the U.S. units, we actually do have here this is metric and this is our U.S.
unit.
This is like a nice little bridge that actually takes us into the U.S. units.
So hopefully that makes sense if it does.
And I apologize and hopefully well, in the upcoming examples, all clear.
Clarify that a little bit more.
Anyway, let's get into this.
So we have how many meters it's one meter is equal to, what, three point twenty eight feet?
OK, so our units will cancel out and leaving us with feet, but we don't want we want Miles, so we
know that we're actually not done with this.
I know that this is a long problem.
But once again, I don't think that's complicated.
It's more complex.
OK, so we have feet down on bottom over here now.
We want to go from feet to miles.
Anthony, I'm sorry, we're going to be just looking at our facts that have to do with feet, so we
have feet over here, feet or their feet and feet, we just use this one so it doesn't make sense.
And those are the only ones.
And hopefully you're saying to yourself, OK, and we have feet and miles over here.
Our goal is to get to Miles.
So it does make sense.
I would be using this fact over here.
How many feet do we have?
We have 4000, 280 feet is equal to what is equal to one mile.
Our feet cancels out, leaving us with miles.
Oh, wait a minute.
Our goal is to actually get miles and we have miles on the top over here indicating to us that we're
done with this problem.
We just need to plug it in the calculator and we're good.
All right.
So just plug in this calculator.
You have five times a thousand times three point twenty eight.
Take that divide by two hundred eighty using the same methods that we used before, and we'll get the
idea that it's equal to three point one miles.
And essentially, once again, this is just saying that the five kilometres is equal to three point
one miles for anyone who is who actually runs track or has ever ran a five K before.
Maybe you're saying to yourself, oh, wait a minute, that's what that's about five K a five K race
is equal to three point one miles.