OK, so I actually did not forget about this question on here what so which system is better, the U.S.
or the metric system?
So I'm just going to actually once again invite you to try these problems on your own and try to come
up with a nice little conclusion here.
What system makes more sense?
So this video at this time and try out these two problems and try to come up with a little conclusion
on what your preferences and why.
So come back into this right now.
I'm just going to kind of breeze through this, as you should by and by now, be able to convert these
on your own.
So we do have our 700 centimeters.
We're going to be converting this to number of kilometers.
So we have our centimeters over here.
We have.
100 centimeters is equal to one meter, you know, cancellation.
We're not done with this just yet.
We want to get good kilometers.
So we have this one over here.
We have a thousand meters over one kilometre.
OK, but.
So we are left with our kilometres in the top over here, and it came to us that we're done and we have
zero point zero zero seven kilometres.
OK, so that's the answer for the first one after plugging the calculator and let's go through the second
one over here.
What am I doing?
OK, so deal with the insurers from Gadhafi and then from Ft.
We're going to Miles, so we have 12 inches, six to one foot.
Cancellation and then we have five thousand two hundred eighty three is equal to one mile.
Tour cancellation over here and we get our answer there.
OK, so I'm going to have to plug this in the calculator, and this is equal to zero point one one Miles.
OK, so one thing that you might have noticed here is when you're typing this in calculator, maybe
this actually got a little clear to you.
You actually do have on the top here 700 times in one times one and then divide by one hundred, divided
by a thousand.
The product of those two.
And you actually do get an answer, which actually looks very similar to the initial problem over here.
And for this one over here, for the bottom one, we do have our multiplication of 700 on the in the
numerator and then we're multiplying 12 times by this and 280.
Those are those are those are difficult numbers, actually kind of comprehend.
And think about tossing the calculator.
It just it just makes a whole lot more sense the the metric system than the U.S. standard system.
And that's a fun factor over here.
To actually go about doing this in an easier way is we have 700 centimeters to a number of kilometres.
OK, so centimeters.
What does that have to do with that?
It has to do with the right and kilometres.
It has to do with a thousand.
Let's take our initial problem and we know that the decimal is there.
All we have to do is move the decimal place over how many times?
One, two, three, four, five.
So one, two, three, four, five.
Fion are zeros.
And we get our answer, look how simple that is, the whole reason why we're able to do that is because
the the metric system actually works with a base ten system.
And the the U.S. system clearly doesn't do that.