So the first three problems over here.
These really don't have anything to do with the physics that we're going to be doing a little while,
but you should actually just know how to do these proms anyway.
But these other two proms right here, they did what they were going to be using the skill, the mathematical
skill sets for those two proms to be able to sort out for the physics problems and a little bit.
So the instruction over here says solve for X, so we have 12 is equal to three times X.
Keep in mind that there's a multiplication of three right there.
So it's three multiplied by X.
So how do we get rid of a multiplication of three?
Hopefully you're saying to yourself, well, we have to divide by three.
So if we divide by three on the right hand side the equation, we also have to divide by three on the
left hand side the equation.
And the reason why we did that was because the two threes over here will cancel out, leaving us with
X on the right hand side of the equation.
So we have to divide by three.
Four is equal to X..
We could check to see that this is true simply by looking at the original problem and just substituting
our four in for our X, and we see that three times four is equal to twelve.
That's a true statement right there.
So we know that we actually did the problem.
Correct.
Next problem over here we have five is equal to divide by three.
Well, it's a division of three.
Right.
So what's the opposite of divided by three?
Well, we have to multiply the branch of the equation by three.
You know, we multiply the right into the equation by three.
We also have to multiply the left hand side of the equation by three as well.
These two threes once game was canceled.
That's the entire reason why we did the multiplication of three in the first place and we're just left
with fifteen is equal to X.
Once again, you can look at the original from over here and realize that if we do substitution of 15
and for the X right there on the right hand side, we have 15 divide by three, which is equal to five.
The right hand side and left hand side are equal to each other.
That's the definition of an equation in the first place.
So that should make sense.
All right.
So for the next one over here, maybe you haven't really seen this exponent over here.
That's what the two is above the X, so we have X squared, plus three is equal to nineteen.
One thing actually really like to do is just tell my students that hey, was over here on the left hand
side of the equation.
What we have here is what's called terms.
We have two terms here.
You're essentially just having to once again isolate the X, so you have X squared over here plus three.
How do we get rid of this plus three over here this second term?
So to actually get rid of that, what we have to do is subtract three on the left hand side the equation
then that we subtract it, three on the left hand side.
The question, what do we have to do on the right hand side?
Well, once again, we have to subtract the three.
And the whole reason behind this is actually do this cancellation.
So we are left with X squared is equal to 19.
Minus three is equal to 16.
All right.
Well, we don't care what X squared is equal to.
I want to know X is equal to.
So what's the opposite of square number?
Maybe you're saying to yourself that we have to take our square root.
So being that we took the square root of the left hand side equation, we also have to take the square
root of the right hand side of the equation.
And so we're left with X is equal to, well, what's the square root of sixteen, what two numbers that
are the same as each other multiply together to get you a 16.
Maybe you're saying to yourself that the answer is four, which is correct.
But it's not only positive four, it's also negative four, because we know that positive four times
positive four is equal to a positive sixteen and a negative four times negative four is also equal to
a positive sixteen, keeping in mind the idea that a negative times, a negative will give you a positive
answer.
All right.
So hopefully those are those are clear to you.
I'm not really fully concerned if this over here, the positive plus minus is unclear at this stage.
It's something that you should review and you should actually know at some point, but maybe it's not
as relevant to you right now at this time in this course.
All right.
So for these next few problems over here, there's two different ways that we can actually simplify
these, I guess, expressions right now.
So we have three times four divide by two.
The one way that we can actually do the simplification is a reduction so we can actually reduce this
fraction over here knowing that four to five by two is equal to two.
So we have three times two is equal to six.
Another way that we can actually look at this, though, is looking at three as if as if it's three
divided by one that doesn't change the value of it just makes it into a fraction form, just like the
four to by two is.
So another way that we could actually simplify this is we can multiply the two numerators together and
multiply the denominators together and then we do the division from there.
So what that looks like is this we'll just have the three times four divided by one times two and that
gives us three times four is equal to twelve, one times to equal the two and twelve divided by two
is equal to six.
Notice here that we have the same answer, just a different method.
So just go and get to this next problem over here.
We have to divide by one which is equal to two words, gumboot reducing the fractions.
And we have four divide by two to see what a two and four divide by four, which is equal to one.
So two times two is four times one is equal to four.
And the other way that we could go back to you.
And this is multiplying our numerators together.
And the denominator is and just doing that method two times fours equals eight times four is equal to
thirty.
To divide that by one times two is two times four is E and 32 divided by is equal to four.
Once again, noticing that we actually get the same answer over here.
So this method over here of multiplying fractions together, that's what we're going to be using in
our lesson.