All right, so now we're ready to actually do some unit conversions here, so the very first Palm says,
to convert the following eight feet to a number of meters.
OK, so the very first thing that we do to start these problems is just to rewrite the eight feet.
Now, OK, let's think about this here.
If I'm to take this eight feet and multiply this by one when I change the value of this at all.
Now, in one times, anything is equal to itself.
So this is also equal to eight feet.
OK, well, let's take this a step further than what if I was to multiply eight times five divided by
five?
Well, five divided by five is essentially one, right.
So this is still eight times one, which is still equal to eight feet.
Nothing actually changed here.
The value didn't change itself.
Right.
Well, OK, so what if we already do 20 divided by 20 and what our needs are need to be insulting our
intelligence over here?
You could see, Celsi, that that's essentially one times a feat, giving us eight feet.
Right.
So what if we were to do this when I'm actually just going to do is let's take a little side sidestep
right now.
We have and meters over here.
What am I to do is actually look over at our nice little fun facts over here, our unit conversions,
and basically look for, hey, which one of these attacks has to do with feet?
What we have here, we have over here, here, here.
Well, nothing in here.
Right?
And no feet in there.
No feet in here, no feet in here, so on and so forth.
None of this actually has to do with feet.
Right.
But these first four actually did.
So what it makes sense for us to actually look at the first fact, which actually has to do with feet
and inches or feet and yards, feet and miles.
One's going to miss miles or feet and meters.
Well, we want to convert from feet to meters.
So this fact over here actually does make sense that we'd be interested in it.
So we have three point two.
Eight feet is equal to one meter.
See, if I take eight feet and multiply this by three point twenty eight feet.
Divided by three point twenty eight feet, hey, that's essentially one, right, giving us once again
our feet, the value of the eight feet has not changed.
Right.
Well, I was actually just briefly look at this over here, so I'm just going to erase everything over
here and we have this three point twenty eight feet instead of writing three three point twenty eight
feet.
Could I just write one meter here?
Yeah, because we know that three point twenty eight feet is equal to one meter, so instead of writing
three point twenty eight feet, I'm just going to write one meter so I just can do this right here.
He raised this in itself around three point twenty eight feet.
I'm just going to write one meter because we know that three point twenty eight feet is equal to one
meter.
I just did a simple substitution here.
So we have one meter, which is equal to three point twenty eight feet.
Once again, this essentially is equal to one.
This over here is essentially equal to one not changing the value of eight feet, but what happens here,
this is eight feet.
We could actually just put a division of one over here.
The feet will cancel each other out and leaving us with meters.
And we're trying to that's exactly what we're trying to do.
We're just trying to convert this into meters.
So if I put this in the calculator, the way that you would actually go about doing this is once again,
you're going to be multiplying the numerators, divide that by multiplying by the denominators.
So we have eight times one divide that by open princi one times three point twenty eight.
And when you plug this in the calculator, what you get is two point four four.
And the units that we have here are our meters.
So what we're doing here is we're converting the units were not changing the value.
We are just simply convert the units.
So what this basically is telling us is that eight fee is equal to two point four four meters.
And that's simply what we're trying to get across right now.
It's this is a unit conversion, not changing the value.
OK, so for the next one, let's set it up the same way, so the very first thing that we're going to
be writing out is our three meters, once again, keeping in mind that our meters abbreviation is just
a little letter lowercase m and we have hey, and we're just going to be using the same fun fact over
here, this fourth one, because that has to do with feet and meters, basically saying that three point
twenty eight feet is equal to one meter.
Now, when I'm just going to do is once again right in our three point twenty eight feet over here.
Divide that by three point twenty eight feet.
And hey, once again, what we do is we substitute our one meter because three point twenty eight feet
equal is equal to one meter.
And what do we do here?
Oh, wait a minute.
It looks like that we messed up somewhere because the whole entire point of actually doing these types
of problems is idea that our units will cancel out if we have meters on top over here and we have feet
on the bottom over here.
Those don't actually cancel out.
They they simply that's not the way it works.
We need to have meters on top and meters on bottom.
So what we did here is we substituted the top there, our numerator for one meter when it was the three
point twenty eight feet, what we should have done was actually rewritten our three point twenty eight
feet to one meter in the denominator.
Look at that.
OK, so once again, the whole point of this is to actually see that our units can't slot.
We have meters on top over here cancelling out with meter meters on the bottom over here, leaving us
just simply with our feet in the numerator.
So when we type this in the calculator, the way that you want to write this out is having your open
parentheses, multiply the numerators together, divide that by multiply, multiply by the denominators
together.
So we have three times three point twenty eight.
Divide that by one times one.
And I'm sure a lot of you write right now, just now, hey, you want the division of one times.
One is just unnecessary to do in your calculator.
But when we do this, what we get here is an answer of nine point eight four and the units here are
fit.
Don't answer these problems without actually including your units.
The entire point of doing this is for the unit conversions include your units in the answer.
And once again, this is essentially saying here is that three meters is equal to nine point eight four
feet.
That's what we're saying when we're doing this unit conversions.
Once again, we did not change the value of the three meters.
We simply converted the units.