All right, so for these problems over here, this next one, we have five pounds, two number of kilograms
once again, that what we're going to be doing here is simply just writing out our five pounds.
And we're going to be multiplying this by a fraction, a unit conversion so far over a step over here
is trying to look for all the facts to actually have pounds in them.
You notice that the first four over here are all having to do with distance.
So that has nothing to do with pounds.
This over here we have having to do with pounds in these ones over here.
Once again, these don't have anything to do with pounds or these ones over here.
So we're just simply going to be looking at this first fun fact, this unit conversion over here.
So once again, keeping in mind that the entire idea of this is to actually be able to cancel out the
units, one kilogram is equal to two point two pounds.
Where do we want to put the pounds?
Well, we have pounds on the top over here and we want to put pounds on the bottom over here in the
denominator.
So we have our two point two pounds is equal to one kilogram.
Being at the numerator and denominator are equal to each other.
We know by now that, hey, it's essentially multiplying to five pounds by one, which once again does
not change the value of the pounds, the five pounds.
It just simply converts the units.
Once again, what we're gonna do here is we cancel at the pounds with the pounds and that leaves us
with kilograms.
We are converting from pounds to kilograms.
And that being the case, we know that we're done with this problem.
OK, so once again, all we have to do here is plug this in our calculator.
We have our five times one, which is essentially just sell the five divide that by our one times two
point two.
And this will give us an answer when we plug it in the calculator.
This way, we, of course, don't actually need the parentheses in this this problem right now for plug
it into the calculator, because it's just two different numbers.
But I typically use parentheses just really to explicitly have it defined.
What we're plugging into the calculator and we get two point two seven repeating.
We could just do two point two seven.
And once again, the entire reason why we're doing this is because we're doing the unit conversions.
So make sure that you include your units.
And what's again, what this is essentially saying is that five pounds is equal to two point to seven
kilograms, and that's the answer for that one.
OK, so let's do this next from.
We have two point twenty seven kilograms to number of pounds.
All right, so we once again start off with our two point two seven kilograms times a fraction over
here.
And we could just simply just do the divide by one over here.
That's fine.
And once again, we're actually just going to be using the same fun factor over here, the same unique
conversion, because once again, we're dealing with kilograms and pounds.
These don't have anything to do with kilograms or pounds, neither of these.
So we are just going to be using the same fun fact.
So we have one kilogram is equal to two point two pounds.
We have kilograms, two point two kilograms with the kilograms in the numerator.
So therefore we know right away that we want kilograms in the denominator for these two units to cancel
each other out.
How many kilograms is it?
Oh, it's one kilogram is equal to what, two point two pounds?
Once again, our units will cancel out with each other, just leaving us with pounds and we're converting
from kilograms to pounds.
So being that we do have our pounds over here, that's a good indicator to us that we're done with this
problem.
All we have to do is put this in the calculator and we'll get our answer cell plug in the calculator
we have to point to seven times are two point to divide that by one times one.
And really this step over here isn't necessary.
We just have our multiplication of.
Two point two, seven times to point two and now give us our answer and plug it into the calculator.
We have our answer of five five what, five pounds.
So what we're basically saying here is that two point two seven kilograms is equal to five pounds.
And if you actually noticed this here, hey, look at the similarities over here.
We just went from five pounds to number of kilograms and we just went from number of kilograms to back
to number of pounds just basically through the same method.