All right.
Over the past few months, I've been looking at the physics of radar systems in some general background
information on that, and one topic I came across was how to calculate the Doppler shift frequency of
a target that's approaching a radar system at a very fast speed.
Now when you do this radar systems, you know, they emit beams hoping to hit a target.
And then those beams come back when you're trying to calculate that frequency.
What frequency you would expect based upon the velocity of that object?
What you find is that if you fail to include a relativistic effects, if you do not account for Einstein's
theory of special relativity, what you calculate will be incorrect.
It will not conform to what you actually observe in nature.
So given that fact, I started reviewing special relativity.
Looking into that again, derivations and stuff, I found a very interesting.
So I thought, why not teach you guys about special relativity?
You'll be fine.
And you know, this is a very cool topic, one of the coolest topics in physics.
OK?
A lot of Einstein stuff is OK.
So what I intend to do in this video is I want to provide some background information, some history,
some background theory and some ideas related to relativity to help you better understand the general
climate that scientists were encroached in back in the day when Einstein made his breakthrough discovery
in a paper he published in Nineteen Oh five.
I want you to understand the dilemma everybody faced what they are trying to solve and why.
Einstein's pretty straightforward idea, you know, he developed all this stuff.
So a very simple thought experiment.
Why this was such a huge, huge breakthrough in physics, one that segment it physics in half between
classical physics and modern physics, in a sense.
OK, so first and foremost, we're talking about relativity.
What exactly is relativity?
Well, as with most SECTS in physics, most topics in physics, the name conveys the meaning, right?
The terminology conveys the physical phenomena.
So this is no different relativity.
If you look at it and break down the word, the main root word here is relative.
Relativity is the study of how our perceptions of physical phenomenon, how our conception of the universe
and how things transpire in front of us, how that is contingent upon the reference frame from which
we conceive it again.
Our perceptions are contingent upon our perspective, our reference frame.
In essence, if somebody perceives something in a certain way based upon their reference frame and somebody
else perceive it in a different from a different perspective, the outcomes, the analysis, how they
interpret that it may not gel up together.
So what relativity is trying to do, it's trying to bridge the gap between perceptions from different
perspectives such that we can get some universal absolute conception of the universe.
Now this can crop up in physics or metaphysical ideas, right in metaphysics, philosophy, opinions,
even politics, for example, somebody's perception, somebody's interpretation of things.
It's based upon their perspective.
It's based upon how they saw things, is based upon what information they had available.
But in terms of physics, relativity has to do with measurements.
OK.
The way in which you measure length time, velocity, momentum, so on and so forth.
But in particular, space and time.
What you find is that.
Your conception of your conception of how physical laws are played out in front of your eyes.
It's contingent upon your perspective is dependent upon your reference frame.
OK, and this is a very cool idea because what physics is trying to do is we want to divulge the essence
of the universe.
All the physical principles that govern motion govern how things are supposed to be right.
Any good physical theory is one that should encompass every event that could happen in the universe.
Every perspective that could observe that kind of phenomenon, it should be absolute.
It should be universal.
So any kind of theory of relativity is trying to do that.
It's trying to find its absolute universal conception of reality that bridges differences between perspectives.
OK.
And what I'm going to say is that relativity, the conception of it, is very, very old.
So it did not come about for the first time in history when I signed developed his theory of special
relativity.
When it came about was back in the day when Newton was developing his theories.
This is a very classical idea, the very classical idea.
So what new was trying to do?
He wanted all of his laws to be universal across these reference frames.
OK.
And when we observe different phenomena throughout the day and, you know, general terms, things that
are moving at a slow speed, key work, keep that in mind.
The back of your head.
Slow speed.
We find that different perspectives.
You know, they can converge based upon transformations.
So what Newton showed first, what he said is that.
There is something known as a Galilean invariance.
This is part of Newtonian mechanics.
What this basically asserts is that physical laws are universal.
They're absolute regardless of how you perceive something, regardless of your reference frame, regardless
of your perspective, the same physical phenomenon will arise.
Things will behave as they are governed by physical laws.
Right.
Nature is not going to play a fast one on us.
It's not going to try to trick us.
So we get into the quantum world.
That's what makes it super interesting.
But in a Newtonian world, Newton's laws are going to rise just as they are so Galilean and variance.
A formal definition states that if Newton's laws are valid in one reference rate for one person for
one perspective, then they are also valid in an in inertial reference frame.
Key word inertial moving at a constant velocity of relative first system.
So.
There are special relativity is only for inertial reference frames that are moving at a constant velocity.
So as you probably learn a physics one to one in inertial reference frames, which the walls are, they
are the dominant governing force at play.
They always apply.
That's why sort of inertial Newton's laws give rise to inertial concepts, and any other reference frame
has to have a constant velocity relative to the first system.
So to illustrate the initial problem that was faced with Newtonian relativity, which people thought
was no big deal, right?
They said, Oh, there's this dilemma, they solved it very quickly, which I'll show you in a little
bit.
They said, this is not interesting.
We're not going to look at this ever again until Einstein came around.
And a dilemma was presented that he was trying to solve, which I will get to in a second.
But let's do a thought experiment.
Let's do a thought experiment.
Let's see if we had multiple perspectives.
If the laws are valid.
A space and time can relate it in a universal absolute sense.
OK.
That's the name of the game.
So to do this, what we're going to do is we're going to say we've got two people who are going to conduct
this experiment.
A guy named Terrence and a guy named Philip Notability MP Al Tarrant's is going to be in a car and he's
going to drive at a constant velocity and throw an object and measure.
Philip is also going to measure it standing on the ground.
So.
Philip and Terence, what they do, they say my reference frames are designated as follows Philip's
reference frame, his perspective on the physical phenomenon transpiring all around him is going to
be a reference frame.
S and Terence is going to be a reference frame.
S Prime Atari's is only going to move in the X direction.
Not going to move in the wide direction or the Z direction coming out of the board.
But the S reference frame is going to have an X and Y system at the origin and before the experiment
is conducted.
What Terence is going to do is say, Hey, I have a clock.
Philip has a clock.
We're going to synchronize that clock.
This references system is primed for Terrence was designated by 02 y prime.
So it's going to be fixed through this car, but initially it's going to line up with the origin up.
So Terrence is origin, which is going to move the car.
I'll call Oprah Prime.
His origin is going to be as follows.
So first, Tenet.
Of relativity back in the day, Newtonian relativity, if you will, you could probably agree that.
The time for fill up is going to be the same time as parents, provided that they sync up, right?
For example, if we both have a clock which is calibrated properly, the good tool, good instrument,
we set it together.
I stay at home and I tell you, hey, take your watch.
Go to the supermarket.
Keep track of your time.
Pick up some chicken.
We'll make some Chinese food when you come back, something like that when he comes back.
You and I would agree.
We would agree.
Time would be the same our watches would match provided that the tool was precise.
That's not surprising.
That's a given fact of life that we observe every day.
So that's not surprising.
So Terence and Phillip, they're going to do that.
They're going to synchronize their watch at time.
T equals zero.
And right when they want to start the experiment, parents.
He's going to hit a pedal that makes him automatically go the speed of V v relative, in this case,
we're going to go 60 meters per second.
And they're going to start their time launches at the same exact time, so their time will be universal.
So the transformation that's going to relate time a team breakfast frame as prime in this.
Time tea for fill up.
It's going to be the same as Prime.
Returns not surprising now.
Terrence, you guys are speeding off.
Then he's going to throw a baseball right here.
And he's going to measure it, so Terrence throws it.
Throws the ball, shoe flies out, Terrance says.
Look at that smirk, baby.
I'm going to measure that baseball.
It's 10 meters per second, it's 10 meters per second, so he gets a call to his buddy.
Hey bro.
Yo, Philip.
I measured the speed, it's 10 meters per second.
What did you measure, would you measure?
Well, Philip says, Oh, oh, my God, what are you talking about then?
You're lying to me, bro.
You're lying to me.
I see so many meters per second.
What's going on here?
Has the universe?
Played a trick on Terrence and Philip.
Well, you're probably thinking this is sort of silly.
And right now it is silly because.
We know that.
And I'm going to show you very shortly that, you know, we just take the velocity of this and add the
velocity of that 60 plus 10 gives us 70.
And we're used to that because we're used to everyday events transpiring in front of us.
I say kids are like the best physicists because they observe everything there of how things are going
to operate and then form their own theories related to it.
They would have.
Form some kind of theatre related, but since they disagree, what they say is, oh, well, let's.
Let's take a step back.
And.
Let's analyze what the distances are going to be.
So at a time, t, we say that if Terrence is moving at a concert velocity, his car will have traveled
a distance viti.
Right?
Makes sense.
Simple physics, right?
The.
Is Delta L or Delta T?
If you multiply by Delta T?
You get Delta Elm.
That's just what that is.
Simple physics, baby, simple physics.
So he says, Oh, you traveled a distance beat and blue right here.
B relative times T.
That's going to give me your conception of the car and you're going to tell me that the length you see
the ball has traveled is relative to your origin, which is implanted on the car, which the distance
from way.
Where your origin is right here at the left side of the car to the ball, that's going to be ex prime,
right?
His reference frame is designated by a prime that's ex prime.
But what I see is that.
It traveled first this distance.
In the car.
And then the distance you threw it.
So my distance x is going to be x prime plus v t.
Which is what we find here.
So, OK, that that makes sense.
And I want to make a note that when he throws it, it just goes in the X direction.
You don't have any change in why it's like, Oh, well, that's cool.
Maybe that's why there's a difference.
But as for Y and Z Y, your Y is the same as mine.
They line up horizontally.
Same with Z out of the board.
Nothing's changing.
There are reference frames in.
Not so.
What does gives rise to what we just arrived is a very simple idea of relativity, what it says is that
you know what?
We haven't proved this yet.
It says the laws of physics are going to hold their universe, their absolute, they govern nature.
Nature will conform to those laws.
Whatever.
Regardless of what we do.
But our perspectives may be changing the phenomena that arise.
So in order to come up with this absolute universal conception, we're going to develop this transformation,
which we're going to call Gavilan transformation.
And it is as follows.
So given this, we say, OK, we have this universal conception of the physical phenomena that happened.
It's true.
Regardless of the reference frame that we choose, it's going to stay true regardless of what we choose.
And it is as such.
Now we could further generalize this by saying that, oh, this is going to move in a cost velocity
in the Z direction or the Y direction.
We could that to realize this and say that.
Are.
You know, Vector R, which is X Y.
Z.
Sorry about that, guys.
Vector like that because they are.
Her fill up is equal to the R.
It's Prime.
That's what the prime designate is with respect to this reference rate, plus the relative velocity
times tick.
This is going to represent V Zvi v z.
So we could have done that.
We could have done.
And this gives us a nice transformation.
What you're saying?
Wait, a second, that's just space.
How does this affect velocity?
So.
If we erase our invariants principle.
Which we hold to be true, and we want to be true because that is the goal is to assert that malls are
universal and crop up in nature regardless of how we perceive them.
All I can say is that, oh, we can take this general form are as equal to our prime plus v relative
sea, and we can just differentiate this right.
Simple count, baby, we could say OK.
Are not all transformative, the.
Is equal to the prime.
The derivative this is a constant remember he's moving out of control velocity.
So the derivative of Constantine's is just the constant.
And then you say, well.
Terrence, you told me the blast, you observed the prime.
It's 10 meters per second.
I have to add your velocity, which is 60, and that give me my 70.
Everything makes sense.
This is known as the lost the edition.
OK, so.
What have we done here?
What have we really done?
We came up with a mechanism.
You can conceive of the world to perceive physical phenomena around us in an absolute universe, universal
manner.
We say that regardless of how we perceive things, regardless of our perspective.
It's going to conform to physical laws.
And it's going to give rise to the theory that applies regardless of your reference frame.
Cool stuff.
But what about the invariance principle?
How can we show that Newton's laws are the same in each reference frame?
That's one of the accomplishments.
Of physics.
I'm just going to write what I raced right here.
Velocity Edition.
OK.
OK, so all I want to show really is.
Philip.
Says.
I took the baseball.
I dropped it on a spring scale.
I measured the force that was going on here.
Force gravity, my force should be the same as yours if physical laws are going to line up.
That's how it has to be.
This is the dilemma back in the day for any tiny mechanics.
So you might be reasoning that regardless of your preference for him, regardless of your perspective,
it seems to be the case that your mass in one reference frame will be the same mass in another reference
frame.
Seems plausible, right?
We cannot create or destroy mass.
Conservation of mass.
Right.
So Philip says let's test this out.
Terrence, take the ball, travel as fast as you can, take my spring balanced, so the same instrument
shot that baseball on it in measure it.
Tell me your force.
We want to find that this is equal to that the forces in both reference frame are equal.
So.
When he does this.
But the spring balanced, he says, Oh, the horses are equal.
That seems plausible.
We've all probably done that, and we probably consider that subconsciously based upon what we observed
in the world in front of us, based upon how physical phenomena has transpired around us.
So you could probably agree that.
Masses in variance in your reference frames.
For now, and you're probably thinking since he married it.
The tool does not lie.
So this is true.
But what about acceleration?
What about acceleration?
Acceleration must be the same.
To make that line up.
Right.
So if we take this, we can differentiate it again.
Note that the relative is a constant.
And we end up with a sequel to a Prime.
What that means is we get that this.
Is equivalent
f equals Emma looks like invariance has held up our physical laws to give rise to inertial effects the
universal.
Philip and Terence are happy.
The only thing they are unhappy about.
Is space their conception of space?
And they came up with this nice universal conception to measure it?
OK, so you might be thinking that's almost that's all fine and dandy shirtless, either.
This cannot be the theory of special relativity.
That's an interesting and I agree with you.
It's not super interesting.
So what's the problem?
Well, my question for you is.
This little experiment here, does this encompass every possible situation that can arise in the universe
because of physical theory is true.
What it should do is it should converge on every situation that can happen.
That is the ultimate test for any physical theory.
Can this encompass every situation, what I'm going to say is, no, we have not tested every single
situation that could arise, and in particular, we have not checked that in variance is true for every
physical law.
OK, so next, what we're going to do is I'm going to outline the main dilemma back in the day that
was presented, which challenged Einstein and gave him a run for his money and allowed him to become
the famous physicist he is today.