OK, so what's the big dilemma here?
We developed this nice theory of relativity.
It helps bridge the gap between different perspectives and gives us this universal absolute conception
of the universe.
What could possibly go wrong?
My question for you is invariance tells us that physical physical laws should be universal across reference
frames.
They should always crop up in the same manner, regardless of our perspective, regardless of how we
perceive the event transpiring in front of our eyes.
But we've only taken a look at Newtonian laws, Newtonian mechanics.
F equals M-A and all the results that fall out because of that easily inertial ideas.
So what about a theory that was developed after this in an electricity magnetism?
What about that?
If our physical laws were good, if the theory was very universal absolute, we would expect that Maxwell's
equations, which govern all of ENM and we've shown give us valid results in numerous experiments.
People were very confident that.
Those laws should be invariant between reference frame.
What I'm going to say is there's a little dilemma, and this is what gave rise to a lot of the questions
in the late 1800s and early 1900s which Einstein resolved with his theory of special relativity.
What was the issue now?
As I've just said, you would have hoped that ENM the physical laws would be invariant to reference
frames.
And that they would conform to this theory of relativity we just put together.
And furthermore, since Ian was newer, people clung to this theory of relativity.
This Newtonian result because there have been proven time and time again, it could not be wrong.
But here's the problem.
Maxwell's equations assert that the speed of light, the speed in which light moves.
Is always constant.
Why is that?
Because.
He asserts that the speed of light sea is equal to one over the square root of these constants epsilon,
not new, not F1, not is the permit tivity of vacuum, while new not is the permeability of vacuum.
So can you see the problem here?
This is the constant, regardless of what you want to say.
But if this is a constant.
If somebody in a movie reference frame shoots out a beam of light.
This guy.
It says that.
The guy who's not moving will measure a different velocity.
But it's supposed to be constant.
What is going on here?
This was so troubling at the time, and I'll illustrate in the new example right here just shortly,
but this was so troubling at the time that scientists started coming up with fabricated ideas and theories
and entities to try to explain this.
But at the time, they respected this theory because it was Newtonian, was classical.
It had more supporting evidence or so they thought, so what they said is, mmm, this law cannot be
invariant across reference frames.
What we're going to say is that there's some unique frame in which the speed of light is a constant
defined by Maxwell's equations and Maxwell's equations hold.
But another reference frames it may be different to account for this theory, and that's how they bridge
the gap.
What they said was that, Hey, look, lane is a wave, and from our previous experience, we've observed
that a lot of waves, such as water waves and water and sound waves in air, they have to propagate
through a medium.
Guess what?
Light is going to do the same thing.
It must do the same thing.
So there must be this unique entity, which we're going to call the Lumina lumen for us, this ether
or ether for short.
This is going to be some medium, which is heavenly, given the name either some divine fabricated force
that we came up with in our minds and light is going to have to propagate through that and only in that
reference frame.
Does this hold?
Only now reference frames of Maxwell's equations.
Come right.
Hold up at play.
So.
This was a problem, and what scientists want to do is they wanted to come up with an experiment with
a tool that could precisely measure light super precisely in such a way that they could find some difference
in the velocity and different records.
So they said, OK.
Let's take the Earth.
The Earth is moving at a speed, we know the speed we can predict that.
Kepler's laws from orbital mechanics, we are confident in that result.
Let's put together a tool that could measure it on the Earth.
And what we assert is that in the ether, which surrounds the Earth, the light must propagate through.
It's going to be this value.
It's going to be.
3.00 times, 10 to the eight meters per second.
The very precise measurement.
What on the Earth?
It's going to be.
Going to be.
So the guy named Nicholson.
It was also or later assisted by a guy named Morley.
And they did an experiment which became known as the Mikkelson Warley Experiment, a drought developed
what is known as an interferometer and Mikkelson in 1880.
What he did was he tried to measure the speed of light, and he thought it would give a different value
than this because the Earth was moving.
Right.
We are in a different reference frame.
So in essence, you tried to find this guy.
What did he find?
His instrument was super precise, and he should have found a difference.
But regardless of where he did it, regardless of how he did it, regardless of the time of day he did
it, he always got that result.
When he published this, scientists blew up, they're like, what?
No.
Our theory is this cannot be right.
You do not do your experiment correctly.
You do it again.
You kept repeating it and repeating it and finding that this was true.
So they had the answer right in front of them, but they came up with this fabricated idea to explain
it.
It's fabricated concession and the greatest lesson you can get out of this.
This history lesson is that physics is intended to observe physical phenomenon and then develop theories
which describe what you see as soon as you start prescribing how nature should behave.
You get led down the wrong path, and that's what happened in this situation, because we had the answer
right here at these walls are invariant in any kind of reference frame, but they refused to believe
it because they are trying to mold nature and come up with these ideas, these fictional entities,
to make the theories work.
Why don't you do that?
You run into problems.
Name of the game is observe, develop theories to describe what you observe.
That's how you do.
Good science.
OK, so.
What was the dilemma here?
I'm going to illustrate for you with Terence and Phillip and a mother, Duncan, a thought experiment,
as I would say.
So in this case, we have the same set up.
We have parents and Philip originally at the same origin.
They calibrate their clocks.
We think that the time is going to be the same.
And this time, parents of Philip were like, Hey, let's put out this experiment, baby, I'm going
to get a Star Wars ship and I'm going to put a blaster on the front.
Let's measure light instead of a baseball that's child's play.
And we got this nice theory here.
We know what's going to happen already, so at time, T equals zero.
Pam parents instantly goes a speed of point ninety five times the speed of light, super fast, almost
close to the speed of light.
And what he does, he says, I'm going to push a button.
I'm going to fire this laser gun.
It's like I'm in Star Wars, baby.
It's going to be awesome.
That's why has this awesome, awkward smirk on his face.
He pushes the button and you fill up his Allen out of space.
He's watching it, and he's running down some theory based upon his new Galilean transformation.
And he says parents.
Getting your measurement, and I'm going to be able to figure out what it should be before I measure
it.
I am so confident in my theories.
I'm not even going to listen to what's going on right in front of me.
So Terrence hits the button.
He measures the laser who flies out.
He says, Oh, it's going to be tough.
See, you must be going through the ether.
It's going through the ether.
I found the ether baby.
We're going to make history.
He calls up Philip.
He's like, Yeah, let's see.
And feels like I'm so excited, so excited.
I'm going to figure out what I'm going to measure it as physics says it's going to be V.
Oh, it's.
It should be B plus B, relative.
We nine people see it should be 1.5 C.
We super exciting.
Throwing it up, he's got his pen.
This is what it is.
As you can see with this big red line.
That's not what it is.
It's not what it is.
In actuality.
In actuality, it measures the light.
And let's see.
What's going on here?
Instantly, just like the scientists, they start saying, oh, no, something is wrong with the announcements.
They were not measuring it.
Correct?
Let's do it again.
Only we go far.
They found less.
They failed to realize that this is what we observed, so that's what it is.
Trust, nature, but verify.
So what they found is that.
Yes, Maxwell's equations are invariant in the universe.
And this was the main dilemma of the time.
People could not understand why this theory was from.
And then Einstein came around and he said.
Guys, it's right in front of us, right in front of us.
You need to take your educated mind, your program and mine.
What do you expect to see?
And throw it in the garbage?
Do not expect, observe, develop.
And then critique.
Do not control reality.
Nature will not conform to your wishes.
It will not conform to your imagination.
It will not conform to what you want.
There is no ether.
There is no special, fabricated idea.
Get out of here, guys.
What I'm going to say is that our conception of space and time is not quite right.
We haven't seen the full picture yet, and that is exactly what happened in his paper he published in
1985.
What he asserted is that space time is going to bend or change.
To compensate for this fact.
But it's only going to arise in certain circumstances.
In other words, we're going to reserve that time dilates and length contracts to very important topics.
Keep that in the back of your head.
So that was the main dilemma at the time.
This is what perplexed scientists back in the day before Einstein came around, slot them on the piece
and said, Wake up, brother.
The answer's right in front of you.
Stop trying to force reality.
Observe and then develop theories to explain what you observe, nature is not trying to trick you.
Nature will not trick you.
OK.
So the next few videos we're going to jump into.
What Einstein asserted he was able to resolve this nonsense, this big mess through a very simple experiment
and get Donkin OK and through that experiment, he was able to show how our conception of space time
is completely and utterly wrong.
And he changed.
You changed the fabric of physics as we knew it.
But at the same time?
He saved ENM in a sense, made everything in that.
Came up with a universal apps like Inception and Progressed The Theory of Relativity.
I hope you enjoyed the video.
A lot of background information, not a lot of math, not a lot of physics, but I thought it was important
for you to understand.
The dilemma scientists face is it seems simple to us nowadays, but this perplexed everybody for years,
years and I wanted you to appreciate.
How a simple experiment.
Simple facts.
Can divulge so much about the universe.
OK, so I look forward to explaining the special theory of relativity next, going through Einstein's
get Duncan and showing you.
How time dilates and life contracts?
Stay tuned.