All right.
At this point in the course, we've taken a brief look at Newtonian relativity and the sort of relative
questions we asked back in the day.
And technically, we are ready to really dive into that wacky world of special relativity.
However, before proceeding, what I want to do is run through an example problem with you in terms
of Galilean relativity and the Galilean transformation.
And then I want to give you an opportunity to run through problems yourself and to check your understanding
of these ideas.
And the reason why is twofold.
First, the Galilean transformation and Newtonian relativity, as it is as stated, as we've studied
so far, it does provide value and it can provide analytical process, even if there are problems associated
with it, right?
We saw that problem started to crop up when we started looking at velocities and speeds close to the
speed of light.
All right.
However, if we look at situations that are in tune with what we typically see, such as, you know,
a car driving by lower velocities, it still does give us good analytical power and allows us to predict
things and could be useful.
OK, so that's one reason why we want to do it.
The other reason why is because if you can build an understanding of how you solve very simple relativity
problems where the situations really gel with your intuition, with how you would expect situations
to unravel in front of your eyes, right?
You can take that same approach the ideas you put forth and develop in solving these problems.
And that can help you to better solve special relativity problems when your intuition is thrown out
of the window and it's harder to decipher what really is going on, right?
So if you feel really comfortable with this material, feel free to skip ahead.
Skip the quiz, jump to the next section.
But I would highly advocate taking a look at this example problem we're going to run through now and
running through the exercises I provide after this video OK.
So let's jump straight into the problem, the problem we're going to discuss today.
The example problem is a classical physics problem you usually see in an introductory physics class.
And that's the problem of how do you really reconcile the different velocities of somebody in a boat,
a boat who's moving across a river with a stream that's pulling it along?
OK, so I'm going to read the problem statement and then we're going to jump into each section of the
problem so that the problem we're going to look at states that a river has a width of de equal to 40
meters and water flowing at a constant velocity V equals negative six.
I means negative six in the extraction.
If you have not seen that in notation before the units from that our meters per second.
What is with respect to a frame of reference that rest?
S.
OK, so it's going to be tied to the ground and that's what you would observe if you were standing on
the ground.
The first thing you want to make note of in any kind of relativity problem, the Galilean transformation
problem or special relativity is the fact that we had a constant velocity, right?
These ideas, and especially in special relativity, as we're going to find, only apply if we have
a cause of velocity.
Once that velocity starts fluctuating, these ideas break down and you can't use exactly what we derive
previously.
So that's an important fact.
Let's continue the problem statement.
It's across the river from point A to point B, but the bop fill up right now is joining us again in
this problem.
Decides to row his boat with a velocity v equal to positive for J meters per second.
That's in the Y direction straight up means.
Second, with respect to the water.
OK, so that's how he's rowing across in this boat here.
And his partner, Terrence also decides to observe what's happening in this river.
He's going to observe this event while cycling on a bike across the river at a cost of Alaska V is equal
to plus two positive 2J again up in the Y direction meters per second.
Now we're going to be multiple parts past this problem.
The first one, and we're going to consider right now is part a what is the velocity to the vote of
the boat?
According to someone on the ground standing here?
So how do we approach any kind of relativity problem?
Whenever you jump into a relativity problem, your path to success lies in identifying the different
reference frames keeping track of them and being organized.
OK?
So let's do that first.
The way in which I like to solve these problems is I like to have a column on my sheet, a given column
where I label all the different information and helped make sense of it.
Help make sense of what has been given to me, so we have quite a few big losses that are given here,
let's try to make sense of what's going on and label things.
The first thing we know is that we have water flowing out a concept velocity in the negative x direction.
And that's this last year.
So we have water here.
It's going to pull the boat to the left, and we know that somebody's on the water would have a different
reference rate and different interpretation of events than somebody on the ground.
OK, so the first thing we're to do is we're going to label that and I'm not sure the label system.
I like to use both the relativity and when you start getting into things like robotics and mechanical
engineering.
So what I'm going to say is I'm going to say the velocity.
All the water.
With respect to the ground, so this is how I read it, and then this notation is going to the power
of it is going to become clearer as we start working through the problem.
I think it makes it nice and easy to really figure out what reference frame is doing what.
So we're going to write this down.
OK, so the water with respect to the Ground G is going to be this vector is going to be negative six
in the eye or extraction meters per second.
All right.
So we got one velocity and that's a cause of velocity.
We know that Philip is in the boat also, and he's going a paddle with respect to the water with a velocity
of positive four j meters per second, basically in the Y direction up on the board.
So what we're going to do is, well, that's the velocity of fill up in the boat.
So we're going to use the same notation.
We're going to say the velocity of fill up.
So up with respect to what with respect to the water, OK, with respect to the water.
So here we had lost water to the ground.
This is going to be the velocity of fill up with respect to the water that's given as what?
Well, we can just reach the a border that's a positive for J.
Meters per second.
OK, so we got two of the three ingredients in this problem.
And the next lawsuit we have on the board is this guy here that's going to be parents.
That's how it's going to be cycling across this bridge as he watches this event.
So what we can say is that's no different than the velocity of parents with respect to what respect
to the ground, right?
He's moving with respect to the ground.
And as you see, as you work through these problems, the hard part is identifying the frame that's
moving, identifying the Fremont rest, which is the ground in this case and then identifying any other
reference frames and figuring out the losses, what that is in respect to with respect to this guy.
Going back to the problem, Terrence, this back to the ground, we have another positive to J meters
per second.
OK.
The only thing you can do is you can have a column is looking for specifying what exactly you're looking
for.
I'm going to skip that in this video just to open up more space for us.
But now we go back to the question, we want to find the velocity of a boat according to someone on
the ground.
OK, so what we want is we can use the same notation.
We want really the velocity of the other boats back to the ground.
And what we're going to use is the velocity addition equation we derive previously.
So refresh your memory.
That guy was velocity of.
Something I grasp on the rest frame around is equal to the velocity, the relative velocity measured
by somebody in the moving reference frame.
Plus the velocity of that moving reference.
That's what we do right now, we're going to take this.
We're going to fly to this problem, OK, so if we're looking for the velocity of the boat according
to somebody on the ground, what we're going to do is we're say, OK, that's in the reference for it.
That's at rest on the ground.
That would be this guy, right?
So we're going to write down velocity, the vertical, some on the ground.
So that's going to be fill up this back to the ground.
Now read the question OK, how do we figure that out?
Well, we know a relative last year, right?
This relative velocity will be fill up with respect to the water, right?
Because he's in the moving reference frame.
Let me break it down for you.
We're standing here.
This is the reference frame that's moving.
It's moving up.
It's moving up the East Coast velocity, according to fill up.
And we know that it's in a reference frame that's moving.
OK.
So.
We say the moving reference frame.
It's going to be VP with respect to water.
Neither vectors.
And then the relative reference frame.
Well, the relative reference frame is going to be what frame is pull up and he's in the frame of the
water and we know the velocity of that reference frame with respect to the ground.
Right.
So that becomes the water with respect to the ground.
So the way in which we set this up is we come right across here, we can identify all our reference
frames.
We can identify what they're measured with respect to.
And what's really cool with this notation is that.
If you want to find some velocity, that's Kopano combined with other velocities, what you can do is
you take this got these ratios, so it's sort of like PE with respect to W, and it can sort of multiply
them together like this so you can get something like this.
You can't pull that out and you get.
Fill up with respect to ground, so it sort of gives you a way to track these things and find the term
you're really looking for.
OK, so that's the notation I like to use.
You can come up with whatever notation you want, but the key idea here is to label everything, be
consistent and chug along.
And you know what?
To make this gel a bit.
Well, the problem a bit better at the problem.
We're going to take these guys and literally put them on our diagram here.
So this is the W.
With respect to ground.
Right.
That's the water, Terrence.
Well, that's larceny of Terrence.
With respect to the ground and similarly, this this guy would be VP with respect to the water, but
we don't have a vector on this diagram, so we got that guy there.
We're looking for the velocity of the boat fill up, according to ground p with respect to ground.
Now we can literally plug and chug because we have all the other ideas here.
We go back to our given column.
We have the unknowns.
It's plug in shock, baby.
So this is that equal to.
Well, let's plug that guy in.
This is a positive for.
In each direction.
And the velocity of the water with respect to the ground.
That's a negative six.
In the I direction.
And the units are all meters per second.
OK.
So what we get is we rearrange this in which we usually use vectors where X we go X and one z, we get
negative six i plus four J.
Meters per second.
OK.
So it's pretty easy problem.
We took.
What we derive previously, we have faith in this.
There's a constant velocity and then the real challenge is really making sense of the numbers we're
giving, making sense of the scenario and keeping track of everything.
If you can do that, if you can label everything and you stay on top of what's going on, then chug
along.
The answer pops right out.
OK, so that's the number we're going to get.
And next what we're going to do, we're going to jump into the next section of the problem.
Try and complicate it a bit further.
Test your knowledge and give you some more practice.
All right.
Now the next thing we want to question and figure out using all the tools we've just developed is Part
B the following.
What is the velocity of the boat?
According to Terrance, as he cycles on the bridge.
Now, in this case, we're going to consider a different set of reference frames, but we can still
use this basic equation here.
And what's really going to guide this problem again?
The solution to this part is really labeling everything, being consistent and having a grasp on what's
going on right in front of us, OK?
So using this thing and going back to the question at hand, we're trying to figure out the velocity.
But according to Terrance, so this is according to a reference frame that is moving.
OK, so we know from here is we have about ensuring that ground addressed is equal to a reference frame
that's moving the velocity according to that, plus the velocity of that reference frame, OK, the
relative velocity.
So we're trying to figure out this guy, right?
It's the velocity according to somebody as measured in that moving reference frame.
So what we can do is, again, we can just write up something similar to this, OK?
We're concerned with this guy.
So we want the velocity of fill up with this to ground.
But now our moving reference frame is parents.
And the one at rest is in ground.
OK, so v. prime the measurement, according to the moving reference frame, the guy on the bike, Terrance,
that's going to be literally the velocity of fill up.
With respect to the movie governance and with respect to Terrence.
And then what's left is the velocity of the moving reference.
So that's going to be the velocity of Terrence with this back to the ground.
Right?
As such.
OK.
And.
Again, we see that once we label everything we could say, OK, I want people to inspect the ground
that will give us PE with respect to Ji, right?
Because the teaser council, that's the power of this kind of notation, OK?
So we're really interested in one of the variables within this equation.
We want to get to the velocity of the boat or fill up, according to talent.
Terence.
So basically, if the velocity as measured by somebody in the moving reference frame or the prime,
so we want to isolate this guy, and if we do that, we have BP with respect to G already and we're
giving or g.
Then the problem gets reduced to a plug and chuck kind of problem.
So let's do that right now.
Let's do that.
This should be pretty straightforward.
Once you label everything out and you get a grasp of what's going on.
So we want to isolate this guy here.
And when we do that, we end up with VP with respect to T is equal to VP, with respect to the ground.
We just subtract VTi with respect to ground.
We get the following.
OK, so.
What we need to do is just plug in shock, so we got this guy right here, we know that Vector is negative
six in the eye direction, plus four in the J Direction meters per second.
And again, if you have not seen that notation, eyes just shoot in that direction, J is in that direction.
We like to think in terms of Cartesian coordinate systems, and that helps us understand what's going
on.
OK, so now we need to subtract.
80th strategy that's two in the J direction, minus two.
J.
Meters per second and all we get is we just.
Combine like terms we get for minus two, so we end up with a result that is negative six high plus
two.
J.
Meters per second.
All right.
And that is the velocity of the boat or fill up with respect to the cyclist parents.
OK, so.
What we want to do is we want to take this to see if it makes sense, right?
We know on the ground the sky is moving to the left six meters per second and closer to Point B in Y
direction by four meters per second.
If you have a guy that's going in this direction two meters per second, it makes sense that what he
sees in the X direction will be the same as somebody on the ground because he's only moving up in this
direction.
It doesn't change his interpretation of the X direction.
But from the y direction he's already going to.
So according to him, this is going to be slower.
What do you want to think of?
Is having somebody in front of you driving a bit faster in a car, right?
If you're traveling 60 and he's traveling 80, right, he's really going 80.
But to you, it looks like he's not moving as fast because he's only going 20 meters per second.
So this jives, well, our intuition.
And you should do this after you saw relativity problem and it makes you Tony Relativity much easier.
But we jump to special relativity.
We all have that luxury because things won't really jive well with our intuition as we're going to see.
That's why the wacky world of special relativity and we have to trust the labeling and the mathematics
and the concepts we derive in subsequent sessions.
All right.
Let's jump to the next section of this problem.