All right, so for this part of the problem, what we're trying to figure out is we're trying to determine
how long it takes for Philip to paddle across the river.
Now where which we solve this is we harken back to elementary physics.
And we know that physics tells us that the velocity of any any kind of unit, any kind of object moving
at speed.
Is no different than the change in the lane or the change in the time, now this is at an infinitesimal
point.
We're assuming that the velocity is constant so we can use something like this without going into calculus
or.
Considering, Ephraim, infinitesimally small units.
But.
For this problem, what we know is that we want to figure we know the distance 30 is 40 across this
river.
I will write it now.
So we got the distance, the length.
It must travel.
40 meters.
We have this guy.
We know the velocity with respect to the ground, and we have to use the ground because this distance
is in the ground reference frame, right?
Distance from Philip to this guy is going to change, this is constant in the ground frame.
So if we use this in the ground frame.
That, combined with the distance D will allow us to solve for Delta T.
OK, so what we want to do.
Is we want to use the Y component because velocity in the X direction does not contribute to diminishing
this devalue in Y right.
It just moves it to the left closer to B, and that's partially why this guy ends up.
At the in the horizontal direction, but in the y direction, every second we're going to go four meters.
And that's what we want to use here.
OK, so if we take our conventions of labeling everything to make sense of what's going on, this just
becomes.
The velocity of the boat or fill up with respect to the ground.
It's going to be equal to the the entire distance de.
So I'm going to put a wide down there.
Over Delta T.
OK.
And I'm using this.
We can isolate deputy and figure out how long it takes.
All right.
That's the name of the game here.
So Delta State.
Becomes.
DIY.
Over VP.
With respect to G8 in the wider action.
OK, so I'm going to go back to that, why there?
Because we're only considering the y component of velocity.
And if we plug this straight in, we're going to get the result that we're looking for.
So, you know, DUI is 40 meters distance, it travels.
And we already calculated the velocity in the wider action.
Right up here, the J component is four meters per second.
We see two meters cancel off.
And the second one pops up to the top.
So.
We get a value of 10 seconds.
So after 10 seconds, he starts paddling.
He quickly gets to the other coast at point B and crosses the river.
OK, so that's pretty straightforward, right?
And since I'm all for intuition, let's jump to the next part of the problem.
All right.
Now that we know the time it takes for Phil to paddle all the way across the river.
Next, we want to figure out in this part of the problem is what is the total distance between points
A and B?
We know the Y component is 40 meters, but what about the X component when which we solve this is again,
we're going to operate in the ground of reference frame.
We've already calculate are velocity.
But if we know that fill up, it takes 10 seconds to get across this river or to traverse the distance
in the Y.
Then after that time, that's going to give us the distance that was traveled in the X direction.
So again, what we're going to use is elementary physics concepts.
And we're going to see that the velocity of fill up with respect back to the ground and the extraction
for a constant velocity that's going to be the distance traveled in the X direction over the entire
time of the trip.
And we already have that time.
It's not going to change between the two.
These two sections, these two calculations.
Now we want to find is Delta X.
We want to find how far it has traversed the extraction due to this velocity last year.
The water is back to the ground, right, because as he paddles across, he's trying to go straight,
according to himself.
But he is going to drift to the left due to this philosophy, so all you need to do is isolate Delta
X, so Delta X becomes.
The fill up with his back to the ground, the X component times Delta T and now we just plug in shock,
right?
Simple, straightforward problem, right?
So what we want is the X component.
So he's going to traverse.
Negative six meters per second.
And in 10 seconds.
That's going to tell us that.
If we cancel these units, the second is cancel.
We end up with meters.
We had negative 60 meters.
And it's going to be in the X direction will superfluous, but I'm going to include that.
OK, so now we know that in 10 seconds, Philip travels 40 meters in the right direction and 60 meters
in the X direction, and now we want to figure out the distance from point A to B. We need the theory
in their own right.
So if we take.
Point A and Point B.
And form a nice triangle that looks terrible.
But we just need a vague representation, what we're doing here.
So in the y direction.
We have a 40.
Meter value.
And in the X direction, we have a 60 years value.
And what we're trying to find is the Typekit hypotenuse stake.
All right, well, we can just take the green theorem.
That's pretty straightforward, right?
So we know that oh h squared is equal to 60 metres squared plus 40 metres squared.
And if you like working with variables.
Is it basically Delta X, Delta Y?
And all we need to do is literally take the square root.
And that will give us the answer we're looking for.
The distance, the total distance he traveled.
So when we do this on the sky calculator, right, you get 30, 600 plus what 600 and then you square
that puppy.
What you end up with is a result of each each.
Approximately equal to seventy two meters.
Right?
Literally just plug and shut.
So, you know, that sort of makes sense.
This is going to be longer than its legs.
Joe Walther intuition.
And now to wrap up the problem or consider one last section, one last part, which is pretty important.
All right.
So we're almost finished the problem.
The last part we want to question and we're going to wrap this up is Part E, which states that or questions.
Rather, how long does Terrence think it takes for fill up to cross the river?
Now, when you read this kind of question, you're probably like, OK, let's do the same exact thing
we've been doing.
Let's start labeling the losses, figure out what reference frame we want to do and who your mind is
probably firing a mile a minute.
And what I want to is stop and say stop.
In order to solve this problem, we already have the answer, right?
What's the answer?
We'll see.
Do we have to do anything?
No, we do not have to do anything.
Why?
Because as we showed in driving all these formulas right, we had an inherent assumption and that assumption
was grounded in our understanding of every situation in front of us, right?
I like to say that kids are sometimes the best physicists because you when you're a toddler, you're
trying to make sense of the world in front of you, right?
You play off blocks, you drop them, you see how they fall, you analyze what's going on and using
that information.
You form your own understanding of the universe, right?
So when a kid would say is that, oh, if I had a clock and I did something and you had a clock or our
clocks would sync up right, there would be no difference.
In other words, what we assumed in putting this together is that time is absolute right.
What we said is that Delta T in the ref's frame is equal to Delta T and the moving frame.
Right?
So in any kind of reference frame that we deal with these problems, what we're going to know is we're
going to say they're equivalent.
So using this problem, the Delta T.
Of parents observing the moving reference frame, they're both sort of moving, but of course, a parent's
right.
He's going to be still.
To Delta and Terrence is going to be equal to Delta.
Delta T in Phillips reference frame.
And there is no difference.
This is sort of a trick question to sort of make you think about this problem and we sort of take this
for granted, right?
I'm sure you would agree that time is absolute.
That's not going to change between different conceptions of it.
But as we start jumping into special relativity, the wacky world of special relativity, what we're
going to find is that assumptions and assertions that perhaps we established as a child or that we take
for granted have to be questioned to sort of get to the result that actually happens in the real world,
right?
We would like to hold our intuition.
We would like to hold these concepts that we take for granted on a silver platter and not really change
them or throw them away.
But sometimes we're going to have to do that.
And that's part of what makes special relativity such a hard subject to wrap our minds around.
And even for scientists back in the day which Einstein proposed, this idea is really to accept them
because they really span the face of all the ideas and concepts we've taken for granted that we assume
are universal and absolute.
But if we want to put together that nice universal conception of the universe, we're going to have
to challenge everyday concessions.
We have the universe in order to get to the truth, to the facts.
Okay, so that's the problem we ran through today.
I hope you enjoyed it.
I hope what?
What I want you to get out of this problem is.
And what I want you to continue to do as you run through problems and special relativity is.
Be cognizant of how you keep track of things, keep track of your reference frames and come up with
some kind of system that allows you to keep track of it.
You can use my system here, but in addition to the problems you run through, some homework you have
is when you run through these problems, and I think it's important to do this.
You got to figure out some kind of system that helps you keep track of what's going on.
Keep track of the different losses and figure out how you can attribute attribute them to different
reference frames, right?
If you can keep track of this stuff.
And it doesn't consume a lot of brainpower that's going to help you stay in tune with what's going on
and help you really pierce through those wacky ideas and special relativity so you can build a nice
intuition and really focus on what's going on in the problem in all kinds of physics.
It's really when you run through problems, a big part of it is really keeping track of what's going
on.
The accounting portion of it and then plugging in your numbers, right?
This is not the physics, but it's math and accounting.
If you can master this, I promise you, I promise you.
You can focus on the weird ideas, the physical concepts, and then you can master physics problems,
right?
This is important.
Focus on that when you run through these problems and then I'll join you in the next section.
As we delve into our first video talking about special relativity and start taking a look at the wacky
effects that are going to crop up.
Stay tuned.