Now we're going to proceed with
a more technical discussion and
derivation of Feynman's ideas,
the Feynman path integral.
And I should mention here from the outset,
that if you're not interested
in these technical details or
if you feel that your mathematical
background is not sufficient to
follow them very closely, you may simply
skip this and the following segment.
Because the rest of the course
is not going to be heavily
dependent on this particular derivation.
But otherwise I would encourage to
actually go through this derivation, and
maybe even work it out on
your own after the lecture.
Because understanding it would help you
develop intuition not only about the path
integral itself but
about quantum mechanics more general.
Now, the object that
we're going to discuss
in this particular segment
is so-called propagator.
Which actually plays an important role
in various aspects of quantum theory.
But at this level,
we can view it simply as an attempt
to make quantum mechanics
as close as possible
to the concepts that we understand
intuitively in classical physics.
And these concepts involve, for example,
the notion of a particle localized at
a point in space and the notion of
trajectory that the particle follows.
Now, at the operational level, what it is,
it involves the following constructions.
So let's assume that at an initial
moment of time equals zero,
our quantum particle was localized in the
vicinity of the regional point R-sub-i.
So by localized, I mean that its
initial wave function psi(0),
t equals 0, is equal to R-sub-i,
this [INAUDIBLE] vector which represents
the eigenvector of the position operator
in corresponding to this point.
Or in physical terms, it means that
this wave function is a very narrow wave
packet, localized in
the vicinity of this R-sub-i,
very similar to the wave packet that
we saw in the very first lecture,
in the last segment of
the very first lecture.
And so
this initial state is going to evolve
under the action of
the Schrodinger equation.
Which is the standard Schrodinger
equation with some kinetic energy and
potential energy.
And as we know from the first lecture,
so this quantum
evolution will involve spreading
out of this wave packet with time.
So instead of a localized
sort of particle like entity,
it's going to become like a cloud
surrounding this R-sub-i and this is
spreading out occurs in a very nontrivial
fashion the presence of potential.
Now the question that we're going to ask,
and
which brings us to this notion
of a propagator, is what
part of this particle will propagate
to a certain final point R-sub-f.
Or in other words,
what part of this spread out wave
packet will be located near this point?
And this mathematically implies
calculating the overlap between the final
wave function psi(t), which again is
governed by the Schrodinger equation,
and this R-sub-f which describes a wave
packet near some other final point.
So of course I don't want to give you
the impression that the particle literally
propagates from one localized
state to another localized state.
It does not, it actually spreads out
in the quantum mechanical language.
But a part of this wave packet will
indeed be located near this point,
and this is what we want to calculate.
And this overlap is the propagator
that we're going to focus on.
Now, another question we may ask is
how will the particle get there?
How will the particle go from the initial
point to this partially final point?
So this question, strictly speaking,
doesn't really make sense in the context
of the standard quantum theory
based on the Schrodinger equation.
Because there is really no notion of the
trajectory which implies the ability to
manage your momentum and
coordinate at the same time,
which is not possible
in quantum mechanics.
But as we will see in this
different formulation by Feynman,
so this question sort
of acquires a meaning.
And going to get ahead of ourselves,
let me reiterate or advertise again,
that what we are going to find is that
this particle goes from this initial point
to the final point for the all possible
trajectories that we can possibly imagine.
So here are a few of those
trajectories that I plot.
Right, now, to move on to actually
calculate this overlap to this propagator,
clearly what we need to find is, well,
the final wave function of psi(t).
We know the initial condition, we know
what the final state we want to get.
Now we need to, well actually,
solve the Schrodinger equation,
which in general is very complicated, but
there is a formal solution we can write
using the so-called evolution operator.
So we're interested in solving
the general Schrodinger equation here,
with some initial
condition at t equals zero.
So I assume that we know the wave
function at the initial moment of time.
So this of course, is a completely
general formulation which is not
specific to derivation of
any path integrals, but
well, in our case of
the initial condition,
we have chosen to be this localized wave
bracket near a certain point R-sub-i.
So in any case, well,
to solve the Schrodinger equation,
this time-dependent Schrodinger equation,
basically means to find the wave
function as a function of time, psi(t).
And the evolution operator
that I just mentioned,
is formally relates the initial condition
to the final wave function psi(t).
So its action is exactly, in some sense,
rotation from psi(0) to psi(t).
I use the word rotation, having in mind
this geometric picture that we introduced
last week to motivate the direct
notations of this calculated psi(t).
Which in sums,
are meant to represent an abstract vector,
in a linear vector space, responding
to the state of the physical system.
Now if we did have a garden variety
linear vector space as our Hilbert space,
which normally is very multidimensional so
we can't really draw the axis.
But if we imagine for
a second that we have, let's say,
just three axis and there is a state psi0,
which represents out initial state.
So the norm of this vector, so
the absolute value squared of this
vector sort of corresponds to the total
probability of finding our quantum
particle in a certain state.
And well, from the Born interpretation,
we can say that this
probability is equal to 1.
We will find the particle,
if it's there, in some state.
So the norm of this vector
should be preserved as we
perform a quantum evolution.
So in some sense, the only thing we can
imagine this vector doing as a function of
time under the action of
the Schrodinger equation,
is rotation by some angle to
a certain new state psi(t).
And this rotation, the operator which
sort of enforces this rotation,
is exactly this evolution operator.
Again, so here I'm just trying
to represent this in an intuity.
If we, in general, are dealing with
a generic quantum mechanical problem,
there is no way to draw it, because we
have, well, an infinitely dimensional
Hilbert space, but still at some
level this picture is preserved.
So this evolution operator
rotates a normalized state,
which describes a particle two different
states, we describe the same particle.
Now, it turns out that we can actually,
instead of writing the Schrodinger
equation for the wave function, we can as
well just write the same Schrodinger
equation for the evolution operator.
The only thing we have to
do is just to plug in this
equation into the Schrodinger equation.
We're are going to see that we have
essentially the identical equation for
the evolution operator.
So HU(t), and the initial condition for
this equation is U(0) is equal to 1,
where 1 is just the identity operator.
So why?
Well, it sort of follows in a very
simple way from its definition.
So if we look at this equation,
we see that the evolution operator evolves
our initial condition to final state, but
if t is equal to 0, there is nothing
to evolve, we just stay where we were.
And so therefore,
if psi(0) is equal to psi(0), so
U(t) is equal to 1, and this is
the initial condition we can enforce.
And one can guess in some sense, or
just pick a general solution to
this matrix or operator equation,
which satisfies both the Schrodinger
equation itself and the initial condition.
By writing U(t) as an exponential
of minus i over h bar h times t.
So well, if t equals 0,
e exponent of 0 is equal to 1,
so thus it is why the required
initial condition and
if we plug it into this equation.
So if we differentiate
this with respect to time,
So while differentiating the exponential
pulls out this coefficient,
minus i over h bar times h.
So, minus i times i is equal to
1h divided by h is equal to 1.
So we're just going to have HE to the bar,
minus ih bar, H times t which
indeed is equal to H times U.
Therefore, indeed so we satisfy
the required Schrodinger equation.
So an interesting and attractive feature
of this evolution operator is that
it solves the Schrodinger equation with
all possible initial conditions in one go.
Because the evolution operator
itself does not actually depend on
the initial conditions.
So we see that it has
a universal initial condition.
And t equals 0, U is equal to 1.
So for instance here in the geometrical
interpretation if we have, let's say,
different psi(0), let's say this
will be psi(0), well, prime.
So the evolution of this other initial
condition in this sort of Hilbert space,
would be a rotation by the same
angle around the same axis but
to a different psi(t).
Lets say, psi(t) prime here,
but the evolution operator that
would enforce this rotation will
be exactly the same as before.
So it'll be exactly the same U(t).
So in our case in particular, so
we're interested in knowing how
this particular initial
condition evolves with time.
And therefore the wave function would
be equal to e to the power minus i
over H, Hamiltonian times time
acting on this initial condition.
So this is a exact and
universal solution of the Schrodinger
equation, whatever it is.
With this and
you show condition of a localized
particle in a certain region in space.
Now let us go back to
the main question that we
posed in the beginning of this segment.
Namely, the question about the overlap
between the wave function
psi(t) propagated
from the vicinity of the point R-sub-i and
wave back it localized in
the vicinity of the point R-sub-f.
So, what we found in the previous
slide is a formal exact expression for
this sub psi(t).
Sub psi(t) is the action of
the evolution operation on the initial
condition R-sub-i, and
therefore if you put 2 and
2 together the expression,
or the propagator,
is going to be the following matrix
element, it's going to be Rf.
Here we're going to have this
evolution operator, Ht R-sub-i.
So this guy is simply this Psi(t).
And so
we get the expression that we're actually
going to use in the next segment to
derive the Feynman path integral.
So Feynman path integral is another
representation of this matrix
element between Rf and
Ri with this operator U(t).
So at this stage you may ask me,
why would we bother to look for
any other expression for the propagator
apart from the one we just derived,
which looks pretty compact and simple?
So the answer to this
is that the simplicity
is deceptive because the main object here,
this evolution operator,
involves exponentiating an operator,
the Hamiltonian.
And to actually calculate such
an exponential of an operator,
exponential of a matrix,
is a rather complicated exercise.
And in general,
even to define the exponential of
an operator is a tricky business.
So as a side comment here, let me remind
you that for an arbitrary operator,
a matrix X, in our case this
X is minus i over h bar Ht.
So its exponential is
defined by the Taylor series.
So it's 1 plus X, plus X squared over 2,
plus X cubed over 3 factorial plus, etc.
And so to calculate this series with
matrices operator is rather complicated.
And so the Feynman approach is, as we will
see, essentially circumvents the need to
calculate this complicated exponential and
from case this series right here.
And basically the end result,
as we will see,
will be an expression that doesn't
have any operators whatsoever.
And not only that, the final result
also will have a very clear, intuitive
interpretation that we already advertised
in the beginning of this lecture.