In this video, I'm going to complete
the most technically demanding part of
the derivation of a path
integral representation for
the propagator that was introduced
in the previous segment.
And here again I show the expression for
this propagator that we derived.
So in the following, I'm going to be doing
my calculations mostly in one dimension,
for the sake of simplicity.
There is no real reason to go to one
dimension, so the calculation sort of
goes the same way in two dimensions or
three dimensions or 100 dimensions.
It's just going to one dimensions is just
simplifies notations a little bit so
we don't have to deal with vector indices.
And also it will allow me to
illustrate certain steps of our derivation
in a sort of intuitive, pictorial way.
So the second comment I would like to
make is that what we call the propagator
also appears in the literature under
a name of transition amplitude, well,
from an initial point x i to
a final point x f, in this case.
And a very closely related object
is also called the Green function.
So if you see these expressions in the
literature, they may be actually very much
related to one another and
all refer to this object, essentially.
Now the main difficulty in calculating
this object, once again, is
the presence of this evolution operator,
which is an exponential of a Hamiltonian.
And to calculate this exponential of
an operator is a very tricky business.
So basically the goal of the remaining
calculation, as we discussed, is going to
be to simplify this expression so that it
doesn't really contain any operators, and
we deal with sort of regular
mathematical quantities, not operators.
And in doing this simplification,
we're going to rely on two very
useful mathematical, or physical
actually in this case, two formulas.
So one of them, the first one listed here,
we already have actually discussed
in the second lecture last week.
So this is the so-called resolution
of the identity operator.
And the fact that it is the identity
operator means that, so
let's say if we have an arbitrary
wave function psi, and
we add by this operator on
this wave function psi,
On this psi, so
what we're going to get is the following.
X sub psi, this matrix elements,
times the key of extra x, dx.
And this is identically
equal to the psi itself.
So this is formula number one.
Another equation which is going to be
very useful actually, it's a property of
the evolution operator, actually
relies on a very simple observation.
So the evolution operator itself
translates the wave function from
the initial moment of time.
So this is time and this is,
let's say, time equals 0.
So to the wave function psi(t),
the time at the final moment
of time t equals t as well.
But instead of going directly from 0 to t,
we can do that in sort of two steps.
We first can go to, let's say, certain t1,
which is between 0 and t,
and then go from t1 to t.
And going from t1 to t corresponds in
the language of this evolution operator,
is applying this operator,
which depends on t-t1,
to the wave function that
we have here in the middle.
So on the other hand, the wave function
in the middle, the psi(t1) itself,
can be represented as the action
of the evolution operator U(t1) on
the original wave function psi(0).
So therefore, what we derive here is
that the evolution operator U(t) can
be written as the product of two evolution
operators here of t-t1 times U(t1).
So the particularly simple way of
splitting the time interval into two,
in this case, is just dividing it in half.
So let's say again we have
this time axis of 0 t and
we just divide it into two pieces.
So from 0 to t2 and from t2 to t.
And so
therefore we have the expression for
the evolution operator U(t)
is equal U(t/2) times U(t/2).
So now if we're going to focus
on the actual propagator
which is the matrix
element of this evolution
operation between the initial point xi and
the final point xf, what we can do,
we can write it as xf U(t/2), U(t/2), xi.
And insert here the resolution of
the identity that we discussed in
the previous slide.
So and if we do so,
we get this expression,
which essentially splits the original
propagator into two propagators.
One goes from xi to x, and the other goes
from point x to the final point x sub f.
This splitting of the original propagator
into two allows a very useful and
intuitive illustration that I'm
going to present now which will
actually bring us closer to
the notion of a path integral.
So let's say this is my coordinate x and
this is time t, and
this is my 0 and final time t.
This is going to be my xi and xf.
And so what I am interested in
is calculating the propagator
of going from the initial moment of
time xi to this xf at t equals t.
So this is essentially what I'm
calculating, and this sort of solid line
connecting the two points sort of
corresponds to my g(xi, xf; t).
Now this equation tells me that
I can take the point in the middle,
so this is going to be my t over 2.
And what I have to do in order
to calculate this propagator,
I have to consider all possible
coordinates in between.
So let's say I will go from x i to x and
from x to x f.
This is going to be one path.
Another path is going to be to go to
a different x like so, etc., etc.
So these solid lines are going to be
sort of representing the first and
the second propagator in this integral.
And, well, obviously, this procedure of
splitting the original time interval and
position interval into
two can be continued.
So what I can do, I can keep on truncating
my time interval into smaller and
smaller pieces, and when I will
continue doing so I will have more and
more intermediate coordinates
that are going to appear.
And therefore, I will generate all
possible trajectories that they're
going to cover the entire space here.
And this is how path integral or
integral over trajectories really appears.
But at the level of this illustration,
this path integral,
this picture is not very useful for
practical purposes.
To make some progress here, so
let me formalize what I just said.
And what I said is simply
the fact that let me just split.
Instead of splitting my time
interval into two pieces,
let me split it into N pieces, so
N here is going to be very, very large.
So that t over N, each individual
time interval, is extremely small.
And so each of these small time intervals,
the evolution operator on each of these
time intervals corresponds to this
exponential e to the bar i over h bar,
h, t over N.
So this t at t over N I can
make as small as I want.
So and if I make it really, really small,
so instead of writing the full
Taylor series for this exponential,
I can write it as simply two trims.
1 minus the first linear trim, and
just to truncate my series right here.
And so basically approximate my evolution
operator in each of these
time intervals as so.
So as a matter of fact, you can say that
I shouldn't have done this derivation,
because at the end of the day
what I have actually derived is
that e to the power -i over h bar h times
t is equal to 1 minus i over h bar,
h, t over N to the power N,
where N goes to infinity.
And this is actually an alternative
definition of the exponential.
And this is absolutely correct.
This is all there is.
Instead of writing the complicated
non-linear function or
exponential of an operator as a
complicated function, we're just going to
write it as a product of a function
which are linear in our Hamiltonian.
And as we do so, in between each
of these terms in this product,
I'm going to insert my favorite
resolution of the identity.
So this dx, x, x.
And well, since I have many x's now so
I'll have to label them differently.
So there's going to be x1, x2,
x3, which will sort of correspond
to these intermediate coordinates
that I have in my trajectories.
Now if we put everything together,
we get this complicated looking
expression for the propagator,
which is obtained by, well,
sort of sandwiching this product of
evolution operators between xi and xf.
And here I'm also going to be using
the notation x0 is the initial one and
x sub n is going to be the final one.
So this will allow me to write this
propagator in a more compact way.
And also, as I mentioned,
so in between of each of
these sort of small evolution operators
for a small time t over N or delta t.
So I insert this resolution
of the identity, but
I have to distinguish different
instances where I have to do so, and
therefore have so
many different integrals.
Now the reason again,
I'm doing this is because instead of
dealing with this complicated exponential,
I now can deal with these linear
matrix elements of the Hamiltonian,
which can be calculated in
a rather straightforward way.
So just to summarize what
remains to be calculated,
if you just look at this expression,
is, well, simply the matrix element
between x sub k+1 and x sub k and
the matrix element of the Hamiltonian.
So all these guys, i, h bar,
N, and t, are numbers, so
they don't really act on these functions.
And the Hamiltonian itself, of course,
is just basically the operator
corresponding to the energy.
And it has the kinetic energy part and
the potential energy part.
And so, apart from this matrix
element I have to calculate two other
matrix elements, which essentially
are the last pieces of the puzzle
that requires to be completed in order
to get this Feynman path integral.
And so in the remaining of this video,
I'm going to be calculating
basically these guys