All right, now that we know that at least in a relativistic setting, massless particles can indeed
exist and that they are most likely some kind of light or radiation or something of that matter.
What I want to do is run through a quick example, assuming that we know what it is.
So I can show you how this can be used in calculations and how can be used in different applications,
because this forms a very core core basis for some different technologies we use in this day and age
in modern medicine and other technologies.
But in essence, I want to give you some background before we actually charge ahead and try to figure
out what in the world this massive particle could be.
So the example we're going to run through is the following.
As I talked about previously and a lot of different lectures and example problems, we can have particles
that annihilate and release the rest energy completely, but we have not actually observed that happen.
We're going to do that in this example.
So the problem these that consider the annihilation of an electron with a positron.
If you have not heard of a positron before, that's basically an electron has the same kind of mass
as an electron, but it has a positive charge as opposed to a negative charge.
So you can imagine positive charge because the negative charge they annihilate, you have no charge
left.
And in this case, they both transform.
They get transmuted into a form of radiation or a form of light, if you will.
OK, so they're both at rest.
They're going to annihilate.
They create that radiation.
We want to do is you want to answer the following question What is the energy of the resulting radiation?
OK, sounds like a very, very simple question, right?
But if you didn't know what we derive previously that the energy of that radiation or that light would
be the momentum p times the speed of light, see, you want to know how to proceed.
So what's going to happen is we're going to have something that looks like the following we're having
an electron negative in green positron e positive in red.
And what happens?
They're going to get attracted to each other.
They're going to annihilate.
And what we find is that the light which I'm going to will the step of light.
For now, I don't want to divulge the true essence of what we're going to find in the next few videos,
but the light or any light or radiation emitting on the left and the right.
And we know that if it's light, it must have this new quantity.
We and therefore we don't fully understand yet.
The energy must be p times c.
So we have a radiation wave going on on the right radiation wave, going out on the left, and I prove
how this energy p c and that's respective to the momentum of each wave.
So the one on the left, we're going to label with a one.
That's why it has p one time C and the one on the right is going to be labeled with two.
Now what we do know is that initially, if these guys are at rest, they only have what kind of energy,
rest energy, right?
So we have to run the energies.
They both have the mass of an electron that's two times MFC squared, OK?
What we want to do on this problem and what you do in every problem and special relativity, you look
at the energy and you look at the momentum and you pull out, you extract the information that you need
is the first thing we're going to consider is the momentum that's going on here.
So in order to do that, we use obviously conservation.
Well, that's him, right?
So we know that the initial medicine. let's equal the final momentum and we can just plug in our quantities
and chug along, right?
So initially, these guys are at rest, they have no velocity.
That would mean they have no momentum, right?
So initially pinot on the left side, that is equal to zero right here.
And on the right side, we know we get momentum from the left radiation and momentum from the right
ready P1 and P2.
So if you add them together, what's interesting from conservation of momentum is that when this annihilation
takes place, we know that the momentum of these cores or these radiation waves must be equal and opposite.
The radiation has equal and opposite momentum, so P1 must equal the negative a pizza and vice versa.
So when we know this, this kid, I wrote some interesting facts that we can utilize when we consider
conservation of energy, which we're going to do next.
OK, so when we do that, we know that the initial energy at state one must equal the final energy right.
We cannot create, not destroy energy, right?
So initially, we know that.
These guys are oppressed so completely that rest energy is completely.
You hear it initially, so that's just two times the mass of the electron.
These both have that asked for an electron positron.
Times Square.
This is our energy on the left.
One on the right.
The rest of energy has transformed into this radiation energy, so it must be equal to E1 and E2.
Now if we didn't have the previous lecture of the energy of a mass loss particle of light, if you will?
Well, you wouldn't really know what to do.
Heading for it, but what we do know is that the magnitude of the momentum.
Are equal and maybe in opposite directions, but the magnitude is equal.
So therefore, what we can say is that all this energy is P1 times PC.
And this is P2 time.
See at the moment to have the same name that's used.
That means that each one is equal to E2, and we're going to assert that both of these guys are just
an energy, the energy of the radiation.
OK.
So what we do is we could just simplify this, that a same variable and we get to eat here and we can
just do what they cancel out those twos.
And we find that the energy of the radiation, each radiation wave is equal to the rest energy of its
respective particle.
Think about that, right?
We've calculated the energy of electrons before, that's 0.5 one, one mega electron volts.
But this is stating something pretty interesting, right?
So we talked previously about mass energy equivalence and how mass is sort of a manifestation of energy.
It's a different form of it.
Well, this is telling us that remarkably, the first time, for example, in this course, that all
the rest of energy can be utilized and converted into radiation or light.
And that's exactly what it's doing, right?
So all that energy or all that mass, which stores energy can be unleashed fully?
Right?
We can only to fully we get all this energy out and radiation is fully converted into a form of light
or form of radiation wave.
OK, so that's pretty remarkable.
Nowadays.
This exact phenomenon is routinely observed in particle physics laboratories where you can do experiments.
And you see a positron whenever you create one.
It pairs up with election annihilates and you can measure exactly this quantity.
So we have experimentally, experimentally verified this idea that you can take the mass of this particle
and convert it completely into a different form, which is pretty cool, right?
Furthermore, we've also seen this occur naturally in the atmosphere of the Earth of a planet, right?
We know of cosmic ray radiation.
Positrons can annihilate electrons in our atmosphere.
And this was discovered by Karl Anderson, which gives more weight to the existence of this idea.
And to follow up with this, another thing which we've observed this phenomenon is our own galaxy because
we've measured light waves.
That actually had the same exact energy.
Multiple times.
And what that suggests that somewhere in the center of our galaxy, we have positrons that are being
created and then annihilate it quickly with electrons that send out these photons somewhere in our galaxy.
This is happening, which is pretty cool.
Why?
Personally, I'm not sure why, but I know that does exist now.
What I think is the coolest use of this phenomenon is in the medical field, in the medical field.
We use something called a pet scan.
Have you ever heard of that before?
Do you know what the acronym actually stands for?
What it stands for is positron emission tomography.
OK.
So as the name implies.
We're emitting positrons, and you may be thinking, well, if there's a pilot trying to make quickly
annihilate with an electron that may send off some kind of light.
Well, what would happen if we had a detector that measured that light?
What we do is we get positron emitting chemicals and compounds.
We inject that into a patient.
And that chemical is going to get concentrated in different areas in a patient's body.
So in doing so, that can allow us to gather information about different areas of interest.
Right.
Let's say we want to monitor where glucose is being used.
You inject the chemical and the glucose is used pretty predominantly within the brain.
Right?
That's its main source.
I believe it's at least one of its fuels for you to think.
So this would concentrate in the brain.
Positrons would be emitted from that chemical.
And then it would annihilate quickly with the election, we have a lot of electrons in our body, right?
And then you would get some kind of radiation that you can observe.
So you could look on a scan and wear this light is pretty predominant.
That can tell you that different phenomena is occurring in the body.
We use this to take a look at, Oh, whether it does, this chemical can concentrated in an area with
cancer that can help us scan for cancer.
So this is a cool utilization of this concept of this idea.
And ever since we theorized about mass particles and verified it, which we'll talk about in the next
video, we've come up with pretty cool technology, pretty cool uses for it.
And yeah, this is a really cool idea.
So I hope you enjoyed that example.
I hope you enjoyed learning that, yes, a massive particle can exist and that it most likely is some
form of light.
What we're going to do in the next video is we're going to explore that idea and explore what scientists
actually had to delve into, what questions they ask, what experiments they conducted.
And we're going to figure out that this is going to elucidate some really, really cool, interesting
facts and we a big ripple effect within the theoretical body of physics.
And then we're going to wrap up the course.
All right.
Stay tuned.