All right.
And our last video, we were on a brief journey through history and learned about some of Einstein's
ideas correlated with the photoelectric effect.
What did we learn?
We learned that in essence, light, although it is a wave, it does demonstrate some properties which
would suggest that it is also a particle.
Right?
We found that its energy is quantized and that there are photons composed along that wave, which in
essence contain all the energy inside of that actual light that we had.
That's the mass less particle we talked about and a few videos beforehand.
Now, at this point, we have seen that in in history that we have begun dismantling the whole notion
that light is simply a wave as proposed through classical electromagnetism.
However, you would think that this day and age, if you heard about this and you are reading about
the history, that this would be enough evidence and convincing enough that people would assert that,
yes, light does have a particle element or property to it.
However, since electromagnetism was the king of the day and we didn't find a lot of discrepancies aside
from those we talked about the photo electric effect, these are new discrepancies.
People tend to adhere to that classical phenomenon, the classical idea, and they are resistant to
adopting these new ideas.
So even though the evidence was right in front of them, even though Einstein said, wake up, take
off your blinders and see the truth, they refused to accept that, which is right in front of their
eyes.
OK, so back in that day, we were talking about 1985, when Einstein proposed this whole theory about
photons and packets of energy.
People still do not believe that there was convincing enough evidence that light indeed was a particle.
So is to say.
So what exactly can you do to convince people of this wolf if life really was a particle, probably
one of the most natural ways to convince somebody of those properties, would you collide that particles
another particle and measure the energy and momentum?
And one argument that scientists had back in the day was, OK, well, you showed with your experimental
evidence that they collected.
I believe Millikin was the individual who did this that.
You know, it seems like the energy can be quantized, the energy is equivalent to each f we got right
here.
Well, if the energy behaves like a particle, what about the momentum?
Surely, if it's a particle, we should have some momentum.
And what do we discover previously in special relativity tennis that Einstein came up with seemed to
suggest that it was indeterminate.
That momentum was nonsensical, right?
We went through that argument and seemed plausible.
OK.
So in order to really convince these individuals what you would want to do is do an experiment where
you collide a piece of light, a full time particle, if you will, and measure the energy of some recoiling
particle.
OK.
And that's what we're going to discuss in this video in going over something which is very important
historically and also in terms of physics, which is known as compton scattering.
OK, now back in the day after these discoveries were made regarding the photoelectric effect, what
scientists were starting to discover is that another hole in the fury of classical electromagnetism
was cropping up.
So what they were doing, they were developing x rays, which had a very small weight.
Yeah, very small wavelength and hence a high frequency.
What they're doing, they're producing these higher energy waves.
And this was mostly produced by the reverse effect of the photo electric effect.
So if you took electrons and shot them directly very quickly, a lot of energy into a huge block of
metal.
Right.
If it goes to the metal and it stops.
What happens is that energy has to go somewhere.
So something known as breaking appropriately named, it's slowing down on that particle breaking radiation
would occur where the electron will be transformed.
All that energy, its kinetic energy into a light or an X-ray, in this case, a very energetic radiative
wave that gets emitted into the environment.
OK, so scientists were doing these experiments at this highly energetic form of radiation.
And what they discovered is that conversely, to what classical electromagnetism asserted, is that
if it collided with something else, this X-ray, they found that they measured the scattered wave.
And that wave did not have the same frequency as that which hit the surface the incident frequency.
Now this is a big question that a lot of people actually saw the evidence it did not lead because it
spat in the face of electromagnetism, because what that asserts is that your wave, if it comes in
at a certain frequency, bounces off some kind of particle.
It should be emitted with the same frequency.
OK, that was a basic tenet that electromagnetism predicted.
But scientists, again, they're finding the contrary result.
And what they should have done is said, Hey, nature's communicating to me.
Let's listen to it and let's develop theories based upon that.
Instead, they want to worship their theories.
And as we found many times in this course, once you ignore nature, it slaps you in the face by pushing
you along in the wrong direction.
And eventually you put forth invalid predictions, evolve theories and invalid laws.
And that's what happened.
So it did not what this was discovered, I believe, was like in 1912, around that kind of time frame.
And it took them all the way until 1923, when an individual named Arthur Compton came around and argued
that I took this x ray right and treated it like a particle and collided with an electron, for example.
He argued that when radiation is scattered by electrons, each scattered photon, which is a particle
we've seen this reminds sign in the photoelectric effect results from a collision with a single electron.
And the rules of conservation of energy and momentum hold in the collision.
Whoa, what one word.
What's going on here?
Let's dive into his experiment and try to understand what he was doing.
He was trying to say, Hey, guys, it's a particle we shown that has energy related to that particle
photon.
It has to have momentum.
So let's do an experiment or take some kind of radiation from incident photon.
We shine it onto an electron right here.
And that x ray is going to be scattered, we want to measure its frequency and also the momentum and
energy of the scattered electron, right?
Right.
So this is an electron right here.
I'm going to put an e right there and another e right there.
And what we can say is that.
Energy has to be conserved.
Momentum has to be conserved, right?
The basic classical tenets of physics have to hold Okay, so well, how do you measure the momentum
of light?
We've never really worked on that before, where we can theorize what it is.
And then you could take your experiment and your data to confirm what you theorized.
That's how you do good science.
We've talked about this many times before.
I'm not going to repeat the many ideas I've put forth in this course, but they should be bang to your
head at this point is very close to the end, right?
I know, get inside.
But anyway, so what we can do is we could say, OK, let's look at the evidence.
What did nature tell us?
Let's take those ingredients and pick something new, a new theory.
And so what we can do is we say, OK.
Previously we found Einstein told us and plonk told us that the photons writing these packets of energy,
it's equal to the plant constant times, the frequency of that light, of that radiative wave.
And we also found for special relativity that energy also equals picks.
What if we combine this to try and find some kind of momentum and try to measure it?
Sounds plausible, right?
Let's let's do that.
Let's do that.
So what we could do is we say your PC divide.
See, over here, we get your receipt and we say, Oh, well, wait a second.
You know, light still has a wave properties so it can use this that's has wave and particle properties.
The way property comes from the frequency F and a particle property comes from the quantized photon
and the experiment we're going to show right here today.
We plug in each half here and we can make note that if we have a traveling wave, we know the speed
of that wave, which is light, is light, right?
It's radiation is just lambda times the frequency now if you've never seen that before.
So I believe we've yeah, we've encountered this before in this course in the Doppler shift section.
You can look at the units, right?
Lambda, that's meters stuff, a length and frequency that's like cycle per second.
So this is the length per second.
That's a velocity, right?
So what we could do is ePrivacy.
Well, yeah, that's just one over lambda.
So we could plug one overlap into here and we got something which just wasn't known at the time.
I didn't call this at the time.
This is known as a deep rolling wavelength.
The he.
Wavelength.
And what are the constant theorizes, hey, it's going to cost the medicine?
It seems plausible that it is like this.
Let's do an experiment.
Let's measure quantities that we can and seize.
This works out in the theory.
Right?
And then I'm going to show you that my son's right.
The evidence is right in front of us.
We just need to listen to it.
We need to accept the gifts that nature is conveying to us.
OK.
So what he did, he got his X-rays and they were shooting x rays into carbon.
I believe graphite carbon atoms.
And what he did is he treated his electrons as stationary stationary particles.
And you might be saying, whoa, wait.
A second in carbon, electron electrons are flowing pretty fast.
They're right.
They're flying all over the place, but they are bound by an electron.
And what what was theorized is that OK, we can essentially treat it as a stationary particle because
the energy of that electron compared to that of its X-ray, I'm going to do a calculation here to convince
you is so the X-ray energy is so large compared to it.
So, for example, an X-ray has a wavelength of like 0.07 nanometres going to use point one nanometres
wicked take.
Our equation here is that we know to be true, we have experimental evidence for and plug in for F F
is just c over lambda from this guy.
And one convenient thing you'll see in physics is as we're seeing quantum mechanics, this h c term
here, it's pre-computer for us, right?
That's that's a constant 12:40 electron volts nanometres.
And all we need to do is plug in the wavelength of the X-ray.
So when we do that, we put in point one nanometers.
We get an energy approximately equal to on the order of 10 to the fourth electron volts.
Well, guess what?
The energy of electron and should make sense, given the units in a carbon atom is a few electron volts.
So this in essence, he is essentially at rest, right?
It's so small compared to this, we could treat it as being at rest.
So that's what we're going to do.
We're far photons in.
They're going to hit hit that electron.
The photon is going to recoil.
We can measure the frequency and using today we reduce particle accelerators, but we can measure the
momentum and also the energy of this electron.
And then we can apply our best friends conservation of energy and conservation momentum.
OK, let's do that.
Let's do.
Let's see what happens.
So what we can do.
First, what to do.
Conservation, no matter what we know, is that initially this guy is at rest.
So we set that momentum essentially to zero based upon arguments we have here.
So initially we have photon coming in.
It has a momentum of p not means the momentum of the photon initially.
And that momentum has to be equal to the momentum that results finally for the final, and that is the
momentum of the photon and the momentum of the election, which we have right here.
And again, these are vectors.
Hence the notation.
So it's easy really to measure the election.
We're going to go with that and isolate the electron.
That's what we've dealt with.
We haven't really dealt much with the light.
And that's what does that study here.
So if we isolate P.E. and that's equal to the momentum of the initial photon minus the final photon,
and what we want to do is recall some useful properties of vector analysis.
So what we can recall is that if we have the DOT product, the Vector V1 with itself right, that is
equal to by definition of the DOT product, the magnitude of the vectors and times each other, the
yuan times v one times the cosine between those vectors.
Now, if we have the two vectors in and of themselves, right, we have one here.
And if it's the same vector, you know, it's pretty much on top of it.
So this this angle between it's let's let's back up here, if you had a different.
Guy, you have an angle between it and now would be thrown into here, but if it's the same vector,
like if we're taking the vector people up north, then Theta must equal zero, right?
That guy must be equal to zero.
And you get some really nice results.
So what you find?
Is the following.
Basically, it's just equal to the magnitude squared, because cosine of zero is one.
Right?
So you just get basically everything that's on the left right there.
OK.
So what we're going to do is want to take make use of this to simplify our life and get rid of all these
vectors.
Just work of magnitudes, right?
So what we could do is we could say, OK, the magnitude of p squared is nothing more than right.
We can use this relationship here.
We can say P Square is going to be p dot p and we're going to use this guy right up here.
Throw this guy into each one.
OK.
So when we do that, we get the dot product of the initial minus the final data into itself.
Again, it's the same vector, so the angle has to be zero.
So what we end up with is the initial momentum that into the national momentum this got here.
And then you get minus p not plans PPF minus PPF.
Oh, right, right.
That's going to be flipped, right?
We could flip it there.
Equivalence, in essence, because we just get this with the two magnitudes 'cause the angle between
them, that's equivalent.
So we get the minus two PBF got it into p o.
The order does not matter.
And then we get plus PPF, not in the PPF.
Well, we know that from this guy right up here, a vector dot it into itself is its magnitude squared,
right?
It's the norm, in essence.
So we get this p not squared plus p s squared minus two.
We basically use this definition here two times the magnitude of p at times the magnitude of p zero
times the cosine of the angle between those factors.
So in essence, it's sort of like placing a vector onto these guys.
So this guy has to go in that direction.
We got the recoil direction.
Let's find the angle between them that can tell us how it's going to recoil.
OK?
Sort of what Arthur was predicting and measuring.
Okay, so we got this nice formula right here for the momentum.
All we need to do is apply conservation of energy, and then we could try to isolate our Lando's Momentum's,
our frequencies, whatever is of interest in your analysis.
So what we could do is, again, conservation of energy.
The initial partial portion right here has to be equal to the final portion right there.
We just plug in Chuck Berry.
So initially we know that we have an electron at rest, so we're not a energy any c squared.
Plus, the incident energy of Atherton, your HSF that must be equal to the energy of your photon and
the energy of your electron, and in this energy of the electron, we're still going to have the rest
of energy, but I'm going to throw it straight into there.
OK, so what happens is we want to get again.
The energy of the electron, we want to isolate that guy.
And when we do well, we end up with is not energy of the electron is you go to the U.S. energy of the
electron plus.
The energy of the incident, photon mines, the energy of the final photon, and this sort of makes
sense because the energy here has to be equal to the rest of energy plus.
Plus, the energy that didn't go to this guy, right?
The difference between incidents and the final third, that makes sense, right?
Some of the energy goes here, the rest goes to there.
That makes sense.
The drywall for insulation, let's proceed.
So in order to proceed, math gets a little messy.
And I apologize.
I don't have a lot of space here, but stick with me.
I'm going to explain it.
You don't understand, OK?
So what would you do?
We can use our relationship that.
E squared is equal to PC squared, plus the rest out of squared.
So we have you.
You have to take the square root of that, right, Angie squares equal to these guys.
So if you take the square root, it's no matter the electrons on C squared plus the rest of energy squared.
And then that has to be equal to the rest of energy here, and we could plug in shock.
So the energy of the incident photon.
Well, that should be easy.
We know from right up here and we're going to use this guy because we are interested in the momentum.
That's what Arthur is trying to show to convince these scientists and also to understand the situation
at hand.
What we need to do is we plug in p p, not c for this guy minus the energy of that guy.
OK, we got momentum's.
Let's try and stop for a mistrial.
Isolate them.
So what we can do is we we need a square, both sides, because, you know, we got this radical side.
We can't really move the terms around unless if ashes.
So if we square the left side, we have to square the right side.
And what I'm going to do is I'm going to say it's a little complicated, but.
It's sort of like this is term one and.
This guy here is term two, OK, so we're here at this time, so we get first initially this turns itself.
So we get the rest of our energy squared and we get this guy times this plus this guy tons that so we
get two times the rest of energy times.
The PC turns right here.
OK.
And then we get this guy.
Term two and the parentheses squared.
We're going to factor that through.
So to do that, we just do this guy times itself, which would be peanut squared and c squared.
Um.
Plus, PPF squared, c squared.
And then you get the cross terms, which would be minus two times peopie, not PPF c squared this guy
here now.
We're running out of space.
What we're going to do is we want to get rid of this term because we're interested in the momentum,
but the photons so we can use this good at good, awesome definition we derived from conservation of
momentum.
All right, we got this guy here.
We literally plug it in here.
OK, we plug it in there because if we put the square on both terms, right, the PPE.
We get p p squared and then we just have to multiply this by c squared on the left here.
All we get is p p not squared times c squared plus p p s squared times c squared minus two PPF p not.
C squared cosine theta.
That's where that came from.
OK, so now we're going to go up here and we're going to cancel terms and also note that this guy cancels
with that guy.
So, yeah, so I got some sort of losing my voice here, but we're going to chug along because it's
for the paramedics.
So what we can do is start canceling terms.
We can cancel this guy with this guy.
We can cancel that guy.
With that guy, and we end up with some interesting terms, we see this on the left, which seems pretty
similar to this guy on the right.
We got the two times each room at SometimesI squared.
So maybe we can move this guy over and pull out kind common factors.
That's what we're going to do.
We're going to move this guy to the left and we get two people PPF c squared right there turns one of
itself minus cosine theta.
OK.
That is all equal to this term here.
All right.
So it's a lot of math, we're trying to consolidate it and make it simplify.
Well, what we find is that.
This guy comes up here two times, Russ Energy and the PC turns.
OK, now we want to do is we want to cancel common terms.
So we're going to cancel the TOS.
We can cancel the C squares and we could pull a C out here.
We do that.
We get an Emmy, not see here.
We're going to abide by Pia and P, not when we do that plebe.
Not over.
P.P.P is one of the PPF.
Minus whatever you know.
All right.
We're making headway here.
So at this point, you have to choose what you want to actually do.
OK?
We could have landed terms.
We can keep the momentum.
We can try and get this term in there.
All right, we can use this, for example.
And what's important is what you're trying to measure in confidence scenario using a spectrometer,
it was easy to measure lambdas of the incident and final photon.
OK, so we're going to use lambdas, but you could choose whatever you want.
OK.
So if we use this formula that you came up with right here,
we plug that in.
So what I repeat?
Equals lambda over age.
Right.
Want to repeat?
So he is going to be Atlanta.
You get an age on the Barney factor route.
That's one overland land lambda.
So that pops up and you get land f minus land and not which is the equation we're looking for, so.
What you find is that I'm going to consolidate this bit more, so it's easier to understand.
So we got Delta Land Don, which is going to be lambda f minus land and not is equal to.
H.
Over and e c.
And one minus cosine theta.
And what you can find is there's cosine theta.
A change in the ladder after this recoil is always greater than or equal to zero.
So does that make sense that it tells us that when it scatters off of that electron?
The wavelength always has to increase, it cannot decrease, which makes sense because it's part of
the energy is going to this electron, right?
You're going to lose energy.
Your frequency is going to decrease.
And as a result of that, your LAMDA must increase, right?
So in essence, what we're saying is if you had some very energetic x ray like this, it might go something
like this who has less energy because right now that's less frequent that you cross the tops.
And hence, the wavelength is much lower, so that makes sense such as well, we would expect the energy
to be lost.
So that's cool.
Well, what's important to know is that.
In his experiment, where he had a spectrometer, where he was measuring all the different wavelengths
and what he found is something like this, he found that Landa of an X-ray is equal to 0.07 nanometres.
And then he found something like this.
So his experiment confirmed that sometimes the photons.
They would have his shift, his Compton shift.
There's constant scattering.
Other times they would just have the x rays and what's going on here.
So sometimes the x rays hit an electron.
Other times they don't.
And when they don't retain their Landa, which is accounted for right here, right when Theta is equal
to zero, you get one minus one at zero.
Basically, flying right through it didn't hit an electron when it does hit an electron.
They're scattering around his prediction, which meant that what does that mean?
What does that mean?
It means that.
The photon, that massless particle and light was a bang conservation of energy, which we saw that
before with the photoelectric effect, but also conservation of momentum.
So when people saw this, they were like, OK, it makes more sense that.
We usually conceptualize light as a wave, but it can have particle properties because it obeys everything
we know about particles, it obeys all our laws, it behaves exactly as nature dictates that it should
behave OK.
So.
This experiment conducted in 1923 was famous because it said, Hey, we have experimental evidence for
what I sign is asserting, so it must be true, and that's when scientists really adopted this idea.
But you have to ask, why didn't light ever show these properties?
Why do we need x rays?
Why do we need that?
And the reason is because.
The wavelength of light, which is much less energetic than an X-ray, which we can't see, we can see
light because the wavelength is much larger, the frequency is lower and the the the way life is so
large.
That any kind of delta you you get is insignificant compared to what we passed, if you didn't experiment
like this.
Basically your your peak, would you be smashed up into that guy?
And it's hard to resolve that you had any kind of change.
OK, you had any kind of change.
So with light, we never really experienced this and we took classical electromagnetism for granted.
And it was not until we had this highly energetic particle that we could take a closer look at it,
that these effects would pop up.
Just like special relativity, how we had to look at relative phenomena at very high speeds for all
these weird, wacky ideas to pop out.
But this is why you like really didn't tell us it didn't tell the full story.
It gave us a limited snapshot of actually a fuller picture, and it took all the way until 1923 to discover
this and to accept that light is a particle and a wave.
And nowadays, scientists take this particle wave duality principle as a fact and would defend it with
their lives, but took a lot of trial.
There took a lot of breaking stubbornness to hold on to the classical ideas to really get to the truth,
get to what was happening.
And as you'll find, this is sort of the end of our journey in the wacky world of modern physics.
But.
If you progressed further into the next really main topic, you would probably study, which is quantum
mechanics.
You'll find that this idea.
Everything we just went through, this whole history lesson really threw the biggest ripple effect into
the body of physics of all time, right?
Because what happened afterwards is they went on to find that, OK, light is a wave, but it's also
a particle.
Well, guess what?
Everything we take for granted.
Yes, everything you're looking at right now was bought as well.
My face.
Anybody who's sitting next to you right now when you're watching this.
Guess what?
They have electrons, they have protons in them, and, yup, you guessed it, they a particle and they
are also a Whoa, that's weird.
That's weird as all hell.
So yes, special relativity.
It's wacky.
It's weird.
It's contradictory.
It doesn't seem to agree with her intuition just because we're not familiar with it.
But their ideas out there, which will go on to study in quantum mechanics, which transcend beyond
the weirdness, the wackiness and the eccentric nature of nature.
So if you want to go into that, I would encourage you to check that stuff out.
It's very enjoyable.
I have studied quantum mechanics personally.
Do you want me to make a course?
Let me know.
Drop me a message.
If there's a lot of support for it, I may consider it.
But you know, our journey so far, it's been weird.
Quantum mechanics is even weirder, so I don't know if I even want to do that, but the possibility
of the interest, let me know.
Yeah, this this is the end of our journey.
I hope you enjoyed learning about this.
I hope you enjoyed learning about how introducing one simple idea can have such a huge, wide ripple
effect in everything we know and understand in this day and age.
If you have any questions, feel free to drop them in our Q&amp;A board.
You want me to do anything.
I do have a YouTube channel.
You can check that out.
I could put up random videos to maybe test drive different ideas.
Perhaps the quantum mechanics, any kind of topic you want?
Let me know.
I want to help you guys learn.
I want to help you conquer everything.
Get that a..
And rise towards success.
OK.
Thanks for supporting me.
I love you guys.
Stay tuned for future products.