All right.
Up to this point in the course, we dive pretty deep into the wacky world, a special relativity as
we've been working to try and bridge the gap between different perceptions of reality and try to come
up with this nice universal conception of the universe.
What have we found so far so far in terms of relativistic effects?
We've only really discussed one important concept.
What we found is that by accepting the two postulates a special relativity which state that one, the
laws of physics are going to arise in any kind of inertial reference frame.
And two, the speed of light is always going to be constant, and that's going to be consistent between
different reference frames.
By accepting these two principles, the consequence that arises is the fact that my conception of time
may not be the same conception of time that you have.
In other words, time flows differently in different reference frames.
Now, the name of this phenomenon that we came up with was known as time dilation.
Or another way of expressing that is that a moving clock observed tends to move slow.
So if we have observed some, some individual in a spaceship that's going close to the speed of light.
His conception of time is going to be slower or rather his conception of time is he's going to have
a smaller length of time between two events compared to somebody on Earth that's observing that same
situation right in his shoes.
Time dilates, or it's going to take longer for those two events to surmise.
Right?
So this is sort of a very weird effect time dilation, as we've discussed, and it sort of puts a slap
in the face of our basic intuition and what we generally observe from a day to day basis.
Now what we're going to do is we're going to rejoin Terrence's fill up as they start looking more into
relativistic effects that arise in different situations that they try to experiment with.
And what we're going to find is that by accepting time dilation, this wacky phenomenon that has a lot
of strange implications already associated with it by accepting it, it's going to give rise to a contradicting
situation that doesn't really make sense.
And we're going to want to try and resolve that situation before we delve into it.
I want to illustrate the contradiction that arises and hopefully allow you to really see that with your
own eyes, OK?
So by accepting what we've just studied and what we've just discovered in terms of thought time dilation,
there are two important consequences that arise.
First of all, what I have here is number one.
All inertial reference frames agree that the relative motion between them is a constant value V and
all physical laws are invariant.
So the second part of this statement that all physical laws are invariant, that's nothing more than
a restatement of the first postulate a special relativity.
And furthermore, this should not be strange, right?
We have agreed by design, by design that if my relative motion is if I'm going on a console velocity
v.
My conception of that motion is going to be the same velocity V.
Right?
That's not strange at all.
We see that in everyday situations, right?
If you hop in a car and you drive, maybe to pick up some dinner, for example, your velocity as measured
by your speedometer is going to match the velocity as somebody measures on the ground.
So that's not earth-shattering.
That's not super interesting.
Let's dive a bit deeper.
The other thing we discovered was time dilation, right?
And time dilation insinuated that different conceptions of time based upon your your perception of reality,
your perspective, if you will, that's going to change how fast or how slowly time is going to progress.
Right?
So that's part two time deletion implies that a moving clock, if observed to take slow or that Delta
T for an observer observing the motion, the moving rocket that is defined by this Lorenz factor gamma
times the proper time Delta T not now.
If you look at these two statements, that velocity is always agreed upon between multiple reference
frames, at least that their inertial reference frames.
And also that their time is different.
Can you see any kind of contradiction associated with that?
Well, what Terrance and Phillip did is they sat down and they started looking at different physics.
They said, Hey, if this didn't gel well with our intuition, with everyday situations, maybe other
phenomena arise.
Other relative is a relativistic effects come into play when we start going or traveling close to the
speed of light.
And when they looked at these two ideas here, what they said was that.
Hmm.
If the velocity is constant between multiple reference frames, but the time is different.
Doesn't that suggest that something weird is going on associated with the light?
For example, if we just take basic physics physics one one baby, we take Delta X equal to V.
Delta T v is constant, but the T changes between a two reference frames.
Well, that would imply contradictory evidence or that imply that Delta X has to be different.
Right?
Can you see that?
But that's very strange, right?
Because if we take this marker here and I look at it well, it might be, you know, maybe half a foot
eight, six inches.
So I would say it's six inches in a rest frame.
But if somebody takes it and moves with it, you would say, OK, who cares?
That relative motion does not change the length of this actual object.
So at first glance, that seems contradictory, right?
How could the length change?
But that is implied by these two, these two implications here.
So what tends to fill up do if they say, Hey, wait a second, whoa, wait a second.
I cannot agree with these two guys.
If it contradicts something that I take for granted, so I am not going to prescribe my ideas, my confessions
of reality onto the situation in front of me.
Rather, I'm going to take my preconceived notions of the universe or throw them into the trash once
again.
And look, do an experiment.
I'm going to do the experiment.
Let the events pan out in front of me, observe, collect information and then theorize, OK.
So once again, we're going to join Terrence and fill up as they conduct another experiment to dive
a bit deeper down the rabbit hole to go deeper into this wacky world of special relativity.
And we're going to see if any kind of strange, interesting phenomena arises to do that.
What happens?
Is it up?
They take the rocket ship they bought to conduct their previous experiments and they say, Hey, we
don't need this like clock anymore.
I'm going to throw that out, right?
I'm going to sell it.
And that's going to be money to buy fuel and we're going to do a trip and measure the distance.
We're going to travel from Earth to a very distant star, Alpha Centauri, which I'm labeled as a C
here.
And on that trip, we're going to measure the length that is observed in the moving reference frame.
We're going to compare that to what we know it to be.
OK.
So this is the experiment they're going to conduct.
Let's join and let's figure out what in the world is going on.
OK.
So what we know is that from the Earth reference frame in the rest frame, fill up, who's going to
weigh on the Earth, right?
He looks this up on Google, and he's like, Whew, I know the distance between Earth and Alpha Centauri
that is 4.4 light years.
It's been like that for ages.
It's always been that it's not going to change.
OK.
So Terence, jump in there.
That rocket, take that trip.
And on the journey measured the length.
Right?
My everyday life intuition is going to tell me that life has to be the same.
How in the world could life shrink?
How in the world could it change?
Right.
That does not jive with my intuition if it changes.
So if it actually does, that's going to be very interesting.
So what they do is.
First of all, they say, OK to make this easy, so the calculations are easy when you're traveling,
I want you to travel at a speed of zero point eight, six seven times the speed of light.
Now we've seen this number previously and this was selected because.
Lawrence Factor Gamma, this guy is nothing more than one over the square root of one, minus the relative
velocity of the oversee.
Square and what we find is that if we use the speed zero point eight, six, seven times the speed of
light in this equation, this guy comes out to approximately.
To a factory or two, so that makes the calculations very easy, very straightforward, and it makes
our life easy.
So before the ship goes off, they plan out what's going to go, go on, what's going to happen.
And they say, Wait a second.
I know that in my reference frame, Delta X is equal to a v delta t.
It's basic physics, baby physics, well, one, I can calculate the time it's going to take him to
travel.
And then based upon what we have observed previously, our theory of time dilation would state that
Terrence's time is going to be different than the time I calculate, right?
So let's calculate what that's going to be.
Before we start, so they line up and they can communicate along the trip.
OK, so what we do is we say, OK, we know Delta X. We measured that.
We have a very precise number there.
We know BP is going to be the same, right?
We just agreed.
Statement one.
We lost conception of the relative motion.
It's going to be the same as Terrence's concession.
It's going to be this point eight, six seven C. All we could just say Delta team is nothing more than
Delta X over V.
So you plug in these guys, we got four point four light years and sometimes in physics, what you do
is you put a little C here, multiply by the years that stands four light years.
And then the velocity is nothing more than zero point eight, six seven C. So the CS cancel and we find
that Rob's conception of time.
Is nothing more than I look that up in my notes.
That turns out to be five point zero, seven years.
So, Philip, does this any lots of things like, oh, that's not very interesting, that's why he has
a grin on his face over here.
Right, that's that's pretty straightforward.
But what is interesting is going to take a long time for parents to actually fly to Alpha Centauri.
So you might be a little bored, but nothing interesting has really arisen from this analysis yet.
What is interesting?
Is the following.
So in terms this reference frame, which we have on the right.
What he sees as he says, you know, Phillips said that Terence is moving at this velocity v, but terrorism
is Oh, wait a minute.
Alpha Centauri is actually moving.
I'm not moving.
I'm standing still, right?
This is the disparity in the asymmetry we discussed previously between the two reference rate.
So he says, wait a second.
Alpha Centauri is coming in my direction.
With this, the speed and the Earth is moving away from me with this speed.
Does OK.
All right.
So what we want to do is we want to look at his conception of time and also try and figure out what
length.
He gets.
All right.
We uncovered this apparent incompatibility inconsistency between these two facts.
Right.
They both think the relative motion is B, but population would imply that their conception of time
is different.
There's a different elapse of time between two events taking place, or they would have to apply.
This life is different.
OK.
So before we do that, what I want to do is take a step back and review some important ideas.
So when we talked about time dilation, I mentioned a very important parameter known as proper time.
And what I said is proper time occurs in the reference frame.
It's the special designation of time where two events occur in the same place.
So let's back up a little confusing.
Terrance has the proper time because in his reference frame, he's just standing on the rocket ship
and the first event, which is take off that Earth.
And the second event landing on Alpha Centauri.
He hasn't moved, it has occurred in the same place in his reference frame.
Right.
So the two events are synonymous and we signify that as proper time now, the proper time is always
going to be the reference frame where the time is shortest.
And when you do any kind of problem like this, you want to start off by designating that OK.
So in his reference frame?
The two events are synonymous.
And the time is shorter, it should be shorter, should be shorter, and we can relate it by this relationship
here.
Now, as you can imagine, if we found this discrepancy, there's probably some relativistic phenomenon
that's going to arise related to late.
OK.
Right.
Spacetime is bending to account for this assertion that the speed of light.
Has to be constant no matter what.
So to compensate for that space, time bends, time may change.
Life may change.
We know the time part we're trying to figure out the life part.
OK, so.
Let's make a special designation between the lines between these guys in case they change, sort of
give it away, right?
Sorry about that.
Anyway, jumping back at the problem, what are we going to designate as proper length, the proper
length?
It's going to be defined the same way we define proper time, so proper time.
We sort of used the frame of reference that guide well, our intuition, right?
We said when we time a trip in a car.
We do it with a reference frame that moves with the car, right?
We jump in the car, we have the timer, we go.
We stop it when we get to the destination.
Similarly, when we measure something, the marker, for example, right?
We do it in the reference frame.
That's that rest.
We don't like to move it and then measure it.
We make it stationary and we say there's one event at less than and there's one.
Even at the right hand, we figure out where they're located.
Take the difference and that's the length, right?
So to.
Help this designation jive well with our intuition, what we're going to say is that the proper length
is the length of an object measured in its restaurant, just like we do with things on Earth, just
like we do with things on Earth.
So it's proper because it agrees with our intuition.
So based upon this definition here.
What we're going to find is that the proper length?
Well, if we measured the distance from Earth Alpha Centauri, the proper length occurs in the rest
frame when you're not moving.
That would be Philip's interpretation.
So we're going to measure this as proper length and we're going to use the same designation, a knot.
We're going to say this is oh, not right.
So that would mean that Phil Terrence's conception of the length of the trip, we're going to call this
instead of a question mark, just a big help.
Now.
We set up the problem.
We got the experiment and play turned to Philip are ready to execute.
What do we need to do?
The first thing we need to do is come back to this board and raise some space.
Give us some room to write and explore.
Do some physics.
And then when we do that, we're just going to take a look at very simple ideas again, as we found
with time dilation, it's a very simple fact and it arises basically from trigonometry, very simple
ideas.
But the implications are very complex, convoluted, and that's what can make it confusing sometimes.
So what we're gonna do is we'll take the first possible special relativity and that says that the laws
of physics are invariant between reference frames.
So that means that, you know, Terrance and Phillip are going to agree that in their space, the velocity
which they have found to be constant, the relative motion between them is constant.
Maybe the way is it is different, right?
Terence, these Alpha Centauri moving to him relapses, Terrance moving away from him.
We know that V is just Delta X over Delta T, right?
Basic physics one one.
Nothing surprising.
So they can both do that physical principle of physical law, and it will be true in their reference
frame.
Right, that's the first possible special relativity.
So Philip could say, you could say, Oh, OK, I can measure that velocity.
That's that's not very interesting.
That's Elmont over.
Delta T, but wait a minute.
Terrorists could say.
You know, Amanda's now, right?
That's not right.
It's actually 11.15am, right, I measure time differently.
Time progresses in a different manner in my reference frame, so you know, there might be differences.
Little weird, little we're but we they both agree that we is confident.
So before we do this?
Parents could say, like what we're just talking about, you say, hey, we know that time dilation
says Delta T is gamma delta t.
Not so.
I mean, if you calculate at the time, it's going to say for me, I know that I should contact you
after the following, we take Delta T not set that equal to Delta T over gamma and then we just plug
in your baby.
So this is five point, oh, seven years.
And we divide by that noise factor, and that's why we chose the speed divide by two.
Well, we end up with is I believe that's 2.5 three or four, and I check my notes.
I put down 2.5 for.
All right, so his time is different.
And thanks to their work previously, they're able to figure out what time they should contact each
other, right?
It's off by a factor of two.
But this that is what gives rise to a new phenomenon, a new interesting fact that we're studying right
now because.
If this is constant.
And that guy and that guy are different.
Then these guys also must be different.
Let's back up a bit.
I want you guys to understand that, OK, that's a very important application.
OK.
These quantities, this quantity is the same as this quantity.
So this is different than this in order for them to be equal in order to assert this fact, which Terrance
and Phillip both agree on this life must be different than that length.
Well, wait a second.
How could the length be different?
That's just what it is that special relativity forks.
So what we could do is we can go boom and we can say, Hey, I know this relationship here.
Delta T over Delta T, not that's nothing more than gamma.
Let me make use of this.
This result, so we could say, well, not overall is equal to Delta T over Delta T not.
All right.
And this is going to be equal to gamma.
So what we find is that if we isolate the new life we're trying to find right here, multiply and multiply
all over here, divide by the gamma, we find that.
L equals L Mart over drama.
Whoa, wait a second.
The two legs are not the same.
They do not equal.
So you should be scratching your head like, whoa.
So what exactly happens?
Let's explore this a bit further and try to understand it.
Try to extract the information that we have gathered from the universe.
Let the universe dictate how things behave, and let's interpret that.
So what we find here is that we have a phenomenon where.
The proper length is being contracted, it's getting smaller, so the length, according to somebody
moving is always going to be smaller, right?
So this we call it length contraction.
That's the formal name.
And another way of thinking about this.
Is the following.
The implied effect.
Of life contraction.
Is that?
A moving.
Body.
I've observed.
To be contracted.
There to get smaller, so the light.
Shrinks, it gets smaller, and yes, this is not a fictional phenomenon that's rising, this is a true
effect.
Just like time dilation, something that you will actually observe.
Somebody who's moving is going to see this distance shrink.
It's going to be smaller.
This is a realized fact and it's something we have discovered.
We have verified evidence of lab experiments multiple and multiple times.
This is a real effect.
This is reality.
This is the universe.
So when Terence is flying to Alpha Centauri, what does this thought experiment?
And he's like, Whoa, man, that's why his mouth is wide open right there with this result right there.
And he's freaking out because his conception of space is not correct.
Just like his old conception of time, and maybe he might get a Nobel Laureate Prize because of this.
So he's freaking out, but he's saying Terrence is going to report a different length, and he's right.
So we could technically calculate this by saying, Well, the length is just going to be the following.
So this light that's going to come out to be two point two.
Light years.
And what I want to make note of is this should not be surprising, right?
This is a weird effect, very wacky effect.
But if you look at what's in front of us, it, it just falls right out of the map, falls right out
of the physics, falls right out of the experiment.
Because look, if Terence is going at a velocity of B.
And his time is shorter than the elapsed time is shorter than what he had, and of course, he has to
travel the same amount of length, right?
Because.
At the end, he's going to be at Alpha Centauri, and they both agree about that event, that at the
end they're at Alpha Centauri.
But in order to make that happen with the same velocity here.
This has to be shorter.
Right.
This has to be shorter, otherwise his velocity would have to speed up to go that same exact distance.
Right?
So as you can see, again, just just as we have observed with time dilation space, time is bending
to compensate and exert the fact that the speed of light is always constant and that that fact is consistent
between reference frames.
Now let's dive a bit further down the rabbit hole.
What we observe with time dilation that this phenomenon is sort of asymmetrical.
We're going to see the same exact idea crop up.
OK, so you want to think of life contraction like this?
It's very slim at a time dilation, and they're connected, as we can see through this equation here.
But it's sort of like the opposite effect.
Let's explore this asymmetry.
So in this situation?
Parents, this conception of the life it's contracted because he's it's moving in his reverence for
him and his reference frame.
This is moving towards him.
OK, now.
We could also explore the alternate situation we can say, Terrence, are you seeing right here?
He's super bored, so maybe he maybe he has like a TV in here with him.
So he's watching TV and here when he's he's going out, S.R., he has to weigh 2.2 or rather 2.5 four
years to actually get to his end destination.
That's why he's super bored in that picture.
So he could have this and you can say, Hey, man, I have some length here.
But in this situation, this becomes the proper length because if we measure it in a moving spaceship,
in the spaceship, that's when it is at rest for the person in the spaceship, in the prime reference
frame.
So you may see this is Elmont, but to fill up, if he observed a themed television that's moving for
him, the length would be contracted, Rick.
So it's an asymmetrical effect where you know the opposite has a different the opposite reference frame
has a different conception of the length of space.
But if you flip it around, that same effect can apply, OK?
And the symmetrical nature of it comes from the proper length.
OK.