Now, in terms of experimental evidence, as I said previously, we can use the same ideas and notions
that were used to prove time dilation, but I want to spend some time talking about one event.
One use of proving this that I talked about previously for time dilation, which was the decay of subatomic
particles.
Now when we talked about that, where time dilation.
What we found is that the half life, which is the time it takes for half of the population of subatomic
particles to decay, to vanish and disappear, that time is dilated.
And that extra time allows it to survive a sufficient amount of time to get to its destination.
And this is taken advantage of and used to prove both time dilation and length contraction actually
in a lot of experiments in particle collider.
So what we usually have is we usually have two protons of tiny particles coming in and they collide
within a particle accelerator in that collision gives rise to a particle known as a pi on which I have
labeled here.
And what happens is we usually don't do any kind of experiment with that particle actually right where
the collision occurs, because you try to, you want to try to avoid that.
You know, that's a very high energy collision.
You want to avoid that for safety concerns.
So what they usually do is they have a pipe that the pion travels down to an experimental site.
We can actually do stuff with that.
That particle now based upon time relation and what was used and actually theorized by Einstein.
If you take the half life of a pylon that is measured in the moving reference frame, as we talked about
with triangulation, right?
The the life that actually sees that is in a moving reference frame.
So we know that the birth and the death of a particle occurs in the same point on that that pylon.
So that has to be the proper time.
As we talked about previously and as a result of that, the time in the lab reference frame in the stationary
reference frame has to get dilated.
So what we find is that you have to size the pipe a bit longer to correspond with that time to account
for it.
So what you find is that Delta rather t. the Half-Life.
He one half.
This has to be dilated.
On the proper Half-Life.
So we get something like that.
And the actual time in the lab reference frame that we observe is much longer.
So if we didn't have this time dilation?
It would actually die before got or decayed before we actually got to the end of the tube.
You would not observe any particles right there would be gone would be poof vanished into thin air.
Now what if we go into a different reference frame, the reference frame that moves with the pylon?
In that case, what you would say is OK, by the time we get to half the pipe, all the particles vanished
and we're not going to reach the end, the end.
But that can't be true because we know that we actually observe them in the experimental site.
So there has to be some other idea, some other kind of physical phenomenon that arises.
Well, in this situation, what we know is the length that is the proper length.
As I said, it's in the rest rest reference frame where the two events occur, the two events at the
beginning and the end of the pipe that occurs in the lab reference frame, right?
That tube is not moving, according to the lab.
So what you say is you see this put in or now not for this length is the proper length and what the
pilot actually sees from his reference frame.
It looks like this tube is moving up right instead of going, look, that it's it looks like this guy
is moving up with a velocity v close to the speed of light because pylons travel at a very high speed
and that makes the Lorentz factor very high.
So from this reference frame, when he is just sitting stationary, that pylon, it looks like this
is moving towards it, so he reaches the end destination.
In a shorter amount of time when he decays down here because this distance is shorter, so from his
perspective, it looks like this is moving up.
So he doesn't have to travel as far as.
As it looks like in the lab reference frame, so for him, his L is no more than the life contraction,
we take the proper life.
The Viper Lorentz factor and that phenomenon allows it to get to the destination because what we all
agree on is the fact that if we observe it in the lab reference frame, in the pilot reference frame,
it has to get there.
It has to exist, right?
So in the lab reference frame, time dilation allows the possibility of this experiment, allows it
to get down here.
But in the pion reference frame, the tube looks like it's moving, so it doesn't travel based upon
its perception as far as what the lab measures, because it looks like that's moving.
So that disparity between the two sort of couples time dilation and length contraction, and you'll
see them arise in opposite reference frames.
But the key idea is this is a true fact, maybe weird or maybe strange and maybe taking a slap in the
face of our intuition.
What we take for granted right the measure of something space time.
But it's a true, verifiable fact that we have proven many, many times in different experimental situations.
OK, so what have we discovered?
What we have done in this video is we took a step back.
Initially, we had to go straight into the wacky world of special relativity.
We found that time dilates or that a moving clock is observed to move slow to tick, slow that time
dilation said, Hey, different conceptions of reality may have different flows of time.
Well, we took that fact and we used different ideas that it stipulates that different times between
reference frames and also that we agree about the velocity between two reference frames.
Those two ideas gave birth to an apparent discrepancy that if the velocity is constant.
Then what is measured between two different reference frames as such?
Must be different because time is different.
So these guys must be different and that give rise to the notion of length contraction, right?
Or rather the idea that.
The life of an object when it's moving, observed by a stationary reference frame, it's going to be
contracting, it's going to get smaller.
And as we saw, that is due to the fact because in the moving reference frame, it looks like that length
is moving towards you.
So that decreased the length that has to be traveled, but that is contingent upon your reference frame,
right?
Your perspective prize your 120 eyes.
Your perspective dictates the phenomenon that arises in front of you.
So now different phenomena and different results may arise based upon your perception.
But we started building that nice bridge that helps us get this universal absolute conception of the
universe, right?
So Terrance and Phillip may disagree about the length they observe, but using this idea using these
these tools they developed, they can say, Hey, we bridge the gap between these, these differing
perspectives.
We're able to get some universal conception of reality.
Life is good.
All right.
So that's length contraction.
It's a little weird, but it's true.
It's a true observable fact.
Yes.
And looks like life does get smaller when objects start moving close to the speed of light.
Next, what we're going to do is going to run through a little example problem to help you get used
to working with these ideas, working with length contraction and the result we get may be interesting.
We're also going to visit something that is known as Einstein's train paradox.
And I'm going to show you some weird ideas that arise again by accepting length, contraction and time
dilation.
Stay tuned.