All right, in our last lesson, we go a bit further down the wacky world of special relativity and
we learn about a new relativistic effect known as length contraction.
What do we find out?
We discovered that a moving body is observed to be contracted, that in a rest frame.
If we observe an entity that's moving any kind of length in that reference frame will appear to be shortened.
OK, so this is known as length contraction and compared to our everyday experience of length of things
in the world, in the universe, this idea was very weird.
It was very contrary to how we would experience things.
We in general, we we feel like the length or the way which measure the length of an object should not
change if there's any relative motion between the two.
OK, so this implied effect of life contraction is weird in and of itself.
So what I want to do in this video is run through a quick example with you.
I'm holding your hand.
Help you to build up intuition with this weird effect so you can understand it.
And then I'll unleash you to do your own kind of problems by yourself to learn independently.
In this video, we're going to run through an example, and it's going to divulge a very weird effect
that arises as a result of length contraction, right?
As we have seen in previous lessons, previous effects we've uncovered, right?
It may arise some weird relativistic effect, but if you dive further down into the rabbit hole, it
just gets weirder and weirder and weirder.
OK, so we're going to make things strange or we're going to challenge your interpretation of this idea,
challenge your conception of the universe and open your eyes to what is actually happening at relativistic
speeds.
OK, so the problem we're going to take a look at is the following OK, we're going to have terrorism
fill up.
They're going to do a new experiment.
They discover this weird effects that they want to build intuition with it, with you.
Two.
So what they do is they buy a standard box car, which has a length of fifty five point four two feet
and that was looked up by standard manufacturers of box cars.
And what they're going to do is Terence, he says, OK, I'm going to travel up some speed and I'm going
to travel into this tunnel.
The question is, if Philip, you're observing this on Earth, how fast do I have to travel such that
my life, according to you, is contracted is shortened so that this tunnel can encapsulate my life
so that I can shrink to such an amount that I fit inside this tunnel, OK?
So the problem statement officially says the pose that a standard boxcar of life 55 point forty two
feet is about to travel through a tunnel of like 20 feet.
So this guy 20 feet, how fast must it travel?
Such an observer sees the train fit inside the tunnel.
OK, so what have you kind of problems and special relativity?
The first thing you want to do is get your bearings straight.
OK, what is the proper length?
What is the proper time?
OK, so first and foremost, what we're dealing with here is length contraction.
We're going to focus on the mike, but it might be a valuable exercise to also identify the proper time.
So what we learned in the last video is that the proper length is the length of which it's the reference
frame where measuring the length of something jives, well, her intuition, right?
And that occurs in the rest frame, right?
When we measure something generally, we don't move it.
We keep it stationary.
We figure out the left and the right side and then we measure it.
And that occurs in a rest frame.
That's the best way to do it.
That's how we do it in everyday life situations.
So what we found is that the proper length is defined as the reference frame where the object is stationary.
OK, and then life gets contract in the reference frame, where that object is moving relative to the
rest room.
So what situation implies that the life of this guy is stationary?
Well, or rather at rest, well in is frame.
What he sees is he's in the car and he does not think that the boxcar is moving at all because he's
moving at the same speed as the boxcar.
What he sees is it looks like the tunnel is moving towards him.
So in his reference frame, the length of the boxcar is at rest and he would measure it just as we do
in any kind of everyday situation, right?
You pull out that measuring tape, figure out the left side, figure out the right side and measure
it.
So based upon that, that I guess interpretation of what's going on, we would say the proper length
would be intact.
This is a reference frame right there, so I'm going to put that element right there.
We know that in his reference frame, the car fifty five point four two feet is not going to change.
So this is going to be fifty five point four two feet now if we're doing things related to time.
We would also want to measure the proper, yeah, the proper time.
OK.
In this situation, we're going to skip that.
So this is the proper light, according to Terrence.
So Philip is going to see a contract at length, and we want to specify the philosophy it takes for
this guy to look like it contracted to fit inside this guy.
But.
Just taking the life right here, we know that this guy is going to be 20 feet.
That's what it is, regardless of a reference frame.
And we need to figure out the velocity that Terrence has to travel.
What should he set the car to travel, such as it looks like to him that it fits inside this tunnel?
OK, so we can do that by taking advantage of what we just arrived our life contraction formula so we
could take L is equal to L not.
Over.
Gamma, and I'm going to back up a bit here.
I want to specify this as well is the length time that we want this guy to shrink to, OK?
Because remember, this is the proper length it's going to be shaped by this shrunk by this Lorentz
factor.
And then it's going to be that we want this to be the same life as this guy.
OK, so we know these parameters.
We know Elmo, and we know.
OK, so let's factor we know is one over the square root of one, minus the relativistic velocity PETA
squared.
So if we divide by this, the radical flips up.
So this just becomes nothing more than Elmont times the square root of one minus theta square.
So if we want to solve for the velocity we need to solve for beta, because remember, theta is the
relativistic velocity.
It's just B over C.
All right.
So how can we do this?
What we could do is we could square both sides.
We can get el squared is equal to Elmont squared.
Times one minus beta squared.
And then we could divide this guy over there to get.
Elsewhere over Elmont Square.
And.
We accept set that equal to one minus beta square.
Now what we could do is we could add the beta squared over here.
Move this guy over there by subtracting it, and then we could take the square root.
So I'll do it in a criminal statute.
Make sure you guys are following along with me.
So data comes over here, we get the data squared and then we get a one minus L over L not.
And I'm going to write it as such, right?
Because if we write as such, the square applies to both terms.
And all we have left to do is just to say well.
Data.
The square root is equal to the square root of one minus L or El Norte.
And then we square the sky.
So with this guy, we can use this to figure out, well, the relativistic velocity.
That's let's be pretty straightforward.
So that's going to be just multiplied by C. We take better multiply by C.
And we get one minus L.
Over Elmont, this guy squared and multiply it by a factor of C.
OK, so what we could do?
What's left is we just plug and chug, plug in the parameters we've identified, and that's why it's
important to identify the proper length.
Just plug it in there.
And that will tell us how fast tenants will have to travel to shrink to the size of that tunnel.
OK.
So if I check my notes, we got the same exact result.
So that's good.
And what we need to do is we need to just plug it shocks.
Let's do that.
So we write the square root.
We put one minus.
We want the Lincoln Tunnel right here as identified 20 feet.
Over the proper length of 55 point four.
And we want to square these guys and then multiply by 50.
So if we whip out to 83 and plot these numbers straight in, we plug and chug chug along.
We find that the train will have to chug along at a value of zero point nine three three times the speed
of light.
OK, so.
It's not surprising that we have to go close to the speed of light because relativistic effects such
as length, contraction and time dilation.
Occur when we're traveling close to the speed of light.
OK, so this says and this is a remarkable feature, remarkable fact.
This is verifiable.
This is exactly what we would observe in real life if this actually happened.
But what we find is that if parents travels at a velocity of zero point nine three three times the speed
of light to fill up, it's going to look as though this guide short shrinks down to the size of this
tunnel.
And it will fit inside of the tunnel.
Whoa.
That's a crazy, crazy idea, right?
So that really takes a slap in the face of our intuition, of our everyday conception of reality.
OK.
But we've sort of seen that.
So it's not a surprising this is what we would have expected.
But as I said in the beginning of the year, we're going to dive a bit deeper.
OK.
So fill up.
This conception of what would happen here is correct.
Let's take a deeper look at what Terrence is going to observe.
What is he going to observe?
So for him in his situation, as I said, it looks like the train is stationary and both fill up and
the tunnel are going to be moving towards him.
So as I mentioned in the last video, there's an inherent asymmetry that is built into this effect,
right?
He may see a life contraction fill up, that is, but Terrence may also observe a life contraction,
and they're both right.
They're both right.
Right.
Because your experience of the universe is nothing more than your perspective than the way in which
you perceive events transpiring in front of you.
So, according to Terrence, if it looks like this is moving well, you know, the applied effect of
life contraction is that a moving body is observed to contract.
So to him.
It will look as though the title contracts, even though to fill up, that does not contract.
And he's right, he's right.
So that's what I feel sort of scratching his head.
He's like, Yo, Terrence, what are you talking about, man?
That makes no sense.
I don't observe that.
You're crazy, bro.
So let's take a deeper look at this.
So according to him, what he's going to say is.
Fill up, you know, this is stationary and his reference frame, so now according to fill up, this
is the proper length.
And the life he measures is going to be.
And then it becomes L, it becomes L, so again, the implied effect is that a moving body is observed
to be contracted.
So he's less moving.
It has to get smaller.
Let's calculate what that would have to be.
So we just use the same exact formula.
These guys are just sort of flipped.
So according to two, I'll put a little line there, according to Terrence.
He's going to say the length of the tunnel is going to be contracted as such.
OK.
So what we could do is, you know.
The Lorentz factor, the square root pops up, we get nothing more than Elmont and the square root of
one minus B the squared.
You know, PETA is no more than point ninety three million plug in show up.
So.
In this case, the proper length is going to be the 20.
So we get 20 feet times the square root of one minus zero point nine three three.
Quantity squared
and that's going to be equal to wait for this.
Wait for it.
Three six feet.
That's right, it gets contracted to two point three six feet.
Wait a minute.
If Phillips says that this guy is going to shrink down to a size, that's 20 feet.
And he's got to feet in the tunnel.
But Terrence says that the tunnel is going to shrink from 20 feet to two point three six feet.
And according to him, the length of his car, which is fifty five point four two feet.
There's no way it could fit inside of this.
Well, what's going on?
According to Einstein Phillips, right?
Terrence is right to.
You want to scratch your head, like fill up.
How can they both be right when their conclusions contradict each other?
What's going on here?