All right and now I want to do just a short introduction on the concept of an electric field.
So we saw four cool Ohm's law that if I have two charges let's just take two positive charges just as
an example we can calculate the force between them right.
We can say that there's going to be a force like this.
There's going to be a force like this.
If one of them has a magnitude Q one this one here has a magnitude of a charge.
Q2 that force that we're going to calculate again and call it F the magnitude of the force is simply
our K constant.
Q1 Q2 and divided by the distance squared.
All right let's go ahead and put that on the diagram as well.
Ops not 2 but rather the distance.
Ah okay so that's Coombs law.
So further to be a force we need at least two charges.
So let's write that down as also.
So for this case need a minimum
of two charges.
The question I have for you now is well what happens if there is only one charge.
Right.
You only have one charge in space what happens.
First of all there is no force because there's only one charge.
Right.
What we're going to say now is what I like to do is I like to think about it in terms of like a spider.
Let me just kind of draw us kind of a quick thing.
So the way that the spider kind of works well it will what it will create a web.
This is a really bad looking Web but it might kind of look something like this.
Start looking a little bit better.
All right.
So here we have a web right.
And our spider produced the Web.
And now if we place anything inside that web it will interact with it.
OK so our spider is the thing that's going to produce the web.
So if we have only one charge we're going to say that this one charge is going to modify the space around
it by producing what's called an electric field.
And then if I place any other object inside that electric field that's when I'm going to have a force.
OK.
So let's go ahead and kind of grid of his bad looking Web and let's just think about this for a minute.
So what happens if there is only one charge.
So you write it down
if we only have a one charge.
Okay we're gonna say that it produces
an electric field
and we're gonna call that electric field.
We're going to name it with the letter E.
First of all it's going to be a vector quantity so it's going to be important to do something like this.
Okay so let's start off with just one charge the charge I'm going to consider is just going to be one
of these two charges that I looked at before.
So just the charge q what I'm going to say now is this is going to produce an electric field somehow
in space.
And then when I placed Q2 inside that space it's going to be a force acting on it at the end.
I better have the exact same result is cool Ohm's Law.
So have a look at cool Ohm's law over here.
Let me write it down.
OK Q1 Q2 and divided by R squared.
OK so what happens if there's only Q1.
Well if there's only Q1 let's forget about Q2.
All right.
If there's only Q1 this is all I have is K Q1 over our squared.
This is what we're going to call our electric field.
This is going to be our definition of the electric field for one point charge Q1.
This tells me how big the electric field is that's produced by Q1.
So the K constant is the same.
The charge is Q1.
That's our guy over here in this case it's a positive charge and are well for cool ohms little law are
was the distance between the two charges in this case here are is a little bit different because there
is only a single charge.
So it depends where you want to evaluate this field.
Imagine I wanted to evaluate the field right here at Point P OK the distance R is defined as this distance
is the distance between the center of that charge all the way to the point where I want to evaluate
it this is how you would define R.
So let's go make sure we write this This is the field and again it's just the magnitude field produced
by a point charge
and the point charges Q One got pretty straightforward.
Now I did say something really important I did say that E is a vector
all we have now is the tools to calculate the magnitude of that vector.
So we now have to do is pick a convention and the convention has been determined for us if the charge
q 1 is positive.
We're going to say that the electric field produced by positive charges points away from positive charges.
So imagine there's a line here.
Joining it all the way to point p and the electric field here would point away from this positive charge
if I chose a different point.
For example what about a point P located right here.
It's a little bit closer to the charge.
Well in that case the direction of the electric field produced by that charge would be.
Since it's a positive point charge it would look something like this.
This would be the direction of the electric field right here at this point.
If I go somewhere over here I'm a little bit closer to the charge now that means that this distance
here is smaller right for the red point the distance here would be this one.
This would be the distance are the direction of the field since this is a positive point charge.
The direction of the electric field would be off in this direction.
OK.
It points away all right.
So let's write that down.
So it's a vector and the direction away from positive charges
and that also means that it has to point toward negative charges.
All right.
Two really really important things.
The magnitude is given by.
It's almost cool arms law.
Except I took one of the charges away and the direction.
You just have to look is it positive or is it negative.
That's producing this electric field.
Pretty straightforward.