OK so to illustrate this a little bit now what I want to do is I just want to draw a cross section of
my plate.
All right.
So let me go ahead and draw a plate here.
I'm going to make it.
Give it a little bit of thickness just like this.
So again the area goes in and out of the page here over here.
And let's assume now that I again I it's a conductor and I've placed some charges on this plate.
And again those charges are going to evenly distribute.
They really want to repel each other.
So what we have here is some charge density which is the total charge divided by the area.
All right.
How would you go ahead now and plot this electric field vector everywhere in space here.
So on the left hand side and on the right hand side.
Well again what I would do is I would just plod vectors right.
The vector at this point is a vector that points away from it everywhere with simply point away from
the plate.
I would equally space those vectors because the field is uniform everywhere.
And the magnitude of this field again.
Here's the equation right here.
So in this case here would be Sigma divided by two times my constant Epsilon 0.
That is the magnitude of the electric field here.
The same everywhere.
How about on the left hand side of the plate.
Again I would do the same thing
again.
This is when I'm close to the plate.
I can move a little bit farther away from the plate.
And this is what the electric field looks like.
Again e is the same magnitude here.
Even if I move farther away.
All right.
This is what I have to have.
The field simply points away from that plate and it's constant everywhere.
Let me do one more set of vectors over here and then we'll add another plate to this configuration.
All right.
So far so good.
Last thing I want to do now.
Well let's add another plate.
Let's maybe put it over here.
I'll draw a similar plate.
The question now is well what kind of charge do I want to place on this plate.
Let's play some negative charges.
So we add some additional electrons on that plate.
Now what I'm going to do here is I'm actually going to put the same number of electrons let's assume
those are the same size.
All right.
So that the charge density for this plate over here is going to be well it's going to be a negative
total charge divided by the same area.
So this is negatively charge.
So what would the electric field look like produced by the negative plate.
How would we how would we plot that.
Well let's go ahead and draw vectors again.
It's a plate.
So the formula is this.
That's the magnitude.
The only difference now is that the electric field points toward it.
So I would have to add a whole bunch of vectors everywhere in space that are pointing toward
this plate.
How about on the left hand side.
Again I have to add a whole bunch of vectors that are pointing toward it.
Or that I draw a whole bunch of them here.
Let's just keep on going just on want this is a really really important thing.
And then we're going to look at the total electric field everywhere in space.
But for now we're going to continue everywhere.
When I'm on the left hand side of this plate the blue one over here the negatively charged plate.
I have to have vectors that are pointing toward it.
All right what we have now are really three regions.
We have region number one which is over on the left hand side of the positive plate.
I have region number two which is going to be between both plates.
And here I have region number three which is going to be to the right of the negatively charged plate.
My goal now is really define what is the total electric field everywhere in space.
So let me just kind of make myself a little bit of room to do some writing here.
So let me just kind of delete these and I can write the total field if you first have a look here what
is the total field.
Well have a look at these two vectors.
What we have here are two vectors that are in the opposite direction and they have the exact same magnitude.
So that means that the total field in this region
total field here has to be equal to zero.
There is no field anywhere over here because these vectors cancel out let's have a look at Region three
region three is something similar is going on here.
What I have here are two vectors cancelling out let me go ahead and write that out vectors cancel.
All right the electric fields cancel.
So that means that the total electric field in this region has to be equal to zero.
All right.
And the last one well let's look at what's going on in the center doesn't matter which one you consider
look at these two vectors right here.
There are two vectors that have the exact same length the length of the vectors given by this except
now they're pointing in the same direction.
So if I plot the total electric field it should be something like this.
This should be e total
let's go ahead and write it out.
So e total should be the field produced by the red one
all right.
Plus the field produced by the blue one.
While the magnitude of that field is Sigma over to Epsilon 0.
So that means that the total field at the end of the day is 1 while simply Epsilon over zero.
Right.
So between the plates you go ahead and write this down right over here between the plates the fields
are additive.
The total field the magnitude.
We know the direction that the direction has to be pointing away from positive and pointing toward the
negative.
But the total magnitude then is simply the charge density divided by epsilon 0.
Okay super super important.
And again what we have here is a constant.
It's still a constant electric field.
It's the same everywhere in space.
So really I could draw other vectors over here between the plates the electric field is uniform.
It's the same if it was right here as it is right here.
If someone asks you compare the electric field at this point versus this point versus this point they
all have to be the same.
They're all the same and they're all equal to the total electric field between the plates.