All right.
So here's our quiz on electric fields here's the first problem.
We have an electron Opes.
Let's try that one again.
Way too big.
All right.
So we have an electron that's moving to the right.
So that's important it enters a uniform electric field directed upward.
OK.
And that's kind of shown over here.
Which trajectory so we're given different dashed lines.
X Y Z or W will the electron follow.
Okay.
So what do you think's going to happen.
Well first of all electron do we know about electrons right.
They are a negative charge.
So if something's going to follow one of these trajectories you should just look at the forces acting
on the electrons so let's do a free body diagram on the electron.
What is the force.
So the electric field points up.
If you remember the fourth equation force is equal to the charge multiplied by the electric field.
But since our charge here is negative what does that mean.
It means that if the electric field is pointing up it means that our force acting on the electron should
be down.
Okay.
The force is always down.
So imagine now we have an electron kind of going in this direction over here what do you think's going
to happen while as a force acting down so it's probably going to get deflected like this all the other
ones it's not going to continue straight.
So w is not the correct answer because there's a force acting on it and it's not going to be any of
these two choices because again there's a force acting down so the best choice here is trajectory z
so D is really our best choice for this problem.
All right.
Kind of a good problem.
Next one.
Scroll down over here.
What do we have two tiny charged particles.
Oh four sorry four tiny charged particles two of them have positive charge.
OK.
Q And two have negative charges and their place like this in this arrangement.
Each charges the same distance away from the origin which is right here at the center in which direction
is the net electric field at point P on the y axis.
OK so point p is up here.
So what would be the net direction of the electric field.
Well let's first draw them.
OK.
Actually what I'm going to do here is I'm gonna use some different colors because it's gonna make it
easier to draw the vectors.
OK so let's draw this first charge.
So at point p this guy here I'm going to actually put point P right over here.
So let's have a look.
So this first positive charge the blue one produces an electric field over here that points away from
it.
So I'm gonna call this the field e.
OK.
What else.
Let's choose a different color.
What about the negative one the negative one over here produces an electric field over here point P
and that electric field should point toward negative charges.
However it should be a little bit smaller than this one so it should point like this.
All right.
What's next.
Well now we have to deal with both of those two charges.
So let's deal with this positive charge over here at Point P it produces an electric field that points
away from it.
Right.
You imagine a little line connected it should be a vector that points like that.
So that should be a vector that looks something like this.
That's the field produced by this green charge.
And our last one over here is choose purple it's a negative one.
OK.
The negative one at point p again if you imagine a line that joins the charge to point p.
It should be a vector that points toward that charge because it's negative so that there should look
like this.
OK.
So we have all of these vectors over here.
What do you think's going to happen since they're all the charges have the same magnitude.
You should be able to convince yourself that this one and this one are the exact same magnitude.
Right.
So if you were going to add both of those vectors.
If all I did was consider both of those I should get a purple and a green.
That sum up to some vector that looks like this.
All right.
What else do we have.
Now we're left with the blue and the red while the blue line is a little bit bigger than that one right.
So at the end really if I add just the blue and the red I should be having an electric field that looks
something like this.
All right.
So let's go ahead now and look at both components.
Let's get rid of this guy and this guy and this is what we're left with.
We have two vectors that are perpendicular and at the end if I would add them up I'll just do it in
pink over here.
I probably should get a total electric field that should point something like this.
OK so it should be upward first of all it's not directly up it's not directly to the left.
It should be upward.
It's not zero that's for sure.
And it should be toward the left hand side.
OK.
So I think C is the best answer for this one.
So a little bit tricky because you have four different point charges but again where you're going to
use superposition in order to add them all as vectors I think the only thing to remember here is that
this guy here is bigger the blue one is bigger than the red one so that's why it tilt a little bit upward.
All right.
Hopefully you understand that one.
Let's go on to the next problem.
So here's problem three.
What we have are the figure over here.
We have two unequal charges.
OK.
So that's kind of important over here so it's kind of highlight that they're unequal positive Q and
A NEGATIVE Q And they also tell us that negative Q here has a greater magnitude than this one.
OK.
The point X is midway between the charges and now they want to know they've identified different sections
whereas the electric field going to be zero in this configuration.
All right is it going to be zero somewhere along this section or along me somewhere in the middle or
somewhere over here.
OK.
So we have to kind of look at the electric field what I'm going to do here is we're going to try try
drawing the vectors so let's take that one to be red and the other one to be green.
Now let's draw some lines.
OK.
So let's first consider the section anywhere between both of those charges.
So that would be a W x or x y.
Okay.
Both of these it doesn't really matter which one you choose.
If you choose a point anywhere between both of those charges let's draw an arbitrary point here.
Imagine it's right here.
OK.
Imagine you're going to use superposition now.
So what would be the electric field produced by this positive one at this point.
Well it would be a vector that should point like this right.
That would be my electric field from the positive one at this point.
What about the negative one or the negative one would produce an electric feel at this point.
You would also choose an electric field that is going to point in the same direction.
Right.
You see that both of those vectors are in the same direction.
So here that's going to be same.
You make the marker a little bit smaller.
Same direction.
So definitely can't be anywhere between both of these two charges because always you're going to have
this addition these vectors might be bigger or smaller depending on where you choose your point but
they're always going to be in the same direction.
So you definitely can't have W X and you definitely can't have X Y because of this reasoning.
All right let's now look at it doesn't matter which one you choose.
Let's choose this segment over here.
Y Z.
So imagine we choose a arbitrary point anywhere over here.
OK.
And this is our point p.
Let me draw point P down here just to give us a little bit more space.
All right.
Now we have to draw the vectors produced by the electric field produced by both of our point charges.
So we have a positive point charge that produces an electric field over here at Point P and it would
produce a feel that points like this.
This would be the red vector.
How about the green one.
Now the green one now also produces an electric field that point p.
In this case what would we get.
Watch what I do with this vector.
Notice here that I've made this vector bigger right the length of E has to be bigger than the length
of the red one.
So why is that.
Why do you think that is.
So you're always going to have that the green vector is bigger than this one anywhere in this section.
And that's because look at this one.
This charge here is bigger charge greater magnitude.
And you're also closer to it.
Right point p is always going to be closer to this charge than it is to the smaller charge down there.
So that means that this vector here is always bigger than that one.
So you'll never have zero electric field over here.
All right.
How about the other section over here.
Let's draw an arbitrary point over here make it orange and let me draw it down here.
So again now if you draw the electric field due to both of those you're going to have a vector produced
by an electric field produced by this positive charge.
And it points away from it.
And you also have an electric field produced by the negative charge and that one points toward the negative
charge.
Now if you have a look at the distances in this case right the distance over here is small.
Right.
So that vector could be pretty big although the charge is small there's always two things that affect
the electric field right.
It's the charge and also the distance if you make the charge bigger you're gonna have bigger electric
field.
But if you make the distance smaller you can also have a big electric field.
Have a look for this negative charge.
Look at how big the distance is now this should be the distance that I would use to calculate the field
and this distance is much bigger than the first distance.
If this is our one and this is our two.
So that means actually that there could be the case even though you have more charge since you're dividing
by a larger distance over here.
You could get the case where both of those fields are equal to each other.
So at the end really this is not the one we just argued and it really has to be only in this section
over here.
Will there be the possibility that both of those electric fields are going to cancel.
Okay all right let's go to the next one.
All right.
Problem for a problem for here we have three equal positive charges.
So that's kind of important.
Equal they're all positive Q there at the corners over here of a square in the side is D.
Which one arrow represents the direction of the net electric field at the center of the square.
All right.
So all we really have to do now is just draw all the vectors so let's start with the red one over here
and the red one will produce an electric field at the center which is going to be like this that the
electric field produced by the red point charge over here.
All right how about the blue one.
Let's go the blue here in this corner over here again since it's a positive point charge.
It will produce an electric field at the center of the square here which will be like this.
All right.
So we have both of those vectors so far that we have to add.
We have one more that we need to do.
Let's do this one in the upper corner in green.
Okay.
So that means now that the electric field right here at the center produced by the green charge is going
to point away from it.
All right.
Two of these vectors here are going to cancel out this vector over here and this one they're equal and
opposite to each other.
So those vectors cancel out.
And actually what you're left with at the end is that the total electric field is simply going to be
equal to this because the other two will cancel out.
This is the total E field
OK so that's really choice.
Azar it's kind of buried underneath there.
Choice is really the correct answer for this problem.
All right let's go to our next problem.
All right.
We have a figure over here that shows electric field lines arising from two small charge particles P
and Q All right.
Here they are.
Consider the following two statements the charge P is smaller than the charged Q All right.
Well what do we think.
So let's make say this one here is purple and let's make this one here in red.
So is p smaller than Q.
And how about the second statement.
The electrostatic force P is smaller than the force on Q All right.
Well electrostatic forces one thing we should know is this here is false.
Right.
This here is false because we know that cool Ohm's Law that the force acting on them are going to be
the same.
The other thing we know is that they should be two positive charges right.
There are two positive charges.
And how do I know they are positive charges.
That's because the electric field lines point away from positive charges how do I know about the magnitude
now of each charge which one has more charge.
Well again you would have to argue that Q the charge on Q has to be bigger than the charge on P.
And how do I know that there's simply more field lines right.
More field lines and where you have more field lines.
For example if I choose an area here versus an area here you could see here there is more field lines
crossing that area then close to the charge P.
So that means that this charge has to be bigger in magnitude than this charge.
Okay so this guy is definitely true.
Okay.
So now we just go read the choices.
Only one is true.
Two is not true.
Both of them are neither.
Okay.
Well we know that a is true.
So that's OK.
So for question 5 is the correct answer.
All right.
And our last one over here.
Let's go to a problem six problem six says we have a small Styrofoam ball which has a mass equal to
point 1 2 grams.
It's placed in an electric field of six thousand newtons per Coolum pointing downward.
OK so let's go have a look.
What excess charge must be placed on the ball for it to remain suspended in the field.
All right.
So let's kind of draw what's going on over here.
Let's draw a small ball.
It has a mass equal now going to convert this to go from grams to KG.
Right you need to divide by a thousand.
Right.
So zero point one two times 10 to the negative three.
That is the mass in kilograms.
All right.
Now we place this in electric field which is 6000 pointing down.
OK.
So this is the electric field.
And this is six thousand Newtons Pakula.
All right.
Now let's look at all the forces now acting on this Styrofoam ball.
First of all there is going to be the force of gravity right.
Which is the weight and the weight is m times little G.
The mass we know over here and little g is nine point eight meters per second squared.
OK.
Now if we don't want this or sorry if we wanted to remain suspended in the field we know that the net
force has to be zero.
So guess what.
There better be some other force acting on this ball.
Well we're going to want now is a an electric force.
Call it FC acting up.
OK.
First of all if the electric field is pointing down the charge on here better be negatively charged.
Right.
We want negative charge on here.
So first of all all of these choices here are negative.
So we can't really cancel any of them.
So what do we get now.
Well so what.
All we could do is we find that we want these forces the balance so QE better be equal to M.G..
And again here it's only the magnitude of the charge.
Clearly I know that the force is in the opposite direction.
So the magnitude of the charge at the end is energy divided by the electric field.
OK.
So now we have to substitute everything in so our masses zero point one two times tend to the negative
three kilograms multiplied by nine point eight.
That's the acceleration due to gravity and now divided by the magnitude of the electric field which
is six thousand.
At the end the magnitude of the charge.
Again it has to be negative charge.
So we get here should be minus one ninety six nano Coolum.
Actually you should get times 10 to the negative nine columns and that's negative one ninety six a nano
Coolum if you substituted all our numbers over here.
OK.
So the correct answer actually at the end of the day should be choice e over here.
So again I'm only looking at the you know that the charge has to be negative because the force has to
be like this over here all our choices are negative.
So it's kind of clear that it has to be negative.
And we really just want to balance the forces because we want it to remain suspended.
So the net force must be equal to zero for this problem.
OK.
All right.
Hopefully you got those ones.