Let's do a kind of a quick calculation here so again we have our electric field that's produced by a
point charge Q1 in this case Q1 is going to be two micro columns and I'm going to place the point where
I want to evaluate the electric field right here.
It's five meters away.
One thing I know automatically is that since this here is a positive point charge the convention is
that the electric field should point away from this positive point charge.
So right here my electric field vector should look like this.
Now define how big it is I have to substitute my values right here.
So I need to use the k constant.
That's the same as before same as cool Ohm's Law.
TEN TIMES 10 TO THE 9.
All right.
What is the charge that's producing the electric field.
What's right here is to micro cool.
So it's two times 10 to the negative 6.
And now I have to divide by our squared are in this case is the distance from the point charge to the
point where I'm evaluating the field.
This is five squared and that again is just the magnitude.
OK.
So if I plug everything in my calculator let me go ahead and do that.
Just bear with me nine of the nine times to either the negative six and divided by five squared I could
do that in my head divided by 25.
All right at the end of the day I get a an electric field that is seven hundred and twenty.
That's the magnitude.
OK.
So what are the units.
Well it's kind of almost like cool homes law that was measured in Newtons.
However we've removed one of the charges so the units for electric field should be Newton's Pakula.
OK.
So that's kind of a really really important.
All right.
So the units use square brackets to denote the units they should be in units of Newton's divided by
columns.
All right.
So if I go over here I should write newtons per column and here's the direction.
So now I have a follow up question here.
What happens now if I take a charge Q2 and place it
at point p.
All right.
And for now I'm going to assume that Q2 is going to be equal to six micro Coolum.
Okay.
So let's go ahead and take my charge Q2 and we're going to place it at point p.
So this is what I'm gonna do here is Q2 now it has more charge it has three times more charge than Q1.
What if I wanted to find the force produced by Q1 on Q2 How can I do that how do I find the force.
Well one thing I could do right away is just the right down cool Ohm's Law.
Right cool Ohm's Law would just say that the forces K Q1 Q2 divided by our squared and I could substitute
in all the values for that.
However we've already done most of the work.
Look at this guy right here.
Woop K. Q1 over our squared.
What is this.
This is nothing more than the electric field so this is where you're going to start seeing the real
advantage of knowing the electric field.
Okay.
If I wanted to find the force in going back to this equation here it would simply be Q2 multiplied by
this guy multiplied by the electric field.
And this is the electric field produced by the first charge by q 1 so right away you're able to write
down this expression that the force on any charge that I place here is going to be the value of that
charge multiplied by the electric field produced at this particular point.
So for this question here would simply be Q2 6 micro cooling multiplied by the electric field.
It's really the electric field produced by the first charge.
This would give me the force on Q2 so we go ahead and we substitute in our values right here.
So the force on Q2 it's the magnitude of the charge Q2 and that's six times 10 to the negative 6 and
multiplied by the electric field right here at this point.
That's where that charge is located multiplied by 720.
OK.
Now I can go ahead and just multiply this out with my calculator six either the negative six times 720
at the end guess gives me four point three two times 10 to the negative three and that should be measured
in Newtons.
Okay so this would be the fourth here acting on my charge Q2.
All right.
So let's go recap all of this in the next video.
I just wanted to show you just the simple example.
The nice thing about this is if I change Q2 if instead if I have a different charge what if instead
I have a charge Q3 that's equal to 25 merely Coolum and I place it right here instead of Q2 I place
a charge Q3 right here or right away I'm able to calculate the force on Q3.
Right.
Because the force on Q3 again I'm just going to use this expression right here since I know the electric
field right here.
The force on Q3 is simply going to be Q3 multiplied by my electric field at that point which is simply
e k so it's very very easy to calculate that.
All right we'll summarize everything on the next video.