All right.
Let's take a simple example over here.
I split into two parts.
So on the left hand side I have a positive three nano Coolum charge on the right hand side I have a
negative three nano cool on charge.
All right.
And I have a point P that's located one meter away from each charge.
The goal is let's find the electric field at each of these points at point p.
Okay.
So again it's a point charge that is producing that electric field.
So it would be k q over our squared here would be nine times ten to the nine.
That's the K value the charges three nano Q alone.
That's three times 10 to the negative nine and divided by in this case it divided by one.
Well that's one square.
That one's easy.
All right.
So the magnitude of my electric field would be oh 10 to the nine and ten to the negative nine those
things cancel out.
So I'm left with just nine times three which is twenty seven and divided by one.
So that's just that's it.
Twenty seven this is newtons per Coolum.
All right.
Actually if I did the calculation over here again if you had a negative sign for the charge you would
get negative but negative just tells me the direction.
OK.
I already know the direction because I know that this here is a positive charge.
So that means that this here produces an electric field that points away from it.
That is the convention because it's positive charge here.
This vector here would have a magnitude of twenty seven.
If I have a coordinate system where this here is positive y then I might actually just write it as something
like this.
Right.
Positive twenty seven multiplied by the little vector in the y direction.
OK.
How would you do it here for the negative charge.
Again the magnitude is twenty seven.
If you're going to draw a vector though look what we have to do.
You have to draw the vector in the opposite direction.
The vector e points like this and again in this case here it would be twenty seven and it's pointing
in the negative y direction.
So at the end you could write it like this negative twenty seven multiplied by y terms of the direction
you would simply write it like this.
All right.
So now here is a harder question now what happens if I take a charge Q2 and that charge is going to
be negative two columns.
Here's the charge it's a negative and I'm gonna go ahead and I'm going to place the charge right here
at Point P.
All right.
So I've placed it at point p for each case.
What if I want to know the magnitude of the force in the direction of the force on this negative charge.
Well again if you want to find the force on any charge you simply take the magnitude of the charge and
you multiplied by the electric field.
In this case it would be the magnitude would simply be to add the electric field magnitude is 27.
So this would be 54 Newtons.
Now what would be the direction of the force.
Again if this is a negative charge again remember our vector equation looks like this right the force
on negative charges is always opposite of the electric field at that point.
So this force here would have to be something like this.
And you know right away since this is positive and this is negative you know that the force on the negative
has to be it's an attractive force.
All right.
How about this case again it would be the same magnitude of the force.
So the force F would still be 54 Newtons
the direction.
Now again our electric field is pointing down here.
It's the electric field produced by this negative charge.
That means that the force as a vector is always the charge multiplied by the field.
It's always four negative charges I'm placing a negative charge right here.
It's always going to be opposite of the electric field this here would be the direction of the force
acting on it.
And it's very clear from cool Ohm's Law right we know if we have two negative charges they are going
to repel each other.
So on this charge there is a force like this actually and the other charges the same force just in the
opposite direction.
All right.
But I just wanted to highlight just these two different cases using the same magnitude of the charge
that produces the field just in a different direction.