All right.
I want to show you here are just some electric field maps here.
So on the left hand side I have just a single one nano Coolum charge placed right here at the center.
And now you could see and all of the vectors here represent the electric field at different positions
in space so you'd see the electric field over here points away from it.
The electric field on this side points away from this positive charge always away from the charge.
At every point you can calculate the magnet to the brightness of the arrow represents the magnitude.
So as I go far away from those charges you could see that the brightness goes down.
And again that's because we have k q over R squared.
As I go far away again the distance R gets bigger.
Right.
Imagine here I'd be looking at a distance R which is significantly bigger.
And if I'm dividing by a large distance I'm going to make the magnitude smaller.
So again over here the vectors aren't shorter.
That's another way to depict them.
In this case here the vectors are just not as bright.
And that means that the magnitude is less but they still point away.
Even out here they point away from this positive charge on the right hand side here what I have is just
the opposite.
OK I have a negative one nano cool home charge and now you can see everywhere that the electric field
always points toward it and always a vector always pointing toward whatever is producing it.
Because I know it's negative over here as I get closer those vectors would be bigger in magnitude again
because of this guy right here I'm dividing by a smaller number one I'm close to the negative charge.
So the electric field gets very very big but again it always points toward negative charges.
OK.
Kind of a nice tool but I want to do now is look at what happens now if we have several point charges.
All right.
How do we apply or how do we calculate the electric field in the space if we have a positive point charge
here maybe another positive or negative somewhere else in space.