All right.
I now want to look at what happens if there is more than one point charge in life.
We're going to have situations where there is more than one point charge.
So how would we calculate the electric field somewhere in space.
So here's a nice kind of simple example.
I only have two charges.
They're both one nano Coolum.
The red one is positive and the blue one is negative.
OK so let's have a look.
This is what the electric field looks like in space.
First of all as I'm close to the point charges see how bright the arrows are.
Brightness in these pictures represent the magnitude.
That means that when I'm close to the negative charge or I'm close to the positive charge the electric
field is pretty big and that makes sense because I'm close to the charge.
Let's get rid of that as I go farther away you could see over here you could barely see the arrow.
That means as you go far away the field is getting smaller and that makes sense.
All right.
Now have a look at just all of the different orientations though of these different arrows.
Right.
Let me show you a couple of them.
So let's look at this guy right.
This guy here is pointing.
It's pointing actually directly to the right which is kind of weird.
It's actually the same everywhere here on this line right.
Right at the center between both of those point charges.
Look what I get I get an electric feel that points like this.
It's a little bit strange.
What else as I'm on this side.
Let's use a different color maybe use an orange when I'm to the left of the positive charge.
Look what I get.
I get a feel that points away from it everywhere along here and as I'm anywhere.
To the right of the negative charge.
Look what I get.
I get a vector that is pointing toward the negative charge.
All right.
That's also kind of unique.
So let me just write this down so toward negative here I would be away from positive.
And over here the yellow one would be again toward the negative.
Right toward negative.
All right.
So what we want to do now is we're gonna use something called superposition.
That means that you're gonna be adding vectors from more than one charge adding different electric fields
because different objects are producing electric fields and we're gonna be able to understand this picture
in a lot more detail.
OK so let's look at some of the math behind generating a picture like this.
I'm going to consider points that are again in the three different positions.
OK.
Somewhere over here somewhere in the middle and somewhere on the side.
So let's consider a kind of different points.
Let's consider them along the axis.
Just to keep the math a little bit easier.
If I start going up here in space then you're gonna have vectors that are in different directions.
And it's straightforward it just takes a little bit more time because you have to add vectors with different
components.
All right let's at least start with understanding what's going on here along this line that joins both
of those charges.
And then later on we'll do other examples where we're going to be further out in space.