Hi folks.
Today I want to solve a problem dealing with electric fields and more specifically I want to calculate
the electric field produced by a dipole so for a dipole we have a positive charge and a negative charge
and they're separated by some distance that I've denoted by the letter D.
The question is I want to calculate the electric field at three specific points in space.
The point p is located midway between the two charges the point X is located just above the axis and
it's a distance D over to above point p and the last case I want to calculate the electric field that
point y a point Y is located on the axis joining the two charges.
However it's a little bit closer to the negative charge now than it is to the positive charge.
So now the only thing to remember for this delay equation we really need to calculate the electric field
for this problem is to remember that the electric field from any single point charged the magnitude
any is given by this equation K is our constant Q Is the charge and that's the inverse squared relationship.
So k q over our squared.
That gives me the magnitude of the electric field produced by any specific charge.
I also have to worry about the direction of the electric field so let's go to the online whiteboard
and see how we solve that problem.
Thanks.
Okay great.
So here's my dipole.
Let's first consider the point p.
We've got our point p located at the center point between the two charges which are separated by distance
D.
So to calculate the total field at this point we need to consider the contribution from the positive
charge and the contribution from the negative charge.
So let's draw the vectors first.
If I'm only considering the positive charge let's plot that vector and read the field produce at point
p by the positive charge should point away from the positive charge it points away from the positive
charge.
That's the convention and the magnitude we can calculate using our equation appear.
All right now let's go ahead and calculate the field from the negative charge in the field from the
negative charge at the point P where we want to evaluate it.
It's going to have a particular magnitude and it's going to have a direction because it's a negative
charge.
The field points toward the negative charge.
So we've got two vectors here that are pointing in the same direction.
One thing you should know right away is since the distance will be the same for both and the charge
is the same.
Only the magnitude is different because we're dealing with an electric dipole.
You should notice that the magnitudes of both of those vectors should be the same since the charge is
the same in the distance to the to the charge to the point of evaluation will also be the same.
In both cases the distance R is simply D over 2 for this particular point.
So therefore the total field
is going to be E plus plus a minus
all right.
We're gonna choose a convention I'm gonna call this direction here as being my positive direction.
I'm free to choose whatever I want.
Therefore if I want to eliminate this vector here and we'll call that the positive x direction.
Okay so the total feel now is simply going to be k kill.
And again the distances deal over 2 squared.
That is the field from the positive charge evaluating that point P plus k q d over 2 squared.
We get the exact same thing.
So we get two contributions.
And again the distance term is gonna be the same for both.
If you simplify that a little bit you're gonna get a one over four here.
Once you square everything in at the end of the day you should get eight K Q over over d squared in
the direction of the field is going to be in the positive x direction and I've defined up above.
All right.
So the total field that point P has a magnitude of 8 q over d squared and the direction is to the left
all right.
So case number one is pretty straightforward.
OK.
Now let's look at point X point X was located above point p and it was a distance D over to above.
And remember of point P was right at the center.
That means at this distance here from the center line to each individual charge is also D over 2.
Okay.
So if we want to find the field that point X again there's gonna be two contributions to the field each
one of them we know the magnitude.
So let's start by drawing the vectors.
The field at point X produced by this positive charge should point in this direction away from the positive
charge.
And I'm calling that he plus in the electric field produced by the negative charge at point X is a vector
of a particular length that I'm going to denote as a minus.
And it's pointing toward the negative charge.
Right.
If you continue this line here should go right through the negative charge.
Okay.
So all we have to do now is simply add those up as vectors.
Now one thing you should note
is the vertical components of those vectors are going to cancel out.
Again we're dealing with the electric field from a dipole so that means that this charge is equal in
magnitude but opposite sign from the negative charge.
And also the distance from the point to each charge is going to be the same.
So that means when you substitute things into our equation for the electric fuel produced by one individual
charge you have the same magnitude.
You also have the same distance from the point where we evaluate the field to the charge.
Therefore both of those vectors have the same magnitude.
So when you add them up as vectors at the end let's drive a little bit clear down here at the bottom
so we've got a vector in this direction he plus and we've also got a vector in this direction.
He minus.
So now let's find the actual magnitudes of each one of those vectors
so we can start with the first one.
All we really need to find is what is the distance from the charge to the point of the valuation.
Right.
And that distance is simply this one over here on the figure.
This is r that's very easy to solve because we know the distance from the charge to the midpoint and
we know the distance from the midpoint to the point of observation.
Therefore we should be able to solve what is the length of that top side.
Each one of these is d over 2.
Therefore R to use Pythagorean theorem.
Okay.
Now you could simplify this.
We're going to get d over a square root of 2 so there's the distance.
So the magnitude of E plus we do it over here magnitude of E plus is simply k q and divided by our square
r squared is gonna be d squared divided by two.
I'll just put the two up on top here.
The magnitude of E minus is also going to be the same.
The only thing that's different is the orientation or the direction that vector.
So at the end now what we have to do is we simply have to break both of those vectors down into two
components.
This year we'll have a horizontal component and a vertical component.
Likewise with the green vector we have a horizontal component and a vertical component of the vector
e minus.
And you should see that both of these vectors at least the vertical components cancel so if we choose
a coordinate system let's choose a coordinate system where we have positive why it's pointing up and
positive X is pointing to the left.
Okay.
And if you want to find the field in the y direction
let's call the angle that that vector makes with respect to the horizontal it's theta.
And again you can find theta because it's gonna be the same angle as the angle over here.
Since both of those sides are the same you should know that the angle theta should be forty five degrees.
So in the y direction what do we have.
We've got he total in the y direction is equal to E plus in the y direction.
And now the component of E minus in the y direction is pointing down.
I would call that negative and at the end that components very easy.
It equals to zero.
Well all we have to do now is simply find the vector in the x direction and again both of those are
gonna have the exact same length.
So the total field in the x direction is gonna be twice whatever the x component of E pluses and the
x component its cos of theta.
So now we can substitute everything we know the two is the fact that we have both vectors pointing in
the same direction.
The magnitude of E plus I've got a written there on the side it's 2 k divided by D squared and coast
of theta.
That's code of forty five degrees coast of forty five degrees is Route 2 over 2.
You can simplify a few things
at the end while we're left with is 2 square root of 2 k divided by D squared.
That is the total field at point X.
So this one's a little bit tricky because the vectors are not along the same axis.
However there is some simplification because the y components cancel out and we're left with both components
of the X both x components adding together to give us a total field in the x direction with this magnitude
2 square root of 2.
Multiply times the constant I can't forget the charge q divided by D squared.
Okay.
Okay so now let's consider the total electric field produce at point Y.
Again we're gonna have two contributions we have a contribution from the positive charge at point y.
That's a vector pointing away from the positive charge and we also have an electric field produced by
the negative charge at point y.
And that vector should point toward the negative charge.
Now we can easily calculate the magnitude of each one.
The magnitude of E plus is K Q And what is the distance.
Now the distance is D plus D over 2.
Well that's three D over two and you can't forget the square that guy at the end of the day you expand
this power to and what do we get.
We're gonna get 4 k q divided by 9 D squared.
That's the magnitude of the electric field produced by the positive charge.
Now let's consider the negative charge k q that terms the same.
What is the distance now.
The distance is only D over to a much smaller distance do you over too.
And don't forget to square that term.
So at the end of the day when we expand everything we can write out that the electric field produced
by the negative charge has a magnitude of K key over d squared.
Okay.
So the total field now again I'm going to choose a coordinate system where everything pointing to the
left is positive.
You're free to do whatever you want at this point.
And now the total field
the magnitude of the total field is going to be plus four nights Kate Q divided by D squared and minus
minus because this vector here is pointing to the right and I've decided that that direction is gonna
be the negative direction for k q divided by D squared.
Okay.
So you just gotta do a little bit of algebra.
Here we have four nights minus what is this.
Thirty six nights and everything is multiplied times the same factor here.
Kick you over d squared and at the end of the day we are left with that the total feel that point Y
is equal to minus thirty two over nine K Q divided by D squared.
Negative negative for vectors simply tells me the direction and that tells me that this vector here
points to the right and that makes sense right.
Because the fuel produced by the negative charge is going to be bigger at point Y because the distance
to the point Y is much closer for the positive charge the distance is much larger it's three D over
two words for the negative charge it was only D over two.
Okay.
So at any point in space you simply have to consider two vectors the vectors the electric field produced
by each charge.
Just be careful how you add them up and you should be able to find the electric field anywhere in space.