All right what I want to do now folks is look at a different geometry.
OK.
So we've looked at.
If I have a positive point charge I can go everywhere in space and I could say well what's the electric
field right here.
Right.
You could draw it draw an electric field vector and you can calculate its magnitude right as long as
you know the distance right here.
So here I would say it's simply k q over R squared and the direction of the vector if it's a positive
point charge that's producing it the electric field points away from positive charges.
Okay.
Well now I have another question for you.
What happens now if I have instead of one point charge if I have a large plate.
So here's a large plate.
Let's just call it like this.
So it's just really a two dimensional plate.
It has a little thickness.
But let's just neglect that.
So it's really two dimensional object.
And what I'm going to do now is on this plate I am going to produce or say remove a whole bunch of electrons
in such a way that this plate here becomes positively charged.
They will just keep on drawing a few of them but there's a whole bunch of these individual point charges
here but they're spread out kind of all over this two dimensional surface.
All right.
Imagine now I wanted to know well what it is.
The if I just pick a direction here that's perpendicular to the plate.
What is the direction of the electric field right here at some point that is above the plate.
It could be some height h above the plate.
Now again although I drew this little area right here again I'm assuming that this area is actually
pretty large.
So I'm just going to write these arrows just to tell you that it's kind of extended pretty large and
I'm at a point that's close to the surface of the plate.
Which direction with the electric field be it.
OK.
Well again you would use the equation for the point charges but you would have to add up all the contributions
from all the point charges.
For example I'd have to add this one.
So this one here produces an electric field at the red point which is something like this.
Now every time there is a point charge on this side there's going to be one on the other side.
That's going to oppose it.
It's going to produce it's its electric field in this direction at the end when we add those as vectors.
Turns out that the electric field is only going to be pointing away from the plate if it's positively
charged.
Okay.
Because every time you have a point charged on one side you'll always have another one on the other
side.
So there's can't be any contribution or any component of the electric fuel that's in the plane of the
plate.
OK.
So let's just define a couple of things.
First of all we have our area of the plate.
What else.
Well we want to know how much charge do we place on that plate.
Is that a lot of charge.
Is it a little bit of charge.
OK.
So I'm going to define something.
There is something called Sigma Sigma is what we're going to call a surface charge density surface charge
density and this quantity is important to calculate the electric field from the plate.
The definition of this in terms of other variables.
So a charge density is how much total charge do I have divided by the total area of the plate.
Now this is important this quantity here because it's used to calculate the electric field produced
by this object by this plate.
So the electric field produced by this plate which I'm going to write here just using a purple E.
Now we know the direction if it's positively charged the electric field points away from it.
If it's negatively charged the electric fuel points toward it.
So that convention hasn't changed the magnitude of the field produced by a charged plate it can be written
some like this.
Now have a look it's different from the point charged depend on this charge density and the rest of
it depends on two Epsilon 0.
Pretty simple equation.
Now I just wrote the magnitude here of the electric field the direction of the electric field again.
We know that.
So notice here it doesn't actually depend on the distance H right.
H was the point.
How far away I was from that surface in here.
This electric field the really important thing here is that it is a constant value.
If it's a constant value it means it doesn't depend if you're close to the plate or a little bit farther
away.
Again we're assuming we have a really really large plate.
All right.
So let's have a look at this formula a little bit more detail now what we're gonna do is we're gonna
place two of these plates next to each other.
This is what we call parallel plates and let's look at the electric field produced by parallel plates.