Here are our kinematic equations, as well as these position velocity, acceleration and time elapsed
quantities.
So write these down, it will help you and just understand this.
So for position, it's measured in meters, velocity, meters per second, acceleration meters per second
squared and time elapsed is in seconds.
OK, so the thing that I really want to point out is, hey, know, maybe your teacher doesn't explain
it exactly like this using XY, VI and V, maybe your teacher actually uses X not and X F or does simply
X not and X or Y.
Oh no, I've never really seen this, but maybe your teacher actually says x1 and x2.
Either way, what these represent is an initial position and a final position and however they want
to go back, describing the subscripts is up to them and it's completely fine.
There's no like it really should be a little bit more standardized, but it isn't and possibly even
for average velocity.
Maybe your teacher right.
Writes it out like this really to explicitly defined the idea that that's the average velocity.
But either one of these two is correct.
Same thing with acceleration, maybe instead of Delta T, maybe they should prefer.
Hey, and what let's explicitly say that's our final minus our initial and maybe they actually don't
use the final initial, maybe the use just T and T not which is this over here that's pronounced not
and I believe that's spelt KNST.
Yes.
So these just represent hand what it's initial.
It's the final.
And you know, I didn't actually describe before.
Maybe they don't have your teacher doesn't even have the kinematic equation written like this.
Maybe they actually haven't written like this.
And this delta just represents a change, the change in a position over the change in time.
So your teacher might be describing it like this.
But, Anderson, that's just simply that it's the final position minus the initial position.
So do me a favor.
Don't push in the comments saying, hey, you know what, you're wrong.
These aren't how they should be.
My teacher teaches it this way.
It's really just a matter of preference on how the teacher actually goes about explaining this is the
way that I'm going to do it.
I'm going to consistently use this notation here.
So this is the way I'm going to be describing it.
If you want to use the way that your teacher is doing it, that's completely fine.
But I just want to have that explained to you.