All right, so let's go through this next problem, so a dragster starting from rust accelerates at
one point five meters per second squared.
How fast is it going when it has traveled 25 meters?
OK, so let's look at this here.
Let's picture this.
We have our car.
It is starting right here.
It is starting here from rest and it accelerates to one point five meters per second squared.
OK, so it's going to be starting over here and it's going to go this much.
How fast is it going when it has traveled 25 meters?
OK, so that's the situation.
Let's start to plug in what we know.
If it's starting right here, what are we going to say?
That initial position is, hey, this is getting a lot more common, right?
We're going to see this a lot unless it really specifies what the initial position is.
OK, and what's the final position?
Well, we know it has traveled 25 meters.
OK, so good indicator to us that that's our final position.
All right, and what does this one point, five meters per second squared telling us?
Well, just right off the bat, being that we see the units of meters per second squared, we know that
it's our acceleration, never mind it are telling us that it's saying that's accelerating at this value.
So what's this right at that?
And one point five meters per second squared.
OK, this is another key word right here, if it's starting from rest, hey, if it's some from just
how fast is it initially going?
OK, and what is the problem, asking us for how fast is going when it has traveled this much?
OK, so how fast is it going?
Well, that's our final velocity.
That's what we're being asked for.
And do we care about our time?
Does it tell us anything about time now?
Do we care about time?
Is it asking us for time now?
OK, so that's the thing that we don't care about.
All right, so we don't care about time.
Well, OK, so are we dealing with it average velocity now, right?
It said nothing about average velocity.
We're not trying to solve for average velocity.
So we know right off the bat that we're going to be dealing with these four formulas down here.
Once again, we don't care about time.
So wherever we see time, we're just going to say, hey, I don't care about time.
We're not using that formula.
What about this one time?
OK.
Oh, there it is.
Right.
I don't care about this formula.
What about this one?
Oh, we got time here on what?
We also have time here.
We're definitely not using this formula that we're going to be using the last one to we see time.
Nope.
Good indicator to us that we're going to be using Formula Number six in order to solve this problem.
So let's ride that out right now, so we have VEF squared is equal to minus X I.
And always, always, always double check to see that you actually wrote in the formula, correct?
OK, so I believe I remember writing that incorrectly, that would be an awful mistake to make and I've
seen students actually do that where they forget, hey, and it's very easy to forget Square, it's
over here.
Or instead of writing to my son, I've seen people actually write a plus sign in here.
Maybe they'll write a minus to a over here.
Either way, make sure that you write the formula correct, because it would just be such a silly mistake
to get the problem wrong because he wrote the formula wrong.
All right.
So let's see your substitution now.
What do we have the is what we're trying to find.
So we're just going to drop this down.
V.I. squared, OK, so we have zero and we're going to square that number.
We know that zero times any number is equal to zero.
So that's not going to do anything for us.
So we have two times our acceleration, minus zero.
OK, and let's just continue to solve this out.
Provides no value.
That provides no value.
Essentially, that's what we're doing, right?
All right, great.
So we have the squared is equal to 75 and what I want the velocity.
I don't care what the F squared is equal to.
So how do we get rid of the squared?
We take the square root.
And that will get us our final answer of eight point six meters per second.