So in the last video, we went through the problem and we pulled out this given information and then
we basically said, hey, and what Delta t the time elapsed.
This is the variable that we don't care about.
It didn't ask about this and it didn't actually give this to us in the given problem.
So what do we do?
We came over here to these formulas down over here.
We exclude these ones because it didn't have anything to do with average velocity.
I basically said what we're gonna do is scan through these formulas, look for our Delta teams and basically
say to ourselves, we're not going to be using these formulas that have the Delta T involved.
And this is what we did.
Right.
So what was the reason why we did this?
Why did we do this?
Now, I'm just getting a little sidestep over here for a quick second and show you this.
I'm going to give you the instruction to solve for X in these two equations.
OK, so once again, we do have to two terms over here.
We have the five X plus two.
Once again, terms are separated by plus and minus signs.
How do we go about Iceland X?
Well, first, let's get rid of this term over here of plus two.
How do we get rid of a plus two?
Let's subtract two on each side of the equation, 17 minus two, which gives us 15 and that's equal
to five X.
Now what we have is a five being multiplied by X.
How do we get rid of a multiplication of five?
We divide both sides by five and we simply get three is equal to X and we will get value for our X.
Now let's do this.
I'm just going to do the same thing here.
Now, let's get a value for X.
Well, wait a minute, I could solve for X, but will this result in a value for X?
Hmm, I don't think so.
All right.
Because now we have the two terms here, once again, separated by the plus.
And my one we we could subtract to Y on both sides of the equation.
And then divide by our five oh.
And this is what's equal to X.
Wait a minute, so if we have here our two unknown's.
Will we be able to get a value for X no, right, because there's two unknowns here.
Hey, wait a minute.
So this is the reason why we were crossing out our delta tears because we have an unknown right here
and we have an unknown right here.
And if I want to solve for this and I don't know this value where I be able to get a value now.
So let's come through here once again.
I want to sell for this Vieth, this equation here, it has to be both, but it also has Delta T and
that's the reason why Beesly said, hey, let's cancel this one out of this equation over here.
Well, wait a minute.
It doesn't even have a V.
So how would I be able to go about getting a valid value for VIth?
I wouldn't be able to.
Obviously this one over here, it's got Veth.
And it doesn't have a Delta T Oh, wait a minute, that's the equation that we did use.
OK, so this one over here, it's got a V and a Delta T, we can't get a value once again because it
simply has the Delta T, we're going across that R Delta T is over here and these are the, the formulas
that we can't use this one up here.
It doesn't have a Delta t it's got to be if we could solve this and get a value and that's the process
and that's the reason why that why we do that.