For this next one, we have a bus.
It's traveling at 20 meters per second, which is equivalent to 45 miles an hour, and it speeds up
at a constant rate of two meters per second squared.
What velocity does it reach?
Five seconds later.
OK, so what do we have here?
We have a bus and it's traveling at this speed and it's speeding up at two meters per second squared.
What velocity doesn't reach?
OK, so describe to me what the bus is doing.
It's going fast and it's going faster.
Right.
So once again, what do you think that the initial position is that of the bus?
What are we going to say it is if it's not told to us or does it always going to say it's equal to zero
meters?
What else do we have here?
What is this?
So a bus is traveling at this, what does that 20 meters per second telling us?
What's the velocity?
Right.
And it's traveling at that currently.
Oh, so that must be our initial velocity.
You might be saying to yourself, well, doesn't a bus always start from rest and then it gets up to
a certain speed and then it goes faster?
Well, OK, but if we're looking at this as a system right now and we're basically just initially observing
the bus to be moving at this speed, that's what we're going to say, is the initial velocity.
And what is this, two meters per second squared telling us, what is that?
Well, if it's meters per second squared, that's a good indicator that that's the acceleration.
OK.
Oh, we have five seconds here.
Simple enough, what does that tell us?
That's the time the time elapsed.
Oh.
And what is it that we're trying to find here, what velocity does it reach?
It sounds like we're trying to find out what the final velocity is.
Does it say anything about the final position or are we trying to solve for the final position at all?
No.
Right.
OK, so that's going to be the variable that we don't care about.
So what we're going to do here is, first of all, are we dealing with a average velocity?
No, right.
It doesn't say anything about average velocity.
As a matter of fact, we know that the velocity is changing.
We know that we're accelerating over here.
We're not dealing with an average velocity at all.
Let's look at this right now.
We are trying to find the foremost that have the final position in it and we're going to say we don't
care about it.
Does this one have final position in it?
No.
Oh, OK.
What about this one yet?
Not right off the bat.
We got final position right there.
We don't care about this formula or about this formula.
Oh, yeah.
Yep.
Right there.
I see it.
And what about this one?
Oh, yeah, we got final position right there and we don't care about that one.
The very first formula that we actually were considering using, that's the formula that that we will
use.
So we have our Veth is equal to our V.I. Plus our acceleration times the Delta T now the de'ath that's
the variable that we're trying to find is equal to the V.I. plus acceleration of two times five.
OK.
Oh this is simple enough.
Look at this.
We could probably just do this in our heads.
And looking at that, we correctly solved this problem.