Is there another way that we could think about during this problem?
Now let's keep in mind the definition of acceleration.
Acceleration is the change in velocity over a certain amount of time.
So the acceleration of two meters per second squared is equal to the change in velocity over a certain
amount of time for every one second.
The velocity changes by two meters per second.
That's what acceleration is.
It's a change in velocity over a certain time.
So let me ask you this now.
Once again, we keep keep in mind that the initial velocity here is 20 meters per second.
So at zero seconds, what's the velocity?
20 metres a second, right after one second.
What's the new velocity, keeping in mind this definition for every one second, the velocity changes
by two meters per second, which is what acceleration is.
So after one second, what's the new velocity?
22 meters per second.
Well, what about after two seconds?
Three.
Hopefully you're seeing a pattern right now.
And once again, we get our answer of 30 meters per second as our final velocity.
Hey, so that's by definition, that's what that means.
That's what acceleration is.
OK, well, we solved it.
And that's that's why this is a this is interesting.
So what about another way?
Look at this formula right here.
Have you seen a formula kind of similar to this?
Well, what we do here is this.
I'm just going to rearrange these two terms right now.
Let me just rewrite this.
Just like this.
Have you ever seen any formulas, any equations looking like this?
Well, yeah, you have.
Have you seen this equation before?
This is the slope intercept formula where the arm represents the slope.
And the BEA represents the Y intercept.
And I'm sure by now that you've actually seen this formal before.
OK, well, let's do this.
What's the value of B?
Well, that's the initial blast velocity, which is our 20 meters per second.
So let's say here, this is our 20 meters a second.
How do we go about plotting this on a graph?
So we have our VEF is equal to our slope or our acceleration times our Delta T, that's going to be
our input variable plus our B, which is twenty.
OK, so what is slope.
It's rise over run.
Right.
So we rise to and go over one.
Rise to over one rise to over one rise to go over one dam when we get our line.
So, hey, you know what?
This is just an alternative method, but once again, rise to go over one that's at 20, rise to go
over one, 24, rise to go over one.
And that's twenty six, twenty eight all the way up until 30 where the time is equal to one second,
two seconds, three seconds, four seconds and five seconds.
Notice once again we have at five seconds our velocity is equal to 30 meters per second.