OK, so let's get into problem number nine, so number nine says when Maggie apply the brakes of her
car, the car slows uniformly from 15 meters per second to zero meters per second in 2.5 seconds.
How many meters before a stop sign Mushi apply her brakes.
OK, well, what's happening here?
Kind of sounds like that Maggie is driving in our car and she's slowing down to a stop sign that she's
coming to a complete stop.
That's what the zero meters per second is telling us right now.
So let's pull out some given information.
What do you think that her initial position is going to be?
Hey, it doesn't really tell us anything specific.
So we're just going to go ahead and say it's zero
slows uniformly from this.
Velocity down to this velocity, we know its velocity because it says meters per second.
So what is this, 15 meters per second actually representing?
Is that the initial velocity or final velocity?
And what she's uniformly slowing down from 15 meters per second to zero meters per second.
Hopefully you're saying yourself that that's her initial velocity, the 15 and that the zero is her
final velocity.
And we have two point five seconds, that's the time span that she's doing and how many meters before
steps on Mushie apply her brakes.
OK, so it sounds like that we're really just looking for the distance or the the final position.
Right.
OK, so the there's no mention of acceleration and it's not asking us for the acceleration, so that's
going to be the variable that we don't care about and that's the one that we're going to be using to
determine our equation.
So once again, how are we dealing with the average velocity now?
Right.
So we're not going to be using that one.
Let's come through here and actually just pick out all the ones that do have the acceleration.
We do see right here we have acceleration, not going to use this one or by this formula.
I don't see acceleration in there.
OK, what about this one?
Yeah, we got acceleration right there, OK.
And what about this formula?
We got acceleration right there.
So we're not going to be using this one.
All right.
So it looks like that we're going to be using Formula number four for this problem.
So let's go through this math.
And once again, just make sure that you wrote the center correctly, and I think that we're looking
good.
OK, so always once again, make sure that you verify that you were done correctly.
Oh, look at this.
I like this.
So we have Zeph over here.
We have Zeph over here.
All we're going to have to do is plug this into the calculator and we get our answer.
I love those promises are just super simple.
All right.
So here we go.
Let's do this at zero plus one.
Our initial velocity and final velocity and.
Times are 2.5 seconds.
OK.
Ah, this doesn't provide any value, this doesn't provide any value.
So all we're left with is one half of 15 times 2.5.
OK.
He played on the calculator once again.
This is one 1/2 times 15 times 2.5.
And when plug in the calculator and we will get our answer so we get XPath is equal to.
Eighteen point seven, five meters.
Right, and that's the problem.
Janine.