OK, and here we go for a problem number 10, so a bus is moving at 24 meters per second when the driver
steps on the brakes and brings the bus to stop in three seconds.
What is the average acceleration of the bus while braking?
OK, so this bus is just kind of slowing down.
Brings the bus to stop.
OK, so I know it's going a certain speed, the bus driver slammed on the brakes and took a bus to stop.
That's the situation, right?
OK, so let's think about this was the initial position and what nothing specifically given to us.
So we're just going to say zero.
What does this 24 meters per second represent?
What does that tell us?
OK, so hopefully you're saying to yourself that this is our initial velocity, the twenty four meters
per second.
When the driver steps on the brakes and brings the bus to a stop, so it brings a bus to a stop.
What does that tell us?
That should be telling us that the final velocity is equal to zero.
Time span of three seconds.
What is the average acceleration of the bus?
OK, so that's simple enough, very straightforward, and it says nothing about the final position and
that's going to be the variable that we simply just don't care about.
OK, so come back over here.
So Zeph is the variable that we don't care about.
Let's go through here once again.
We're not dealing with our average velocity.
So we're coming down through here looking at these over here.
So EXIF, we're looking for zaffar.
We don't have Zeph over here.
That's a good potential candidate right there.
All right.
We do have Zeph over here and we simply do see we have excess Zeph over here.
These are not going to be for us.
And coming through over here, we have oh, there's Zeph right there.
So we're not interested in those.
How about that?
All right.
That's just our very first formula that we initially suspected that it would be.
So let's just write that down so we have the AF is equal to V.I. plus our acceleration times our Delta
T, let's plug in and go from there CERV.
V.I..
Our acceleration times three.
OK, so we're just gonna have to solve our acceleration, so we do have two terms here.
We have one term over here, which is just the twenty four in our second term is going to be R eight
times three.
Once again, terms are separated by plus and minus signs.
You might actually remember hearing about terms when you say to yourself, hey, you know what, let's
group up the like terms.
So if we actually have our two X plus five X and Y, are these like terms?
Yes, they are.
So once again, terms are separated by plus and minus signs.
So R A is what we need to isolate and let's just get rid of our first term over here.
Let's get rid of this positive 24.
How do we get rid of a positive.
Twenty four simply by subtracting twenty four on both sides of the equation and that will give us this.
And how do we get rid of this multiplication of three.
Simply divide both sides by three and we'll we will get our negative eight meters per second squared
and that's equal to our acceleration, which is the answer that we get right there.
I've got one more question for you about this problem.
Why is the answer negative?
Why is it negative eight meters per second squared?
Why isn't it eight meters per second squared?
Why is it negative?
And don't tell me it's because this is negative right here.
OK, so the reason why it's negative is simply because.
It's a deceleration in, aren't we breaking right now?
Isn't this actually coming to a stop?
So we are describing it's it's not accelerating.
It's decelerating.
And what that might have signed scientists represents a negative acceleration or a deceleration.