I will be referring to this -- over here while going through these problems, so I will be bouncing
back and forth between this sheet and the worksheet itself.
One thing I really want you to do is actually just go through this and make sure that you have a good
understanding of that position.
We're going to be using EXI and access the units that it's going to be measured in meters for velocity.
We're going to be using v the IVF and the units are meters per second.
Acceleration is going to be A and that's meters per second squared and the time elapsed is Delta T and
that's going to be measured in seconds.
For the most part, these are the units that we will be associating with these variables.
So just keep that in mind.