But let's go into the next one right now.
Problem number two says during a three second time interval, a runner's position changes from 50 meters
to thirty point five meters.
What is the runner's average velocity?
OK, well, let's talk about this here.
It says.
During a three second time interval, the runners position changes from this to this.
OK, well, what is this three seconds to represent?
Oh, hopefully you're saying that that's our Delta T.
And what is this 50 meters represent?
What does that tell us?
That's where he's starting.
That's the initial position of the runner.
And what is what about this thirty point five meters?
Well, that's where he's ending up, right?
Or she or whatever the success of the runner.
And it's asking us what is the runners average velocity, that's what we're trying to find.
How about that?
So and once again, to really clarify this for the position is going to be measured in meters.
We do have time measured in seconds and our velocity, the units should be meters per second.
So once again, we do know that we're trying to find the runners average velocity.
Which formulas do we want to use?
One, two, three, four or five or six?
Hopefully you're saying formula is one or two being that those are the ones that have to do with average
velocity?
And are we giving our initial velocity and final velocity now?
But we are given the initial position and final position.
So therefore, hopefully you're saying, hey, you know what, we have initial and final position in
equation number one.
Let's use that.
And all we have to do is plug in, oh, this is simple enough because we actually have the very poll
that we're looking for on the left hand side of the equation by itself already.
So are we going to have to do is take this plug it into the calculator and we'll get our answer.
So we have our final position, which is our thirty point five minus our initial position of fifty,
and we divide that by three and we'll play this in the calculator, we'll get an answer of, wow, this
is a negative number.
Six point five in our units, which are calculator won't tell us, but we do know it because we know
that every velocity gets measured in meters per second when we're dealing with meters and seconds.
OK, so this is our answer.
Now, you might be saying to yourself, oh, wait a minute, why is it negative?
What's what's going on there?
Well, OK, so thinking about this, say if we look at this problem, look as if it's on a number line
where we have a zero over here and we're going across x axis.
Well, our position initially is at 50 and we're going.
To thirty point five, that's what the runners deal, right?
So the runner is going backwards.
What do you think that that negative represents?
That's the direction because of velocity, it's a vector and vectors have both magnitude and direction,
that negative is representing our direction.