Number three, how far could a cyclist travel in kilometers or kilometers in 2.5 hours, a long straight
road if her average velocity is 18 kilometres per hour?
Keep in mind that 18 kilometers per hour is roughly 11 miles an hour.
OK, so let's think about this once again.
Let's read this again.
How far can a cyclist travel in this much time along a straight road if her average velocity is this?
OK, so let's say that the cyclist is starting right here and we're trying to figure out, hey, how
far could the cyclist travel in a certain amount of time?
Let me ask you something, if you're starting right here, what would you say that the initial position
is of this person or do you actually say to us now, let's just say that's going to be called a zero?
And we're doing this in kilometres, so I'm just going to write that 10 kilometres.
So looking at this, what does this 2.5 hours represent?
Oh, that's our Delta T..
Hmm, OK.
And I know that we actually were saying before that we were going to be using meters and seconds, but
as of right now, it looks like kilometres and hours, let's say, here.
And then it says the average velocity is 18 kilometers per hour.
OK, so our average velocity is 18 kilometres per hour had been that we're actually using kilometres
and hours in every single part of our problem right now.
That's OK, because it's like one of those things where the units, they will just work with each other,
but we can't really mix and match between using kilometres and meters per second or meters and kilometres
per second.
We really can't mix and match.
But if all of our units are, we have kilometres here, kilometres per hour here and we've ours over
here.
Hey, know what?
Those are all kind of like a line with each other.
That's one of those situations where you're like eight.
I could just work with the sear.
These units look like I'm not really crossing between hours and kilometres per second or and just really
mix matching.
My units were just staying consistent over here.
And that's OK.
We could do that.
This is one of the situations where you could just be not having to use meters and seconds and meters
per second units and everything.
So and it's asking us how far can the cyclist travel?
That's what the question is.
So if it's if the cyclist is starting over here and ending up over here, well, isn't that just simply
the final position, how far the cyclist is going to travel?
So that's what we're going to be finding right now.
And if we're looking at our formulas, once again, we were given an average velocity.
So therefore, which formulas do we want to be using?
Hopefully you're saying that we want to be using that one of the first two formulas that that has to
do with the average velocity.
So which one of these foremost we want to use?
Well, we don't have our initial velocity or final velocity.
So once again, we're just going to be using this one right now.
I know that this seems a little repetitive and everything, but these are different principles, different
kind of concepts that I want to be covering in the first few problems before actually getting into the
thick of it and everything.
So, OK, so we just simply plug this in.
And what do we have here?
So we have our 18, that's our average velocity, our final position.
That's what we're trying to find.
Our initial position, which is zero divide, that by two point five, the obstruction of zero doesn't
provide any sort of value.
Being that we have a division of 2.5, what do we do?
We multiply both sides of the equation by 2.5 and we get our final position of 45 kilometres.
And that's the final answer for that one, usually, once again, our position is typically in meters,
but once they've been pumping that, we were consistent with our kilometres over here.
Our final answer will be in kilometres.