Are in this section we're going to look at energy and electric circuits.
More specifically we're going to look at things like power power being supplied by batteries power being
dissipated by resistors.
I'll talk about Electromotive forces and batteries and their internal resistance and everything that
I discuss in this chapter.
The currents are going to be constant.
So in order for there to be a constant current Sometimes you call this a steady state current in order
for there to be a steady state current.
You can imagine here I have a battery and if I want a steady state current regardless of what I have
I need to have a closed loop like this.
This is going to be a requirement for there to be a constant current.
So you need to have close loops if the loop is not closed.
Well what happens if you imagine just a piece of conductor just like a wire.
Here is a piece of wire which doesn't form a closed loop.
Now you can imagine connecting this to or producing an electric field inside this wire.
If I do that well guess what I'm going to produce a current there's going to be a current in the direction
of the electric field that we saw from Ohm's law.
Right.
The electric field is directly proportional to the current density in that conductor.
Now what happens however is if it doesn't form a closed loop Well you're a Benci going to get a build
up of charges on the sides.
So you have positive charges build up on the one side you'll have negative charges build up on the other
side.
And while these charges they also produce an electric field.
So read at the building right at the beginning the electric fuel produced by those charges is small
because there's not a lot of them there as a function of time that electric field gets bigger.
And as if I'm going the time it gets even bigger.
Up until the electric fuel produced by these charges at the end is equal and opposite to the electric
fuel produce you know that set up the current to begin with.
So once the total electric field which is the sum of both of those equals zero.
There's no more current.
OK.
So what we want is we don't want any buildup of charges like this if you get build up of charges your
current going to go to zero and it's not going to be constant.
So what we're going to need then is we're going to need something that keeps on pushing current and
that something is basically effectively a pump.
Well we're going to need now is a pump and it's kind of analogous to kind of water in this water fountain
over here.
Right what the water does or what the pump does is it pushes water up to the top and then water kind
of trickles down through holes and eventually kind of works its way back down.
But without the pump right the water is just simply going to fall down and that's it is not going to
go back up.
So that current that flow of water is basically going to stop if there's no pump in the system.
So our batteries are basically simply going to act like pumps.
They are going to do work on charges and then charges are basically going to be allowed to fall down.
And that's what an electric current is.
Basically this water coming back down and then the pump is the battery that's going to be driving it
back up.
We'll look back at this water analogy in a minute.
But without the pump the water would just fall to the bottom and stay there without the battery the
charges will not move because there is no electric field inside.