All right consider now a certain segment of wire.
And we're looking at a current or charge and the charge is going to be moving.
So it's initially kind of we're just looking at a particular volume here of charge.
Then over time that charge moves so the way it moves it's as though you kind of took some charge from
the back end of that cylinder and moved it all the way to the front.
But again if there is an electric field produced in that wire which is kind of driving this charge to
move it means there is a potential difference.
So you have vitæ and you have a potential VB.
And what you're doing is you're moving this amount of charge you're only moving a little bit of charge
at a time or you're moving that a little bit of charge from the position where the potential is V.A
toward a lower electrical potential toward VB.
So the voltage at point A is bigger than the voltage at point B.
Now if I'm moving some positive charge remember how the potential energy now is related to the voltage
at any point the potential energy is given by the charge.
Multiplied by the potential at that point.
So what happens when you move from A to B is you go toward a lower electrical potential but really the
potential energy now at a goes toward the potential energy.
B.
So there is a loss in potential energy.
So that's important.
So if you look at all the energy that is lost so you initial is at point A.
Now let's look at the change in the potential energy.
There is a change in potential energy when this charge moves from the back end of the cylinder through
the front means we've changed the potential energy of the system.
Now if you do that at a particular rate as this kind of current moves down it's as though you're always
bringing in charge from the back and moving it to the front.
This is done at a particular rate and this is what we call the power.
The power is the rate at which you do work.
And in order to move that charge from one end to the other there is work done.
Now if you substitute things in here what you get is again we're reading potential energy to the voltage
and the amount of charge that we're bringing over is this little bit.
Delta Q and multiplied by this change in voltage.
So this is actually vitæ.
Mine is v.v.
And again since I'm looking at a rate at which I'm changing the energy of a system you can look at you
still have to divide through by this change in time.
How much time does it take to do that.
All right now we can combine some terms.
Again V-A mine is.
VB is typically what we simply call the voltage.
So the power at the end ends up simply looking like this delta Q divided by Delta T and multiplied by
just the voltage V where again the voltage is simply equal to V.A. mine is VB for short.
It's always a difference of potential.
Now Delta Q over delta T that is the definition of our current and v is the potential difference across
two points that we're looking at.
So here is a power equation.
It's the rate at which there's either work done by the battery or it's the rate at which energy is getting
dissipated in a resistor.
If we look at the units of this current multiplied by voltage.
So let's look at the units of our power units of current and cool ohms per second that's an AMPS multiplied
by Jewel Procul.
That's the units of voltage.
And at the n cool ohms cancel out.
And what you're left with here are units of Joule per second.
And this is what we call a watt one joule per second is equivalent to 1 watt.
So the units of power are Joule per second.
Which is equivalent to what's OK so this is kind of an important equation.
Now it really can be written in three different forms this power equation.
So let's have a look at that.
So this is kind of one form.
Now you you combine this with Ohm's Law Ohm's law if you remember said that voltage is related to the
current by the resistance.
Right.
We had this equation here for Ohm's law.
Again we have the three variables.
And the way it's written now in the black box over here is it doesn't include the value of the resistance.
However if I substitute V into my power equation what I'm going to get is a slightly different form
so let me write it down over here.
It's the same equation but you just substitute V using Ohm's law and what you find is it's you're going
to get I.
You're going to get another.
I found that V.
So the power equation can sometimes be written like this and it can also be written by eliminating the
current.
I can eliminate the current by using Ohm's law by substituting the current in my power equation by V
divided by R.
And if I do that the power here can be written as the squared over are.
So here are kind of two other forms of writing the exact same equation.
There are some cases where this form might be kind of more convenient we'll see and simple circuits
that I kind of like this form if I'm looking at the power being delivered by the battery I usually can
figure out how much current is flowing through the battery and I usually know what the voltages are
what the IAM method the battery is.
So this is very easy to calculate when I'm looking at resistors if I'm looking at resistors you typically
know the value of R and then we'll have tricks to help us find what the current is so these forms are
kind of good but it's also you know we have to remember that the voltage here always means the voltage
across the element that we're looking at.
If you're looking at a resistor it's the voltage across the resistor.
If you're looking at an IMF it's the IMF or the battery.