All right let's look at some conventional symbols over here.
So voltage sources when we're going to look at circuits are not represented by those big batteries that
I had on the previous one.
And again they're usually represented just by these parallel lines that are of different lengths the
longer length represents the positive terminal the negative for the shorter one represents the negative
terminal in a circuit.
Would kind of look like this.
Sometimes you write the letter E sometimes you would just write the letter V next to it.
And again that always represents the voltage the terminal voltage across across both ends.
And this particular case there is no internal resistance.
If there is an internal resistance you'll sometimes just add another resistance right next to it.
And usually you give it a letter a little our resistor is everywhere in our circuits are going to be
represented by these kind of Sawtooth here again.
And usually you have some value of the resistance next to it.
Now these are often connected by wires and in our circuits here wires are just lines.
For example the segment that goes from 8 to B is just a wire.
And for most of what we do unless the problem explicitly tells you to calculate it and most of what
we do we will neglect any resistance of these wires that connect the batteries to the resistors.
OK.
So the wires let me just do something like this.
Segment of wire
usually no resistance.
All right.
The other thing that often shows up sometimes you have these lines like this it just represents a switch
you'll see more of these switches later on when we talk about capacitors.
But for now you still might see them sometimes in circuits.
So clearly when it's open it means there is no current flowing through that segment of wire that includes
the switch.
And when you would close it well when you close it you could draw like this.
And then you make an electrical connection and now current is free to go by.
So what it's like in this position here is open again no current can flow through there.
And it's basically no current can flow through that segment.
If there's a switch only in one part of a circuit then it could be you might have current flowing in
a different part.
And when it's closed in this position current flow yes the current
an open circuit like this basically represents a case where the resistance between this point and that
point is basically infinite.
And if we have an infinite resistance as we saw from Ohm's law there is no current flowing through it.