Before focusing on the mysteries and paradoxes of the quantum world, we must learn a couple of elementary
concepts such as momentum and spin, angular momentum and spin that we will find throughout the rest
of this course.
And again, please distinguish between momentum, angular momentum and the kinetic energy, kinetic
energy is something quite different and check out if you don't know the difference.
Check out the brief lecture that you will find in the appendix.
So what is angular momentum in classical physics?
It is not very hard to understand it.
It is the amount of rotational momentum, the quantity of motion of rotating bodies, such a particle
flying around an orbital center like in the left figure here.
Or the amount of rotational motion of an extended object spinning around its own axis, which could
be, for example, the Earth or that of a more complex object, that could be a spinning top.
And these material bodies could spin faster or slower and could be more or less massive, which means
contain more metal, and therefore we used to say that they have more or less angular momentum.
Let us first look at the notion of the angular momentum of a single particle rotating around the center
as shown diagrammatically with the diagram with vectors in this figure.
Recall how the linear momentum of a particle which moves unperturbed, which means linear means in which
it moves unperturbed along a straight path.
This is proportional to the product of its mass m times the velocity we at least in non relativistic
classical mechanics and which is P equals M Times v..
Similarly.
The general expression of the angular momentum l l with capital letters of a particle with rotation
velocity of about an origin is defined as l equal.
Our gross product P.
Which means our gross product and times we ve where we are is a position vector of the particle relative
to the rotational origin and the cross, this cross here denotes the vector across product, a sort
of multiplication for vectors, which is not so extremely relevant now for us.
Yeah, but it's just to tell you that you have to multiply in some way vectors with scholars, scholars,
which means only numbers like math and vectors like that position or vector R and velocity vector V.
Please note that both the linnear and the angular momentum are vectors vector quantity, so which means
they have a magnitude and direction.
In fact, usually we letters representing vectors are written with an arrow.
Above it or in bold, here, we use the name, the letter and the bold style Symbolics.
Now, what about extended bodies made of several particles, not just one?
In the event of a body made of GNR particles rotating around a center is external to itself that is
orbiting around a center of origin.
The so-called orbital angular momentum, which is written capital or arbiter, can be obtained by determining
that some of the linear momentum of each of its constituent particles sum over all the particles of
masses, M-I times the respective rotation and velocity.
V.I. for each of it as an orbital equals the sum from equal one to N, and the number of particles of
which the body is made are high, which is again a vector cross product.
My times v i.
Where the index eye is, the index of the ice particles and our our eye is ice particles distance from
that axis and any.
As the number of particles, it is just the same formula as above, only indexed by a day by a number
parameter I in this case, however, an extended body can also rotate around itself.
A typical example is that of the Earth, which not only orbits around the sun, but, as everybody knows,
spins once around its polar axis approximately every 24 hours.
In this case, four bodies whose interior have a complex, mass disparate distribution like the Earth,
the density distribution inside the earth can be quite complicated and one must calculate the so-called
moment of inertia of a body.
Inertia is a physical quantity that measure measures the resistance and material body exerts upon a
change of motion.
In the case of just off a point particle, it is simply it's mass, the mass is, in fact in physics
mass of particles.
The mass of the particle is just defined as a resistance to a change of motion.
If one can define it as such, in the case of a body with an extension and a more or less irregular
complex geometry and internal mass or mass distribution or method distribution, it is escala quantity.
And no, I, I in capital letters.
Which can be calculated with mathematical procedures.
Here are given some examples and the formulas of the moment of inertia for these bodies just to deliver
an intuitive view, of course, you don't need to know the details of the calculations, but loosely
speaking, if a body rotates around its center of mass.
The mall or around some, some.
Other center at the moment of inertia of a body is usually somehow proportional to the mass of the body.
Times the square of the radius of the body itself.
It depends, obviously, how how complicated the body is.
Sometimes you cannot just define the radius.
But in these cases, at least in some cases, you can you can do so.
In general, the spinning angular momentum L.
S is given by this formula as equals I the moment of inertia times Omega, where Omega is a mathematical
expression of the angular velocity, which is a measure, so to speak, of how fast it spins around
around itself.
That is how quickly it completes 360 degrees rotation per unit time, which in the case of a spherical
body is just Omega equals V.
Over are the rotational speed of the body divided by its diameter.
Therefore, we must distinguish between between the angular momentum of a particle or a body moving
around the center, for example, a planet around the sun and the angular momentum of a body around
its own central axis as the examples above the above mentioned case of angular momentum of the earth
spinning, spinning around its polar axis.
These are two closely related, related, but slightly different quantities.
One is an orbital angular momentum, while the other is a spinning, angular momentum, also known simply
as spin.
Therefore, the total angular momentum is the sum of the two, the total is equal and orbital plus a
spin.
When we speak about angular momentum, it is important to remember and very important universal law,
which is to keep in mind is what what we have to keep in mind is that of the conservation of angular
momentum, which is a direct consequence of the of the conservation of energy.
That is, as you probably know and have learned in schools in your school.
And energy can never be created or destroyed, but energy can only be transformed from mechanical energy
into heat or into electricity and vice versa and so on.
The law of conservation of angular momentum states that the total angular momentum cannot change if
there is not an interaction from outside and if there is no friction or it.
For some reason, the system does not lose this energy and its angular momentum.
So in a closed system, angular momentum cannot change and must be conserved that it is conserved unless
an external torquil acts on the rotating body.
In this equation, the radios are on the speed we are allowed to change and the equation that we saw
previously, but the overall momentum l must remain constant.
If a particle gets closer to the center, which means are decreases, the angular velocity therefore
must increase to maintain a constant otherwise would not remain constant.
It's just a matter of math.
This also holds for an extended body.
And the very common the typical common example illustrating the principle of the conservation of angular
momentum is that of the ice skater.
When ice skaters bring their arms closer, closer to the to their bodies, the angular velocity must
increase and vice versa.
If they bring their arms far from their body, their rotational speed decreases.
In fact, this act, that of moving the arms, decreases the inertia eye of the body of the skater ice
skater according to the law of conservation, of angular momentum and increase of omega must follow
to maintain unless there's been angular momentum, constant and vice versa.
Now that we have been introduced to the main concept and principle of the the angular momentum in classical
mechanics, let us see its meaning if there is any meaning, but at least how we can apply this concept
of angular momentum also in quantum physics.