Let us focus now on another very important concept of quantum physics, which is the so-called quantum
superposition principle.
It is a very interesting but also weird aspect of quantum reality, which has been discussed by scientists
and philosophers throughout the 20th century and still remains a deeply counterintuitive property of
particles at not only particles.
So let us see what it is all about by looking back briefly again to the good old Dubbo's little experiment.
You recall how on that occasion we conceived of an experiment where we could use only one particle at
a time, say, a single electron at a time, which we sent through the double towards the screen.
It is hard enough to imagine a single particle distracting and interfering with itself, but if we stick
with this picture, we must give up the logical or reasoning.
We must think of the particle going through this little one and lead to something that in classical
physics as well as classical logic, would be mutually exclusive.
As weird as this may appear, experimental facts show that our intuitive understanding, which presupposes
an interpretation based on a logical, disjunctive or would be in contradiction with the observed interference
phenomena.
Since this state of affairs sounds counter to intuitive and the model of a single particle becoming,
so to speak, ubiquitous and going through to or eventually also Maunsell, it is a quite doubtful.
One physicist refrain from trying to imagine any model and ontology at all, one then simply says that
the state of the particle, as long as there is no measurement, is undetermined, uncertain or simply
undefined.
We encountered a similar situation with Heisenberg's Uncertainty Principle, which we visualized with
the with the help of a single bullet or the pinhole experiment and which is summarized again here,
you should know now at is not what we observe on the screen is the distribution of points of pride,
tiny spots on the screen, which statistically can be interpreted by a bell shaped, bell shaped curve
centered on the lit aperture.
This tells us where the single particles hits the screen, accumulating one after the other in a region
around the little center, and which describes our uncertainty on the whereabouts of the particle that
formally is given by the Heisenberg's uncertainty relation.
This means that before the measurement, we can interpret the particle as being in all places at once
when it when it traverses Region Delta X of this size, and once it is in front of the screen, which
is shortly before the wavefunction collapses to a point, it is everywhere simultaneously allowing the
space interval described by the distribution function.
Considering that the position in space of a particle is also a property that describes its quantum state,
recall that in quantum mechanics the position is in fact obtained via the position observable the upright
position of the operator, which is the ex operator, then this suggests a more general interpretation,
namely that before this instant of interaction of the particle with the detector or the detector screen,
we must consider it in a superposition of states before they enter that area.
The interaction, the particles location in space is not just unknown.
It is in a position of several possible locations.
That is also why we cannot interpret Heisenberg's uncertainty as something due to our ignorance about
the position of the particle in terms of a logical or reasoning that that is the particle is in one
or the other state, it must instead be interpreted as a logical end, as a coexistence of states,
that is, with all possible states superimposed.
We should we should say the particle is simultaneously in many possible states.
Note how this is in line with the linearity of Schrodinger's equation and that we defined in the lecture
on Schrodinger's equation.
And this is an equation which is ultimately that which one calculates to calculate the evolution in
time of the quantum state.
And in that occasion, we said that if you have two solutions of this, of the Schrodinger equation,
the sum of these two solutions is, again, a solution of running an equation here.
The same reappears in a different form, but it is the same principle.
If a particle is allowed to be in one or another place, then it is also allowed to be in both places.
Quantum mechanics should be taken seriously in this sense.
In fact, it challenges us to believe that a physical object can be in two or even many possible places
at the same time.
Or in no physical state at all, we might say.
This strange ubiquity of particles conveys a deeper meaning to the computational relations, the fact
that observable the of the observable X and P do not commute means not only that, once we try to determine
X with high precision the values of the get zumaya, so to speak, but that this implies also the existence
of state superposition.
If two dynamical variables are represented by two NONCOMMUTATIVE operators, once a measurement of the
first is done, a superposition of states corresponding to the other dynamic variable is automatically
induced.
This suggests also how this weird super position effect must not be exclusive to space, but is a much
more general principle of quantum mechanics, since, as we know, there are also other observables
that do not commute.
For instance, as you will remember, the spin does not commute in quantum physics, the concept of
the state uncertainty must be interpreted as superposition of states, not as an and our ignorance of
which state is realised.
It is not about not knowing there is some state out there that is realised.
The particle is perhaps in spin up, but we don't know know the particle is in spin up and spin down
state.
Let us visualize and define this a bit more rigorously with the with the help.
Of this scheme, and that should be known to you if you followed the lectures on the S.G. experiments
and the commutative and the computational relations.
As usual, a first as jetset device prepares a particle in that Kate Plus eight and state here to prepare
means that those particles showing up with a spin upstate along that were first selected from the source
by performing a measurement that project them into the that plus I can state that is the best that observable
comes into the plate.
First, since the asset observable this that operator does not commute with A.
S, X and Y observables.
This measurement automatically renders the particle spin.
State along the X and Y axis as uncertain.
And uncertain does not only mean that once measured, there is a 50 percent chance of finding the particle
in a XCAP plus or minus Eisenstaedt, but that before the next measurement, it is in both states.
The XCAP plus and minus states coexist.
Before such a measurement takes place, therefore, we can represent the state of the spin up particle
along that that axis that that plus I can state in superposition of both spin up and spin down along
the x axis basis as shown here.
That is, we have that plus equals one over squared, two times X squared plus.
Plus one over square to X minus, this is not just a mathematical description which furnishes the statistics,
the probable probabilities of a result, that little tiny plus here represents a superposition of spin
and states.
Whereas, as usual, the square root of coefficients tell us something about the probability of getting
one or the other result should an X directed measurement take place.
Therefore, the two particles intrinsic momentum along the x axis and this example, similar considerations
would hold for the Y axis as well.
These are both present as if the particle is spinning clockwise and anticlockwise at the same time.
Again, formally, one can see this as a natural consequence of Schrodinger's equation linearity, if
the eigenvector get X plus and the eigenvector get X minus are two allowed states.
And our solution of the Schrodinger equation, then also there are some get X plus and minus are also
an allowed single quantum state.
That is a solution of the Schrodinger equation.
And the same fits also for the Z and X, Y and Z component, whatever component you wish.
Not only do quantum particles, so to speak, multi locate and are ubiquitous, but they even multi
spin, so to speak.
If you make a second measurement, then let us so proceed with a S.G. construction that we have already
seen, but now at this time we will interpret it with a superposition principle.
Therefore, if we make a second measurement which projects the particles spin along the x axis with
the SGX device, the X spin has been measured and the spin up in state X plus selected.
The get minus 18 states are blocked internally in the S.G. device, I place the equation of the first
set of eyes on the EU that the device figure here, block diagram here again, there's a superposition
along the x axis has gone.
Now Wetterstedt reduction has occurred.
But since the spin operator as X does not compute with that, the particle state along the Z axis is
now no longer in.
I can state that get plus the spin up particles igan state along the x axis basis, the X plus I can,
it can be represented now as being in superposition of both spin up and spin down along that, that
axis basis.
So we have a similar equation as before, but with the X and Z.
Directions replaced with one another.
Yeah, we have.
X plus equals one always right to square root to that Kate plus plus one over square to that minus with
the usual interpretation.
Finally, the third stage device in that selects out either that kid plus or the that kid minus state
as amply discussed in the section on the S.G. devices.
And from this equation, this means it selects out one or the other against it, which however it previously
was in a superposition state.
So now we have a different state of the system each time that they're.
Selection is being made or the measurement, of course, therefore the same quantum state that Kate
Plus represented in that basis can be represented in the X-axis eigenvector basis as well.
But there it appears as a superposition along that component in a similar fashion.
Quantum algebra allows for the representation of a quantum state in any desired eigenvector basis.
We just made an example between that set an X coordinate system, but we could make this equally well
also for the Y axis basis or any basis in between.
It is like seeing the very same quantum state from different geometric perspective by a change of coordinates
or just rotating the system, for example, with a rotational translation, but leaving it physically
unaltered.
So far, we have considered particles with a mass, but another example where quantum superposition
takes place is a superposition of photon states.
Photons are massless particles and in vacuum, always travel with the speed of light, which is about
three times.
Ten to the power, eight meters per second, whatever the speed and dynamic state of the observer or
the measurement apparatus is, this is one of the main principles of special relativity that tells us
the speed of light is always the same.
You will never see a photon at rest as you do as you can can do in the case of particles, material,
particles possessing a mass.
And we already saw that the positive or negative spin of a photon is oriented along the direction of
propagation or contrary to it, and is determined by the right or left handed rotation of circular,
polarized electromagnetic waves.
What polarizers select out?
However, are not spins, but if the photons electric field orientation, this does not mean that photons
can't be in superposition state as particles can be in two places at once.
Material particles can be in two places at once or have two spins at once.
Also, photons could have two polarizations at once.
We can apply a similar reasoning to photons as we have done to two electrons, provided we remember
that the former are particles with spin, one directed along or contrary only to the momentum.
Of direction, momentum, contrary to fermions, which are particles with only two possible spin one-half
outcomes that, however, can point towards any direction.
And for photons, we must also keep in mind that the polarization vector is restricted to any x Y plane
perpendicular to the direction of propagation in this case, we labeled it that Z direction and that
photons are not described by Spinous, but by the electromagnetic field vectors which return on to themselves
after 360 degrees rotation.
That is all angles here are half as much as those of fermions.
Then let us agree on how to use certain symbolic conventions, since in the literature, this can be
quite different.
Let us be flexible and use different symbolic conventions according to the context.
We will use the following state rectors notation for the up and down vertical polarisation state vector.
This cat here with the arrow that goes up or just a.
And we get vertical standing V Capital Letter V extending for vertical and also the arrow pointing down
because they are obviously parallel and parallel to each other, but both represent the vertical paralyzation
for the right and left, horizontal paralyzation there, right and left.
Kett, which correspondence corresponds to the horizontal parallelization?
Keat for the diagonal, 45 degrees under 35 degrees to under 25 degrees and 315 degrees polarizations
their respective cats and cat arrows that you can see here, or the corresponding codes written in degrees
respectively.
And we can also just write a generic polarisation of teta degrees as cat teta degrees.
Here, let us use first GraphicLy, more intuitive error convention here.
First, we have linearly polarized light along the vertical direction or simply vertically vertical,
polarized photons.
Now notice how due to simple geometrical trigonometric considerations, a vector, a vertical vector
can be decomposed as a sum.
That is the superposition of two diagonal vectors of 45 and minus 45 degrees or instead of minus forty
five degrees.
We can also consider a 315 degrees component.
Then we can reason by analogy and say that as an electron spin along at the Z direction, it changes
its X spin component into X spin superposition state.
So a photons polarisation again, not to confuse with a photon spin along the vertical y direction selected
from an unauthorized light source superimposes it's minus 45 degrees and plus 45 degrees.
Polarisation components into a diagonal paralyzation superposition state as.
Written.
In the equation here.
And what this equation tells us is that a photon in a vertical polarization state.
Is as superposition of the two diagonal.
Polarizations state, and when we measure the photon and vertical polarization stayed a long one or
the other diagonal 45 degrees direction, we have 50 percent chance to.
Have a photo getting through or not?
That's what this equation tells us, and it is about superposition and it tells us about the quantum
state of a photon in a vertical position, in a vertical polarization state and which can be decomposed
as a superposition of two diagonal states and the corresponding measurement outcome in case we make
a measurement along these two diagonal directions.
Notice how we use the word selection when speaking of the action of polarizers.
Polarizers do not involve state reduction.
State reduction is always something that happens when a measurement is done.
That is, there is a measurement device from which we can read out information.
As long as there is a polarizer in between, it changes.
It selects the state of a quantum particle.
But there is not still not a real measurement since there with let alone you do not read out any information,
you transform the state of the system.
So it is also necessary to distinguish between a selection and a state reduction, which are two different
things, as we will see later.
Since this turns out to be extremely important for.
Understanding also other quantum phenomena.
Similarly, similarly, the same thing can be said about a diagonal polarization vector.
This also can be decomposed as a sum of two vectors, namely as a superposition of two vertical polarization
vectors of zero degrees and 90 degrees.
That is, one can represent the diagonal polarisation as a superposition of the vertical and horizontal
one as shown here.
I assume now that you understand the meaning of these equations.
Or another example not shown, we just display the equation here, the horizontal polarization vector
can be represented as a sum of the 45 degrees and 135 diagonal vectors as shown here.
Of course, many other combinations are possible, after all, that is nothing else than the vector's
summation, according to the parallelogram law.
See also how this has been shortly explained in the appendix and that you should have learned in school
and does not look particularly surprising.
Paralyzation Vector's as any other physical vector quantities such such as speed, accelerate, acceleration
forces, etc. are treated with a vector formalism and can be decomposed appropriately in different ways,
different vectors.
In quantum physics, however, this acquires a deeper significance.
A quantum state superposition superposition is not just the addition of two states resulting into another
state, but the realization of both states simultaneously.
Let us place the previous equation here and this angle on the upper left just to get an overall view.
Now, this suggests to introduce for Fortum polarization a more general, better basis description,
as we have already done with Fermín Particle's.
Here, the first base is Vector is the vertical paralyzation, the second base is vector is the horizontal
parallelization Keat and which are described by these vector one zero and zero one, respectively.
And the third is a generalized version.
Pluralization state director, Independence of the Angelita.
The letter one can be treated as a superposition of the two Baz's vectors and be can be formulated as
follows, a catheter is nothing as as a superposition of the vertical and horizontal Keat vectors.
Times for the horizontal force, for the vertical get, because I'm Teater.
Plus, the horizontal at times, Santita, note that this time the cosine and sine functions have titta
instead of to dependent's, which means photons return to themselves after rotations of 360 degrees
and we might see the world behave nicely in human terms again.
Then finally, applying Bond's rule, as we have done for Spinous, taking the model square of the state
vector gives finally this expression for the probability to find some.
Polarization along some direction, that is, this tells us that there is a cosine square teater probability
that a photon slips through a polarizer, rotated relative relatively to the vertical y axis by two
degrees if it has been prepared in the.
Cat, we are state and equivalently assigned square to probability to measure a photon if it has been
prepared in the cat.
Horizontal Eisenstaedt.
To sum up and conclude this tour on the quantum superposition principle, what we should keep in mind
is the bottom line of all this, at least for noncommutative observables, it makes no sense to say
that a particle is in one or another state until a measurement has projected it into an Afghan state.
We can only say something about the probability to measure one or another outcome and not because of
ignorance, but because the system is intrinsically in a position of states until you measure it.
Or that might look impossible or unappealing to some, but what is definite is that once you use the
quantum superposition in the mathematical formalism of quantum mechanics, then everything, everything
works fine.
Only if the superposition principle is taken seriously with the match between the theory and the experimental
check with reality turned out to be correct.
And later on, we shall encounter other experiments which will underline this further.