Another interesting effect that you will find in the rhythm of the quantum world is the so-called quantum
tunneling effect.
It is a strange phenomenon that emerges quite naturally once the time energy relation, the Heisenberg's
uncertainty relation and the wave particle principle expressed by the debris relation are taken together.
This implies that we have to expect very different behaviors between classical, mechanical and quantum
objects.
For instance, according to classical mechanics, we can throw an object over a wall only if it has
a sufficient kinetic energy that can overcome the wall, which means more precisely, that there is
enough kinetic energy that can be transformed into potential energy to reach the hate, the hate of
the top of the wall wall.
If it does not have that or more speed in the form of kinetic energy to overcome this potential barrier,
it will hit the wall and eventually bounce back by more and more or less elastic or inelastic reflection.
However, in quantum mechanics, things are a bit different.
Any object's position and energy is due to Heisenberg's time, energy, uncertainty, always a bit uncertain,
intrinsically fuzzy and smeared out over an average value and the figure for simplicity.
We depicted the classical trajectory here with a solid line while the dashed lines stand for the quantum
fuzziness.
And this now is in turn means that due to this slight but sometimes, sometimes not negligible degree
of uncertainty, a quantum particle which was prepared with a kinetic energy of a value near to that
necessary to jump over the wall, but still classically insufficient to do that might yet possess due
to this Quantum added.
And certain quantum uncertainty might possess that little bit of additional energy that will eventually
allow it to overcome the barrier.
Therefore, in quantum physics, it is always possible, though usually with low probability, that
sometimes particle will be able to overcome an obstacle, even if they have a slightly lower kinetic
energy than that which is classically necessary, necessary to overcome it.
This classically not allowed slipping through a barrier is called quantum tunneling.
This was a bit of a down to earth and intuitive way to put things, a more rigorous understanding of
quantum tunneling can be achieved if we also recall that the particles have a wave character, they
due to the particle wave particle duality.
We can describe them also with waves.
With this perspective, we no longer conceive of a particle hitting a wall as a point like or eventually
extend that well defined object which overcomes it or not.
But rather we will visualize it as a travelling probability wave, which is in part reflected and in
part transmitted through the barrier.
Just like a light rail can be partially reflected and transmitted by a glass plate, a wave can do to
diffraction effects be deviated from classical path, especially at the boundary of a sharp edge.
In microscopic structures, it is more realistic to think of thin, atomic or molecular layers.
These two are barriers that, for the sake of simplicity, can be approximated as a step function like
this one.
In this figure here, if you insert the wavefunction into the Schrodinger's equation and constrain the
particle appropriately with the potential V of X, which represents the barrier, then you will obtain
a different solution for the wave function BPCI of X before inside and after the barrier he ipsi of
X is shown instead of its model of square and to show how the solution behaves inside and outside of
the well.
In the upper figure, you can see the image, imaginary and real parts of the wave function and how
this is reflected and transmitted through the potential barrier in the lower figure, an analog representation.
However, in this time, with a model squared of the wave function, that is, it is represented as
a probability wave on one side, the left part of the figure here and incoming and reflected probability
wave will overlap, that is, interfere and result in the left standing wave.
Again, in principle, a similar standing wave effect that we saw for orbitals or in the black body
radiation cavity.
Inside the barrier, one gets an exponentially decaying wave function, which means an exponentially
decaying probability with the thickness of the barrier of finding the particle inside it.
But for the transmitted wave after the barrier, another solution will result and oscillating non-zero
solution, implying a non-zero probability to find the particle having tunneled through the barrier.
So before the barrier, there are several regions where we will find the particle being reflected since
its kinetic energy was not sufficient to penetrate the barrier, at least classically, but there is
also a small probability to find it after the barrier as well.
Despite the fact that the classically did not have sufficient in the energy, kinetic energy to do so.
Statistically, that means that multiple particles, even if all are prepared in the exact same kinetic
kinetic energy again state, must have nevertheless slightly different energy values distributed over
a mean energy due to the uncertainty that governs the quantum world due to the energy time uncertainty.
For example, while most are reflected, a few will nevertheless make it through because these few will
have a slightly higher energy content than the average value and which is considered the classical mechanical
one and will be able to penetrate nevertheless the potential barrier, even though they were prepared
in a lower energy, energetic state.
This is in stark contrast to the classical behavior, where if a number of particles all have the same
energy, they will all behave together in the same way.
They will all bounce back or all jump over the obstacle.
Nobody has been seen to be able to walk through a wall, for example, and yet little tiny quantum particles
are allowed to do that.
Atomic decays display quantum tunneling effects in a particularly striking manner.
In fact, quantum tunneling explains why radioactive elements decay.
An atomic nucleus can be represented as a potential well, where the protons and neutrons are trapped
inside a square potential, a proton or neutron bound inside the atomic nucleus never has an entirely
normal energy because of Heisenberg's position, momentum and certainty.
It has a ground state energy, which in classical mechanics would be perfectly zero.
But in quantum mechanics, it is tiny but non-zero.
Recall how the same applies to the ground state energy of an electron in the hydrogen atom.
It to this reason, there is a tiny but non-zero probability to tunnel, which the particle will acquire
sooner or later, a sufficient impulse to overcome the nuclear barrier and traverse it sooner or later
means that the time at which the signal decay will occur is completely undetermined.
Also, one can speak of a mean lifetime for nuclease.
For special nuclear strike, structural and energetic configurations, this period of time can be almost
infinite.
In that case, the nucleus is considered to be stable and that means for extremely long, eventually
also longer than the life of the universe.
Halftimes also very short, say, of the order of a few microseconds.
An element is considered radioactive when several nuclei decay every second.
But the underlying principle is substantially the same if we apply the Schrodinger equation to the nuclear
potential well and set the appropriate boundary conditions, we obtain a solution for the wavefunction
which will furnish the probability to tunnel outside.
There is a little wave part of the solution, the small way the left and right side of X in the figure
here, which is also non-zero at great distances from the atomic nucleus, and which means that there
is a tiny but non-zero probability given, as usual by the model square of PSI of X to find a proton
or neutron ejected outside the nucleus.
And then we say that a nuclear decay even has taken place here.
Also an example which shows nuclear decay, often uranium isotope into thorium, one with emission of
an alpha particle, which is a helium nucleus.
An important point to keep in mind for all these examples is that there is no way to determine.
Or decide apriori which particles will tunnel through and which will not the tunnel effect, like all
quantum effects, is a purely random stochastic effect.
It is a probabilistic and completely unpredictable process which determines which of the single particles
will tunnel through or not.
You can never say when an element decays only the mean amount of time that it takes for half of the
nuclei to decay.
We can tell this fact will be used later to illustrate also the Schrodinger's cat paradox.
Quantum theory is not just something theoretical, most of the physicists working on are with quantum
theory today are mostly concerned with all sorts of possible practical applications rather than questions
about its foundations.
One interesting example, which shows how quantum effects are not only interesting phenomena for physical
or philosophical ruminations, but also can have very practical applications.
Is this so-called scanning tunneling microscope or shortly ASTM?
And ASTM is a microscope that uses quantum tunneling effects to investigate surfaces of materials and
the resolution of the atomic scale.
It was possible to build such such microscopes only after the 1980s because they require particularly
precise mechanics, cryogenic cryogenic techniques and extremely fine positioning methods.
Their working principle, however, is relatively easy to understand.
Once you know the ones, you know how quantum tunneling works.
Very briefly and schematically, this figure shows a tip which is usually made of graphene.
This tip must be extremely thin and sharp, a sort of needle which is only a few atoms thick itself
in order to position it exactly on each individual atom from time to time.
This tape is positioned through another very precise positioning system made of pizza, electric crystals,
the genetic properties of which can be varied and modulated very precisely by applying an electric tension
and which positions it the tip.
This little needle above the surface that is to be analyzed.
This graphene tip is positioned very closely to the atoms of the sample surface onto which also an electric
potential is applied.
So you have this electric potential on both sides.
At some point they get so near that the electrons of one atom of the tip can quantum tunnel through
the potential barrier induced by the tunneling voltage to the atom of the sample.
This really is a tiny but measurable electric current, which can be read out if appropriate, appropriately
amplified through some electronics.
The tape then moves along on the sample surface by means of this pizza electric positioning system and
through a computerized distance and position, control scans the area of interest step by step.
It becomes then possible to reconstruct pixel by pixel an image that represents the atomic landscape.
Thereby.
Can one obtain images like this one, which is a Graffin surface?
In some sense, we might say that the scanner is scanning tunneling microscope, the system allows us
to see, so to speak, atoms.
But you should by now be able to understand that what these images actually show are probabilities,
more precisely the probability that is at the specific position, the microscope type measures and interaction
with the atoms.
And in what sense does this imply seeing, one might ask?
Are these images really showing us an objective reality as things they are really.
It's difficult to give a real answer to this, because, after all.
It is difficult to say if a probability wave or a probability density distribution is something objectively
real, but after all.
This is what we are left with, the universe that we observe is at a quantum level is always and only
a quantum probability distribution.