Another interesting aspect of quantum theory is the so-called zero point energy of empty space, also
called the zero point field, or more appropriately, the ground state energy of the vacuum, according
to classical physics, which after all, reflects our intuitive understanding, empty space is just
that.
It is space devoid of anything except empty space itself.
If you empty a volume of all its molecules, atoms and particles, and if you enclose this volume,
say, in a hermetic box at the absolute zero temperature in order to empty it further also of any thermal
radiation, recall the blocked dead body cavity.
And if you isolate this box from any external influence or perturbation from the environment, then
we think of this volume as being perfectly empty by definition.
However, from a quantum perspective, things are not as simple as that, even if we pump out all the
air until the last particle and molecule and atom and obtain perfect isolation at chilling temperatures,
according to quantum mechanics, that space is still not really empty and the temperature still also
not exactly absolute zero, as we see.
Then later, we got a feeling in the preceding section of some phenomenon which have implicitly already
suggested this.
We studied Heisenberg's uncertainty principle, the time, energy, uncertainty, quantum tunneling
and the quantum tunneling effect.
We saw that the energy of a particle in a box that is, for example, inside a potential such as, for
example, the protons and neutrons inside the nucleus is in a ground state energy, and that cannot
be reduced to zero and at the same time cannot be quantified.
Exactly.
And and this ground state energy can lead to effects such as radioactive decay at random times.
All this together suggests as odd, it might seem that there is always a small amount of energy literally
appearing from nothing, so to speak, and therefore it can do something that it classically would not
be allowed to do.
What then about the idea that if particles can be in a superposition of states, why not also in superposition
of different energy states from these considerations?
One can shift the reasoning also onto empty space or what is believed to be classically empty.
Are we speaking, therefore, from of energy, from nothing, could that be true?
Frequently you will see among textbooks of physicists talking about to popular science magazines, to
a popular audience, to non-academic audiences, and approach to this question framed by invocation
of Heisenberg's principle or the energy time of uncertainty.
Sometimes, especially in the popular literature literature, one reads about the time uncertainty as
a direct consequence of energy fluctuations in empty space.
In this scenario, one thinks of empty space filled filled with a continuous fluctuating quantum energy
form, which is allowed to violate for very short time intervals energy conservation, according to
the time energy uncertainty.
If we conceive of sufficiently small time lapses, Delta T, so goes the theory, the energy is indeterminate
according to the time energy relation and at Mach microscopic scales for space intervals not larger
than light can travel in the time interval.
That is Delta X equals three times Delta T recall that we can imagine then energy popping into existence
for a very brief moment and then.
Popping out of existing existence, disappearing again in some sense.
This might sound very convincing and could be taken as a first approach of understanding the nature
of empty space in quantum physics, after all, where does that Delta E in the time, energy uncertainty
relation come from?
We expressly excluded any classical measurement error due to due to imperfect measurement devices.
This little bit of energy that comes into or goes out of existence really remains something quite mysterious.
If we recall that the energy conservation law is one of the most universally proven and accepted facts
of classical physics, according to this law.
Energy can be transformed but not destroyed.
It can be transformed from heat into mechanical energy, chemical into electrical energy and so on.
That can never be created or destroyed.
Does quantum physics violate the principle of an energy conservation, a possible way out of this is
to admit that the energy conservation law can be violated for an extremely short time.
We have seen that a typical atomic transition lasts for about fractions of billions of a second and
nuclear reactions are ever even shorter.
But then the energy budget must be, so to speak, restored after the phenomenon has occurred.
In other words, in quantum mechanics, tiny bits of energy are allowed to pop in and out of nothing,
nothingness if they exist only for a time lapse, which is almost an instant.
One also finds professional physicists talking somewhat improperly about borrowed energy from the vacuum.
Calling it zero point energy, this is how the law of energy conservation can be saved on the classical
and microscopic level as we perceive.
A world in which the shortest time of which we can be aware of is no shorter than, say, a tenth of
a second or so.
While we can view things happening intuitively, according to this model, a more rigorous analysis
shows that this.
Extra energy is conceived of as a ground state of the vacuum and is obtained by the NONCOMMUTATIVE properties
of observables, not through the time, energy, uncertainty relation, because as we pointed out in
one of the previous sections, there is no time.
Operator contrary to the position and momentum operators, zero point energy is not a consequence of
time, energy, uncertainty, relation for the same.
For this reason, the vacuum state is considered the lowest possible quantum state of empty space and
is obtained in quantum field theory.
That is an extension of classical quantum mechanics by a mathematical procedure which goes by the name
of second quantization.
The first quantization is the one we introduced in this course here the interaction of operators for
observables and which replaced the classical notion of Newtonian mechanics that the dynamic variables
of the Newtonian mechanics.
The second quantization replaces the concept of the particle with a field motion and works with special
relativity, even though still not general relativity.
A field in the quantum field theory is defined in space and time.
So as the second quantization and in quantum field theory replace, you make a secondary placement where
instead of the particle, you replace the particle with a field motion and which is defined in spacetime.
And it does so by expanding the operators again as itself as a sum of more fundamental operators called
the annihilation or creation apparatus.
That is by a mathematical procedure which quantities every point in space and time in terms of harmonic
oscillators and which is able to correctly describe special relativity, relativistic quantum mechanical
phenomena.
Quantum field theory is a mathematical, quite complicated theory, which, however, describes successively
the standard model of particle physics.
It is not necessary to describe it here in detail, since from a foundational point of view, it does
not really introduce many novelties.
However, the important point to keep in mind is that that it is from this that physicists obtain from
their calculations and non-zero ground state energy vacuum and which can be imagined somewhat inappropriately
as a quantum form in which every spacetime point fluctuates.
In this interpretation, we do not perceive these fluctuations at large spatial scales because they
become relevant only for small microscopic regions and also for extremely small time intervals.
Just as a small rippling on the surface of an apparently perfectly flat object might be invisible to
the eye.
If you were to look at it through a microscope, you might discover it to be very rough instead, just
to use this analogy.
In fact, if we continued zooming into space regions as small as ten to the power minus 34 meter, which
is an incredibly small scale, it is a number which is written as a zero, followed by other 33 zeros
after the comma until you reach the first non-zero digit meters.
And this is called the so-called Planck scale, because Planck was the first to describe it.
And empty space, empty space is considered, therefore, to be full of these energy fluctuations.
This is often depicted as a spacetime form, as sort of white noise pervading empty space at very small
scales as shown in the in the last magnification of the right hand side of this graph here.
This.
Noisy objects here and which is somehow pictorially artistically depicted also here.
Is this an animated Jeff?
At these spatial scales, space is no longer empty, but a place where any sort of extremely fast bubbling,
energetic even's in extremely short time spends Arcore about ten to the minus forty four seconds.
This is called the Planck Time.
And do your homework and see how short this time is.
And there's nothing that we can do that we know of that is has such a short time.
And even also the most precise clocks are far, far from being able to measure such short time intervals.
But that's what the calculations tell us.
And so the energy state of the vacuum in quantum mechanics is not zero zero point energy, despite what
the somewhat misleading name might suggest, is not a point at which that the energy is zero, but rather
a non-zero energy ground state of the vacuum.
A word of caution about the concept of quantum fluctuation, you might frequently hear the general public
and often often also physicists, too, speaking of these quantum fluctuations of the vacuum at small
scales we have done this year to pictorially because this is Smeets, our intuition.
It's easy to speak in these terms.
It is an interpretation that might be useful for an intuitive understanding, but it isn't entirely
correct, a more rigorous way to interpret the quantum mechanical vacuum state is not that of describing
it with fluctuating energy states, but rather with quantum with a quantum superposition.
Also, atomic energy states can be in superposition.
The excited and non excited energy state of an atom can be realized at the same time.
We know how particles can be also in two places at the same time.
That's what we have learned with quantum superposition principle.
The same holds for the spin and their magnetic momentum.
We saw that measuring the spin on one along one axis renders undetermined the spin value plus or minus
on the other axis because the observables of the spin, the spin observers do not commute.
And we said that they are in a superposition state.
We didn't speak of fluctuating spins that flip the flip from one value to the other, up or down spin,
plus or minus the same holds also for molecules or any other objects.
There are no limits in principle where quantum superposition holds and when a measurement or interaction
occurs, only one of the possible states is observed.
And a state projection, of course, but nothing is fluctuating there.
This is so important to keep in mind.
So this is the same fits for the energy of the vacuum.
It can be in superposition of possible energy states and only one of the these actualise is when observed
or as we shall see now, when particles interact.
So in this sense, there are no fluctuations of states, despite what the common language and common
discourse between physicists and also in the popular media, you will hear that.
But this is there is a superposition of states and the subsequent realization of one of the potential
evens by a measurement.
Which is a very different thing.
At the microscopic level and for a very short time intervals, empty space is in a superposition of
energy states.
On the other hand, what really fluctuates are the outcomes we obtain at each measurement.
Statistically, if we perform several extremely fast measurements looking at empty space, we would
obtain a set of fluctuating, fluctuating data.
But again, this has nothing to do with the imperfections of the measurement device, and it is nothing
to do with fluctuations.
It is an intrinsic property of the quantum.
Universe, so to speak, this is another example of how in quantum physics, we must be very careful
with the counterfactual definiteness reasoning which must be applied with great care.
The fact that measurement results fluctuate does not imply that the system we are measuring fluctuates
in time from one state to another.
And this leads us to the next step, that of the conception of virtual particles in this scenario,
one also conceives of the existence of virtual particles filling empty space and popping in and out
of existence.
In fact, if empty space can be filled for short times with small microscopic regions of non-zero energy
states, we can also think of the vacuum as being filled with particles, having that energy as photons
or even with the mass.
According to the famous Einstein mass energy relation, which states and equivalence between mass and
energy as equal EMC squared photons or even massive particles like electrons or protons are allowed
to come into the exist into existence from empty space and almost instantly disappear.
This might seem a bit too far fetched of an idea, this idea that of particles pop into existence out
of nothing, just out of the blue.
So but the fact is, once accepted, the whole quantum field theory resulting from this assumption is
just that theory which turned out to be the right the right one, and which was tested experimentally
many times to clarify the meaning of virtual particles and quantum mechanics.
Think of two approaching particles as two electrons in this image.
This is one of the typical diagrams called also Feynman diagrams, diagrams that we will discuss in
more detail later.
It is a different way of conceiving of force fields no longer as continuous regions surrounding a particle
or a body like the gravitational or electric field of classical physics, but as particles that exchange
other force particles.
This is one of the main aspects that distinguish quantum field theory from a classical one feels are
quantized here when the electrons approach and come sufficiently close to each other.
The reason there is this region of space that separates them.
The so-called vertex region is so small that due to the vacuum energy, a certain amount of energy becomes
available, so to speak, though only for a very short period of time.
During this brief time interval, zero point energy manifests in form of a virtual particle here, a
virtual photon in this case here in this diagram.
But it can be also massive particles with the mass and which is exchanged between the two electron electrons,
resulting in an impulse exchange debating them from each other.
They have the same charge and therefore must repel each other.
That is, we are talking about a scattering process here all the time.
Energy uncertainty tells us that the distance between the two electrons must be small enough that the
photon can travel from one electron to the other in a shorter time than that allowed by the time and
energy uncertainty.
Then at the end of this force exchange process, the photon must be absorbed.
That is, it ceases to exist.
Virtual particles can never be observed directly and do not exist in the same way that other particles
do, we might say that they pop in and out of existence for that short time period in and in that tiny
space volume to allow for force and momentum, exchange for the scattering process to occur.
However, they cannot be compared to other real particles that can be absorbed directly.
That is why, after all, they are called virtual particles and they are not real in your usual sense.
Things a bit more intricate, and we will see this in more detail when we talk about Fischman path integrals
and diagrams.
However, for the moment, for the moment, this might be an image that can help our intuitive understanding
of things.
Another question might be to ask ourselves if these visualisations represent a real process.
Do virtual particles really exist out there, as in the film and diagrams?
The fact is that Feynman's approach was extraordinarily successful in describing particle physics with
the theory that today goes by the name of the standard model of particle physics based on five months
quantum electrodynamics, so-called QED, and was confirmed by a large number of experiments in particles
in particle accelerators.
There can be no doubt that the theory is such mathematically, abstractly is correct, and it calculates
correctly the phenomenon we observe.
However, we must be aware of the fact that Feynman diagrams represent only an intuitive tool for our
limited human mind to depict interactions, the complexity of which escapes our cognitive abilities,
they are an attempt to force into the rhythm of the microcosm our classical representation of objects
in the area of the macrocosm.
Another proof regarding how a quantum.
Vacuum can manifest its quantum superposition state, which reveals itself as ripples of energy over
a large space volume, comes paradoxically from a completely different region, one that is the opposite
of the microscopic world, namely from cosmology.
We have already hinted at this in the lecture on the black body radiation, but it is worth to mention
what this image is thought to represent.
According to modern Big Bang theories, all the matter and energy of the universe was once concentrated
in such a tiny volume that quantum mechanical effects were very relevant during its first instance of
birth.
Even if all the matter were distributed in a perfectly and ideally homogeneous manner, the quantum
effects of the vacuum must have caused tiny in homogeneity that should be observable in today's microwave
cosmic background radiation or shortly GNB.
So these vacuum fluctuations or quantum effects?
Caused tiny ripples in the GMB radiation, even though these ripples of income in homogeneity of the
cosmic background are very tiny.
In fact, they are only if they depart from the cosmic background, two point seven Kelvin temperature
of only a few thousands of degrees.
These ripples could be confirmed by measurements from satellites in space.
The cosmic microwave background radiation is one of the many examples one can make to show how the idea
of the quantum vacuum is not just a fancy theoretical speculation, but the reality of the physical
world.
However, particle physicist instead take as proof of the existence of the zero point quantum vacuum,
vacuum energy and the existence of virtual particles, an experiment performed by the Dutch physicist
Henrik Kazimir.
In the Casimir effect, the ground state of the quaintest electromagnetic field, that is the electromagnetic
vacuum energy, which can also be seen as mediated by virtual photons popping in and out of existence,
is thought to be responsible for the attraction between two almost perfectly flat, parallel and uncharged
metal plates distanced from each other by only a few micrometers.
According to the standard interpretation, the Kazimir forces arise because the ground state of the
vacuum between the plates will have different electromagnetic modal configurations than that of the
outside vacuum as its ground states are constrained by the two metal walls, sort of the modes we considered
in the black book black body cavity.
This implies that the literal photons inside the plates have a different energy than those outside it.
This leads to a difference in the energy density between the two spatial regions inside and outside
the plates and produces a force pulling the plates together.
And this is called the Kazimir Force.
The variation of energy in space does always produce a force.
So you should remember this, that every time that there is some differential in the energy, it means
a variation of energy in space or time.
Then in some way or another, a force arises.
This effect has been repeatedly tested with increasing precision since then, confirming the theory
that predicted it predicted it.
Therefore, one he several physicists referring to the Casimir effect as evidence for its zero point
energy that is a form of virtual particles supposedly filling empty space.
However, some physicists do not share this view, despite the popularity of this interpretation.
In fact, Kazimir himself originally described the same phenomenon as an effect of Wonderfalls forces.
Wonder why advance forces are intermolecular forces responsible for the attractive or repulsive forces
between polarizer molecules at short distances.
The Kazimir forces can be described as an interaction between the materials.
The reason why in quantum physics that zero point energy interpretation prevailed is that with this
theory and for elementary quantum particles or structures one encounters, usually the mathematical
calculations are easier to perform.
This is not because it adds something new to the physical picture.
In fact, in chemistry and biology, scientists prefer to speak of.
But there was forces at any rate.
However, one interprets sarcasm, enforces the most amazing and unexpected display of this effect in
nature comes from the animal kingdom, from the tiny and elegant lizards, which are the geckos.
Most members of the species are quite skillful at climbing walls or any kind of flat surface, like
for, for instance, a vertical glass window.
This ability comes from their abrasive toe pads, which enable attractive vanderveldt forces between
the so-called Sitti structures.
That is the stiff hair like or dislike structures and the surface.
These bristles are approximately five micrometers in diameter.
Just to make a comparison, the smallest human human hair is about 15 to 20 micrometers.
The use of the small one attraction forces require very large surface areas.
Every square millimeter of geko foot pad contains about 14000 hair like Sitti.
The end of each sector consists of approximately 3000 spottily, that is structures, structures shaped
like an isosceles triangle.
The Spatola are approximately 200 nanometres on one side and 10 to 30 nanometres on the other two sides.
These structures are invisible because they are below the wavelength of visible light.
So you can't see them even not with some optical microscope.
You need an electron microscope or some other microscope that does not work with light.
And this plethora of Spatola all act like tiny Kazimi Kazimir plates, which together sum up to an additive
force allowing the gecko to climb walls without further aid.
I wanted to conclude this lecture with this example just to show how the zero point energy determines
our existence in so many different contexts.