Before we proceed to the famous phenomenon of quantum entanglement to better understand what it is about,
we must introduce the concept of quantum indistinguishable indistinguishably, which emerges from quantum
scattering processes.
This is another weird thing about quantum physics, quantum indistinguishable.
It might at first look like the classical indistinguishably of two objects having the same physical
properties between which one can not distinguish, say, for instance, two billiard balls or a collection
of billiard balls.
For our everyday experience, every physical object is distinguishable, even inside a collection made
of many objects having exactly the same properties.
When in our human, macroscopic classical world we want to maintain two equal objects as distinguishable,
say, subjected to a complicated shuffling process that is difficult to keep track of.
We can do this simply by labelling them, say, with A and B.
For example, just take two billiard balls and lather them with A and B, then start the process scattering
process or whatever, for example, shake them inside a box and later look at where one or the other
object is simply by reading the labels.
One might argue that a pending LaBelle's is already differentiating between two unequal objects, then
alternatively, we can follow their path separately, looking at where one or the other object moves
in space and time, even without labels.
If this will be too fast and complicated, we can eventually record it using a video camera.
And for example, consider two billiard balls having exactly the same properties mass size, color,
etc. and colliding.
This is our everyday experience with the classical mechanical scattering process, which involves hard
and well-defined objects, just chunks of metal.
This collision process could be elastic or inelastic, but that fact is not so relevant to our considerations
here.
In any case, you can follow the path of the particles, billiard balls or the objects or whatever,
and you can find again.
Their whereabouts, if they interact, we can nevertheless distinguish one from the other, for example,
by letting them collide head on, as in this figure here and then observing that the first is scattered
in one direction, while the second is scattered in the other direction.
We can track that trajectory simply by looking down at the billiard table from above.
In the classical view, we determine during the process whether billiard a went along with eye and billiard
B went along path jay or whether to the contrary billiard ball B went along path a while A went along
path J.
It is as simple as that.
So in this Newtonian mechanical perspective, nothing is fundamentally indistinguishable, and if it
is, that is only because we have not looked at the process carefully enough.
In principle, distinguished ability is always possible.
Classical in this distinguished ability is only a notion which reflects our ignorance.
It is not an ontological statement.
If, however, we would like to know what happens during a scattering process between two elementary
particles, say two electrons, we must consider the collision as not like that of two billiard balls
coming in direct contact with each other.
That is touching, so to speak, and repelling each other.
Rather, we must take into account the fact that an electric field surrounds them, a field of forces
surrounds them.
In this case, because the electrons have the same negative electric charge with the same polarity,
they repel each other for tiny charged particles, the scattering never involves direct contact between
particles.
The repulsion, of course, because of the mutual interaction of the extended electric field of both
Therefore, one must refine the previous mechanical scattering model with this that kind of scattering
model that we see in this figure here.
The trajectories are the aviation path caused by the mutual interaction of the two electric fields without
the particle having any direct contact, at least not in the classical mechanical sense of which we
are accustomed to think of.
Keep in mind that also at the macroscopic scale, there is no such thing as direct contact as naively
suggested by the previous figure.
Every interaction, contact and scattering between material bodies, including that of billiard balls,
is microscopically an electric repulsion between the electron clouds of the atoms and the molecules
of which a body is made of.
In our everyday lives, we perceive the existence of hard objects like stones.
But this hardness boils down to microscopic interactions between particles of the kind of that are depicted
in this figure here.
So in this conception and which is a modern quantum field conception, we must think particles as just
mathematical abstractions point like mathematical points that are surrounded, however, by a force
field and are not.
Marbles or billiard balls, as we would like to believe.
Therefore, as to what regard distinguish ability, things turn out to be a bit more complicated here,
you may have already seen a rather naive assumption we use for the case of the billiard balls to observe
the collision process.
We must have some light in the room which the billiard balls reflect to obtain an image that tells us
which.
Of the two objects went along with Speth at human macroscopic scales, the reflection of photons on
billiard balls is such a tiny perturbation of the system that we can consider it completely negligible
for two electrons.
However, we cannot forget this little photonic perturbation.
Here we are in the domain of Heisenberg's microscope, in the microscopic riam of elementary particles,
the light photons would scatter the particles.
We would like to distinguish and would disturb their trajectories, rendering impossible the kind of
classical distinction process mentioned above that.
Something we have already seen somehow with the microscopic with the microscope, Heisenberg.
However, as we have already mentioned, the perturbation argument is not entirely correct, or at least
it isn't the whole story that Heisenberg's uncertainty principle is telling us.
As we will see later, indeed, it is possible to build experimental set ups in which the perturbation
is negligible or even absent, and nevertheless, the uncertainty principle remains unavoidable.
Let us therefore consider a more quantum mechanical version of the whole problem.
Imagine again that the two identical particles say two electrons, A and B, scattered with each other.
Add in this figure and thinking of it.
As with packets, we do not shine in this case, any light particles on them to try to track their whereabouts,
to find out for their path.
So there is no perturbation in the first place and we have not to bother and think about perturbation
the role of the observer or things like that.
Rather, we attempt to distinguish the two cases by detecting one of the particles at a detector here.
We label it with detector deep.
Now, with our Aristotelian intuition, we might think again, like in the previous case of two possible
cases, the two particles scattering at Angel Teeter or at ENGELKE by minus Teater or which means 180
degrees minus detail.
We are using radion units from zero to two pi instead of angle grades from zero degrees to 360 degrees.
We might then be tempted to bring the the ever closer, closer and closer to the small interaction region
called the collision vertex and observe which particle took Path I and which particle took path.
Jay.
Unfortunately, Heisenberg's uncertainty principle prevents us from doing so.
We are not allowed to know what is going on inside this collision vertex as this is a tiny interaction
region where quantum uncertainty reigns.
And because we do not know what happens inside this interaction space, we can't tell which of the two
particles, A or B, hits the detector.
The.
However, all this is not just like shaking a couple of billiard balls in a black box into which we
can't look, as we have clarified while discussing Heisenberg's uncertainty, quantum tunneling and
the superposition principles here, we are not allowed to think of the two particles in this region
as having exact position and momentum at all, not even in principle.
Here, the wavy nature of particles, which must be thought of as to wave packets are no longer negligible,
or, if you prefer, the algebraic standpoint, the computational relations for the position and momentum
operators can no longer be ignored.
The trajectories inside this region cannot be definite particle path, as our naive intuition would
like to consider them.
There is no such thing as a point like particle falling, a precise trajectory, eye or trajectory.
J There are wave packets and which help us to find for the position of particles only by a probabilistic
notion, by taking the model square of that with wavefunction.
What instead becomes important at this case are the diffraction and interference phenomenon between
wave packets.
In quantum mechanics, a certain process is at the fraction of probability waves.
Therefore, we must resort instead to a description with a wave function.
In fact, physicists say that the wave functions overlap and interfere at the collision vertex.
It is this that makes particles indistinguishable in quantum mechanics, not the idea that the observation
as such perturbs the system.
They are not distinguishable, not even in principle.
It is a form of indistinguishable that again, we must carefully avoid confusing with any classical
form of indistinguishable particles are not distinguishable because of our ingredients, say, because
we could not look at the collision vertex with sufficient accuracy here, that they are indistinguishable
because we must understand the two particles as to wave packet's merging and becoming one and only one
whole system without distinctive subparts in the interaction region and which is described by one single
wave function.
Therefore, this figure represents a still somewhat naive understanding of what is really going on in
this area and the previous figures, we considered only a special case Catherine.
And Peter, if, however, we consider all the possible angles occurring in scattering process, we
must build a wavefunction that also has an angular dependence on Twitter that is at the collision vertex.
The two particles must diffract each other in all directions, like a plane wave diffract at an object's
boundaries.
In fact, to simplify the scattering process, consider one of the two interacting particles as a point
like center of wave diffraction, the DOT and this figure here and which is addressed, fixed in the
laboratory reference system.
And consider the other particle as an incoming wave packet.
If we consider the waste packet of the incident particle to be large relative to this point, like the
fraction center it can be represented as an incident plane with.
Then once the plane wave hits the localized region, the local target region, the point like particle,
the resulting wave function involves a superposition of in an incident plane wave and a scattered spherical
wave.
From the perspective of the other particle, the same can be said.
It also will see, so to speak, and incoming front and diffract it into a position of an incoming plane
wave and an outgoing spherical probability wave.
The resultant wave is a more or less complicated outgoing spherical probability wave expanding from
the interaction center towards the outside world until a similar scattering and interaction process,
of course, again with another particle.
This is still a somewhat simplified description of the real gathering process, because in reality,
both particles should be represented as incoming and outgoing wavefront as Anthe Rutherford first introduced
to examine the atomic nucleus, bombarding it with radioactive particles.
And then there is also an even more relativistic correct calculation in.
Which involves a complicated hire or the fireman path, integral formulation and diagrams of quantum
field theory, which we will mention briefly again later.
However, at this point, this should give you at least a qualitative understanding of what quantum
physics interactions and scattering of particles are about, it is about the probability of finding
the scattered particle, which is no longer given by the well-defined path of tiny particles or fields.
But it is determined by a spherical, outwardly expanding probability wave.
Let us see how the situation can be displayed in its temporal evolution and with the detector induced
quantum state reduction first and this figure figure A, we have the two incident wave packets of each
particle capital letter A and B that before any mutual interaction are still distinguishable in space,
what makes them distinguishable are simply their different spatial coordinates, not any inherent property
as they are to electrons.
Exactly.
With exactly the same properties.
In figure B, this figure represents the short time interval during which the two particles interact
here, the two way functions overlap and the individual spatial coordinates of the individual particles
are no longer distinguishable.
The two probability waves deflect and interfere with each other in complicated processes.
The scattering process is represented graphically, simply by a little bubble, so to speak, in space,
which hides the details of the interaction in quantum field theory.
This is also represented by the exchange of virtual particles, as we have discussed earlier, and we
will also see more about that later.
After the collision, what emerges are still not too nicely separated wife packets, but as spherically
shaped shell wavefunction as inefficacy, it is still a two dimensional view for realistic calculations
in three dimensions.
We have catering's in all directions, not only around Circler region, but we have in that case, a
spherical surface.
This would imply another angle dependent's, a solid angle distribution and whose amplitude is modulated
by a function that has an angular dependence in spherical coordinates.
It is also called the scattering amplitude.
However, for the sake of simplicity, we depict here only the two dimensional section.
This spherical probability wave, which is proportional to the square models of the scattering amplitude,
as you know, spreads into outer space according to the particle speed, as long as there is no detection
or any other interaction with other particles.
This spherical wave precedes undisturbed, outwards into space, and no logical inference is allowed
about the particles as distinct entities.
This is because at this stage of the process, there is still nothing like to point like particles,
nor even such a thing as to wave packet's, only a spherical probability wave expanding outwards in
space.
Only when the spherical envelope reaches the detector and when the detector clicks with the wavefunction
function collapse back again, with the spatial localization to a nicely defined spot inside the detector,
say, on a pixel of a camera, and which tells us that they're what we call a particle, must have interacted
with it.
And that is what is depicted in the art, as we shall see later.
And to express it in a more rigorous quantum parlance, decoherence takes place, which causes the projection
of the state vector onto one of its eigenvectors and the respective eigenvalues.
At the same time, the other particle which emerged along the other path must be visualized again with
a wave packet travelling in the opposite direction.
At this point, we no longer have any means of establishing which of the two particles made that detector
click, this is for the simple reason that what emerges from the collision vertex is nothing like two
particles particles at all in the first place, but only one single and Unicol wavefunction spreading
out and waiting to be detected only when the detector clicks with the whole suffer.
This whole quantum hole, so to speak, suffer quantum decoherence and reveal itself again as what we
call two particles, the one showing up at the detector itself and the other possibly even light years
away on the opposite path where we could eventually place another detector as well.
This is something which hints at a holistic interpretation of reality, as everything in physical reality
can be considered a large number of particles continuously interacting with each other.
In addition, those particles that interact that here and now form for a very short instant, an entirely
new system which has no parts as long as the next interaction, of course, and where this whole again
collapses instantly into its particle nature.
And then again forms another indivisible whole system with the new particles they encountered on their
path.
This newly formed wave function temporarily evolves, spreading out until it finds other particles with
which to interact and thereby collapsing again.
And so on and so on.
Another typical place to consider this could be the undistinguishable electrons inside the atoms, we
already saw that modern atomic theory no longer conceives of electrons as moving along precise and well-defined
orbits.
But they must be modelled with the with orbitals.
We should not consider orbitals and therefore atoms as objects made up like a puzzle structure, as
this would again imply that the current constituent puzzle pieces can, in principle, indistinguishable
from each other.
You must instead conceive of atoms as a single complicated function, a probability wave that represents
a whole a single unit which manifests itself in form of distinguishing different parts that electrons,
protons and neutrons only at the instant of interaction or observation, but not before that.
If all this really is about quantum holism or is an abstraction that emerges from the mathematical formalism,
is a question difficult to answer.
This representation of a scattering process and the quantum indistinguishable of parts of a quantum
system is indeed a holistic representation.
But fact is that at the end of the story, we always and only observe point like interactions in space
and time as the objects that we are observing.
Would be particles, what we are observing behaves like particles, never spherical wavefunction spreading
out.
So this is a subtle matter of debate and philosophical speculation, however.
Going on with our lectures, we will see how this holistic aspect of reality will emerge over and over
again.
He instead to go somewhat further in our understanding about the shattering process and the indistinguishably,
let us proceed with a bit more formal analysis.
We have seen how particles can be in a spin up, down and spin down.
State opposition states in superposition for a single particle are described by a state vector as a
some of the possible igan states.
As, for instance, here in our case, all good, all spin up and spin down states for a single particle.
What about the quantum superposition state of more than one particle?
The answer is that the Wetterstedt of a system of many particles is no longer described by the Sun,
but by the product of the possible Agon states of each particle scattering processes lend themselves
quite well to illustrate this.
In fact, in a similar manner, we can also describe a superposition of scattering states.
To see this, let us return to the previous picture of the scattering process that we already saw and.
Consider here particle a capital letter, A which follows Path I as being instead a cat I.
And the other particle be following path, Jay, as being in State B kept Jay.
Then we can represent the state vector of this system as the product of two states, namely as a kid,
I times B kid J.
The same goes for the other situation in which particle a follow CSJ, therefore, as being in state
A cat and particle B, which goes a long path I as being in state B cat I.
Then the overall state vector is again here and for the second case, a cat, Jay.
Times be good, I.
However, this cannot be the whole story, because if the quantum state algebra, this quantum state
algebra would be correct, this would still allow us for distinguish ability as even for identical particles,
the formalism this formalism distinguishes between the two cases in which particle went along, which
path.
In this sort of quantum algebra, a classical indistinguishable is still encoded.
A real quantum indistinguishably must also take into account the superposition principle.
Hence we must allow also for our intuitive understanding of the quite disturbing eventuality that each
particle travels both paths at the same time.
That is the state vector of the whole system must describe both particles travelling both pairs at the
same time, and this is given by the sum of subtraction.
And then we will see now later why subtraction.
But for now, just take it as it is.
This is given by the sum or subtraction of the two possible states.
Above that is, we have the state vector overall state vector capsid, which is equal one over square
root, two times the sum of the two states that we have described here above.
The square root of two is simply a normalization factor that stands for the probability coefficient
that we or you should know now by what what it really means in which the model of square represents
the probability of getting the first or second case.
That is that model, the square of one of the square root, two is equal, one half that is zero point
five, which means 50 percent, 50 50 percent chance of getting the first or second case each.
Now the plus minus sign corresponds to two different particles, a positive, symmetric way function
for bosons.
As we know, particles like photons with internal spin as equals zero, one, two, etc. and a negative
anti-Semitic wave function for fermions particles like electrons, protons and neutrons, etc. with
half odd integrase spin as equal one half, three 1/2, five five and so on.
We will discuss the meaning of the negative sign later in detail.
Please accept this little ambiguity for now.
So we have taken two steps, first, we are presenting a system of two particles, taking one or the
other path as a product of their respective states.
Then we added or subtracted the two states as a superposition superposition of two possible scattering
states.
That is, the particles taking both one and the other path at the same time.
By doing so, any notion of distinguished ability fades away.
Not only is it impossible to distinguish the two electrons after the scattering process, but the question
no longer makes sense if both electrons travel along both pairs.
At the same time, the single electron measured at Detector D is simply another entity that emerges
from the collision vertex, which is a spherical wave function that we have seen.
What detector the measures is a particle which of course preserves exactly the same properties of the
incident once, but can no longer be considered either B or B.
Or maybe A and B are the same very same Electrum again, quantum physics reminds us that any logical
reintroduction implies counterfactual definiteness is a bad habit of the human mind.
This is the real quantum indistinguishably.
It is just another form of quantum superposition.
One might ask at this point, why should we take the above mentioned second step, that of superposition
of certain states seriously?
After all, it offends our common sense to consider that particles travel distinct paths at the same
time.
Can we not simply skip that passage and ride the state vector as the two products separately and be
happy with that?
The proof that nature instead insists on taking superposition seriously is an expert in experimental
proof, you will be able to predict the correct scattering rate as well as the probabilities of how
the electrons are deflected over all the possible angles, data and that are empirically observed with
laboratory experiments.
If and only if the calculations are done with a wave functions, that takes the two products states
as a sum or subtraction of each other.
Any other description from mathematical description fails to describe reality.
In conclusion, generally speaking, what we must bear in mind is that indistinguishably does not emerge
because of our ignorance or the imprecision of the measurement devices.
Nature insists on the indistinguishable quantum version at all costs.
There is no perturbation effect or measurement in precision preventing us from distinguishing between
them.
Rather, quantum indistinguishable emerges due to the superposition of possibilities.
The simple fact is that there is nothing to distinguish and there are no differentiated parts to differentiate
in the first place.
This is the base, the conceptual foundation of a closely related phenomenon that has puzzled and that
continues to puzzle so many bright minds and upon which we will now build in the coming lecture's the
phenomenon of quantum entanglement.