In quantum mechanics, one is usually more concerned with single particles or many particle systems
than with extended bodies.
So what about elementary particles like electrons?
When it comes to the notion of the angular momentum, it is not difficult to extend the notion of the
orbital angular momentum of a material particle having a mass like, for example, the electron.
In the case we conceived of it in Bors atomic model as a particle flying around the atoms nucleus.
This conception is dubious enough because we should actually have in mind the atomic orbital model not.
Borse atomic model, but the orbital atomic model that in any event, so far, this picture of reality,
that, of course, atomic model to some degree still works.
And here the orbital angular momentum of the electron can be defined as the product of its mass times
velocity at which we imagine, believe it to orbit the nucleus times, the orbital distance from it
according to the formula we have defined in the previous lecture.
However, this is where the analogies to the classical world, uh, finish, they they end here.
In fact, what about the spin that is what in quantum mechanics is called the the intrinsic angular
momentum of a particle rotating around an axis that goes through its center, as in the case of the
earth?
The problem is this analogy analogy breaks down because we think of so-called elementary particles as
a mathematical point like objects.
Thus, it becomes somewhat unclear what the spin of a points structure should mean at all.
What is a point that spins around itself into it intuitively and even mathematically, it doesn't make
much sense.
So either electrons are not point like.
But no experiment has so far revealed any internal structure, at least not as of 2019, where I'm speaking
now.
Or we must consider the notion of the spin of particles in quantum mechanics as something that must
not be viewed as we do intuitively.
The macroscopic scale.
For this reason, in quantum mechanics, one more loosely speaks of particles carrying an intrinsic
momentum, intrinsic angular momentum or spin simply without suggesting literally the the image of a
spinning sphere, as in a classical theory.
And yet we know that even elementary particles, such electrons or protons and neutrons, well, protons
and neutrons are not really elementary because we know nowadays they are composed of so-called quarks.
But in any event, that also these particles have a tiny but measurable spin.
Can the spin of a particle as tiny as an electron be measured?
The answer is positive and even surprising.
It is possible to measure and associate a spin to elementary particles.
The interesting point is that as we saw energy being quantized in quantum mechanics, the spin also
of particles, this also turns out to be quantized.
Nature allows only discrete, not continuous quantities of intrinsic angular momentum spin.
Therefore, in quantum mechanics is a quantized dynamical property of all particles.
How physicists reached this conclusion will be elucidated now.
We will explain this now with the so-called Stand Galla experiment.
It is easier to understand how this works if we first introduce some basics and anticipate some of the
results.
For elementary particles, the spin has only two possible values if we take as a convention the vertical
axis being the upward set axis, we can show experimentally that, say, an electron or a photon has
only two possible spins along that axis, a fixed specific amount of spin up or spin down states.
We will never, ever observe the electron having other amounts of spin and being directed towards another
direction in between.
Or if you would like to stick to the classical intuitive understanding, elementary particles rotate
clockwise or counterclockwise around an axis, always with the same angular frequency.
What must be added to this picture is the fact that we should not forget that several particles like
electrons and protons are electrical, electrically charged particles.
They have an electric charge where neutrons and not the fact as such.
But internally, the internal structure of a neutron is made of quarks again, and these have an electric
charge.
So from the outside, a neutron is seen as not being electric charge.
But this is another matter.
Let's focus on electrons.
Eventually they all possess an equal.
So electrons, protons possess an equal tiny charge, which is also taken as the elementary electric
charge leveled with a small letter E which amounts to E equals one point six to a six seven two times
the power of ten to the minus 19 km where the letter C stands in fact for Coulomb and is the standard
international unit for the electric charge.
This is the number E should not be confused with the oil, a number, which is a completely different
thing, of course, at this elementary charge.
Is an extremely small charge.
For example, a typical household electric device, say, is more lamp that works with an electric current
of one ampere.
Ampere stands for a.
For the unit of the intensity of an electric current that you probably have also noticed in your household
as something of the order of six times.
Ten to the power, 18, 18, which means six quintillion electrons, six billions of billions of electrons
per second flowing through this, the secretary of the small lamp.
So you can imagine that the charge and the end of an electron and the electron itself is an extremely
small object.
However, despite its small value, the electric charge of an electron can be measured using relatively
simple consideration and consideration and experimental arrangements.
Well, not so simple, but they believe this could be already measured in the beginning of the first
of the last half of the last century.
In fact, electrically charged particles produce an electric field in the surrounding space around an
electric charge, their electric field.
Otherwise the definition you would not have an electric charge.
And this interacts with other charged particles or also with other magnetic fields.
These electric fees are graphically shown with the field lines in case of a positive charge.
Uh, the lines are directed outwards and for negative charges inward.
The stronger a field is in general and is, the denser the field lines are represented also for other
types of fields like the magnetic fields, the gravitational field or whatever.
Just to add another example, similarly for the interaction of two positive electric charges, one obtains
pictures like these.
These are, however, only pictorial representations.
You must not consider these lines as being really existing objects out there.
They just represent the intensity and of the field and the direction in which the forces of these fields
act.
They are, however, in any case and aid for our mind to represent the strength and structure of a field.
Electric charges are also themselves the source of magnetic fields.
In fact, it is a simple law of nature that every moving electrically electrically charged particle
always produces a corresponding magnetic field.
For example, also a cable through which an electric current that is electrons flow will also manifest
a magnetic field.
This is always true and is fundamental, a fundamental physics.
Wherever electric particles travel throughout space or through a conductor, there will always produce
a magnetic field.
The construction of electromagnets, for example, relies on this principle, a loop of electric current,
a bar magnet, an electron, a molecule, and the planet always have magnetic moments as they all contain
in one form or another, circulating electric charges.
This is something we imagine also happening with the earth's magnetic field, the earth's interior must
contain a huge amount of magma, of hot currents, of magma fluid, which is electrically charge charged,
and therefore its movement around the earth's axis causes the earth, the Earth's magnetic field, to
build up.
However, the interesting point is that also the opposite is true as well, wherever a magnetic field
changes in time.
An electric field will appear.
This is what we already hinted at when discussing the nature of light as an oscillating electromagnetic
field, and it is at the foundation of Maxwell's equations.
Therefore, an electrically charged spinning object is also expected to display some magnetic field
as it is a charge in rotation rotational movement.
And because only to fix spin states are possible, the result is also that only two magnetic moments
with the magnetic field lines directed in one or the other direction, according to the Spin's, particle
orientations are possible.
The magnetic moment of a magnet is a physical quantity that tells us how strong the magnet is, more
precisely, it is a vector quantity which determines the talk to you that the magnet here, the particle
will experience in the presence of another external external magnetic field.
Say some produced in the laboratory with electromagnets, and if we can measure a particles magnetic
moment, we can be sure that it possesses a spin and therefore we can evaluate its magnitude.
Of course, because the spins of quantum objects are quantized, the same must hold for its magnetic
moment.
Electrons and protons therefore have only two magnetic moments due to their corresponding spin as equals
plus minus half one half, which are accordingly labelled as M.
S equals plus minus one half Y half integers and not plus minus one.
Well, we will see this later.
This approach, this is precisely this is an experimental approach is precisely what in 1922, the German
physicists, Otterton and Walter Gaila were able to demonstrate.
In particular, they showed they showed this, first of all, on Adams and Silver items, but this can
be used also to this day that they are technique, I mean, can be used also to show the existence of
intrinsic angular momentum, of momentum of single particles.
This D'Angela experimental set up from now on, let's just label it as G.
O or S.G. experimental setup was constructed as follows.
They sent a beam of silver atoms and they said.
Previously prepared in a source of head at hot items, in that case using a furnace and column column
into the beam of outcoming atoms by Haslet sending it through and in homogeneous magnetic field created
by magnets that had a special form and orientation of the sort seen in this figure here.
The choice of silver atoms was due only to practical considerations, silver atoms are easier to handle
and have only one unpaired electron and the outer atomic shell.
Why the electric and magnetic properties due to all the other inert electrons are canceled out mutually
will explain this further when we are dealing with the Pauli exclusion principle.
Therefore, the measurement of the magnetic momentum of a solar silver atom reduces to that of one single
outer shell electron.
Now, when an atom or a particle or whatever object that has a magnetic moment is sent through an inner
homogeneous magnetic field, it experiences a force and therefore is deviated in one or the other direction,
relatively relative to the poles of the magnet.
That is relative to the direction of the magnetic lines and according to the orientation of its own
magnetic moment.
It is quite intuitive to understand why this must be so, just as a couple of magnets must repel or
attract each other.
The stangl, the the S.G. magnet and the particles or atoms which are also tiny magnets, must mutually
repel or attract each other according to the directions of their magnetic polarities.
That is, if one sends the particle, which has a spin up, say, preconvention relative to the Z axis
through the S.G. device with its north south magnetic poles directed along the that Z axis, it will
be activated upwards.
On the other hand, the spin down particle will be activated downwards.
And if the magnetic moment of quantum particles is indeed quantized, in only two possible states,
we will observe only an up or down deviation in the S.G. experiment, which must therefore create two
distinct spots on a detecting screen that the particles strike.
Otherwise, if the magnetic moment were continuous, that is would not be a discrete physical property
of particles, the deviation of the S.G. magnets induced on the particles would also be continuous,
producing instead a continuous line on the detection screen, as expected by classical physics.
This was a conceptually simple method of showing that atoms and particles indeed possess a quantized,
intrinsic, angular momentum, Stan and Galla observed.
Always and only the binary possibility, the binary outcome, not the expected classical results.
What they showed with this is that the quantization quantization of spin is not simply speculation,
but an established experimental fact.
Before we discuss other interesting discoveries one can make with devices, let us fix this first result
with the Dirac Dirac notation we discussed in the lecture on the State Vector's.
The two possible spin states could be labeled with the cat plus and minus symbols.
If not further specified, it is convention usually to assume that these states are measured against
whatever axis or the standard that axis of the laboratory.
Just for the record, keep in mind that in the literature, you might find also other symbolic conventions
like these, the plus minus get as that or Keat as that semicolon plus minus and so on, especially
when it is important to distinguish them from the other X and Y directions.
And we will use the first ones, however, because there is no universal standard convention, uh,
in this regard, please learn to be flexible enough to read the symbols that we use interchangeably
according to the context and the literature.
The important point in any in any in any case is to keep in mind here is that the Tangela experiments
can easily show that the quantize character of the spin does not change, even with a change in the
direction along which the measurement is taken.
Whatever axis you choose in a three dimensional space, you will always get as a result of the measurement,
a spin up or spin down.
That means a.
Kate, plus or minus particle, as strange as that might seem.
The fact is, in the quantum world, there is no longer such a thing that can mostly worry its spinning
direction, interpretation of speed as we imagine it, for example, with spinning top or spinning billiard
balls.
Instead, we have a quantum objects, which once a direction has been chosen.
Can acquire or display only two possible spin states along that direction.
Nothing in between.
In physics, one formalizes this with an elegant formalism that puts all three Igen states, that is
the spin state vector's along a preferred that axis into one single description.
For the sake of simplicity, let us restrict ourselves to the that explain.
Define a spin up and spin down along that that axis, as with the formalism reminiscent of vectors on
a Cartesian Cartesian two dimensional plane as this one here where you have a dead cat plus equals a
vector or.
Something that we will now call Spiner one zero and that Kate minus equals at zero zero one Spiner.
These are not really vectors and that's why they are called Spinous to distinguish them from the usual
Cartesian vectors.
In fact, note that these are not the Baz's vectors of the Cartesian two dimensional plane you learned
about in school, or as we have also repeated for you, for you in the appendix videos of this course,
because these were one zero for the Baz's vector along the x axis and zero one for the basis vector
along the Y axis here.
Instead, we are not speaking about a geometrical directions in space, but these represent directional
spin directions in not a.
Geometrics, three dimensional space that we live in with, we perceive with our senses, but so to
speak, in a spin Spiner space.
We are going to see later that spiders are quite different objects, therefore, and require a different
treatment, that is to obey, they they obey other algebraic rules.
The amount of intrinsic angular momentum or the spin can also be measured, one can relate it to the
separation of the two spots on on the Stanzler screen.
And it turns out that it is equal to plus minus each bar, half each bar being as usual, Planck's constant
divided by two times pi.
In fact, Planck's constant has the dimension of an angular momentum, by the way, if you consider
that it is a value of the order of 10 to the PI, to the power minus 34 jowls per second.
When we recall what we have said in the section on the black body radiation, we realize that it is
an incredibly small but not zero amount of angular momentum.
We have also seen how if a measurement on a particle takes place, this is represented in mathematical
abstract terms by operators that we called observables acting in a Hilbert space on vector states.
That is the case in the direct notation.
On that occasion, we describe the measurement process by means of an operator Igen equation with an
eigenvalue representing the measurement, the measured quantity.
Go back to the previous one of the previous lecture.
We have clarified this because the spin is a physical, measurable quantity it must have associated.
Operator in this case it is the spin operator.
Capital Letter S.
A spin operator is also defined along one of the three dimensions of space, again, usually that directed
along that axis as as Seth.
And however, there is no reason to restrict ourselves to the measurement along one axis, three possible
spinning directions exist in a three dimensional space.
We can therefore also consider measuring the spin of an object along the other two X or Y spinning axis
with associated operators as X and as Y, respectively.
Recall that in quantum mechanics, every act of measurement represented by an operator, the observable,
the observable of the physical property measured acts on a wave function or state vector and delivers
the eigenvalue the quantity one measures through the eigenvalue equation translated in.
To the spin, uh, turns, if the particle is in an Afghan state, the same state which will always
turn out to be even after repeated measurements, the spin operator is acting on the eigenvector of
an electron in a spin up or spin down.
Can state therefore get plus minus the spin measurement of the Gallet device, for example, for all
three axis is represented, as we have shown here.
The measurement process along the Z axis is written with the operator as.
As that.
These operators that acting on the eigenvector that got caught plus and resulting in a plus h ba eigenvalue.
The result of the measurement times that that get plus a vector itself, the same holds for the particles
in spin down state both but with the opposite side and so on, measuring making the same measurement
along the X axis is the same thing in principle only.
You have to remember that you are using another observable, namely you are making a different measurement
than that.
But you're making a measurement with the operator as X onto a particle along X direction.
Therefore you're presented with operator s X acting on the X Kate plus minus vector, which again as
being an eigenvalue equation, results in plus minus eight times the same vector and so on also for
the x y axis and so on.
However, generally speaking, the outcome is not known, and the probability of finding the particle
in one or the other state is usually 50 percent if it is not in an angry state.
We have learned that the probability of finding the system in a specific igan state is encoded in the
in the coefficients of the state vector, which contains all the possible states in which a system can
be.
Therefore, the spin state of an electron is written.
The spin the vector state is a quantum vector state of.
Particle like an electron in a specific, non determined spin state, which is not the Igan State spin
state, is written as follows.
And here we omit for sake of simplicity the axis level.
Just imagine them according to one direction.
Um.
Let us closely inspect the state vector equation, the cat.
Sigh is not or not necessarily the state in which the particle is observed to be.
It is a state before the measurement and comprises all possible outcomes, we might say that it describes
a potentiality of realization.
Because for an elementary particle like an electron, only two possible measurement outcomes exist for
the spin states, namely the net plus or minus I can state and because there is no reason to believe
that nature prefers one over the other.
And in fact, measurements show that it is not.
It is so they must both have an equal 50 percent probability of being measured.
That is of being realized.
It is an easy fact that one can determine by measuring how intense the spots on the screen are.
So this probability is encoded in the coefficients one over the square to, in fact recall that the
squared models of these coefficients furnishes us with the probability of observing one or the other
associated igan states realized by the measurement process here, the model square of one over the square
of two is just one half, which means zero point five and which means 50 percent each.
These coefficients, that is the model, the square of one over the square root of two.
They are summed up together because before the measurement, we do not know which of the two will emerge.
And in quantum mechanics, you imagine that both.
State's.
Are in potential of existence, so to speak, and to be realized, but only at a time where you make
your measurement, that is only at the time where you apply your operator?
S capital letter s on the eigenvector get BPCI.
In general, the igan equation for spin, for the spin of the quantum system can be described by this
more general agan equation.
These equations with its coefficients are one of the most typical equations you will find in most every
treatise on quantum physics and will follow us throughout this journey in one form or another.
So with these fundamentals in mind, we can discuss other revealing experiments that one can perform
with Stan Galla devices.