Let us connect the concept of quantum indistinguishably to another important concept, that of quantum
entanglement.
If you got the message about why and how quantum in this indistinguishably is very different from our
ordinary conception of indistinguishably, it should no longer be difficult to grasp the quantum entanglement
concept.
We will now see how this sort of quantum wholeness, so to speak, not only is a phenomenon that stands
behind indistinguishable particles, but in quantum mechanics, is a more and much more general and
fundamental fact also between very different particles, like the entanglement between an electron and
a positron or a proton and a neutron, or as is usually done experimentally nowadays, simply between
two photons, but with different polarizations for for example.
So what is quantum entanglement, the term was coined by Schrodinger from the German word for shrunken
and physically quantum entanglement can be realized when particles such as electrons of protons, photons
or even larger molecules interact with each other, quantum mechanically at a macroscopic scale and
then separate after separation.
As long as they do not interact with another particle, atom or molecule or whatever in the in the environment,
they remain entangled, just as we saw in the case of the quantum scattering and the spherical probability
wave.
As long as one of the electrons does not interact with the detector, the compound system is not described,
by the way, function of two particles or even not by two wave packets, but by a unique, undifferentiated
hole expanding into space or simply state, which one must describe as undefined.
A first possible example of producing entangled photons is that obtained by using radioactive materials,
consider a radioactive source of decaying atoms.
We know that this is a typical quantum process.
Recall what we have learned on quantum tunneling.
A typical radioactive decay is the better, the better.
Plus, decay whereby a proton in an atomic nucleus decays into a neutron atom.
It's a positron that is the anti electron with positive charge and opposite spin.
And this happens together with the emission of other particles.
That is an electron neutrino and eventually gamma rays.
And these gamma rays are up for our interests of our interest because these are then entangled protons.
The neutron remains inside the atomic nucleus and converts the atom into another element, one with
a proton, less with atomic number decreased by one.
The positron instead is ejected out of the atomic nuclear nucleus.
And unless the environment is not a perfect vacuum, it will soon find on its way another electron and
annihilate by emitting two photons in the opposite directions and with opposite circular polarizations
that is recall with opposite Telecity.
That is opposite spins as shown in this figure here.
This is just an example with photons as photons are usually the most manageable objects in the laboratory.
That's why we make this example.
Many other possible sources of entangled particles are possible.
So let us keep general and think of particles, photons or material particles generally, and which
are emitted by radioactive decay or by a source, just generally a source from which they had a common
origin.
They are emitted in exactly the opposite directions because the origin originating, decaying in single
particles is addressed in the in the laboratory.
And therefore, because of the universal law of conservation of moment and energy, they must fly in
directions which can sell their momenta.
For the same reason, the two particles must also have opposite spins as the original particle from
which they originated had opposite intrinsic angular momentum, which sums up to zero momentum.
Therefore, the two spins must cancel each other as well.
That is, if one particle shows up with spin up, we can be sure that the other will show up with pin
down.
And the opposite is true as well.
This means that we have only to look at one political spin to know that the other particle will have
the opposite spin.
Moreover, think of them moving apart to a great distance, say, giving them sufficient time to eventually
separate separate light years away in space and through to another star system before you make a measurement
on it on one of the two particles.
I mean, during this time, we must also imagine them having along their path no further interaction
with anything else in the environment.
The particles must maintain their state of coherence.
Now, as we are accustomed to doing in this series of lectures, let us first take the naive classical
understanding and then shift shift to the correct quantum description of what is going on.
Naively, before any measurement, we might imagine the system to be in one or the other state, that
is that one of the following two possible cases as first case, let's call it case one, we have a particle
will spin up travelling towards the left side.
Let's level it direction A on the opposite side in direction B, we have the particle with spin down.
Then in the exact same fashion as we did in the section on Quantum in this indistinguishably, we can
represent the system using a product state vector.
A couple times we get minus.
The other possible case case, too, is that in which we have the particle on the left with spin down
and the particle flying in direction, B will spin up, as in this figure here.
Therefore, the state better must be written as a kid, minus times we get plus.
We can have only these two cases, we can't get both particles to spin up or spin now, they must be
a. correlated, as is customary to say.
But we get to know this only after the measurement, before the measurement, we don't know which of
the two possible outcomes will be measured.
However, again, this is a naive classical understanding of things, why the point is that the two
states, those of course, one or two are not what quantum mechanics considered the state of the system
during flight time because the particles would in principle still be distinguishable.
In quantum mechanics, indistinguishably is much more radical, as we know, than the classical one,
and extends into all quantum phenomenon, not just scattering processes.
Therefore, the same must fit in the present situation as well.
We are not allowed to distinguish between which particle goes left or right.
Therefore, we are not allowed to distinguish between which has been up or spin down, as we would like
to imagine naively with case one or two.
Therefore, this must be expressed again in the algebraic expression of quantum mechanics when we have
still not measured the system during flight time, quantum mechanics forces us to take the superposition
principle seriously.
That is, it wants us to consider the position of both possible cases.
Case one and case two.
Which means which means the situation somehow depicted in this figure here where we see.
The two particles spinning at the same time with two over superposition, angular momentum, intrinsic
angular momentum.
Therefore, the full quantum state side of the system must be described by a single state vector of
particles with opposite spins and zero total angular momentum, also called a singlet state, which
is a sum of the two possible igan states of the two particles and which is given here.
And this expression should not be new to not do you know, you should be able to decipher it.
And also the plus minus sign, again, representing the case of bosun's or fermions, respectively,
as we shall see better later.
So according to quantum mechanics, during flight, we have neither case one or no case two, but both
at the same time and we again face the logical end case.
However, when the measurement is performed, then the state vector is projected onto one of the two
eigenvectors that is a cat plus B minus.
That is a particle on the left appears with spin up and the particle on the right appears with spin
down or the opposite case.
A cat minus B plus the particle on the left appears to spin down and the particle on the right appears
to spin up.
Each case was 50 percent pure chance.
And that's obviously the one over square root two, as you know, that in this figure levels A and B
were omitted at the end on the third figure to highlight indistinguishably little.
Once a measurement of the spin occurs.
On one particle, one speaks of the state vector reduction, a state vector reduction takes place if
we measure speed up state of the for the party on the left side, we already know that even without
measuring it, the other particle must possess a spin down state and vice versa.
Of course, that is the act of measurement collapses, the entangled system of particles either in state
of case one or case two.
But before that, both exist and I realized.
The point is, according to quantum mechanics, the state reduction of WAF can function Kaleck collapse,
if you prefer, happens instantly.
The state vector projection is an instantaneous process.
This, at least, is something that has been questioned more recently.
But.
Take it as such for it for the moment, the click of a detector which determines the state of one particle
automatically and instantly, also determines the opposite state of the other particle.
Again, it is not that we discover the state of a particle, which we did not know because of our ignorance
or the lack of precise measurement, the two particles are in superposition state as long as no measurement
takes place, only once the detector clicks with the measurement, so to speak, define the state of
one particle.
And therefore, all of the other also only then.
Will the other particles opposite state become defined to.
A common fallacy is that to believe that the fact that the outcome is unpredictable and that we always
have 50 percent.
Pure chance of measuring one or the other state implies that we are allowed to believe somehow that
the particles intrinsically possess one or the other state when the source has emitted them at a time
of emission.
According to this view, based on a counterfactual definiteness reasoning, some very complicated process
is going on at the source emission of the particle whereby we must describe their states with statistical
probabilities.
But they nevertheless supposedly possess a definite and correlated state that we will know only by measuring
it.
I hope, however, that you now understand and know and got it why this can't be the case.
This would contradict quantum indistinguishably lity, which we know correctly predicts scattering processes
as measured in the laboratory.
Once we accept that went to equal quantum objects, interact with each other, they can no longer be
considered separate systems made of two or more particles.
They, so to speak, melt into one single quantum entity, a sort of unique, undifferentiated whole.
Moreover, if that would be true, this idea of particles which are already a. correlated intrinsically
at the instant of creation in their source, this idea would imply that quantum mechanics must be a
theory with hidden variables.
We will see, however, that the idea of quantum theory, of quantum theory containing hidden variables
is possible only in the context of a theory which must accept nonlocal, instantaneous interactions.
We must conclude that in the case of the entangled particles, their respective state is decided only
at the time of measurement, not before that instant.
This justifies also the name cingulate as we are dealing with something which is supposed to comprise
two particles and yet behaves as a single entity.
Entanglement given by this equation can be thought of as the realization of a physical state that sums
up the principle of superposition, the principle of indistinguishably and the uncertainty principle.
At this point, you may already have sensed the big problem with that if the instantaneous state reduction
that defines the state of one particle must instantly determine that of the other particle as well at
the time of measurement, even if they are light years apart, this seems to imply a sort of faster
than light interaction.
Keeping entangled particles far apart is experimentally a very difficult thing to do, as any particle
will soon react with another particle in the environment causing therefore decoherence.
Conceptually, however, it is a perfectly legitimate physical, physical possibility.
Let us take, for instance, the case of a particle measured on Earth and another entangled one which
has reached another stellar system, say, on the Alpha Centauri star system, which is about four point
three light years away.
This instantaneous state reduction or collapse of the wavefunction, if you prefer to call it that,
implies that the the the measurement on Earth immediately determines the state of the particle on Alpha
Centauri.
The question then is how can a particle on Alpha Centauri immediately know the state of the measured
particle on Earth?
Taking its opposite spin state?
A light signal from Earth to Alpha Centauri needs four point three years to transmit this information.
Obviously, there is a huge problem with all of this because Einstein's theory of relativity strictly
forbids faster than light interactions.
That the speed of light is a physical limit which cannot be overcome is a fact that several experiments
have confirmed.
If that were not the case, the entire theory of relativity itself will be fast, too, because it forbids
it, though it has been tested and shown to be corrected over and over again throughout over a century
of experimental evidence.
You can understand the kind of feeling this must have instilled in Einstein, the father of the theory
of relativity.
Einstein called that strange behavior of entangled particles as a spooky action at a distance.
He obviously could not accept that at all.
There seems to be a conflict here between quantum mechanics and relativity.
Even after his debate with Moore, Einstein could not accept the state of affairs, at least not in
this form.
He was very puzzled by the idea that in the quantum reality, things could be entangled seemingly through
faster than light correlation and was totally random outcomes.
As the theory describes, he simply could not believe all that to be true somewhere.
Somehow there is something that is escaping our understanding.
This was at least his idea, his point of view.
He continued pursuing the idea that all this must be only a provisional description of reality, which,
however, cannot be complete and must lead to contradictions.
Einstein was looking for something which shows us that we must return to a classical view.
And indeed, at some point it seemed that Einstein, together with a few of his colleagues, found a
powerful argument again in the form of a thought experiment, which seemed to be a final proof that
Heisenberg's uncertainty principle somehow indirectly implies faster than light interaction among quantum
entangled particles.
And this could not be compatible with relativity.
This is a famous paper which describes what nowadays is known as the EPR paradox and which will be the
topic of the next lecture.