The EPR paradox in its original form with the opposition momentum measurement is technically, in practical
terms, quite difficult to make.
For a long time, it remained a thought experiment that was impossible to realize.
Originally, David Boehme tried to translate the paradox into its spin analog.
He proposed using electron positron pairs that are created by a decay process, more precisely by a
neutral Pye meson subatomic particle that can be produced in an accelerated accelerator collision process
and that quickly decays in an electron and positron pair.
And these have a total of zero angular momentum that is zero total spin.
So in principle, these could be used as entangled particles to make experiments on most of modern experiments.
Testing quantum mechanics rely on the measurement of the computational relation of the spin absorbers,
not the position of many observers.
In fact, throughout the modern literature, you will usually usually find the EPR experiment explains
straight away with the particles intrinsic angular momentum.
And the advent of modern technologies, modern electronics, lasers, quantum electro optics, devices
and so on made this feasible.
It is possible nowadays it's relatively easy to measure the spins and properties of photons much better
than single material particles such as positrons, electrons or other particles.
Lasers are technically an easier and cheaper option, and modern experiments use photons.
That is, particles with integrase spin.
To produce the entangled photons, physicists, physicists, use laser beams that excite the atoms of
some particular substance, usually so-called beta barium borate, crystal or shortly also be OK in
such a way that it really emits the absorbed energy in the form of entangled photons.
And obviously with some special polarizations or Telecity that is spin.
We will go deeper into the subject of entangled photons in some later lecture.
For now, just keep in mind that in the case of an entangled system, you will never know which of the
two particles will show up with up and down spin or four photons, the left or right handed polarization.
So for this reason, with these facts in mind, it is worthwhile to reformulate the EPA paradox in its
modern version.
To visualize Epirus thought, experiment with the spin operators, suppose the two entangled particles
with opposite spins and zero total angular momentum that is in a single state have been produced by
some source and fly apart in opposite directions towards two observers.
Let us call them Alice and Bob, like a..
Figure here.
If the two particles are entangled and if Alice will measure, say, along an axis that spin up, that
is that.
Plus she can send this information to Bob who without any measurement on his particle, will deduce
that it must be in the opposite spin state, namely that that mean minus state.
Now, Bob can instead measure along a different axis, for example, the x axis.
Let's say that Bob gets a.
XCAP plus spin state, then he returned the favor and sends a message about his particle's state to
Ellis.
Therefore, she concludes that the state of her article along the X axis should be X minus again without
having performed such a measurement on her particle.
At this point, both might believe that they have the full set of information about the two observables
for their own particles, the spin along the X, Y and Z axis, but having measured only one of them
on each particle while reducing the other indirectly after being informed through some standard communication
channel.
Ellis particle must be therefore in that court plus X minus state, while Bob's particle must be in
that minus X, Kate plus state, and neither of them had to measure the particles along both axis.
However, we know this is not allowed according to standard quantum mechanics, which imposes the commutation
relations on the spin operators and which tells us that it is strictly forbidden to obtain both spin
states at once because that commutator of as that and as X is not equal zero.
So the question is, do the two particles really possess objectively these spin's properties along the
two axis?
At the same time, we already saw with the Tangela experiment that this is highly doubtful, to say
the least, in any event.
The problem with all this here is that if we want to answer this question, we will have to measure
Alize particle along the X axis, while Bob will also have to make a second measurement along the Z
axis to be certain to be sure that this is the case.
We know that the laws of quantum mechanics, strictly forbidden, forbids this and we know how it would
end.
If they did so, it would again render indeterminate as Z for Ellis' and as X for Bob.
The only thing that is sure is that a strong correlation exists between the two particles.
So if you understood the paradox in its original version with the opposition momentum, the termination
of a couple of particles, then you should be able to recognize it in this more modern version, which
resorts to the spin of particles, both versions are substantially equivalent in the sense that they
seem to imply that the cumulate computation relations of quantum mechanics could in principle be violated.
And if so, this would vindicate Einstein's strong conviction that quantum mechanics must somehow be
an incomplete theory and that a more refined and better theory must exist possible based on hidden variables
which would explain things better without paradoxes.
However, historically, it should be noted that when this interesting paper of Epper appeared, it
did not attract attention at all, even though one of its authors, Einstein, was a globally known
high ranking physicist.
Nevertheless, almost nobody cited the article, and it remained completely ignored for almost three
decades, 30 years.
This was quite characteristic of the spirit of the time during which almost all physicists embraced
the Copenhagen interpretation and stopped thinking about these more foundational and philosophical aspects
of quantum mechanics.
Action was considered an old man who would had his moments in the sun, but who was no longer able to
produce new and original contributions.
Yet history has shown that Epper were probably too far ahead of their time.
The fact that the technology required to perform epis experiments or like was still not mature was not
the only reason why they were ignored.
It was an evolutionary necessity, so to speak.
The culture of the time and minds were not ready to focus on the subjects.
This changed in the late 1960s with Bell's theorem.
But before we analyze EPA's legacy in the light of bells in intellectual achievement as a logical continuation
of the spirit of investigations into the foundations of quantum mechanics, let us first focus on the
other issue that of the faster than light transmissions.