We are now ready to understand the famous, perhaps too famous Schrodinger's cat paradox, we saw that
superposition in the strange world of quantum mechanics implies that objects can be in more than one
igan state simultaneously, for example, in several places at the same time, or spin clockwise and
anticlockwise at the same time and so on.
If you assume that you understand all this, then, as American physicist Richard Feynman used to say,
you probably don't understand quantum mechanics.
This totally paradoxical universe confused and eluded any reasonable explanation by the best minds of
the 20th century.
Until his last days, Einstein could not accept the state of affairs.
This prompted other great scientists, such as the Austrian physicist Erwin Schrodinger, to propose
a slightly eccentric thought experiment.
Schrödinger wondered about the weirdness of quantum superposition principle.
The question to which he was seeking an answer was why do we not observe objects in the macroscopic
world in our everyday experience in superposition states?
It seems that these strange and counterintuitive properties, such as superposition, emerge only in
the tiny microscopic Riham.
And yet there is no reason nor any known physical law that forbids the same effects from taking place,
all also on larger scales for objects as big as a human body or a cat, for instance.
To better visualize the problem, Schrodinger uses the cat experiment to illustrate why there is no
reason to believe that superposition should not hold equally well for cats as it does for elementary
particles.
Here reasoned as follows.
Imagine a cat in a closed box having no interaction with the outside world in the same box is a radioactive
substance which at any instant can emit a particle due to atomic decay.
We have learned that radioactive decays are also strictly probabilistic phenomena.
It is quantum tunneling that determines the decay of an atom's nucleus.
Because this quantum tunneling is a purely quantum phenomenon, you can't ever determine when an element
decays before you observe it.
Just as you can't say that a particle has a specific position or spin state before you measure its position
or intrinsic angular momentum.
So does the element which finds itself in a position of decayed and not decayed state.
However, from the statistical point of view, we can predict how much average time is needed until
half the atoms to decay, the so-called radioactive half half life time.
This tells us the probability that the case will take place and how many decays on average will take
place.
After some time, however, we will never, ever be able to predict when exactly the single decay event
will take place.
Schrodinger, therefore imagined imagined that the box also contains a Geiger counter that is an electronic
device that clicks when it detects a particle emission.
When it measures a decay, it releases a hammer that breaks an ample containing poison, and then this
kills the cat.
However, this will occur only if that one atom of the of the radioactive substance decays.
Because because this is a perfectly quantum probabilistic event, as long as we do not open the box,
the wavefunction still has not collapsed according to the rules of quantum mechanics, the cat radioactive
material, the hammer, the mple containing poison must be in a superposition state.
This means that the apple is broken and intact.
At the same time, the hammer is released and not released at the same time, and therefore the cat
must be dead and alive at the same time.
Only when we open the box to check on the health conditions of the animal.
Does the wavefunction collapse, which means we make the observation, the act of measurement and project
the cat in either the dead or alive I state.
However, before the instant of observation, quantum physics seems to suggest to us that the cat indeed
exists in a sort of ambiguous reality in which it is alive and dead at the same time.
This is substantially the famous Schrodinger paradox, cat paradox.
In fact, as in the case of the single elementary particle such as an electron, we know that it can
be in a coherent state as long as it does not undergo a measurement which projects it on one of its
definite Igen states.
Quantum coherent means that the face relation between the way functions describing all the constituents
does not change.
Recall the characterisation of quantum coherence and decoherence.
We applied for the phase, the relation between the two light beams in young stubbles lit experiment
there.
Also, the presence or non presence of the interference term that causes the appearance or disappearance
of the interference fringes is per definition, the coherence or coherence between the two beams.
If interference exists, the single photon is supposed to go through both slits.
That is, the photon is in a coherent state which we interpret interpret as being in a superposition
state and we observe the fringes.
If no if no interference is present, we imagine the photon going through only one slit, which means
it is in a decoherence state.
There is no superposition and we observe the bell shaped probability distribution intensity curve.
The same can be extended to a large number of particles, describing them as waves, the debris meter
wave relation, and it's that interfere or not that is are in a coherent or coherent state.
The same applies to quantum cats, as long as a measurement does not take place, the cat finds itself
in the superposition dead and alive at once.
This is formalized in quantum mechanics with the state's vector as a sum of the representing Keat states
over the normalization coefficients or whose models square gives a 50 percent chance for one or the
other case happening, as you already know by now.
And then once the measurement has taken place, the system here, the cat in its superposition state
is projected onto one or the other axis representing a definite igan state, dead or alive.
Note how all this is nothing else than the restatement of the measurement postulate and the linearity
of Schrodinger's equation before opening the box, the cat is in a linear superposition of two possible
igan states as necessarily prescribed by Schrodinger's equation linearity.
And once we open the box, we project the cat into one of the two igan states, which will be confirmed
by any other subsequent observation as stated by the measurement postulate.
With this thought experiment, Schrodinger could show that it is not at all clear why we do not observe
superposition states in the macro world as the strange possibility certainly exists in the microscopic
quantum world, at least in principle.
At this experimental set up shows that it is possible to have quantum superposition states for beings
or objects the size of a cat.
Did therefore, Schrodinger find a loophole in the this concept, if quantum mechanics is true, we
should be able, at least in principle, to perform such an experiment and put cats in the dead alive
superposition state.
However, the fact is, in our everyday life experience, nobody has observed this.
So we're aware it is a mistake.
Are we perhaps working with some false assumptions?
Showing us at deer is only a thought experiment experiment which can can't really be performed not so
much because of technical or, if you will, ethical limitations, but because one must first open the
box to see in which state the cat is.
However, this is an act of measurement which will cause the collapse of the state production.
Therefore, we will never be able to determine how the cat felt before the box was opened.
Even if the cat survives, it can tell us because cats don't speak.
So guess what we are.
Why not use a human instead of cat?
And after the experiment, ask him or her, him or her, how it feels to be in a dead and alive superposition.
Would this be an alternative idea?
Fortunately, we do not have to go that far to understand why there is no real paradox.
However, we must first elucidate one of the most frequent misconceptions about quantum physics, one
which is frequently stirred up by many popular media, as well as by some physicists who are eager to
sell their books and which is a supposed role of the observer in quantum physics.
This little phrase, the role of the observer in quantum physics, has caused many misunderstandings.
This is a famous YouTube video you might recognize, which suggests that there is a role of a conscious
observer, the eye blinking eye here in determining where the electron or the photon or whatever kind
of particle in the double slit experiment will place itself on which interference?
Fringe fringe on the detector screen.
It suggests more or less implicitly, the role of our mind or of our consciousness in the experiment.
This is quite incorrect.
What is meant by an observer in quantum physics?
This is a question that we have to pose ourselves.
What do we really mean by the word measurement in quantum physics and how should we distinguish it from
the word observer?
After all, an observer measures.
Doesn't it?
It is necessary to be cautious about not playing with words which might lead accidentally or intentionally
to several misunderstandings and measurement in physics is, after all, nothing but a physical information
readout, which we usually but not always, as we shall see later, is carried out via an interaction
with the system to be measured.
Is it really necessary that a measurement be linked to the observation of a conscious being like a scientist,
a human being looking up and something, this is a question.
The point is, and this will turn out to be of paramount importance when we when people speak about
the consciousness of the observer influencing the outcome of a quantum experiment.
The point is that in quantum physics, the notion of observation and measurement must be intended as
being extended to any possible interaction of one system onto another.
No physicist in their laboratory has ever directly observed a quantum phenomenon at the microscopic
scale, every measurement is not an observation.
They perform with their senses of sight or touch, but a read out performed nowadays, usually by electronic
devices like photo dietze cameras with laser beams.
The wavefunction collapse or state reduction is caused by a measurement that these devices make, and
that has no contact whatsoever with the Observer's mind or consciousness.
Should we consider the photo diode a conscious observer?
Can a thermal meter measuring the temperature in a room be regarded as an observer that observes observe
temperature willingly and consciously?
That is, if we would also like to think of an act of measurement performed by a mechanical apparatus
as an observation, it must be clear that the mind or consciousness of the scientist using using these
devices to perform the experiment has nothing to do with what causes the outcome of the measurement.
Therefore, this is unfortunately widespread myth of the supposed role of the human mind or consciousness
in quantum physics is only a misconception that has no scientific or logical ground.
Observing in the quantum mechanical sense also means the interaction of one particle onto another.
There is no logical reason to believe that the interaction between two particles or between a molecule
and an electron is physically and conceptually different from the interaction between two physical objects,
one which is the object to be observed and the other of which is the measurement device.
Measurement is always about the interaction or information transfer transfer between two material objects
in quantum physics by an act of observation.
We must not intend a conscious being, our only macroscopic device, but must also include the interaction
of a particle with another particle.
Every single interaction of the gazillions of particles in our environment is according to quantum physics
measurements, so to speak.
Also, a single particle onto another can cause the entire wave function that describes the entire system
as a unique quantum hole in a quantum coherence state to collapse instantly into a system of its separate
constituents that is into the single particles which make up the cat, the hammer and all the objects
surrounding it.
That is what is called quantum decoherence, quantum decoherence.
But the number of molecules which make up the air, the cat's body and the surrounding objects is huge
is of the order of Avogadro's number.
And that is no Avogadro's is abogado number is a number which tells us how many constituents a mole
of a substance is made of.
For instance, for instance, a mole of water is about eight point three grams.
And Avogadro's a number of states that this these eight point three grams of water are made up of six,
about six point zero to two times ten to the power 23 parts.
This is an extremely huge number, and if you think about about how these constituents interact with
each other continuously due only to the thermo motion of the atoms and molecules, the so-called Brownian
motion, the Brownian motion that this was also described by Einstein, it becomes clear that the decoherence
time must be vanishingly small only because of the interaction with the thermal excitations in the environment.
This is called thermal decoherence.
So does this imply that a single particle could collapse the way function of a quantum system?
Well, things are a bit trickier than that.
It turns out that it is only part of the truth.
It's sold the Schrodinger's cat paradox only partially.
In fact, in quantum mechanics, several particles can also be entangled and in quantum position while
they are interacting with other particles.
But this does not necessarily immediately lead to what we imagine as the wavefunction collapse.
In fact, to have Schrodinger's cat experiments succeed.
Not only must the tiny atom be in superposition state, that is, we can describe the state function
BPCI as a some decade plus not decayed, but this is a superposition must also hold, at least for a
short time, for all the atoms and molecules of which the Geiger counters, the hammer and the poison,
the walls of the box, the air molecules in the box, and especially all the cells of the body of the
cat are made, and with them all being quantum entangled in a unique and coherent whole.
All the particles, quantum decoherence still does not completely explain quantum collapse.
It tells us only that few particles get entangled with many.
But that does not alone avoid the possibility to observe entangled objects also at microscopic scales.
Still, after the opening of the box, we should see the cat in a superposition state entangled with
all the particles or the environment, even though only four eventually only maybe a very short time.
And since nobody has ever observed such a weird thing, there is a conceptual disconnect between what
quantum mechanics suggests microscopically and what we experience macroscopically.
Furthermore, since quantum decoherence does not really explain quantum collapse, not how this seems
to imply that for macroscopic objects as we are, the linearity of Schrodinger's equation is violated
and the measurement postulate remains unexplained.
That's why it has been framed axiomatically as a postulate.
After all, at what scale?
Why and how does nature prevent linear superposition to take place, which it allows for at microscopic
scales?
And what is the true cause of the quantum collapse?
This disconnect is an aspect of what is called the measurement of the quantum measurement problem,
and in the next lecture, we will see how the Schrodinger's cat paradox can find only a partial solution
with what is called the quantum decoherence process and in what sense.
The measurement problem still leaves some questions open until the until today.