This is a somewhat more advanced lecture on decoherence and quantum decoherence and the measurement
problem where we will make a bit more use of a formal mathematical description, if you feel uncomfortable
with this, you can eventually also skip this single lecture.
It is not so necessary for the understanding of the content or content of the following lectures.
However, it is important for those who will eventually continue to research further in the quantum
philosophical domain, so to speak, especially that concerned with the measurement measurement problem.
It is also interesting in the sense that it represents still an unsolved problem of quantum physics,
at least from the more philosophical foundational point of view, and might be useful if you intend
to go deeper and dig further later on in dealing with these typical modern issues that philosophers
of science are busy, busy with.
In a in a previous lecture, we saw how the Schrodinger's cat paradox shows a paradoxical aspect of
quantum mechanics.
There is no reason to believe that quantum superposition, as every quantum law should hold only in
the macroscopic area of particle physics.
Quantum mechanics should hold equally well also at the scales of humans, cats or coins.
Therefore, it is somehow a mystery why we can't set cats or any other living beings or objects into
a life and death quantum superposition or coin in their heads and tails superposition at the same time,
just as we can do with the particles spin.
For example, we advance the hypothesis that somehow this could be explained away with the mutual interaction
of particles of the cat's body scattering with the particles of the cat's body itself and all those
of the environment that could cause the immediate collapse of the wavefunction and which is called also
the decoherence process.
Let us look at this somewhat further, in fact, that this state of affairs cannot be taken so, so
lightly in quantum mechanics is illustrated through an application of Dirac's notation to a system that
transitions from a superposition to a definite state that is to one of its agan states.
Consider first an isolated system in a generic superposition state, and that does not interact with
the with the environment.
With, as usual, that.
State vector BPCI given as some of the two igan states, A and B over a square two, which is of course,
as usual, as you should know by now, that probability coefficient.
And a and being, for example, spin up or down or kept alive and dead or generally two mutually exclusive
igan states that is orthogonal physical states, when you describe it with the vectors you in a three
dimensional vector space, you can recall that we describe it as two orthogonal vectors.
If we want to calculate the probability that the Squantum system will change from a state BPCI to one
of the two possible states say kept a record a we must work with the transition amplitude we introduced
in the lecture on the state vector and Schrodinger's equation, namely that the probability of a transition
from an initial state bracket BPCI to a final final state of A is given by this little formula that
we discussed in that occasion, and which is the square models of the inner product of C and A.
Now to proceed, you should know how to calculate a model squared, often in a product, if you are
not acquainted, acquainted with this, please see also in the appendix where we dealt with this, it
is the part which deals with the addition of two complex Wavves which added together and squared deliver
the intensity of a beam with an associated interference term that are also how we calculated the interference
fringes with a double slit experiment.
Go back there and you will recall and we'll see how we are substantially doing the same thing.
So let us do this here with the coherent state side.
And if we take this expression for BPCI and take the model square with the Cat Agan state, we obtain
this expression.
That is, we simply insert the superposition state in this model square.
In a further step, we calculate using the distributive law or the distributive rule.
And we have the model square of a bracket, A plus a mixed term.
Brought a cat B over of, of course, square to.
Square it this, again, is equal to one half, obviously, because one of the square, two square is
one 1/2 times the model, the square of the numerator here, which, if expanded, becomes this expression
here, because recall that the Model Square is nothing as of quantity.
The model square of a quantity is nothing else than the product of this quantity times its own complex
conjugate.
Therefore, we have here at the start the complex times the same value.
This again is equal.
We calculate now again with a distributive law.
We take this to brackets.
Here you have the complex conjugate times itself of the bracket A, which means that we have on one
side we collect the terms and we obtain one half times the model square of bracket A plus one half model
square of bread bracket A, B, the mixed terms and a more complicated term expression here, which
is in fact complicated, but it is not so important to understand what its real meaning is term by term.
We just sum this up and have a more compact term, obtaining again one half of the square of bracket
A plus and term that we will call the interference term, because here this term expresses the interference
between A and B, the two possible igan states.
It contains the combined inner products products of Coté and can be it can be called an interference
term because it is the same type of inter interference term we encountered in the double slit experiment
in the electron.
The double slit experiment we only.
Exchanged, we only replaced the two light beams, side one and side two with here, in our case with
a two Igan States, A and B. However, here, this has been set to zero in the last passage for the
simple reason that the inner product of bracket A B equals bracket pay is zero because the inner product
of orthogonal state vectors is zero.
Recall how we encountered our orthogonality for spin states in the electoral lecture on Spinous and
what remains is just what we already know, namely that there is a 50 percent chance of getting state
bracket eight.
This is fortunate.
Otherwise those remaining terms would not make much sense if the inner product of bracket baby AI were
not equal to zero, it would mean that there is still a non-zero probability that we could measure the
system still being in two states in the same sentence at the same time against anything our worldly
experience suggests.
The disappearance of this interference term is a formal mathematical representation of the quantum decoherence
process.
It is this decoherence process people invoke to explain why microscopic bodies never show up with quantum
properties.
However, this is true only for a system in isolation.
The fact is these conditions are very rarely met, any system that is not in a perfect vacuum will quickly
somehow interact with its surrounding environment.
Moreover, if we perform a measurement with some microscopic device, we must also take into account
all the interactions with it.
This means all the quantum states of the system to be measured will be will become entangled with a
virtually infinite number of particles of all the environment, plus the measurement apparatus.
Formally, this implies that the igan basis of the quantum system in our case get A and B, but its
interaction with the external macroscopic world will become entangled with the environment and the apparatus
as a whole as well.
Let us therefore level the igan basis of all the possible quantum states of the environment, together
with the measurement apparatus as Khaddafi, I wear the index, I runs over the virtually infinite number
of igan states.
Then the general environment and apparatus quantum state could be represented as a product over all
of these all of all these igan states.
As a Khaddafi, a level with Aetate, which stands for Environment A for the apparatus equals the product
of one timeously to two, three and so on.
Then the quantum state of the system entangled with the macroscopic world could be written as follows,
that is now we have a new state side of the whole system and is represented by the capsid EPA, which
is nothing else than the product of Capsid, the site that we had in the previous case in the isolated
case.
But this time it is not isolated.
Therefore, we must take the product Khaddafi, E.A., and which if we calculate it explicitly, we
obtain this expression here and which is nothing else.
And the product of the previous superposition state times the Khaddafi E.A..
Repeating then the calculation above all over again with this last term, which is quite cumbersome
because it entails a multiplication of brackets running on the index eye and which we omit here, one
obtains an analogous result as a previous equation, but extended to the environment and apparatus as
well.
So what we obtain here is a system driven amplitude between the state side of the system.
To, uh, from a superposition state outside of the system to its igan state, A. under the condition
that it is entangled also with the environment and the measurement apparatus formally, this goes as
a model, the square of that bracket, a sigh of a and which is equal, again, as previously one half
of the model square of the bracket A..
This time, however, over a that means with entangled with environment plus an interference term.
Of.
Bracket B a.
And where we use the shorthand that get a E.A. is equal, cut eight times the product of kaffiyeh and
analogously Cat B is equal, B times FITA and with the interference term.
But this time we cannot sweep under the carpet so easily by setting it to a zero value, because this
mix term here, the bracket B A over the environment is the inner product of interacting igan basis
that is non also non orthogonal basis.
What this seems to suggest to us is that at least for a short time, the Kwanten system must be in the
in its superposition state, which is truly entangled with the external world.
So the upshot is that there is effectively a quantum interference between the object and its surroundings.
This is another way of seeing quantum coherence extended to quantum systems, quantum systems that we
imagine are made of many particles.
In other words, we should truly observe the cat alive and dead at the same time, because now, since
we have no longer orthogonal and orthogonal basis, the inner product baby does not disappear.
It's still there.
The fact that the decoherence interference term does not vanish, that is still some coherence seems
to be present also after the measurement is contrary to whatever we know in quantum as in classical
mechanics.
However, the question is, how short is that short time of coherence?
One can show that this loss of coherence, the so-called quantum decoherence or course on timescales
that are inversely proportional to the number of particles involved and decreases exponentially with
time.
The number of molecules which make up the air, the cat's body and the surrounding objects and the measurement
apparatus is of the order of Avogadro's number.
And we already discussed in the lecture on the Schrodinger's cat paradox how huge this number is.
It's something about the order of 10 to the power 23, and that because of this huge number of particles,
the interference term had to disappear.
And here we are discussing how fast does it disappear.
And so according to this understanding of what is going on is that the macroscopic objects could also,
in principle be in superposition or in an entangled state.
But due to the Brownian motion, this thermal decoherence is extremely fast because the number of particles
involved in this Brownian motion, in this thermal decoherence is so huge that the time interval of
being in superposition is so ultra short that it can be considered, for all practical purposes, as
instantaneous.
Quantum decoherence sets in extremely quickly, and we won't notice anything strange that might suggest
anything other than our good old classical world where cats live or dead or alive, but not both, but
for an extremely short time interval.
According to quantum physics, it is indeed possible to have cats in a superposition dead and alive.
In principle, to avoid decoherence, we must be able to perfectly maintain the coherence of all the
particles of the environment and every measurement device by eliminating the thermal agitation.
This, in turn, would practically mean that any measurement device could not function in the first
place and that the poor cat must be frozen to an absolute zero temperature, which, by the way, would
at least solve that dead or alive dilemma from the outset.
So when we consider a huge macroscopic systems which are not cooled down to absolute zero temperature
and are not placed into very special physical conditions, we will never, ever observe quantum coherence.
That is anything in quantum entanglement or in quantum superposition state.
It is not that the laws of quantum physics no longer hold the hold at all levels.
However, for large objects or the quantum effects disappear almost instantly.
Nowadays, exceptions to this can nevertheless be realized with the so-called Bose Einstein condensate
by complicated procedures placing a gas of helium in a container at fractions of degrees Kelvin avoiding
its contact with the chamber walls.
The realization of the Einstein condensate is in fact show that it is possible to create a relatively
macroscopic systems less than a millimeter in diameter that are in a coherent state.
So this is possible.
And finally, the so-called Schrodinger's cat paradox is not a paradox at all, it can be explained
with quantum decoherence taking place in very short times because of the interaction between the huge
number of particles of which a macroscopic system is made and the particles of the rest of the environment.
This is at present the most acceptable explanation.
Showing us contribution was to point out that there is no reason to believe that, at least in principle,
quantum superposition is a scale dependent, universal future of physical reality.
However, the story still does not end here.
One also hears professional physicists not particularly informed in the foundations of quantum physics,
say that decoherence decoherence process solves the measurement problem.
This is not completely correct.
The quantum decoherence provides an explanation of why Schrodinger's cat paradox is not a paradox,
but it does not entirely solve the measurement problem.
Decoherence explains why we perceive objects as being classical, together with Borse corespondents
principle.
According to this principal, classical physics is a limiting case of quantum mechanics, quantum mechanics,
that is quantum mechanics who produces quantum physics in the statistical limit of large quantum numbers.
For example, recall how the the increase in energy quantum numbers behaves in the limit as a large
or as large orbit's or large energy as we saw in Bors atomic model or how quantum numbers determine
the orbitals, as we discussed in the lecture on atomic orbitals.
However, note that decoherence is, strictly speaking, not the usual way function collapse, rather
it is, so to speak, a quick interference suppression.
The Schrodinger cat paradox cannot be explained with the coherence alone, the coherence souls, the
measurement problem only partially as it still leaves open an anomaly that is intrinsic in the formalism
of quantum mechanics as fast as it might be, decoherence should be described by an evolution in time
described with the evolution operator, the unitary operator we discussed, and that, as you might
recall again in the lecture on the Schrodinger equation in which I display here again for your convenience.
In general, we spoke of the evolution, quantum evolution of a system, of a quantum system from a
time zero to a time T. And we displayed this with a quantum state vector BPCI at time zero, which goes
into BPCI at time T. This was described with a unitary operator, unitary because it's complex conjugate
times itself gives identity or one if you prefer, and is described also with exponential function.
And the Hamiltonian Hamiltonian.
If you don't remember this, go back to the lecture we where we discussed this, at which this unitary
operator transports, so to speak, evolves the state vector at time zero zero.
To state better at a time to step back to apply so the application of this unitary operator describes
the quantum evolution of the system.
If so, in our case, the same unitary operator must describe the time evolution from the quantum state
of the system entangled with the macroscopic world, that is a state entangled with the environment,
plus the measurement apparatus, and that we can label as cat, BPCI, E.A. to one of the two possible
macroscopic state outcomes.
And that we describe this time also analogously CAT, a E.A. as also.
Get BGA, because these are two different possible outcomes of the same initial state.
Informal language, this implies that Keat, a E.A., is the result of a time evolution of capsid.
Entangled with the environment and the apparatus.
Under the application of the unitary operator, that is, you times the cat CETA and at for the same
reason, this one that can't be E.A. is equal.
If you applied on to the state vector capsid, E.A. then recall also from the lecture on the direct
notation, that indirect notation, the model is squared off the in a product of BPCI with itself.
Is equal one just because it is the sum of all the probability coefficients and which obviously must
be certainty, then applying, putting this together, we can right that the transition probability
from a state A to a state B of a system microscopic system, which is, however, entangled with the
environment and eventually a measurement apparatus.
And with that we can describe with this bracket A B.
With level E.A. is equal to the same bracket where we replace the A and B states by their description
with the evolution operator as as the outcome of an evolved state from side to a or from side to B,
then we obtain this expression here.
But you start you is per definition of unitary operator one, therefore, we obtain, we reduce this
expression reduces to this expression.
With the identity operator in between and since this is an identity operator, it can be left out,
just is just the multiplication by unity.
So we arrive at this expression here, the inner product of PSI.
Right.
And as we said, this must be equal one.
This, however, is a strange result because this means that indeed we have certainty to observe the
two states and superposition.
Also at the microscopic environmental scale of the measurement apparatus or the cat.
This is contrary to the previous statement that due to decoherence, the interference term is rapidly
suppressed.
That is previously we had that the bracket A B of A with the environment is equal zero.
So this has led us to a contradiction that this contradiction is somehow intrinsic to the mathematical
description of quantum mechanics and emerges when we resort to decoherence only as a solution to the
measurement problem.
But with that, we have proven that it isn't.
Here, the main discrepancy with the known rules of quantum mechanics is that besides the violation
of the linearity of Schrodinger's equation and the measurement postulate also unitary t seems to be
violated.
That is this expression here.
This is one of the most fundamental pillars of the rules of quantum mechanics, as we have discussed
in the lecture on training on the training equation.
It guarantees that the theory is time reversal invariant, which means that if a operator, you evolve
the system forward in time, the complex conjugate of it that is used to evolve it backwards in time,
implying that the product you start, you must keep that identity necessarily because so it means that
you go back and forth in time and you get the same system as in the initial conditions.
If that would be incorrect.
Everything what quantum mechanics tells us the theory of quantum mechanics tells us would be wrong.
And yet we know it works another way.
Another way to state what the measurement problem is all about is to recognize how the physical state
of a large object like a detector is not deducible from the properties of the quantum state of the small
objects, it is made up of the measurement postulate.
The linearity of Schrödinger's equation and unique clarity are at odds with reductionism.
The issue is still debated among physicists and perhaps even more among philosophers, because it does
not really prevent, uh, physicists from carrying out their calculations and make precise predictions
on the macroscopic scale with elementary particles.
Uh, some of the interpretations of quantum mechanics, such as the many world interpretations, the
Bali bomb pilot wave or the object of collapse interpretation, these are very different interpretations
that we eventually will discuss, could in principle resolve this contradiction.
However, these interpretations why they reproduce the predictions of quantum physics and are empirically
indistinguishable from the orthodox theory, and which is why they are called interpretations, also
suggests mutually exclusive ontologies.
Nobody knows which must be preferred and whether any of it at all has something to do with reality.
Maybe this shows us that Einstein was not so wrong.
After all, quantum mechanics might not be so complete them.
Some seems to be still something missing.
However, whatever resolution the measurement problem might find inside an alternative complete description
of reality, it's certainly it certainly will not be that for which Einstein had hoped for.
Moreover, also, what all this tells us is that we still have not a clear understanding what at bottom
a measurement is.
It is something somehow unclear, it remains an overall intuitive concept and this concept of measurement
and that everyone speaks about, but it escapes a precise and clear definition that does not lead to
contradictions or paradoxes.
So finally, the measurement problem is still not solved, and this shows us that we still do not understand
completely why there is this divide between the classical world as we experience it and the quantum
world.