As well known cuts don't speak.
That child.
Question then is what if we replaced Schrödinger's cat with a human and asked him what it feels like
to be in a superposition state?
Moved by this a bit weird question.
A Gene Wagner, Hungarian-american physicist, proposed in 1961 an extended form of the Schrödinger's
Cat Paradox, and which is nowadays called the Weakness Friend Paradox.
In a thought experiment, Wagner imagined how a physicist say Wagner himself does not directly observe
the quantum system in superposition.
Say a cat that is dead or alive, or as we are going to do here, a system of particles that are in
a superposition state with measurement.
Results one or zero.
But rather let another physicist, his friend, perform the quantum measurement on the system in a laboratory
isolated from the environment.
Later, his friend will communicate the results to him.
Perfect Isolation from the environment is essential in this idealized experiment.
As otherwise, the system would quickly cohere and collapse into an eigen state.
And in this ideal situation, one could apply the laws of quantum mechanics and consider the time evolution
of the laboratory laboratory quantum states unilaterally.
As unitary transformations.
So here we can see in this picture on the outside is Wagner.
And who lets his friend inside this box perform the measurement on the quantum system.
And he lets first his friend make this measurement, and only then he makes the measurement on his friend.
That is asks his friend about the result.
So this is the situation like shown in the figure before.
Both weakness friend and weakness himself.
Make any measurement in this situation weakness.
Friend considers the state of the system as in superposition to be as follows.
That is alpha get zero plus better get one for system s and where obviously the get zero and get one
being the spin zero and spin one respectively or whatever binary state of the system as and as usual
alpha and beta being the probability coefficients for each state.
Meanwhile, for Wagner, who stands out of the system plus friend laboratory context, that is an out
of the box, literally pun intended before he measures anything that joins State.
Must be the following.
Meaning that it must be a superposition of all the possible states between the system and the friend
that is the system in.
Zero state.
Then the friend sees zero and gets himself in a corresponding zero state.
F.
R.
The system is in state one.
Therefore also the friend must see and finally measure one.
But before this measurement for weakness, there is a superposition of the these two possibilities.
Note that this this equation assumes the linearity of Schrodinger's equation.
That is when two solutions, that is two states are allowed, then also the sum of their two states
is allowed.
This will become important for some later consideration.
So now let weakness friend perform a measurement on the system.
According to the rules of quantum mechanics, this means that he has to select out this collapse project
or reduce or whatever you would like to call it.
The state function and this must be projected into one of its possible bases.
Say, for example, that the eigen basis gets zero s meaning in the zero state, which for him then
becomes a physical fact.
Meaning that his state, that the state of the friend becomes zero as well.
So we have cut zero se and cut zero F combined because they must be the same otherwise.
That's because that's what weakness friend is has measured.
However, for Wegner, who stands outside the laboratory and still hasn't made any observation of the
joint structure system plus friend that is on the box, there has been still no collapse then no reduction,
no projection or whatever of the wave function of the state vector.
He must consider the system still in a superposition state.
And therefore from weakness.
Standing outside, he says the joint state must still be that of this equation here.
That is still in a superposition state between the zeros and ones of the friend and the system.
Finally, also, Wagner makes a measurement and projects the state function into one of its bases.
Say, for example, cut one cat one F that is, he says, I measure.
The friend in state one and the friend in and this system in state one and considers this also a physical
fact that the system is in state one and his friend is also in a state one.
Why is this so?
Because according to Wiener, from the outside and according to the laws of quantum mechanics, as long
as there is no measurement, the system must still be considered as being in a quantum superposition
of the friend, seeing the system in zero or the friend seeing the system in State one.
And as long as Wiener does not make this measurement.
Both alternatives have equal probability to realize.
That's what quantum mechanics tells us.
Both possibilities still are possible for the outside observer and the state reduction can occur.
That weakness Mather measures his friend in State one and the system equally in State one.
This weird conclusion seems to suggest that in quantum physics, two observers can observe the same
physical event differently.
They can disagree on what for both is a physical fact.
This amounts to saying that weakness Friend claims the cat is dead.
While Wiener observes, observes the cat to be alive or vice versa.
Weakness Friend claims the cat to be alive.
While Wagner says No, I see the dead cat.
Or in other words, objective reality does not exist.
And reality seems to be, in a certain sense, subjective, because there could be different accounts
of the very same process and there is no observer independent fact that seems to exist.
This bizarre conclusion led to the wildest conjectures and speculations.
Many see this paradox as proof of the role of the observer and quantum mechanics according to the interpretation
that is so in fashion nowadays, and that if you follow this course, probably you know that I don't
favor at all.
But that's what many people believe and say and favor according to interpretation.
The key to avoid this mutually conflicting results between observers is in the mind or the consciousness
of the observer.
Observer observers themselves.
That is the weakness, strength and weakness.
Because when weakness friend observes the system, we can say that the wave function collapses immediately
to to a definite state.
Say zero.
Before Vigna makes any observation on the joint system.
Therefore it is weakness, friend, mind or consciousness that causes this collapse.
And therefore, because this collapse has already occurred.
Wagner will, of course, obviously observe his friend being in a state zero as well.
And then if both see the system in a state zero and Wagner sees his friend in a state zero, then there
is no paradox.
There would be no contradictory observation between the two, and the paradox disappears.
Wagner, in fact, pointed out that the physical act of measurement isn't sufficient to cause a collapse,
according to.
Rather, it must be the conscious awareness of an observer.
This is necessary to cause a collapse, according to with Wagner.
As long as no conscious observer is involved, see save, there are only microscopic quantum particles
instead of cats, friends and other physicists.
Yes.
Then we can say they are effectively in a permanent superposition state all along the temporal sequence
of the processes.
Thus, Wagner moved the dividing line between the quantum system, the quantum object to be observed,
the quantum world in general, and the classical measurement apparatus.
The macroscopic.
Device with which we make a measurement into the conscious mind of the observer.
To put it into the words of weakness.
The being with a consciousness must have a different role in quantum mechanics than the inanimate measuring
device.
It is from this kind of speculation that the infamous role of the observer in quantum physics gained
an overwhelming celebrity.
But there is less weird interpretation, one that is much more in line with current knowledge.
If we ask ourselves what physical process constitutes a measurement?
What does it mean to make a measurement?
As you know, and as we have discussed in the previous lectures in quantum physics, a measurement is
always a quantitative assessment of the eigenvalue associated with the dynamical variables.
Operator.
For example, measuring the spin of an electron implies the projection of the state vector onto one
of its ion bases, and that is spin up or spin down and a real scalar quantity, the eigenvalue being
its intrinsic angular momentum.
And that is the result of measurement.
Whereas if there is no measurement, there is no collapse of the wave function or also the other way
around.
If there is no collapse of the wave function, there could be no measurement, not even in principle.
So if weakness friend makes a measurement, a projection of the state vector also, of course, which
settles the result for weakness as well, and therefore no inconsistency arises.
Meanwhile, if there is no collapse, then weakness Friend did not make any measurement in the first
place.
There is nothing we can call an observer independent fact to begin with.
And we could not even begin to ask his friend what was measured.
Either way, there is no paradox.
If we assume that measurement always causes or rather is the collapse of the wavefunction.
In other words, the weakness friend paradox arises only if we assume that the that the state collapse
takes place at the time of weakness.
Question.
But according to the rules of quantum mechanics, as long as no measurement takes place, the system
must still be considered as being in a quantum superposition of the alternative outcomes.
But in the weakness friend paradox, one assumes that in the temporal sequence for weakness friend,
the quantum collapse of the wave function occurs much earlier than what weakness observed.
There must therefore be a discrepancy between the temporal sequence of the state reduction, according
to the two observers.
And since no known physical law or rule lift's weakness or weakness friend to the status of a privileged
observer.
A paradox arises.
However, no paradox arises if we accept the fact that whatever measurement leads to a state reduction.
It occurs whenever weakness friend makes a measurement, not when weakness makes a measurement.
Some object saying that the state reduction is only an update of our knowledge about the system and
does not indicate a physical change in the system itself.
When weakness friend makes a measurement, he does not change the system superposition state and indeed
he also must be in a position state.
Now.
This reasoning, however, implies that a measurement is not a physical process, but only a pure information
retrieval that updates our knowledge.
Yet measurements that assess a value always imply some sort of physical process, such as a particle
that hits a detector screen or that is absorbed by a CD camera, or that makes a photomultiplier click
or that makes a pointer swing, etc., etc..
Therefore, at the bottom, the paradox arises only if we assume that measurement that the measurement
isn't a physical process.
But it always is in some form or another.
More recently, extended experiments have been proposed as an extension of the weakness and thought
experiment to a scenario with two weakness and two friends, each measuring an entangled, entangled
particle.
The experiment and the formal theory describing it are quite complicated, and we won't describe them
further here.
It might only be said that essentially the same happens as in the conventional weakness thought experiment,
but with two entangled particles rather than a single particle in superposition.
What came out from this is the scientists concluded that quantum theory cannot consistently describe
the use of itself and that single world interpretations of quantum theory cannot be self-consistent.
And these claims made big headlines throughout the press claiming that it was experimentally shown that
objective reality does not exist.
This was about 2018, and a year later, a group of Scottish physicists realised an experiment intended
to test this extended weakness thought experiment.
Their experiments seemingly confirmed that there are no locally observable, independent facts.
But who or what did they use as the weakness, the two weakness and the two weakness?
Friends.
They used photodetectors for the weakness and photons for the two weakness friends.
This, however, makes the whole experiment doubtful.
While a photodetector is a measurement device that undoubtably makes a measurement that is projects
the state vector onto one of its ion bases, a couple of photons can't be considered physical objects,
causing a state reduction.
The claim that a photon is an observer.
Making a measurement is a questionable statement, to say the least, let alone that it is a conscious
observer.
Thus it is questionable if these experiments prove anything at all.
Notice also that another, more or less unaware assumption leads to weakness paradox.
We assume that quantum mechanics must necessarily be unitary and linear.
Again, recall the definition of linearity and unitary ity we discussed in the previous lectures.
Four.
For simplicity, I sum it up here again.
Before a measurement, Schrodinger's equation linearity and the unity of the time evolution that describes
the quantum states continues to hold.
Whereas, after the measurement line, linearity and unit parity are, so to speak, broken up in the
sense that we observe one and only one result, that is, there are no superpositions left.
And once the system is in an ideal state, only one probability is assigned.
That is one meaning certainty to observe over and over again the same result for each subsequent measurement.
Once the first projective measurement has been done.
The probability and even before the measurement had to be observed, say 50% of probability to be observed
now will be observed with 100% probability.
That is probability.
Conservation has been broken.
This is essentially what we mean by a state projection according to the projection or measurement postulates
and what measurement is in itself.
In weakness thought experiment.
However, quantum superposition and entanglement are supposed to continue.
Also after the measurement by weakness, friend.
Which means unity, unity and linearity are assumed to continue to hold.
There has been no projection or reduction or collapse, whatever you would like to call it, as a result
of a measurement interaction.
One attributes outcomes to entangled systems or in quantum superposition.
Contrary to the well-known fact from our everyday macroscopic microscopic experience that once a measurement
has been performed, it never reveals a system to be in two states at once.
Any correlation obtained from a unitary and linearly deduced fact at weakness level has no equivalent
relationship to an outcome that accord or effect that has been obtained at his friend's level.
If superposition and entanglement are to be observed, then nobody would see any result to see anything.
Unity must be broken.
And because we see in our everyday experience measurement results, This is yet another reason to believe
that the present quantum mechanical formalism, which is exquisitely unitary, should be considered
incomplete and may have to be expanded to a non unitary.
Quantum theory in the future.
So you see this thing with weakness.
Rent is still a controversial issue.
Physicists could not converge on a general consensus of how it should be interpreted.
If it really tells us something about reality that is supposedly dependent from observers, if it has
to do with our mind and consciousness.
If it signals an inconsistency or in the theory of quantum theory or not, etc., the discussion on
this is going on and you will find several physicists having very different assessments on this.
In my opinion, however, the weakness friend paradox is only an extension of Schrödinger's cat paradox
and only a generalization, if you wish, of the measurement problem.
It furnishes yet another perspective on the measurement measurement problem, but without telling us
really much more.
It raises again the question of when and where exactly the collapse, of course, and whether this collapse
or.
Projection or whatever you might call it, is actually a real physical process or only an abstract mathematical
description of reality.
As long as no real measurements are made without thermal decoherence, processes say we consider only
microscopic quantum particles instead of macroscopic bodies such as cats, friends and physicists.
These microscopic quantum objects are effectively in a permanent superposition state all along the temporal
sequence of the process that is all along the so-called von Neumann chain.
The question is, where is the demarcation line between what we describe as the wave function and a
collapsed wave function?
The point is that nobody knows where to place the demarcation line and if it exists at all.
This is what is sometimes called the Heisenberg's Cut.
Thus the weakness friend paradox restates in a certain sense the measurement problem in a somewhat different
manner, but does not really add any new insights.
At any rate, whatever the truth, this debate is interesting.
Interesting in itself.
The history of science shows that whenever internal inconsistencies arise in the theory, this is usually
an indication that it is incomplete and must be replaced by a better theory.
These sorts of conceptual anomalies that suggested the incompletion of a theoretical framework have
often led to great breakthroughs in science.
The future will tell if this is the case here as well.