The philosophical implications of quantum phenomena evidenced in the experiments, in the proceedings,
in the preceding lectures are in fact, many in particular, the kind of world view that emerges from
it is a matter of debate.
And to a certain degree, we may also say it's a matter of personal preference and tastes.
So to speak, however, before concluding this chorus, I would like to focus our attention on an aspect
that most physicists and not really philosophers as well who would like to maintain an ordinary form
of realism, prefer to suppress and ignore, namely that quantum physics seems to support some sort
of idealistic worldview.
The doctrine of philosophical idealism dates back to the time of Plato, it reemerged then in different
forms over and over again throughout the centuries and continents and continues to influence philosophical
inquiry to the present day.
There are so many versions of idealism and subtleties to be considered that it is difficult to define
them in a few sentences.
And we won't be able to go through all of the details here.
However, what they all have in common and what is relevant for purposes of philosophical considerations
in quantum physics is the recognition that mere empiricism, that is the act of measurement of physical
quantity alone and which characterises all the exact sciences, does not lead to the revelation of an
objective and ultimate reality and truth.
Whether we like it or not, we are always forced to observe reality through our throughout through our
perceptions and which are mediated by human senses or through also measurement devices, and we have
to interpret reality through the lens of our mind.
The question of what should be regarded as an objective reality, independent from our sensorial means
and mental representations, is a much more contrived matter than we are accustomed to believe in,
especially among scientists, I would say.
We have already seen many examples of this in quantum physics, and it is precisely in the quantum domain
that this issue presents itself most pressingly.
However, to clarify the question of what reality is and what the world what what the word reality is
supposed to mean, let us reason first with experiments taken from a classical world.
For example, think of the measurement or the measurement of temperature, we associate temperature
with the sensation that of a body being hot or cold.
However, human sensations are subjective and are relative characterizations of the physical domain,
not scientific statements that are supposed to describe what we believe to be an objective reality.
Out there, so to speak, and which is supposed to be independent from what we believe, perceive or
think.
What then does a thermometer really measure according to thermodynamics, a temperature is a measure
of a quantity directly proportional to the average kinetic energy of the molecules of the body, solid
gas of fluid, and which is caused by the Brownian motion and resulting from its random scattering of
the particles in physics.
Another way to express the same phenomenon is to state the temperature measures the ability of a body
to transfer to transfer heat.
The hotter object will transfer heat to the colder one.
However, when we read a temperature from a thermometer, we see a number evalu just as color quantity
expressed in a particular scale Kelvin Celsius or Fahrenheit, Fahrenheit or whatever.
Instinctively, we associate that number with the sensation or in the case of scientist with a mental
projection that depicts molecules vibrating randomly due to Brownian motion or imagining he transfers.
Of course, you can take a microscope and literally, literally see the random walk of pollen grains
and water, as Robert Brown did, and convince convince yourself that the thermometer is a device that
translates the objective reality of the Brownian motion of molecules into a number.
We should, however, be aware of the fact that the measurement of physical magnitude, reducing it
to a sign on a number like that of a temperature tells us nothing about the objective truth for which
that symbol stands.
If we knew only the symbol, the number without relation, we any relation to what it levels, we could
say nothing about what it really represents.
Moreover, Brown only shifted the measurement from a measurement apparatus like a thermometer to a human
side sensor mean amplified by a microscope.
Does this finally tell us something about an ultimate objective reality?
Hardly any scientist or philosopher will admit that human perception furnishes an objective understanding
of reality from the practical point of view.
We don't bother.
We just take a measurement.
And most scientists are happy with the empiric data and introduction in exploring how we perceive and
conceive the world could be that of following British philosopher and author Owen Barfield and who once
invited us to do and ask ourselves the following question.
Look at the rainbow.
Is it really there?
Of course, we should not regard a rainbow as an object having and any concrete spatial and material
existence, it is, so to speak, an intangible appearance about which we can't say that it is really
their.
We believe that only the raindrops and the sun are really there.
But the rainbow is not.
Nonetheless, we can't state that the rainbow is a mere hallucination either, since also others are
seeing it.
This fact, however, doesn't imply that the rainbow is actually there, rather that it is a shared
or collective appearance or representation that is an inter subjective experience, not an objective
entity.
While we agree that the rainbow isn't really there, in what sense instead is a tree, a mountain or
the moon really there?
The distinction between the two cases is less obvious than we might believe, because as the appearance
of the rainbow comes into existence, due to the interaction of the sunlight with the rain droplets,
so the appearance of the tree, a mountain or the moon comes into existence due to the interaction of
the sunlight with their molecules and atoms.
One can press the argument for further and note how also molecules and atoms are themselves again,
another appearance which is realized due to the interaction of a measurement device with the elementary
particles they are made of and out of which by a mental extrapolation, we construct a mental atomic
model.
In fact, nobody has seen molecules, atoms and elementary particles directly.
And this leads us into the realm of quantum physics, where instead of reaching a final objective entity
that is really there, whatever that might mean and from which we can in principle build by a bottom
up process, all there is nature instead answers us, as you know by now, very well, with even more
elusive phenomena further detached from any of our sensory means and conceptual constructs at bottom.
Everything boils down to representations of our sense minds, so to speak, our sensory, our mind based
on our sense perceptions, using barflies words.
The familiar world, which we see and know around us, the blue sky with white clouds in it, the noise
of a waterfall or a motor bus, the shapes of flowers and their scent, the gesture and utterance of
animals and the faces of our friends, the world to which, apart from the special inquiry of physics,
experts of all kinds methodically investigate.
Is a system of collective representations.
The time comes when we must either accept this as a truth about the world or reject the theories of
physics as an elaborate delusion.
We cannot have it both ways.
But to illustrate how the demarcation between objective and subjective is much subtler, then we are
accustomed to believing let us employ another example still remaining in the classical macroscopic world
from the standpoint of neurobiology.
Let us think how we know that objects exist.
How do we know that an object exists?
What does it mean this world existing?
Say, for example, you see a table in a room.
First of all.
For that to be possible, you would need a light source illuminating the table, obviously not without
light as a medium which encodes in an electromagnetic signal the table, you can tell nothing.
What you see is not the table directly, therefore, in itself as it is in itself, but the light reflected
from it.
You can't claim that you see the table as it is, you can say only how the table presents itself to
your eyes through an electromagnetic interaction.
However, the decisive point we should realize is that when the light reaches the retina, our eye retina,
at which point the eyes anatomy has already distorted the input into it.
Two dimensional Upside-Down image, by the way, at that point, there is still a long way to go before
you see something.
Because the photons must, first of all, be transformed and translated further into another representation,
they must first trigger a very complex sequence of biochemical reactions in the retina photoreceptors,
photoreceptors of your retina.
Once the electromagnetic wave has been absorbed, it it is now an electrical and chemical signal which
represents the table that you are seeing, not still not seeing.
Because, in fact, do you see something at that point?
No, you still don't see anything.
The visual information codified in the electro biochemical impulse must still travel from the retina,
from your eye retina and through the optic nerve to a part of your brain, the so-called optic miasma.
Where the left and right visual fields get mixed up between the left and right hemisphere brain hemispheres
and before being sent to the lateral Jenny Koolade nucleus, so-called air relays a relay center in
the thalamus.
Then.
These information can get through your brain, but still at this point, you still see absolutely nothing
because the visual information must be relayed further to the visual cortex of the posterior part of
the brain.
We at this point, we still see nothing because the visual cortex not only receives signals that no
longer have much to do with what once represented the table, but must first perform an extremely complex
process of analysis, segmentation and integration of information.
The visual visual cortex is divided into five areas based on function and structure.
First, the relayed signal from the thalamus reaches the first area, which processes information for
pattern recognition purposes, but you still see nothing.
The second region of the visual cortex cortex receives this further altered representation from the
first layer and continues to filter out other information, such as colors, spatial properties and
more complex patterns of the objects perceives.
And still no table is inside.
Still, at this point, you see nothing later.
The remaining three areas perform other tasks, other tasks such as spatial tasks and detection of movements
and so on.
It's quite complicated matter.
And still nowadays we do not know exactly what the brain is doing.
But this is not so important for our purposes.
But at this point that ends the information processing of the visual cortex.
And then finally, you see something, right, no, you still don't see anything to become conscious
of the table, the visual cortex must disseminate all its synthesized information to all areas of the
brain.
Then after another very complex neuronal electrochemical process that takes place throughout the brain,
suddenly, for some mysterious reason that nobody can explain, you become literally enlightened by
a visual conscious experience and become aware of how out there is what we call in common language,
a table.
You never had not in the least any contact, direct contact with that object you call table, what you
see at this point is something that has absolutely nothing to do with the electromagnetic signal that
encoded the representation of this representation by biochemical and neuronal representation of the
table and let alone the table itself.
What you perceive of the outer world of the table is a biochemical and electric single signal inside
your brain.
Not more than that.
It is not even a model or not even a representation in the best case, we could call it a mere symbol.
The difference between a model or a representation and the symbol is that the former retains something
of the inherent reality of an object.
The latter is just a symbol, an index.
For example, the sculpture of Plato is a model since it retains something of the form of his appearance,
form and figure.
The name Plato, however, is a symbol you are reading on a piece of paper and you write it Plato and
retains nothing of the of the inherent reality of the person.
It indicates it were played.
Plato is an index.
What we perceive of reality is therefore not even a model.
It is.
Not even a representation, it is a symbol, an index.
However, fortunately for us, it still conveys an illusion of objective reality that is clearly extremely
complex.
Reshuffling of altered, converted, transform, transformed and remodeled impulses is what we perceive
of the outer world.
Nothing else.
What is what we call reality.
Therefore, from the standpoint of you, we have never experienced the world outside of the biochemistry,
inside our brains, and nobody can have any clue as to what reality is objectively, objectively out
there as it is inherently independent from our sensorial and mental representations.
Or symbols, if you prefer.
Turning to the analogy of the previous example with the thermometer, our perception of the world with
our senses and mind stands to its objective reality, just as the read out of temperature with a thermometer
stands to the zigzagging molecules.
And nothing is left of that reality other than an electoral biochemical.
Representation triggering a conscious experience inside of us, just like the heat of Mercury column
in the thermometer, represents the Brownian motion.
Unfortunately, this time we can't resort to Brown's microscope, so to speak, because we don't even
know what that is supposed to mean in some sense, we live in a virtual reality without knowing it,
sort of like in the film The Matrix and can't have access to the real reality, so to speak.
At this point, it becomes clear how while all of this is of no concern for our practical lives and
also for most scientists, I would say the philosopher or the scientist aiming to arrive at objective
truth in questioning the ultimate intrinsic reality of things has a much bigger fish to fry here, because
the distinction between real and unreal, objective and subjective things and the representation of
things, or even the existence or nonexistence of something becomes becomes not at all obvious.
This is not really a new issue for the philosophers of ancient Greece or of the 18th and 19th, 19th
century, did not know anything about nature, about biology and quantum physics, but they were acutely
aware of the fact that our senses and our minds have no direct access to reality as it is.
This led several of them to take sides regarding a conception of reality in which we cannot abstract
from human sense, cognition.
Broadly speaking, one can distinguish at least two categories of philosophical idealism.
One is the so-called ontological or metaphysical idealism, which holds that all reality is a mental
construct and at its foundation regards mind instead of matter as a fundamental constituent of reality.
One of its most notorious supporters was the 18th century Irish bishop and philosopher George Burke
Berkeley.
But since quantum physics does not or does not necessarily support the claim that all of reality is
a mental construct, we will focus our attention on some formulations of the second type of idealism
that of the so-called epistemological or former idealism expressed by the 18th and 19th century German
philosophers such as Immanuel Kant, phratry shelling out to Schopenhauer and later taken up by the
20th century British idealist movement represented by philosophers like Thomas Hale Green and Francis
Herbert Bradley and so on.
These are just some names that may furnish you a direction for further for further reading.
We will certainly not go into their philosophical thought in detail here.
Instead, we will try to illustrate how a similar, very similar worldview emerges from quantum physics.
If we give up our naive realism and embrace a larger concept of reality that questions whether science
is the ultimate tool for investigating ultimate truth without having the pretension of exposing a rigorous
definition and explanation of epistemological idealism, we try to characterize it as follows.
Epistemological idealism posits that all our knowledge about reality being innervate, inevitably mediated
through our senses, is only a formal representation emerging in our minds.
And that these forms can be taken as representatives of things, as they are really relating to an object
should not be mistaken for knowledge of the thing in itself as can't use, used to call it being undistorted
and independent from any mental activity.
Every insight that our knowledge reflects is a structured thought in our minds where we conflate knowledge
with the object of knowledge.
Our minds process census data by organizing it into abstract propositional knowledge that refers to
a quantitative and qualitative properties which the things in themselves do not have.
Kant, in his magnum opus critique of Pure Reason, introduced the form of idealism known as transcendental
idealism.
Idealism, says Kant, does not concern the existence of things, but is only about our modes of representation
of the perceived things.
Also, entities that we take as self-evident and fundamental, such as space and time, are not things
in in themselves, but rather are emerging phenomena in our minds.
Whatever we know, we can't avoid knowing it by filtering it through a sense mine perspective, this
doesn't imply that there is nothing at all or that we must surrender to some form of relativism or nihilism.
There exists a mind independent reality out there in which something else must be the ultimate foundation
of all things.
However, that ultimate reality of things cannot be apprehended by our senses and our minds, which
can present us with only a representation.
Or, I prefer to say, only a symbol of it.
Once we realized this, we must conclude the scientific knowledge which extends and delegates our senses
by mechanical measuring devices also cannot avoid investigating reality by modes of perception and the
representation.
Science, it is is objective only in the sense that it is entirely subjective, but not truly objective.
By intersubjectivity, we mean common, consensual, subjective experiences that.
Can be shared among scientists without ambiguities.
Also, the strictly empirical science is essentially inevitably and necessarily inter subjective and
not really objective.
We can all agree that we see a table in a room or measure the same physical value of a property of something,
say the length of the table.
But that does not imply that we are becoming aware of the way in which the world is constituted beyond
the appearances fabricated inside the brain of a human subject.
Nevertheless, most scientists hold the opinion, more or less unconsciously, that science is the tool
for arriving at an object and subject independent conception of an ultimate and intrinsic reality.
We are, however, not aware of the fact that already is down to earth and simple but strictly scientific
reasoning itself.
As we have exemplified with the neuro biological example of the site process, one can make it clear
that the issue must be somewhat more complicated.
The belief that replacing the human perception such as that of of eyesight with that measurement device,
say with a photo detector and a microscope or a telescope, supposedly allows us to rise to a higher
ontological level from a subjective to a purely objective understanding of a pure and inherent reality.
That is a delusion strongly engraved in our modes of cognition.
This may also be hardwired genetically in our brains due to survival necessities, however, we must
realize how we, as cognize subjects actively contribute to the construction of the object of knowledge
that might well be a subject independent world with things having a being.
Without us looking at it, but this is beyond the possibility of our normal cognition, one by one might
argue for or against an absolute truth, but if any.
Also in science, we are allowed to know it only by a fiction based on subjective experiences as acts
of cognition.
It is precisely when we forget that this process takes place in our mind and our brain in our consciousness,
that we are lured into counterfactual definiteness, which assumes the existence of the properties of
objects even when they have not been measured directly at this point.
We might also answer Einstein's question about the existence of the moon by saying that it continues
to exist when nobody is looking at it, but does so as a subject, the independent state of being that
has nothing to do with a faked existence that our visual and mental representations of the moon lure
us into believing what we take for real.
In contrast to a subject, independent reality stands like the picture of an object projected on a computer
monitor to the electric charges that encode in bits and bytes the picture in a memory.
The picture on the monitor is a projection on a screen which has absolutely no ontological connection
to the letter thing, namely that bits and bytes the electric states in the chip memory.
Instead, in our naive and instinctive apprehension of the things we misinterpret, the former for the
latter, it is the picture for the electoral states in the chip.
As we have seen, EPWs, realism states that if we can predict with certainty the value of a physical
quantity, then there there exists an element of physical reality corresponding to this physical quantity.
From the Idalis point of view, this is not necessarily an incorrect statement, provided, however,
that we realized that the value of a physical quantity tells us absolutely nothing.
What about what the essence of that element of reality is?
No more no less than that temperature, the sculler quantity that we call temperature reflects the reality
of the Brownian motion.
Transcendental idealism remains agnostic as to the constitution of the ultimate reality of things,
if by realism we mean that objects exist independently of us, then idealism does not contrast with
real realism, though we know only the mind content structure of perceptions inside of us without any
possible direct contact with things outside of us.
We have no reason to deny the existence of the external objects that trigger these sensations, concepts
and apprehensions the human mind can't have and knowledge by identity with things.
Our knowledge of the world begins with a sensorial experience which translates itself into representations,
pictures, figures, symbols, figments and reflections leading to a state of mind.
As I said, this is no new realization or philosophical conception of the year of the relationship between
our conscious perceptions and reality, but it is something we tend to forget, perhaps blinded too
much by the overwhelming success of science and that we instinctively but falsely take for the ultimate
tool to unveil the object of reality of things as they are in themselves.
In fact, already Plato tried to make us aware of this, that we live in what is called nowadays Plato's
Cave, it is like those who lived all their lives chained inside a cave, forced to stare at a blank
wall without having access to the outer world, other than by seeing on the wall the project of the
projected shadows of people passing in front of a fire placed at the caves entrance.
We misinterpret the shadows for real persons because we know nothing else.
Unless we become aware that we know only projected shadows of reality, we will forever live in a world
of delusion without even being aware of it.
Even if we become aware of the fact that we are living in a virtual reality, we can't avoid refiring
inside of us those phenomenal appearances in our minds.
For idealism, things exist, at least for epistemological idealism, things exist.
There is something really out there.
It's not all an illusion of our mind.
Your reality is not degraded as mere illusion, but it is this reality is not endowed with the forms
and qualities we represent it as having.
It's like for the observers in Plato's Cave, they see the shadows, they believe the shadows are the
ultimate reality, and once they awaken, they may believe that then shadows are just illusions.
Yes, they are illusions, but they they are the projection of true reality out there out of the cave.
These persons which shadows they see.
Exist, really, but not in the form of the shadows.
So there is indeed some sort of underlying reality, the universe is not just a fiction in our mind,
but that reality has nothing in common with the constructs and appearances it triggers inside of us,
no more than a shadow of a human body telling us something about the nature and complexity of living
of a living body.
Metter forces, space time forms and numbers subjected to the physical laws have some in here, in here
and existence in itself independent from us, we are able to create in ourselves on an internal screen
of consciousness, like the projections of the shadows on the wall of Plato's Cave, sensory representations
of things which, however, do not reveal to us anything about the things in themselves.
The fact that things like stones and mountains are permanent objects of perception and are subjected
to what we call the laws of physics is by no means a guarantee for an object of knowledge.
If by objective we mean the inherent essence of things as they are independent of our perceptions and
modes of cognition.
What we call matter space, time and forces and particles also are the reflection of a cosmos, which
we experience as mere fabrications in our mind without any objective truth, what things are in themselves
remains completely unknown to us.
The real nature of things independent from ourselves is forever precluded to our human and also scientific
sense.
My knowledge, at least in our evolutionary state, at least as human beings, perhaps some higher form
or more evolved form may be able to have knowledge by identity.
But in our case, that's not for humans.
This is not the case because to use still again Plato's allegory, again, cutting the chains and leaving
the cave so that we know things in themselves as they really are, means that we must first eliminate
the sensory perception and the mental construction of it.
We live in the world given to us as being without allowing us to gain direct contact with that state
of being.
At least not with our present abilities of cognition.
Having existence of being is all there is, everything else is derivative idealism, at least in the
form of a epistemological.
Idealism is therefore not an anti realist conception of the world and of the universe, but rather is
a different form of realism, which does not posit matter spacetime forces or any other phenomena and
mental experiences as a fundamental stuff of reality.
It is in this sense that science should by no means be considered exempt from philosophical idealism.
Also, the most empiric exact rational and analytic science as physics could be considered, must resort
to experiments composed of mechanical sensors and measurement devices which replace, extend and delegates
for our human sensory abilities.
But at the end of the experimental chain, it must always and inevitably convey its result in the form
of numbers, data or pictures that the human mind can interpret and which are interpreted by and through
the human mind.
The character of things in themselves cannot be inferred from any amount of empirical data, science
can only speak about the appearances of cognition, but can it can't go far enough to tell us anything
about the inherent essentiality of the things it cognize us.
Also, our experiments in the laboratory as precise and objective and independent of human intervention
as we might consider them, must be reduced to a cognition of appearances rather than an inherent objective
knowledge of things.
Ideas, concepts, laws and mathematical abstractions are useful guidelines for scientific research
and are necessary for our practical survival, but they do not tell us much about things as they are
really.
In itself.
Scientists should be aware.
And of this something which unfortunately, most of the time they are not that empirical facts are not
the revelation of ultimate truth, and at least when making philosophical claims should distinguish
between appearances and things in themselves.
So let us look at quantum phenomena from the perspective, from this perspective, that of the philosophical
idealist, then several aspects that previously seemed utterly at odds with a naive sense, mind based
form of realism now acquire a different significance.
For example, we realize how the notion of spin, the rotational intrinsic angular momentum of a particle
is already a heavily sensorial and mental laden representation borrowed from the everyday macroscopic
real.
Here, we imagine, which means we project a shadow on our internal mental screen, an extended body
with some form and properties changing its appearance, appearances periodically in space and time.
The very notion of rotation is, however, a concept we reconstruct from a series of subsequent subsequent
appearances, presenting themselves as stimuli in our brains and that we bind together like one does
with the sequence of photographs of a film into a mental movie.
And when it comes to the question of whether this macroscopic notion we call angular momentum makes
any sense at the fundamental level of the of the of an inherent reality of things like they are really
we must realize that we are speaking of useful interest, subjective qualities that, however, have
nothing to do with properties of an ontological reality.
In this sense, the spin of a particle stands to an objective reality, like the subjective experience
of the color of an object Stansel to the object itself.
What about quantum superposition?
This is aspect of quantum mechanics become so weird because we unconsciously equate the very elementary
concept of what we call a physical state of an object to a precise configuration of properties that
this object is supposed to inherently possess, but without being aware that these properties are our
own, just the proposed sense mind constructs.
When we say that the particle has a specific position in space, we are already working with an internal
representation of it, which mistakes mental projections like space and point like entities for real
properties of something that is out there, so to speak.
By doing so, we have already projected into ourselves a fiction of reality that is detached from reality
as it is.
In this sense, the position of a particle in space and time is no more or less objectively real than
its taste, smell or color.
Finally, we can't say with our limited sense mind abilities what a physical state of an object really
is in itself other than formulating it as a state of being.
Quantum states are states of being which we would like to project into a conception of a distinct and
unique spatial temporal relation of properties typical of the macro world, and that we are accustomed
to mapping into our brains.
However, a map does not say much about the territory.
The superposition of a quantum state is simply another state of being, of something that finds no correspondence
in our cognitive map because the reality we perceive with our bodily senses is always in an Afghan state.
To use a metaphor, again, we could compare it to the projection of the shadow of a cylinder on a two
dimensional surface, the measurement of an object in quantum superposition and its related way, function,
collapse or state reduction in quantum projection onto an Afghan state correspond in this analogy to
the projection of the cylinder into the figure of a circle or a square, as you can see in this figure.
At each measurement, we randomly get one or the other result, and we cannot understand how that could
be considered, that from the quantum mechanical point of view, the initial physical state of the object
is always the same.
The cylinder represents the real object in itself, in its state of being, in its essence, as it really
is.
Why are the two possible Two-dimensional figures that Square or the disc stand for the shadowy scientific
sense mind perspective that modifies and alters a projected experience into an abstract internal representation
which is inside of us and which no longer has anything of the essentiality proper to the measured object?
The random appearance of one or the other shape does not imply a modification of the original state
of the cylinder to force the system into an Afghan state means by analogy to maintain the orientation
of the of the cylinder with the direction of the light source.
Additionally, quantum entanglement appears somewhat less mysterious from the standpoint of the philosophical
idealist, our difficulty in accepting a state of being of something singular with no parts and distinctions
can be tracked back to the intrinsic disposition and natural cognitive function of the mind to distinguish,
particularize, dissect, divide and fragment in space and time for analysis and interpretation or what
it perceives all the things of the world.
A quantum entangled object without differentiation and distinguishable parts is in a state of being
which is inherently other and opposite to what the mind's function is able to apprehend.
Because my mind always particularize is fragments, the sex it is in its nature.
It is like trying to understand the meaning of a word by analyzing it in terms of phonemes.
If one is cognitively unable to bind together, sounds into a unique and undifferentiated perception,
the real meaning that the word represents will forever remain precluded.
A quantum entangled system is in a state of being of inherently unity in plurality.
Something that to the mind is self-contradictory and that cannot be reconciled, the principle of quantum
in this indistinguishably is an inherent state of being of electrons or particles.
It is the mind with its instinctive and natural function of separation and distinction that can follow.
At least for those who embrace a bit in this epistemological idealism and who do not regard mental constructs
as a representation of an inherent reality, it is not entanglement that constitutes a conceptual and
ontological problem.
Quite the contrary.
Once we accept that mental conceptions of space and time are mere projects and projections in our conscious
internal experience and that they have no substantial reality.
The question arises why does a fragmented universe appear to us at all in the first place?
Why isn't everything permanently entangled and undifferentiated state, why does this appearance of
fragmentation emerge in the first place?
This is a much more mysterious fact than the question which asked about things the other way around.
From the point of view of idealism, it becomes clear why the pervading and almost irresistible desire
to reduce everything to deterministic path of point particles is simply another sense.
Mind reification in us and does not represent an inherent aspect of reality as it is.
The very notion of a particle is a conceptual entity that arises due to a cognitive mental act of distinction
and separation that points dots on a mental screen of consciousness due to the interpretation of a sensorial
datastream.
But this is already a fiction created by a state of mind.
And a representation arising in our conscious experience and must not be mistaken for the inherent reality
of things.
Quantum uncertainty is a natural state of being, of things which become defined and determinant only
at the instant of the experimental measure, which is always and inevitably a mapping into a mental
representation based on distinction, reduction, division and separation.
We must come to the conclusion that just as we can't describe the physiology of a person's body by looking
at the shadow that the body projects, so can physics describe the inherent truth of things like Espin,
a path in spacetime, the position of a particle, or the notion of a particle itself as they are independent
of our sensorial perceptions and mental constructions, which are built up in abstractions that are
in turn based on the other sensory data and cognitive constructs.
The world we perceive is a symbol, everything we perceive is a symbol of what is experienced.
The question is no longer why microscopic things appear to be uncertain and resist being cast into a
reductionist worldview, but rather why an intrinsically undifferentiated whole allows itself to be
reduced to what we perceive at the macroscopic scale as being an extremely fragmented and definite reality.
Another intimately related question is, why should we regard quantum physics as a source of idealistic
considerations?
After all, this is a philosophical school of thought that existed long before the inception of quantum
physics itself.
As I already underlined and pointed out, since the times of ancient Greece, philosophers questioned
what reality is and the fundamental essence of things.
Philosophical idealism can also be discussed and defended inside a purely Newtonian paradigm, and one
does not need to resort to quantum mechanics.
The point, however, is that quantum mechanics let us a step further or many more steps further, I
would say, by confronting us with facts that clearly evidence how mental abstractions and constructions
are tools for practical purposes, but not represent not are not representations of an inherent reality.
Previously, we could still delude ourselves into regarding the appearances of the permanence and solidity
of a deterministic and predictable clockwork universe as the ultimately true properties that built up
and in here and in inherent in intrinsic reality, independent of our subjective perceptions and conceptions
of Newtonian mechanics and also Einstein's relativity are still in line with these unaware assumptions
and idealism seemed to be a distant philosophical remnant or romanticism.
However, if quantum mechanics is taken seriously, that is not just as a calculation tool or a theory
that we would like to see fall back to a naive Newtonian or Einsteinian deterministic realism, then
philosophical idealism in one form or another is inescapable.