Now that we have become accustomed with the concept of angular momentum, intrinsic angular momentum
of a particle point particle, that is the spin and know how these physical quantities can be measured
with D'Angela experiment and can be described with some simple Dirac connotation, it is time then to
analyze better the physical properties that result from the spin of particles and how these properties
then are encoded into an algebraic language.
To illustrate this, consider first these figures.
These pictures, this grass which depict in form of a block diagram the stangl device for the two possible
quantized measurement outcomes.
Here you see the saurus sense spin plus minus one half particles, saiz silver atoms or electrons or
whatever towards an estimate.
That device, which means a Garlock that measures along.
There's the measures, the spin along that Z axis is the electron is in that get plus or that get minus
spin and state it will be deviated towards the upper or lower part of the apparatus respectively.
Let us begin with a story that measurement outcome of the spin up electronic and construct in different
steps, the experimental procedure now we know just speak of electrons just to speak about quantum particles.
But let's think of electrons.
Begin with this diagram.
Physicist, speak of a system here, just a single particle prepared in the that Kate Plus Eigen state.
However, we are good experimentalists and want to be absolutely sure that when the electron went through
the asset, that device it stayed was not destroyed by the measurement itself and that it is still in
the that cat.
Plus I can state that.
And to do that, what what can we do?
We simply cascade another another S.G. that device, that is another stangl like device that again measures
along the same direction, in this case, that Z direction as in measurement be.
If we made no mistakes and our laboratory equipment worked fine, one would again observe the electron
coming out of the corresponding plus plus that output.
This is an experimental fact.
So we are sure that the measurement as such does not destroy the electrons intrinsic angular momentum
along the Z axis.
We feel therefore authorized to say that in fact the electron is in that particular spin up I can state.
However, the quantum world is a bit weird world, and things are not as easy as that.
To demonstrate this, let us extend our measurements along other directions.
Consider measurements, see as in this figure here, here, we first select again the electron with
that along that direction, and that is we prepare the system in the.
Said Kate Plus.
I can state so therefore, our electron has spin up along that direction with the first S.G., that
device, which measure measures the spin along that tracks and then sends it through another stangl
device.
But this time it measures not along that the headset, but along the x axis, the spinning perpendicular
x axis.
Therefore, we know what we do is that we put together.
Kaskade, the GST, that was the SGX device.
And therefore, one measures the spin along the X axis, to do that, one has only to appropriately
rotate the S.G. device magnets.
Think about how it is constructed.
What will be observed as output from the letter is from the letters last stand, Garlock is SGX device,
is that both spin XIENG states will show up.
That is, if you send several electrons through such a system of cascaded S.G. devices, you will have
a 50 percent, 50 percent chance of seeing it come out in a spin up and 50 percent chance of seeing
it in a spin down again state always.
This is something we can measure empirically with experiments.
Initially, you might have no problem with that, we may simply believe that of all the particles initially
prepared in the state, that plus Kate plus I can state 50 percent of them have an X, Kate plus spin
state I can state while the other 50 percent I am minus X X minus X minus except minus spin.
After all, we are dealing with two different spin directions that we think of as being independent
from each other, so their principal issue, I think there is no problem for our conventional classical
logic.
It sounds entirely legitimate to state that in preparing the system in the first stage along the Z axis
as a plus particle spin plus a particle without caring in what state it is along the X axis, it makes
sense that statistically we obtain 50 percent of the X Keat plus and X get minus particles at the end
of the chain.
And if our dangle like device is our idea and do not destroy the Igan states during any measurement
processes, we might effectively, effectively consider the electron that spins along the Z axis to
really be in a spin up state and along that axis, and there is no reason to believe otherwise.
This interpretation, however, will not hold up because the experimental evidence evidence will show
us otherwise.
In fact, we are scientists who want to be very cautious and maintain absolute certainty that the intrinsic
angular momentum along the Z axis is still there.
Therefore, we again now.
Append another S.G. device, this time along the that axis, we again measure the spin along the Z axis
of one of the outcoming particles of the measurement see say that will spin up right in the X, Kate
plus eight instead.
And we cascade another as that device, which measures measures a spin along that direction.
Again, as shown in this figure here of measurement, the.
What we will discover is now that the particles spin up against state along the Z axis is gone.
It is no longer determinate and becomes uncertain because again, sending many electrons, we have a
50 percent chance of getting the spin up or spin down state.
So it seems that along that axis, everything has been.
Mixed up again.
If you are not surprised about that, almost certainly you did not get the point.
So please go over the whole thing again, because for our classical understanding of the world, this
is a complete contradiction in measurement.
Be.
Didn't we twice measure that spin to ensure that the measurement did not destroy a particles intrinsic
angular momentum?
We can repeat the same experiment of measurement B with such as that S.G. X device cascading another
X, and we won't see any destructive activity along the X axis either.
If applied twice, it won't disturb the system, and yet if we first measure the spin along the Z axis
and along the X axis, we see that nature does not allow for that.
And by the way, if one would make the same experiments along the y axis and or in all its possible
combinations, the result will not change.
What all this tells us is that we cannot know at the same time the value of the spin along to Axis.
And again, this is independent from any interaction between the measuring apparatus and the particle.
It is important to keep in mind that this has nothing to do with the interaction between the observing
device and the observed object and even less with the supposed mind or consciousness of a human observer.
So does this remind you perhaps something it should, because here we have again a phenomenon which
is strongly reminiscent of Heisenberg's uncertainty principle.
In that case, the position and momentum were indeterminate.
There could not be measured at the same time.
Here they are, the spin's in the case of Heisenberg's uncertainty principle.
This is expressed with the position and momentum operators here, the spin operators along three directions
coming to the play.
However, the underlying principle is of the very same nature.
Namely, that the precise knowledge of one observable seems to be incompatible with certain knowledge
of another observable.
Once you measure one dynamic variable, you are no longer allowed to extrapolate anything about the
state of the previous one in general, once a measurement prepares a quantum system in a specific igan
state, that is, it projects the state better sign on to one of its igan basis vectors.
Uh, X squared plus minus or Y get plus minus or that get plus minus.
Then it also renders indeterminate the outcome associated with the other two igan states.
This automatically implies that the order in which the measurement is performed is important, is very
important.
It is not you cannot just change the order of the measurement without a potential possible effect on
it independently from the.
Interaction of the measurement apparatus of the measure with the measured object.
Performing a measurement on a quantum system, first with the observable as X, for example, and then
with that will not lead to the same result as that stemming from performing it first with the observable
as that and then as X.
This is because in the former case, the system is projected, say, in can state X plus X squared plus
with that.
Kate, plus minus and why, Kate, plus minus uncertain why in the latter case, the system is projected,
say, in Oregon State that Kate Black.
Plus with nothing that can be said about the ex plus minus, Kate plus minus.
And why Kate plus minus eight states in sign bulls.
This means that if we first operate with the appropriate asset on the state, function on the hour,
I better get my.
And then operate with as X, which means apply the stone Gerlach device along the Z direction and then
along the X direction.
This is not the same time.
This is not equal to applying.
First, the ASX operator and then the asset operator on the.
Same initial state capsid.
Or just.
Rewriting the same equation, you bring the right hand side of this equation on the left hand side,
you have this simple algebraic expression which tells us that in parenthesis as X times as that, minus
as that as X operating on the.
GABSI does not give the result.
The same applies to the other spin operator combinations such as as X, Y and S, Y and Z, physicists
and mathematicians say that the observables do not commute.
And express this, formerly, it was a former expression with the so-called commutation relation.
Written with a square square brackets, the commentators, that is for two generic generic operators,
a cap and B cap, the caps are symbols to distinguish operators from numbers that is scholars or vector
quantities from operate as operators from Scotland back to quantities.
The commentator is defined as connotation a cap.
B cap equal a cap.
B cap minus B cap a cap.
For example.
Here commentator ASX asset equals ASX asset minus asset ASX and so on is just an algebraic way to write
the same thing that we have explained above.
So when observables do not commute, this simply means that we can't know them both at the same time
and formally that computation relations do not commit.
The observers do not commute without going into too much into the algebraic details which would go beyond
the scope of this.
Of course it can be sure.
Let us only.
Say, hint, the fact that it can be shown that the spin commentators obey the following following rules,
the commentators of the ASX as that observer gives a quantity, I imagine that now in no age bar.
The plank's constant divide, two pi times the.
Spin operator along the way axis as why the same thing commutator of X, Y and Z is equal I, h, bar
X and X and the commentator of X and Y spin operators is equal.
I imagine there is no age bar as that, so you see that these operators are interchangeable in this
algebra, so to speak, it what this means is a bit because, again, a bit more beyond the scope of
this course.
But simply it is important to remember that simply these commentators do not give a zero result.
They give something else.
This allows us also to formally formulate Heisenberg's uncertainty principle itself, in the case of
the uncertainty principle, the position and momentum operators do not commute because as we know,
only one or the other observable, but not both can be determined with high precision.
One can show that if one applies the position and momentum operators consecutively on the wavefunction,
one will not obtain the zero result.
But again.
A quantity, which is the imaginary number times the Planck's constant, the bar divided to by.
Therefore, formally, Heisenberg's uncertainty principle is stated by the computational relation for
the position momentum observables in a three dimensional space as given the year.
So it's very similar to the spin operators.
But here we have the position and the momentum operator X and P or X, Y, Z and B, X, Y, Z, because
we are considering the three axis and the three dimensions.
And the commentators of these two operators give again something which is not a zero Skoller number,
but here a number, the imaginary number of times each bar.
Again, because this is a formal way to say you cannot you are not allowed to measure at the same time
the two observables, if you try to do that, things become fuzzy and your.
Values of your observations will become smeared out, so to speak.
Therefore, very in general, it is important to keep in mind the meaning of the commutation relations
and what visitors mean when they speak about observables that do not commute the nonzero nonzero commutation
relations, expressing the impossibility of establishing the value of two observables at the same time
is one of the most fundamental principles of quantum mechanics.
This is also the former mathematical expression of what is called the Borse complimentarity principle
when observables exists that we cannot know precisely at the same time they are complementary to each
other.
That's for both complimentarity principle.
However, this does not mean that observables never commute, there are observables that commute.
That is the commentator.
Computational relations result is zero.
This is the case when one measurement does not render the previous one uncertain.
You measure make two different measurements and there nothing becomes uncertain for that.
This is always the case with one observable with itself.
Now, we have already seen that, which is to say that same measure is made twice.
For instance, what we saw in the case B and this means that as the commutation or relation of as that
is equal to zero, quite obvious fact.
Otherwise we could not speak of igan states as states of a quantum system in the first place, states
and of quantum system in which a repeated measurement always provides the same answer.
I hope you get now the logic that stands behind all of this formalism.
Another example is that space operators, uh, for example, ex commentator x y is equal to zero, which
means that quantum mechanics allows for simultaneous determination of a particle position along the
three space axis.
Contrary to the case with the spin.
That's also why we must distinguish carefully the so-called spin space state, which is just a mathematical
algebraic notion from the position space, space, space states of a particle in three dimensional space.
What we have seen so far is one of the basic relations of the so called quantum algebra, it differs
from classical algebra because in the quantum world, the order of the product terms is no longer arbitrary
in classical physics or classical mathematics, if you wish to put it in there.
In that way, it is normal to think of numbers following commutative laws, for example.
No one would doubt that two times three equals six is the same as saying that three times two is also
six.
Not so in quantum mechanics, that is why in quantum mechanics, physicists and mathematicians were
forced to consider a completely new quantum algebra in a Hilbert space that is very different from the
math, describing classical Newtonian physics in standard real space.
The main difference is that in quantum mechanics, the objects of this algebra describing the dynamical
variables are no longer numbers or classical variables, but observables mathematical operators acting
on a complex wave function or state vector.
For this reason, they are sometimes also sometimes also called queue numbers, these patterns, instead
of the scene numbers, classical numbers, quantum numbers, classical numbers, despite not being numbers
at all.
This also answers the answer to the question of how physicists got to that strange and so fundamentally
different form of description compared to classical physics by taking them, by taking measurements
in the quantum domain.
Physicists were first led to formulate new laws, which they later encoded into a formal language,
not the other way around.
It is true that this quantum algebra was developed by great physicists and mathematicians in the 1920s
and 1930s, like John Norman, Erwin Schrodinger, then Heisenberg, McSporran, Paul Dirac and several
others, and has today reached a high level of sophistication.
However, its inception came into being not because of the application of common sense and logical rules,
but because of rock solid evidence.
Empiric experimental evidence of what the Garlock experiments have shown, as well as of other empirical
evidence of, of course.
Nature imposed it on us, the impossibility of establishing the value of two different quantum dynamic,
dynamic variables like to spin orientation, the orientation of an for for example, for an electron
is not a logical consequence of some phenomenon.
It is a given fact that has no classical parallel.
And even though classical logical reason to be it is as it is.
That's also why several textbooks entirely skip and ignore the S.G. experiments and posit instead as
basic axioms and approach that, if I may say Fev to me feels pedagogically detrimental because it skips
the conceptual physics standing behind it and presents quantum mechanics as nothing more than a mathematical
exercise.
At any rate, the great service of Stann and Gala was not just that of measuring the magnetic momentum
of a silver atom, but that of disclosing a weird quantum physical world to us, as well as that of
opening the way to a huge mathematical development which turned out to be extremely useful and which
is being theoretical and practical for it to this day.