In introducing some important concepts which will establish the foundation for further discussion on
which we will rely later, it is worthwhile to include a special section that extends the Garlock experiments
to non perpendicular spin directions.
Now, the natural question at this point is what happens if in the second measurement, instead of choosing
the x axis perpendicular to that, we opted for some other axis in between the two, say, at 45 degrees
instead of 90?
Half probability and half as much as half each bar, half angular momentum, or if we measure the spin
along a direction which is only slightly divergent from the Z axis, say only one degrees, will we
have still 100 percent certain certainty to get that cat plus or a little bit less?
And if so, how much less or more in general, what happens if for the second measurement, we measure
the spin along a direction tilted by an annotator relative to the that axis?
Let's label it the new axis.
There is no way to learn this other than experimentally.
And this can be done by smoothly rotating the second stangl magnet and one can measure.
So by doing so, the spin component not only along the 90 degrees axis, but along any orientation in
between by an arbitrary angle data as shown in the figure here, where for clarity, I display the same
block diagram of the previous slide.
Again.
But this time by labelling the second axis as U.
U instead of X, such an experimental setup allows us to measure how the probabilities vary to find
a spin up or spin down particle.
You will never get anything other than such a binary response, whatever angle you chose, you have
to remember this.
And by tilting the magnet by an angle theta between the Z axis and a new generic direction, the you
axis.
The source of particles in the first Asgeir magnets have only the function to produce, produce and
prepare a stream of particles in Eisenstaedt state.
That plus you could do the same thing also for that Cartman's.
But just for convention, just let us take let's take this as an example of interest.
Here is what the second is.
You device will measure along a generic U.
Tilted axis relative to the axis by tittered degrees.
So what will happen by doing so?
One obtains the probability distribution summarized in this graph.
Along the axis of the graph, which is this line here, there isn't a line we can trace that tilting
angle theta in degrees of the second as the magnets while on the ordinate axis, that is the vertical
axis here.
We can obtain the probability piece of data.
That is the probability of getting a spin up or spin down measurement result in function of that angle.
Let us briefly discuss this in more detail.
Now, consider the EU oriented as the first one that is with Enel data equals zero.
We are dealing then with the same situation we already examined, namely that of having two consecutive
S.G. that devices with output that plus and we know that twice measuring the particle in angst etcetc
plus along the same, that axis does not change anything.
We will obtain with certainty P equals one the particle to be in that cat plus state where whereas with
no chance at all you p equals zero of getting that cat minus state particle even through repeated measurements.
Let us now change only by a little bit.
The orientation of the EU relative to the Z axis, say by one degree.
Then one would not expect much change.
Taking repeated measurements.
One will still get in almost all the cases, a particle in a spin upstate along the slightly tilted
you axis.
That is the you get plus state.
However, on a very on very few occasions.
You get minus will appear as well, after many measurements, it will turn out that on average, only
about seven or eight particles out of 100000 will show up with a spin down state.
This corresponds to an almost certainty, certainty of an almost certain probability for the spin up
of.
B equals zero nine nine nine nine two four probability.
So almost certainty.
I just tell that it is not displayed here.
Tilting the EU further say setting data equal 45 degrees that is in between the two perpendicular axis
will, however, definitely change things.
About 85 percent will still be in spin up, but the remaining 50 percent will show up with a spin down.
While four states are equal, 90 degrees, which is the measurement, again, of the spin state, Peralta's
positively directed X-axis that we we saw previously the probability to find one or the other, then
state, of course, 50 percent, as you should know well by now, and which, of course, is nothing
other than what the equation with equal probabilities told us, that with the one over two square two
factors that told us, as you might remember, once the SGU magnets are rotated by 180 degrees to each
other, they are then a. parallel to the exact axis.
And the second stangl at magnets looks for that cat minus particles.
Obviously, though, nothing comes through, we have P equals zero because they were all prepared in
that that Kate plus eight in St..
Then continuing again for a degrees, we are in the same situation as that for the 90 x 90 degrees x
axis, but with the magnets aligned in the opposite direction, direction, measuring for looking for
the X minus particles.
Finally, a full rotation of 360 degrees brings us back to the original parallel set axis measurement.
So from these follow a couple of summarizing considerations which are necessary and necessary to keep
in mind to try to avoid later confusion first, don't forget that with whatever angle one measures has
been, it will always be has been up or spin down, each of which has an intrinsic angular momentum
of plus or minus each paragraph, but never half or a fraction of it.
The rotation of the S.G. device does not change the amount of angular momentum measured.
It changes on the probability of finding the particles in one or the other.
I can state it will never measure a different angular momentum.
And this is the point which is very contrary to classical mechanics in quantum mechanics.
From whatever angle you look at a spin, this remains a democratized.
And quantized observable, secondly, recall that this is only a statistical and probabilistic prediction.
A prediction that.
May be also violated.
We are talking only about probabilities.
This is a curve, a continuous curve, not quantize curve, which, however, deals with quantized quantities.
This means that only four P equation or P equals zero.
Do you have absolute certainty of observing or not a certain spin value while in all the other cases
there could well be statistical fluctuations?
For instance, for theta equal 45 degrees, you may sometimes have a bit more or less than 50 percent
spin down particles slipping through the S.G. device.
Where do these random fluctuations come from?
In quantum physics, randomness appears to be an intrinsic feature, something with no causes, as if
randomness is without a hidden cause, that is without hidden variables.
We will return to this important point later when we will discuss Bell's theorem theorem.
So what does this graph finally show us?
It looks wavy, doesn't it?
Indeed, we are again dealing with a probability wave.
It is like the wave function in the double slit experiment.
On that occasion, a wave function seemed to spread throughout space from the slits and interfere on
the detector screen, the squared models of which represented a probability distribution.
We questioned whether it was a real object or simply a calculation tool.
Here we again have probability, but we cannot associate it with anything we might imagine as an entity
moving in space and time, it is simply the probabilistic description of a particle having a spin up
or spin down.
It turns out that the curve and the previous figure is directly proportional to the cosine squared function
of half the tilting angle, that is this formula here, the probability that the to measure Espin up
in this case, this is a.
Particular example that we have done, but you can apply this to any angle or direction is that the
P in function of data, the probability and the function of data is given by the causing the cosine
squared of theta half.
In physics, one formalizes this was an elegant formalism that puts all three igan states along a preferred
that axis into one single description.
For the sake of simplicity, let us restrict ourselves to that.
Explain.
Let us place for completeness, the queen cosine squared probability equation here again.
And now the final spin up and spin down along that axis, as with a formula, formalism reminiscent
of vectors and Cartesian two-dimensional plates, as we have already seen with this Spiner components.
This so-called spinous, which, again, we should distinguish from the two dimensional Cartesian plane.
But again, note that they represent, in any case, orthogonal quantum state matters.
Uh.
Recall how this product of orthogonal vectors is always zero, and this is something of this sort here
where you have this color product of plus and minus get vectors along the Z axis in Spiner Coordinates
is given as the complex conjugate of the first Spiner one zero and which is written horizontally the
other vertically.
They are summed up according to the product rules and laws and and and properties and you have it equal
zero.
This is simple.
Algebra, linear algebra that you will find in every linear algebra textbook, and you probably many
of you may have done this also at school, then the two Spiner equations, which still represent only
two cases, the orientation for theta equals zero and data equals a hundred eighty degrees can be generalized
to any anger in a single state as this one here.
This object here, capital letters, are of wire of data.
Why are Y of data is a rotation matrix which rotates the one zero Spiner.
About a half about data and gives as output accused half data sign-off data Spiner, it is rotation
matrix which transforms the spine of one zero into the spinal.
Because I wanted to have signed that sign that I have rotating it about the y axis and.
It represents a transformation which is induced by the rotation of the.
S.G. magnets, these S.G. magnets perform a transformation on the state side.
So any any on the state, that cat plus and return as a result, the state better say, um, this is
a transformation.
It might look like an observable acting on Spiner one zero that is on that cat.
Plus, however, there is a subtle but the size of difference between transformation and an observation.
And this, therefore, the rotation matrix does not really represent an observable.
It is just.
An object, a mathematical algebraic object, which represents the transformation of the state spectrum,
will go into this subtlety later on.
But for now, just remember that it is the rotation matrix is a transformation matrix, not a real observable.
Then applying Bond's rule that is taking the model square of the state to say that we have given here
gives, then finally as a result, the probability of having a specific outcome in our case led to observe
a spin up particle, having rotated the Dan Glickman magnets by Ted that decrease the probability of
theta equals the square of the bracket of PSI and which is obviously the cosine square that the have
over sine squared at the half.
This tells us that there is a Cusanus square, a high probability of measuring Espin up particle along
an arbitrary direction, rotated relative to the Z axis of teta degrees.
If it has prepared the Z Kate Plus State in line with the graph of the previous light and equiv, equivalently,
sine squared 35 probability of measuring Espin down particle if it has been prepared in the set minds
and state.
The sum of the squared sine and cosine cosine functions always give independently from the angle one.
Well, this is a normal algebraic identity.
The cosine, cosine squared plus sine squared is always equal, one that is certainty as it should be,
because it sums up over all possible outcomes.
That is also why any transformation that transforms a state vector or wavefunction, maintaining the
total probability invariant equal that is equal to one goes by the name of unitary transformation.
Recall from what we have seen in the lecture on the state vector observables Schrodinger equation,
how we defined there in that occasion and unitary operator, I read it here again, namely as an operator
you that acts on the initial state function on time zero in such a manner that it evolves the state
vector forwards or backwards in time.
To a time T. But that leaves and alters the model, the square, that is the sum of all the probabilities
of the possible outcomes.
That is, it must be still one.
And from which we follow the complex conjugate of the unitary operator, U.
Times itself is equal the identity identity operator.
So loosely speaking, we can say that the tilting of the Tangela magnets acts on the system of particles
quantum particles.
By unitary transformation.
It transforms one state into the other, making one outcome less probable, but the other outcome more
probable.
But the sum of the probabilities remains the same.
And this is called unitary transformation represented algebraically by this unitary operator.
You capital letters.
All this could in principle be also extended to the Weich plus minus 18 states, but we will not get
into this subject here.
It's just would be just a repetition.
It may only be said that a comprehensive treatment leads to a beautiful, very beautiful algebra, which
paved the way to a phenomenal mathematical development in quantum theory group theory representations
and also so-called algebra's in quantum physics spins with its Spinosaurus are represented by the so-called
special unitary group in two dimensions the the S.
U two group, and which represents all the transformations that preserve the length of two dimensional
complex vectors, which after all, reduces to what we already have said, the conservation of probability.
However, don't dare to imagine this sort of rotation of complex vectors.
It is a sort of weird three dimensional rotation inside a four dimensional space.
So but this is now would be a very tricky issue of, uh, geometry, multidimensional geometry, and
that we will not go into here from.
This will also follow some very curious facts about the notion of rotation in the quantum world.
And this is precisely what we will illustrate in the coming lecture.