As an exercise, it is instructive to play around with the Spiner or Spiner representation of the Spine
One-half particle with different angles, data or data.
Well, in the previous lecture I called it Spiner, but the correct pronunciation is Spiner, not Spiner.
But I like the word Spiner.
I don't know why.
Uh, at any rate, I will try to remember that I should call it Spiner.
My apologies for that.
So let us take up.
From the from the equation on the lecture on Spinner's this equation here and which tells us something
about the state of the particles spin once it has been rotated or transformed here around the Y axis
by a certain amount of degrees.
Tita.
If we said to equal 90 degrees, that is we rotate the spin.
State vector, said Kate Plus.
That was spin vector indicating along that axis, as you know, and tilt it by 90 degrees relative to
the Z axis around the Y axis as shown in the figure here, then we transform the particle state into
a XCAP plus state that is one spinning around the x axis.
And the corresponding state vector will therefore be this one here.
So we rotate it set again, state into an X and state.
In fact, the cosine and sign of 45 degrees are both the same one over square two.
And we can therefore write the resulting state vector as one of squared two times one one, and which
is the sum of the corresponding that get plus and that minus state.
Just add these two quantities here together and multiply with one over square to.
This should not come as a surprise.
We know that once a particle is in an iron state here, the X plus the same state must be represented
as a superposition state along the other axis.
This is a natural consequence of the commutation relations.
We know that the spin operators do not commute and therefore one cannot determine the spin along other
directions at the same time, which means that once you transform the system into another, I can state
here from the Z Kate Plus to the X Kate Plus.
I can state then its former spin state here again that that plus must become undetermined.
And we will obtain 50 percent chance of observing the dead cat plus or that cat mindstate, which in
a certain sense is gone, this should become slowly clear to you, since this is nothing else than restating
in another way what we have already seen with this Garlock experiments and the computational relations,
therefore.
It must be described with a state function as a superposition of these two possible outcomes along that
axis.
What is more precisely meant by superposition was the superposition principle.
We will explain in more detail in coming lectures.
Meanwhile, let us see how all this implies another weird phenomenon of the quantum world.
It is, at least for me, one of the most alien facts to be confronted by our naive human understanding,
which is totally incomprehensible for our intuitive daily, three dimensional life experience.
Check out what happens when you make a complete rotation that is set to equal 360 degrees, if we set
360 degrees, that is we make.
We believe to make a complete rotation, one does not get back with that plus that that cat plus state,
but obtains a minus that cat plus with a minus sign in front of it.
Instead, you must rotate it twice for an angle of 720 degrees to get back the island state.
That cat plus.
Please do not confuse the minus sign in front of the cat, which simply indicates a subtraction operator
with a plus or minus signs in the spin state vector, which as usual, stands for the spin up or spin
down state, respectively.
Yeah.
In fact, not that one can also ride, minus that Kate Plus is equal to the oil and Amber.
Power I buy, which is the imaginary number times, by this time the same.
Vector, I'm state vector that could last if you are not accustomed with complex Imagineer numbers and
the unit circle in the complex domain, please see the appendix lecture, which describes complex numbers
in which the nodes with this little minus a phase shift of the wavefunction by PI radians or equivalently
by 180 degrees more on this next.
Now therefore, this should not be confused with that minus Keat state.
That is the minus.
That gateless state is not equal that that minus get state one is the spin up and the other is spin
down state.
And it is not about switching from one spin state to another, but there is yet a little minus in front
of the plus spin state.
It is a 180 degrees phase shift.
Off the state function.
What this means, according to this binary representation, is that one must perform several hundred
twenty degrees rotation to attain the same speed again physically.
This amounts to saying that electrons, protons and neutrons as all fermions, the spin one-half particles
must be rotated by at 720 degrees or four pi radians angle to return to their identical initial state.
Only with two full rotations will you get back the original object.
If you are wondering how this could be explained according to an intuitive geometrical understanding.
Well, forget about it.
It is simply a fact, a physical datum that hardly any normal human being will ever understand.
I am afraid, at least I don't.
However, mathematically, it is a natural consequence of group theory.
When one works with complex instead of real numbers mathematically call it that.
It is called the double cover symmetry of the S02 group and which again confirms the powerful application
of math and physics against all our preconceived ideas of what the world is supposed to look like.
Nevertheless, analogies might help our intuition.
Visualize what is going on here.
A typical example of an object with a 720 symmetry is a famous Mobius strip.
It is obtained by cutting a band and giving one of the two ends a half twist and then attaching the
two ends.
The Mobius band or maybe a strip is quite famous.
Probably you have already seen it.
And this figure shows how a Mobius strip changes the orientation after one full rotation.
Simply follow the small arrows on the boundary at the tip indicated by the large arrows parallel displaced
on the surface after 360 rotation 360 degrees rotation one does not reach the initial point, but travels
from the tip to the bottom of the arrows.
Another full rotation is needed to return the original place where the small errors meet again and regain
their original orientation.
This is just an analogy that even though it cannot display the full picture of a four dimensional rotation,
it helps one intuitively to grasp the spin or rotation of property.
At any rate, one should refrain from thinking of spinners as being vectors spinning on the unit circle.
One might also ask whether the last full rotation that transformed that cat plus into a minus that cat
plus has any physical significance.
After all, what we really measure experimentally is not the state factor, but it's squared modulus,
which informs us about the probability of obtaining certain eigenvalues.
As you should know by now, the sign in front of the Dockett might seem therefore irrelevant because
the square of a negative sign.
All gives a positive number, so to speak, disappears anyway.
This belief is, unfortunately, something one finds also in textbooks, not only is this belief wrong,
but as we will see later, this seemingly insignificant minus sign is the manifestation of one of the
most fundamental laws of nature, the Pauli exclusion exclusion principle, without which the entire
universe would collapse into an undifferentiated amalgam on and perhaps not even exist, at least not
as we know it.
In general, a phase shift of a wavefunction.
Fireworks, fireworks by an angel titre is given by the prime of X equals oil, a number that is fascia
and power I data that is facelift applied on the same way.
Function of X again in the appendix.
I discussed this a bit more in detail.
Recall what we have said about the importance of a way of space.
The destructive or constructive interference between two ways, between two ways depends on their relative
face.
Not only are waves characterized by their amplitude and wavelength or frequency, but especially when
they are interfering with each other, they must be described using their face component.
That's the principle on which the good old young double slit experiment works with this you already
know very well by now.
Therefore, the minus sign in front of the full rotated, that cut-price that get plus I can stay tells
us that it must be thought of as the same state, but face shifted.
So subprime effects and side effects are not the same mathematical object they represent, two waves
shifted to each other.
But the point is that once the state expression is model squared to obtain with the usual born rule,
the outcome probability, any a shift is truncated and one might believe that it is plays no role,
however, because phases play an extremely important role in interval interference phenomena.
One might wonder if the strange properties of Spinner's has can be detected by some experiment which
uses, uh, interference.
And therefore, if it can be detected, might have any physical reality and could lead to physical effects.
Or is it just a mathematical abstraction?
The answer is that it is a real physical phenomenon and that could be observed in neutron interference
into parametric experiments.
Neutrons are fermions like electrons, but with no electric charge, therefore, they are easier to
handle in experiments involving interference from other phenomena because they do not interact with
the rest of the environment.
Moreover, neutrons are about 800 times more massive than electrons, and they're liberally wavelength
is much smaller.
When they travel, travel at the same speed, they have the same momentum which allows for high precision
measurements.
If a neutron is sent through to Perth, as was done with photons in the double slit experiments and
one performs a rotation on the neutron travelling along one path, say, with the magnet, like in the
S.G. experiments, the change in the interference pattern should be observed.
And in fact, this figure illustrates a neutron interferometer which uses three slices of silicon crystals,
the Dasht vertical lines.
And which the frat's the new Transmeta ways, as we explained, with the black diffraction experiments,
so the years we should not imagine here being pece, there are no paths in the classical sense, as
you should know by now, but only the propagation of spherical probability waves.
However, once a detector clicks, one can buy naïf retroactive or reverse engineering reasoning, imagine
the upper or lower pass, the oblique, oblique dashed lines as a trajectory the neutron has taken according
to one or the other.
Detector clicking.
You can say that Newton when the upper or lower pass and this that's also what you will find frequently
in the literature.
Where they show only the path, not the spherical wave propagating.
Here instead, imagine the neutrons wavefunction incident on the first slice and being directed by the
crystalline lattice.
Creating, therefore, an almost or approximately very good plane wave and which then is deflected again
at the second crystalize.
At the second layer, the new Transmeta wave sees, so to speak, the analog of the young doublets that
photons see.
And so to speak, then at the southerlies, the two metal waves interfere constructively or destructively
or something in between.
And since it is easier to detect the signal neutrons with clicking detectors and this southerlies works
as a beam splitter, that is, it separates the incident.
Neutron beams again in two directions with 50 percent probability towards the respective detectors.
Assume the two pass having exactly equal length.
Doing this is not at all an easy task from a practical point of view, because you have to align the
slices with exactly billions, the tens of billions of a meter.
And technically this is a quite challenging task, but not impossible can be made.
So this figure shows the case with no face shift induced on the two path.
An interference pattern forms along the vertical direction parallel to the crystal slices on the plane
where the detectors are placed there.
The upper detector, which is placed at an ATM in the ference fringe, always registers a neutral particle.
The other detector be in a position where no fringe's is measurable, therefore never clicks.
Instead, the same situation is shown, but with a little magnet.
Put in place in the.
Correct position inducing a phase shift on one of the possible neutron path effect magnet magnetic fields
always shift wavefunction phases.
That is, they cause Spiner rotation.
Is already strange enough for a neutron, since being an electrically neutral particle, we don't expect
it to have a magnetic moment.
Recall how magnetic fields are always caused by circulating electric currents.
This, however, only signals how the internal structure of a spinning neutron must be composed by electrically
charged particles, the quarks, which however from the outside, cancel, cancel each others field
and results to be apparently neutral.
At any rate, this is a detail that is not so decisive here, what is essential is that the existence
of a magnetic field induces a phase shift on the particles wavefunction.
This phase shift is proportional to a static magnetic fields extension and or strength through which
the particles travels.
As stangl device also induces a phase shift on the particle it measures.
Therefore, by modulating appropriately a magnetic field, one can induce on the neutron beams the desired
defacing on its way function.
The wavefunction we labeled as SIPRI.
It turns out that after 360 shift, the place on the neutral detection screen where previously without
the magnetic phase shift, the bright Frenches fringes appeared is now occupied by dark fringes and
vice versa.
This full rotation 360 degrees shift causes the interchange of the detectors to click.
Now it is the second detector that clicks, why the first does not reveal any more Newton's.
That is, if one shifts by one full turn, the face of the wavefunction, one does not obtain the same
interference pattern to obtain the same interference pattern, it is necessary to shift the way functions
face by 720 degrees instead of 360.
This was the experimental proof that showed that the spin phase factor of particles is important.
It counts later.
We will find further proof of this in the Aronoff bomb effect.
Meanwhile, we can say yes, spin one half particles live in a weird seven hundred twenty degrees world.
This, however, only true for spin one, particles, electrons, neutrons, protons, not so full for
photons as we are going now to see.