The cosine squared spin orientation, probability distribution emerging from the Stangl experiments
did not really come as a surprise to physicists.
Something quite similar was well known much earlier than the advent of quantum physics by observing
the behavior of polarized light.
We already hinted at the property of polarization that an electromagnetic wave can have in case of a
vertically polarized electromagnetic wave.
We said that the vector of the propagating propagating electric field oscillates along a vertical y
axis perpendicular to its direction of propagation.
However, usually light from natural sources is not polarized.
There is no preferred playing along which the electric field of a beam of light is polarized.
It is allowed to oscillate along all possible directions and and polarized source of light emits electromagnetic
electromagnetic waves randomly as shown, for instance, here.
However, it is possible to filter out polarised light from an unauthorized source polarizers our optical
filters that allow only a specific polarization to pass through and absorb or reflect any other, not
be confused with wavelength filters that select specific wavelengths of wavelengths intervals.
They these polarizers could be made of special crystal glass plates, thin films, metallic metallic
wire grids and so forth, which can all perform a polarizing function on light.
Polarizing filters are used in camera lenses and photography, as you probably know, or in sunglasses,
as you probably also know, to avoid an unwanted reflections.
Dark skies suppress glare from the surface of a body of water and so on.
A relatively simple type of polarizer is a wire grid, wire grid polarizer made of many fine parallel
metallic wires on a plane which filters out linearly, linearly polarized electromagnetic wave with
the electric field papen perpendicular to the wires as shown in the figure.
Once polarised light of intensity, let's label it I zero capital letters, the I zero, and once this
is obtained with this filter, this first filter, a second polarizer can be added to them.
The polarized beam, the first polarization of electromagnetic waves of photons is analogous to the
selection performed by the first STEM Galla device on the electrons that we saw in the previous lectures
and it selects which selected it the spin along a specific orientation.
However, here, instead of selecting out the electrons with the spin up, I can state it is the photons
with the specific polarization, not not their spin polarization, which are filtered out along one
preferred direction.
Similarly, the second polarizer acts in a way similar to that which we saw with the second S.G. device
on electrons.
If it is oriented along the same direction of the first polarizer, it simply lets the same photon and
its paralyzation ion state pass through through the polarizer with 100 percent probability.
The question then is whether and how the so let's call it dimming factor.
Uh, dependent on the and the rotation of the second light polarizer for photons is comparable, comparable
to the squared cosine probability law we discussed earlier for the electron spin.
Again, the answer cannot be derived from logical reasoning, but must come from empirical data by measuring
how the intensity of the outcome of the outcoming beam depends on the relative orientation by an angle
Twitter or data of the two polarizers.
One obtains the following the following graph.
Also this time, as you can see, the intensity varies according to a squared cosine law.
But and this is of paramount importance to keep in mind with a teacher with an angle.
Peter instead of Peter have.
It has to have dependence, for instance, it takes 90 degrees rotation to stop the electromagnetic
beam instead of the 180 necessary that we saw for the electrons, compare this graph with the one we
obtained for Fermín particles, and I will depict it also in the next slide.
And this graph summarizes the so-called law.
It is the intensity in the independence of data is equal I zero the entrance intensity, the initial
intensity times this squared.
Kozin.
Off Teater not to have.
It can be seen as a natural consequence of the fact that the polarizer simply selects out only the vertical
component of the electric electric field vector tilted by 32 degrees relative to the vertical axis.
In fact, by simple trigonometric considerations, the cosine of the original wave amplitude remains
and the and to obtain the intensity, one has only to square it.
So.
At first, there is nothing particularly strange or quantum in this phenomenon.
It is two centuries old knowledge that light can be polarized.
The French physicist Etienne Louis Mallows discovered this law in 18 or nine.
But considering what has been discovered in the time since, especially comparing photons with the fermions
behavior, we can recognize interesting facts about both.
Let us translate what we have acquired so far into a corpuscular picture in point like particle picture,
so to speak.
Since the probability of a photon going through a polarizer is nothing else than the proper proportionality
factor of the number of transmitted photons eye versus the incident, photons eye zero, that is B equals
I over eight zero.
Then Miloslav amounts also to saying that the probability of a single photon passing through the polarizer,
the second polarizer is simply the cosine squared lower piece of data.
Theta equals cosine square squared detA.
Nowadays, this can be checked directly, it is possible to dim the light source to such a degree that
only one photon at a time goes through the polarizers.
Recall how we have already seen this for the double slit experiment, and one can count the single photon
with a clicking detector detector that simply clicks for each single photon on the other side at and
count this one at a time.
By doing so, one discovers that in fact, the probability which the detector clicks follows a cosine
squared law.
With this we re-establish the the the wave particle duality again.
One can take the classical point of view of the classical physicists like Marlos did, who assumed assumed
light to be a wave.
The polarizer in this case does not block the wave entirely entirely, except, of course, for 90 degrees
orientation, but simply dampens it.
Whereas from the corpuscular perspective, from the particle point like perspective, there is no dimming,
only a cutting the number of photons allowed to get through the polarizer without reducing the single
photons energy.
However, the single photons energy.
Is always the same, remains the same, by rotating the polarizer and dimming the flux of photons,
I only reduce the number of photons, not their energy, the photons.
The single the single photon passes or does not pass, that is is absorbed or eventually reflected when
it does not pass, but you will never register half a photon, for example, also for eighty nine point
nine degrees.
That is almost by complete dimming the flux of photons.
There are on average, still three photons out of a million, which will pass the polarizer.
But once there will have managed to go through, these will be exactly like the incoming photons along
our journey.
We will later discover how the marlos law will lead to one of the most unexpected consequences for our
world view.
It is the death sentence for any local and realistic hidden variable theory.
But until the 1960s, this was something far from obvious.
Other principles, facts and foundational issues had to be clarified first.
An important question and at this point is why do we measure for photons and Teater instead of a two
1/2 squared cosine dependence, as we saw for electrons?
Recall that for the intrinsic momentum of an electron and that of all odd half integrase spin particles,
the so-called fermions named after the Italian physicist Enrico Fermi, one gets through any measurement
of the spin component that is the eigenvalue associated to the eigenvector state.
Always spin of the electron here as capital letters E minus equals plus minus H half, which is plus
minus H over for PI where this little four pi is nothing other than the than a 720 angle in radians.
Planck's constant H is a natural constant and is derived experimentally as you know with the photoelectric
effect and the spin s e c minus is also not something that can be derived but must be measured experimentally.
For example, as we know with a S.G. device, the fact that just H and as have an inverse for PI proportionality,
which is related to the 720 rotation reflect reflected in the squared cosine of T Tav instead of TITRE
is not a mere convention, but reflects some deep principle that is imposed by nature.
Therefore, since four photons which are part of a class of the so-called bosun's named after the Indian
physicists, General Boser, we have the same cosine squared intensity.
But for a Teater dependent's that is normal 360 degrees full rotation, it is a plausible assumption
that the photons intrinsic angular momentum amounts to plus minus H bar.
It is as gamma equals plus minus H bar, which is equal H.
Planck's constant divided to PI instead of four pi or in other words, photons do us the favor of living
in a less weird world.
They perceive rotation's as we humans do.
More generally, one can state that the spin value of a particle reflects the kind of rotational real
it lives in, we can extend this reasoning by predicting that spin to spin three etc particles need
only 180 degrees, 120 degrees and so on rotations to bring them back into the same quantum state while
spin three have spin five, five, etc particles will they will need less rotation, not more, namely
240 degrees and at 44 degrees and so on.
Rotations to look again the same as in the initial state before the rotation.
Finally spin zero particles never change for any angle.
One chooses to look up them.
They look always the same.
Independently from the direction upon which we look on them, since they have no momentum.
Veterans are in the first place.
However, nature seems to restrain itself, since all non particles are Aspinwall have plus minus half
of particles, that is fermions, the so-called leptons and quarks or spin one particles, most bosons,
for instance, the photon, and with only one spined zero particle, the famous Higgs boson, that kind
of particle one uses to say that it gives mass to the balls to make it become material and make it make
part of the so-called so-called standard model of particle physics physics that then there is also the
graviton that is the particle supposed to mediate the gravitational force and is predicted to have spin
to while other speculative speculative prizes, theoretical particle speculative particles like those
predicted by so-called supersymmetry theories are believed to possess other spin values eventually as
well.
But these have not been detected so far, despite intense research and might be possibly not exist.
And all the theory supersymmetry, super gravity, super string theory might be probably a wrong theory.
The world we perceive with our human senses is therefore dominated almost exclusively by spin one and
one half and spin two particles.
Also the Higgs boson if you wish.
But this has lifetimes of the order of 10 to the power of minus 22 seconds.
That is billions of billions and thousands of billions of billions of seconds.
And it is way beyond human perception.
But how must we intend the photons spin so far?
We discussed only about paralyzation.
The polarization of the photon, which, however, is not to be confused with the spin, another main
difference between the spin of massive particles and that of massless particles such as light particles,
the photon is that the letter has not only two possible spin states, but also only two possible spin
orientations, namely that along the direction of propagation or opposite to it, one says that a photon
has Felicity.
Hilly city, which tells us whether the spin is aligned or anti aligned with the momentum that is its
speed direction.
It cannot have a spinning axis directed, say, at 90 degrees perpendicular perpendicular to the direction
of motion.
This is another difference between classical mechanics and quantum physics.
In classical physics, an object must not necessarily rotate around the direction of its most motion
in space.
I think, for example, of the Earth.
It has a north South Pole not at all directed along the orbital path.
In general, a particle is said to be right handed, that is, have positive Telecity if the spin and
momentum are parallel.
While it is said to be left handed that have that that that means they have negative publicity if the
spin and momentum are anti parallel.
So each individual photon will have its spin either along the direction of motion or against it, other
spin, their actions are not allowed.
The conceptual connection between waves and photons with their positive or negative publicity is realized
by the electric field rotation of circular, so-called circular, polarized electromagnetic waves.
So instead of being vertically paralyzed or not paralyzed at all, we are speaking now of circular polarization.
Circular polarization means that the direction of the electric field vector rotates with time at a steady
rate in a plain.
Perpendicular to the direction of the wave propagation.
For right circular polarization, the electric field vector rotates in a right handed SiSense with respect
to the direction of propagation.
Just use your right hand with the thumb pointing towards the direction of propagation of the propagation
of the wave and the fingers wrapping the anticlockwise movement of the black arrow, the electric vector
field, and you will get the right circular polarization of the electromagnetic field while for the
left circular polarization, the electric field vector rotates in left hand side, which means that
you have to use your left hand and doing the same thing, as I just mentioned.
The photons of counter clockwise, right, polarised light, Kerry, and angular momentum of as gamma
equals plus H bar along the direction of flight.
When light is clockwise, less polarized, the photons instead carry an angular momentum of as gamma
equals minus H bar along the flight direction.
Finally, note how in the case of linearly polarised light, photons can be considered to be in a state
of superposition of the right and left, circular polarization geometrically.
This sounds almost obvious.
Adding together two vectors, spinning with the same angular frequency, but in the opposite directions
will give as a result a still standing vector.
It does move, but is.
It indicates a linear polarization.
What this precisely means and implies from a quantum perspective will be clarified next, where we will
expressly discuss the principle of quantum superposition position and which will turn out to be one
of the most fundamental concepts of quantum mechanics.