Until now, we have been studying
mostly quantum theories and
physical phenomena, which were
discovered a relatively long time ago.
So I think maybe the latest theoretical
development we talked about,
the path integral itself,
goes back to the 40s, 1940s.
Today in this video,
towards the end of the video,
I'm going to tell you about a more
recent theoretical development,
so-called theory of quantum localization,
or more precisely, weak localization.
And I will do so using the main
ideas of the Feynman path integral.
So I should mention that the full theory
of quantum localization is an extremely
complicated mathematical theory, and it
could be a subject of a separate course.
So I don't have time for
that, and obviously,
we don't have the mathematical sort
of background to talk about it.
But it turns out that some basic
ideas behind this phenomenon
can be understood using
the basic concepts behind
the Feynman path integral,
which comes handy here.
So just in a few words, what I'm going to
be talking about here is the following.
So we know that in solid state physics,
materials
sort of can be divided into roughly
two categories, insulators and metals.
There are also semi conductors,
but from this perspective,
they are much like insulators.
What insulators are, if you apply
with electric field, the electrons,
which is just inside the material,
don't move.
And so, there's no current really in
response to electric field, so if you
think about a piece of wood or something
like that, so we obviously understand it's
an insulator, it's not going to be
a very useful electric component.
On the other hand, if you have a metallic
system, let's say a piece of copper, and
if we apply electric field, or a voltage,
there will be current in response to
this electric field, and so
this characterizes a metal.
So and then in your real material,
whether it's an insulator, a metal,
there is some imperfections.
Disorder, impurities, dislocations,
all kinds of things, and this,
in metals, these impurities and
dislocations, etc, so
these imperfections,
they lead to a finite resistance, okay?
And so, first in the next slide,
I will tell you about how this
resistance comes about, but later on,
we will see how the essentially classical
theory of transport that applies to
most metals at high temperature get more
defied as you go to lower temperatures.
And at low temperatures,
quantum effects come into play.
The way of nature, for
instance, comes into play.
And this is very interesting.
And it turns out that under
certain circumstances,
you can get completely different
heat at low temperatures.
The nipples, actually,
would become insulators.
And this process of trapping the electrons
due to quantum mechanical effects is
called localization.
So of course, it's a very mathematical
theory as I told you, but
we will try to get some idea
about where it comes from.
But before discussing
a complicated quantum theory,
let me first talk about a basic classical,
very simple theory of how we
can understand electrical
transferred in a metal.
So here,
this black dot labels an electron,
which can move around in a piece of metal,
and these red dots here, larger dots,
they represent some impurities,
of which the electron gets scattered.
And that's exactly what it
does is it moves it around, so
it gets scattered by these red impurities,
and
so the trajectory of this electron
is this diffuser trajectory.
So, the random walk.
Of course, it's not just one.
There are many, many electrons in
the metal, and they all experience
this random walk, which in the absence of
an electric field just averages out to 0.
There is no net current,
there is no preferential direction.
There is nothing which
breaks the symmetry.
But now if we, let's say, apply electric
field in this direction, the electrons,
which have a negative charge,
are going to move in the opposite
direction preferentially.
They are still going to move around in
all directions, but there will be sort of
a drift in one particular direction,
and this will give rise to a current.
Now it turns out that
the first theory of this
conductivity of this current in
the metal was put together back in 1900.
And this theory is
the so-called Drude theory,
which is a very simplistic theory
that I'm going to explain now.
So basically,
the Drude model assumed that we can just
view the electron as a classical particle,
which therefore satisfies the classical
equations of motion that Newton equation.
And in the presence of electric fields,
so let's say the charge is q, so
it experiences this force
due to the electric field.
And these impurities,
all these imperfections,
he just replaced with the friction force.
And this friction force was assumed
to be proportional to the velocity.
Let's say, it sort of make sense if you
have a viscous fluid for instance, and
if you put an object that's
going to move in this fluid.
So it's going to experience some force,
friction, which is proportional
to the velocity and with a minus sign of
course, and there is some coefficient.
So the velocity is momentum divided by the
mass, so we can write, instead of writing
the frictional force this way, we can
write it as minus p over t over some tau,
which is a time scale which describes
momentum relaxation in this process.
So in some sense,
you may think about this tau as
the typical time between collisions for
the electron.
But in the Drude model, it was just
a sort of phenomenological parameter
that described friction or
momentum relaxation of this electron.
And now, what he did, he simply wrote
down this model, and so of course,
we can write the left hand side
of the Newton equation as dp/dt.
And so the right hand side is putting
this together is going to be the electric
force and
this friction force ,and in equilibrium,
we demand that there's no
acceleration of electrons.
So if we take, let's say, a piece of
metal, apply some electric field,
eventually it's going to come to
some sort of steady equilibrium.
There is going to be a current,
but there's not going to be
indefinite acceleration of electrons.
So they're going to come to
a certain sort of steady state, and
this steady state will
determine the current.
Now from here, what we can do,
we can just solve for the velocity.
So momentum from this equation is
going to be equal q times E times tau.
And velocity therefore is going to be
just momentum divided by the mass.
And at this stage, what we can
do is we can write the current.
So the current is simply the charge of
the carriers, in this case, the electrons,
times the density of these carriers, how
many of those participate in transport.
And v is the velocity,
which we just determined.
And so if we put everything together,
we're going to get this expression, so
it's going to be this coefficient,
which is called conductivity, and
times the electric field.
So by definition actually,
the conductivity is the coefficient of
proportionality between the current and
the electric field.
And so this expression,
this n q squared tau over m is the so
called Drude conductivity,
which as you can see,
the purely classical entity, so there is
no quantum mechanics here whatsoever.
Now embarrassing thing that I have
to admit at this stage is that
almost all sort of useful theories
of metals, of transporting metals,
rely on this Drude
equation up to this date.
So since, for more than 100 years,
we've been using this equation and
in most cases, it actually works fine.
But fortunately, well for us scientists,
otherwise it would have
been really boring.
So if you go to lower temperatures, the
situation becomes a little more tricky.
And this is because quantum
mechanics becomes important.
So quantum mechanics come into play.
And what it means is that in this picture,
for instance, with how we can envision
the appearance of quantum is that instead
of just straight trajectories of classical
particles, we're going to have waves
bouncing around of these impurities.
And so these waves are going to
interfere with each other in some sense.
So it's going to be the particle
is going to interfere with itself.
And these quantum interference
effects are going to modify
this picture very significantly.
So now let us look at
the electron motion in a metal,
in a disordered metal from
a slightly different perspective.
Actually, from a completely
different perspective,
because now we want to explicitly
turn on quantum mechanics.
And we will use quantum mechanics and
partition quantum mechanics due to Feynman
and ask the question what is
the probability for an electron to
diffuse from an initial point to final
point through this forest of impurities.
And according to the Feynman, this
probability can be written as the absolute
value squared of a sum of
quantum mechanical amplitudes,
associated with all
possible classical paths.
This diffuse the trajectory in here.
I'm just showing two such
possible trajectories.
This blue one and the black one and
these guys are going to
interfere with one another.
And this interference, so for
instance, if I pulled this trajectory,
trajectory one and
this is going to be trajectory two.
So the interference term, which is
going to appear from this expression,
is going to involve a product
of this black exponential,
e to the par i s1 h bar,
times the blue exponential,
which is complex conjugate,
i s2 divided by h bar.
Plus its complex conjugate, so all in all,
the interference term, coming from
these two particular trajectories,
again, this is just two examples.
There are infinitely many
such trajectories and
infinitely many such terms, but in any
case, each of these terms is going to
produce a sort of cosine of s1- s2 and
divided by h1.
So this is basically
the quantum interference terms.
And the terms, which don't involve
the cross product of different
trajectory site, classical terms.
So in some sense, these are the terms,
which are responsible for
the Drude conductivity,
the classical Drude conductivity that we
obtained in the previous discussion, okay?
And so now, the question of what
is quantum mechanics doing,
what are the quantum corrections,
boils down to figuring out
what these terms are actually.
Now, in the beginning of this video,
I mentioned something about temperatures.
I said, well, at high temperature,
these terms don't really matter,
at low temperatures, they start to matter.
And the reason this is the case, because
at high temperatures, what the temperature
really is, it involves a lot of motion,
which occurs around these electrons,
which are sort of doing their thing,
moving around, diffusing around.
But there is also, let's say, lattice
vibrations, all kinds of things, and
this sort of shaking of
the electron disturbs the phases.
So in some sense,
this is what is called sometimes,
in quantum mechanical literature,
this is called dephasing.
So basically here in this expression,
whatever theory we're going to be doing,
we're going to determine those actions.
We're going to assume that phase
1 mechanical phase is going to
remain constant, during or
uninterrupted method,
say during the motion of
electron along these projections.
But it turns out that even if we assume
that there's no disturbance of the phases
and no dephasing, so classical
physics in some sense protects itself
in that these quantum interference
theorems tend to cancel each other out and
completely disappear from the picture.
And we'll actually have to search
really hard in order to find
the situation where they
start being essential.
And in order to see all of this,
let me estimate the typical action
that appears in this equation.
So remember that well, at this stage,
we are just talking about particles
bouncing around from these impurities, but
otherwise, in between this sketching,
they are free particles.
So their energy is essentially
just mv squared over 2,
the kinetic energy of a free particle.
And therefore, in order to estimate
the action, we can just say that well,
by the order of estimates
is going to be mv,
which is momentum, times another
velocity times dt, which is sort of.
So this is going to be the double
length of the trajectory, and
this is going to be the typical momentum.
So we can estimate our
action on each path as
the typical momentum of an electron times
the typical length of the trajectory.
So, now using this estimate,
we can also estimate the typical quantum
interference terms,
which I described by the sum
of overall pairs of non equivalent
different trajectories, L1 and L2.
And now instead of the action, S, we
write explicitly at the typical momentum,
which by the way is called
Feynman momentum divided by h
bar times the difference in length between
the two trajectories under consideration.
Or we can write it equivalently as the
cosine sum over all L1, not equal to L2,
cosine of typical momentum
times delta L divided by h bar.
So it turns out that this argument of
the cosine in the typical metal is
actually very large.
And this is because the typical velocity
of electron in a metal is less than
the percent of the speed of light,
which is 100, so
the speed of light,
which still is pretty fast.
And therefore,
the typical wavelength turns out to be
less than an anemometer,
10 to the -9 meters,
which is usually much more than
the distance between these red dots here.
So I'm just giving you facts.
If something is obvious, it doesn't
follow along the previous discussion,
I'm just giving you certain information.
And the bottom line here is that
the typical wavelength, in some sense,
you may think about the electrons
really being a wave, and
this wavelength is much, much smaller
than the distance between these red guys.
And so the interference terms
are not very important.
And how it plays out here is that so
this typical ratio of delta L divided by
essentially this lambda is very large.
And so you have different trajectories
contributing to this sum, and so
you have cosines of different phases,
completely random phases.
And cosine, as we know,
is the function which can be a positive or
it can be negative, depending so if this
our cosine of phi and this is phi, so
it can be positive or negative.
And so if we completely pick,
if this phase is completely random, so
the average value of
the cosine is going to be 0.
So the terms with different signs of
cosine basically cancel each other out,
and this is exactly what happens
with quantum interference terms.
And so, seemingly,
classical physics survives, and
we can just completely forget about
this quantum interference phenomenon.
So fortunately, it's not quite the case.
It's almost the case, actually.
In an ordinary disorder,
the main pulse is in three dimensions, but
it's not always the case.
And how the quantum interference
terms sort of appear we can see
by noticing that there is a very
special class of trajectories,
where this organization and
this consolidation doesn't happen.
And these are so-called self crossing
trajectories, which actually,
one of those trajectories
is sort of presented here.
So you see there is a loop here when
an electron can actually travel
in the clockwise direction, and
this is going to be our path number one.
Or it can decide to travel in the opposite
direction, counterclockwise direction,
in which case it's going to
be a path number two.
And the two paths,
they're going to be different paths, but
they're going to have
exactly the same length.
And therefore the quantum interference
curves responding to these paths
are going to survive.
Phase difference is going to be 0, and
these terms are going to
play out very significantly.
And so this is where we're going to
discuss in the second part of this video.
Now going back a little bit
to physics in order just to
give you an intuition about what
it has to do with conductivity.
So we can sort of intuitively
understand that the easier it is for
an electron to move from an initial
point to some distant final point,
the better this material conducts.
Okay, the battery diffuses,
the battery conducts.
And the classical level, it is just
determined by the true conductivity.
On the other hand, the easier for
the electron to return to the same form,
the more often it just sort
of goes back and back.
So the worse conductor it is, so in some
sense, the probability to have these
self-crossing trajectories should
in general, by general arguments,
reduce the conductivity, and this is
exactly what happens in most cases.
And therefore,
it is called so-called weak localization,
basically tries to bring collection
back to where it came from.