So in the second part of this segment,
I'm going to elaborate on the phenomenon.
And in particular, I will discuss
in more detail the self-crossing
trajectories that are responsible it.
And [INAUDIBLE] identify
the physical circumstances
under which they are actually important.
And this discussion is going to
be under the title I put here,
Quantum corrections to diffusion.
But before going back to this quantum
corrections that we already mentioned in
the previous video, let me remind you
what classical diffusion actually is.
Actually the phenomenon of diffusion,
you can observe at home by performing
a rather simple experiment.
If you put a droplet of a dye in water and
watch it spread out with time.
So this evolution of this droplet,
time evolution spreading out of this
droplet is going to be described
by the diffusion equation,
presented here with some
diffusion coefficient, D.
But the phenomenal diffusion and
the diffusion equation itself
are of course much more general than
this particular physical realization.
And they happen whenever
we have a large number of
particles experiencing a random walk.
So random walk is, if you can think
about it as particle which moves,
every time step it moves
in a certain direction.
It can go up.
It can go right.
It can go down.
It can go left, up, etc.
And so, at each moment in
time there is a probability,
an equal probability to
go in any direction.
And so, if a lot of such
particles are put together and
if you look at this particles
from a large length scale.
So their density,
the evolution of their density is
going to be described by this equation.
And so here is in general,
a function of position and time.
So how it is relevant to the previous
discussion about elections and
moving in the metal.
So there, as we mentioned, so the
disorders, some imperfections in the metal
play the role of sketchers, that somehow
randomize the electron trajectories.
And so we can think of what electrons
experiencing this random walk.
And since there are many, many central
electrons in a piece of metal, so
if we want to describe their density,
the disc is going to follow
the diffusion equation.
So another interpretation of
the diffusion equation is that the straw
is actually a probability density
of finding a particular random
walking particle in a certain moment
of time at a certain position in space.
So there is probabilistic interpretation
of this equation, if you want.
Now, another common note I'd like to make
about this equation is that actually,
in some sense,
it looks similar to the Schroedinger
equation in quantum mechanics.
So if we were to put in
the measuring constant I here,
which we don't have to put, but
if we were to measure some imaginary time.
So, and instead of the coefficient D,
we would have had, let's say,
minus H squared over 2 M.
Then this equation would have become free,
a Schrödinger equation of a free
particle for the wave function.
So this is a purely mathematical analogy,
I should say, but
this mathematical analogy, in certain
cases, actually goes a long way.
And allows us to calculate
things that otherwise would have
been very difficult to calculate.
So at this stage,
however, we don't want necessarily to
involve in any of these analogies.
Instead, let me focus on the equation
of relevance to the phenomenon of
that I mentioned.
Namely, on the self-crossing trajectories,
so in here,
I'm talking about self-crossing
trajectories of some diffusive particles.
So let's say, to here actually what I mean
is that there is some small length scale
each particle diffuses around.
But as a result,
in a realization of this random walk,
it may lead to this
self-crossing trajectory.
And so from the perspective
of this crossing point,
what it actually means is that
I'm asking the question of what
is the probability for a particle to
return to the same point where it started?
So let's say,
I set an initial condition for
my density at t = 0 to be
a delta function in space.
So delta function, very sharply localized
density in this particular point.
Now it turns out that one can actually
solve exactly the diffusion equation
with this initial condition.
It's actually called the green function
and this fundamental solution,
the general solution to the diffusion
equation is written here.
Here again, r denotes the coordinate
in space, T is time, D is
the diffusion coefficient, and this small
d denotes the dimensionality of space.
So it can be either one dimensional
space or three dimensional space or
two dimensional space.
And in order for us to find
the probability to return to the origin,
let's say we are looking for
the probability with a self rising
trajectory which starts from r equal 0 and
goes back to r equals 0.
So it means that we have to set
r equal 0 in this expression or
set exponential to 1.
And that's what we're going to get for
the probability of self-intersection.
So again, what this guy implies is that
if we take it random working particles,
put it by hand in the orange and
let it random walk.
So this guy gives us the probability of it
to return to the vicinity, the probability
density more precisely to return to the
vicinity of this point in the time sheet.
So now, let us recall about why you're
talking about this self-crossing
trajectories.
So the context in which they
appear was the diffusion of
electrons in the metal and
we wanted to see again.
We wanted to find the probability for
an electron to diffuse from an initial
point to some final point and
there are many different
trajectories that have used that.
So and we focus on the quantum theorems,
the quantum interference theorems
where different trajectories,
l1 not equal to l2 would
interfere with one another.
And the interference theorem was
this cosine of the difference in
length between two given
trajectories times p
typical momentum of an electron
divided by each bar.
And the statement was unless L1 was
actually equal to L2 this interference
theorem would kill each other or
every each other to zero.
Because you will get just a collection of
negative and positive random numbers and
on issue we'll get 0.
But for the special kinds of terms
where it can go clockwise or
counterclockwise around
a certain trajectory,
this delta L here would be 0 and
cosine of 0 is equal to 1.
So we'll get a prescribed
contribution from these guys.
And so, what we're trying to figure
out now is how probable it is for
us to actually get this
self-crossing trajectory at all and
this is determined by this equation.
But this guy tells us
this probability density
to return to an original
point in a particular time T.
Well, what we are interested
in is any self-intersection.
It doesn't have to be accurate
necessarily in this particular time T,
it has to occur at some point.
So in order to calculate the total
probability which I will denote as piece
of total, I have to integrate
this expression over time
from some minimal t to some maximal t.
So in here, I should mention that I am
dropping the overall coefficients, I'm not
keeping track of the coefficients, I'm
just focusing on the most important terms.
Now, the minimal time here is the minimal
time that the diffusion equation
is able to resolve.
Being an approximation, it cannot
describe the motion shorter in time than
the consecutive collisions, let's say
of the electron between two impurities.
So these guys of the order TAO, which
was actually introduced In the beginning
of the previous video but I should
mention that it's actually not important.
What it actually is, it is only
important that there is some cut off.
On the other hand,
even if there is no dephasing processes.
If there is defreeze quamtum mechanical
phase is perfectly preserved,
there is no maximum data.
So this guy actually goes infinity and
therefore,
the integral that we actually have is
an integral from TAO to infinity of dt,
t to the power of d over 2.
And this integral we can
now easily recalculate and
what is extremely important, what is
crucial, is that this integral is finite.
If we are in three dimensional space,
and which we leave but it's infinite,
it's equal to infinity if we
are in a one or two dimensions.
So physically, it implies the full
lengths, so that if we start let's say,
imagine you're in a spaceship and you're
sort of flying around in a completely
random directions in three dimensions.
So this result tells us that
you're going to be lost,
you're never going to return to
the point that you started from.
On the other hand,
if you start walking around in a city,
in a town or city you don't know and
you walk randomly long enough.
You are actually guaranteed to return
to the vicinity of the point where
you started.
From the point of view of the electrons,
so this result implies that if we have
a motion of electrons in one and
two dimensions.
So there will be an infinite number
of cell crossing trajectories and
the probability of cell crossing
is going to be equal to 1.
So this term is actually going to matter
enormously at low temperatures and
they're going to blow up and lead to
localization in low dimensions, and
this is actually what happens.
So if we now actually think about
the physical concept once this of course
begins.
So this in principle, everything
I'm talking about here is a rather
complicated theories,
if we were to study it in full details.
But, I just basically want to,
maybe we'll leave this result here,
total probability of self
intersection is really the key.
The reason for this video is just really
to get you this a result, essentially.
What it tells us in conjunction
with the path integral argument and
some intuitive arguments is that
in low dimensions the electrons
are going to get localized
at low temperatures.
They're going to tend to return to
the same point and this localization is
going to be consequence of
the wave nature of particles.
From the experimental point of view,
what it actually means is that
if you perform a measurement of,
let's say resistance, which is one
[INAUDIBLE] as a function of temperature.
So at high temperature were various
effects, disturb the phase, so
this quantum interference
phenomena basically unimportant.
Whether or not the trajectories cross or
not doesn't play any role, so
you will have some resistance and
it will slowly actually decrease but
then at some point, it will actually
shoot up and become an insulator.
Now in this quantitative curve, so
this part of the curve responds to
the weak localization phenomenon
that we have been discussing.
And this part is the classical
conductivity which
goes back to more than
a hundred years ago.
And the prediction is that in one and
two dimensions per this argument,
these quantum interference terms
are going to take over and
you're going to get a insulator.
While in three dimensions, actually what's
expected is that they're going to remain
a metal and the resistivity is going to
saturate in 3D for some finite value.
And this is indeed what happens, so and
there do exists the quasi one-dimensional
and quasi two-dimensional materials.
Let's say, nanowires and
so-called semiconductor heterostructures,
two-dimensional films where
this behavior is observed.
So I should emphasize again that the full
theory of this localization is extremely
complicated theory and we just got
a flavor of it, so hopefully, but
it's not the full story.
And interestingly enough,
what I told you about here,
actually this weak localization is
a precursor to a different phenomenon.
Which is actually called strong
localization for which Phil Anderson,
a Professor [INAUDIBLE] Princeton
got his Nobel Prize in 1977.
So we obviously don't have time now
to discuss in any detail this very
interesting and
complicated theory of Phil Anderson.
But let me just mention that next week,
we're going to go back to standard quantum
mechanics and one problem we're going to
solve is a particle in the potential well.
And in this problem, we're going to see
that the particle when put in a potential
well, gets localized by the well
with some discrete energy levels.
Not continual energy levels but
discrete levels.
And so,
the essence of the theory of Anderson,
it can be summarized in a few seconds.
Is that in a random [INAUDIBLE]
shows potential wells, so
this is let's say, V of r.
So the energy levels that
electrons are going to acquire
are going to match each other.
And so, they are going to be able to
move half from well to well because of
the energy conservation.
And this would completely
suppress the conductivity and
this will lead to the strong [INAUDIBLE].
So that's the only thing I'm going to
say and next week, actually we're
going to study simpler phenomena
using the Schroedinger formulation,
in particular the appearance
of energy levels.