I now want to talk about Gauss his law and how you would apply to conductors.
So let's take an arbitrarily shaped conductor over here.
The one thing to remind you to remember about conductors is that the field inside a conductor.
Let's just call it the inside must be equal to zero.
OK so what happens now if I place some charge a net charge on that conductor of 10 micro cooling or
what do you think happens to that charge.
Well first of all what's going to happen is if this is positive charge again.
So what would happen would be would distribute itself on the outside surface of that conductor.
You can't have any charge inside and in order to prove that you can't have any charge inside you imagine
if you have a Goshen surface over here which has kind of the shape which is just inside this surface.
Right here's my Goshen surface
if you were going to apply GAUSS LAW TO THIS PROBLEM IT WOULD LOOK LIKE THIS.
YOU WOULD SAY THAT THE FLUX THROUGH THAT SURFACE must be equal to the charging closed divided by epsilon
0.
However have a look at it inside this Goshen surface.
If all of this charge goes on the outside surface of the conductor the charging closed.
In this case here has to be equal to zero.
So we'd have that the total flux through that surface is equal to zero.
The only way you can have the total flux is equal to zero for any arbitrarily any arbitrary shape of
this Goshen surface is if the total field inside is zero.
Because remember our flux is the field multiplied by the area.
All right.
The only way you're gonna have this equation is if the total field inside is equal to zero.
And that's really really important about conductors okay.
So we have to have that whenever you charge a conductor.
Charge goes on the outside surface.
All right let's have a look at a slightly more complicated case all right.
So have a look at this case.
Now again we're gonna say that our total conductor has a charge of ten micro cool on the outside.
What now would happen if my conductor had a cavity on the inside of some arbitrary shape.
So that means that the space inside this cavity is just empty space and all the conducting material
is out here.
Again it doesn't matter because e inside has to be zero.
There can't be any charge inside this Goshen surface.
So all the charge goes on the outside.
The question is now imagine I do this inside this cavity.
I place a charge of six micro cool on purple charge right here of six micro cool.
Let me clean that up a little bit.
Maybe use a smaller pen.
Positive 6 micro cool home right here on the inside of that cavity.
What happens to that 10 micro Coolum charge.
What do you think happens to it.
All right.
So in order for now if you think about it.
If I have a ocean surface the way I have a drawn right here now I'm enclosing some charge.
I'm definitely enclosing the six micro cooling charge right because it's inside this purple charge is
inside my Goshen surface.
So but I do require that the field inside the conductor has to be zero.
How do I square the circle over here.
The only way I can do that is if this happens over here.
You pick a different color so what's going to happen for me to get zero total charge inside here.
And this is really what's required.
I really need cueing close to be equal to zero.
That's the only way to ensure that the electric field is zero inside the conductor.
But if you have a look at it I'm already enclosing the six micro cooling
because it's the purple charge inside my Goshen surface.
What that means is I also have to enclose something else.
There's also going to be some charge on the inside wall of the cavity.
And for this equation to work out the charge of the inside wall must be equal to negative.
I'll just call it I for inside wall must be equal to negative six micro cooling.
So this is what it looks like.
Let me draw those charges in pink.
What's going to happen here is that you're going to have some charge equal to negative six micro cooling
that's going to go on that inside wall of the cavity.
Right.
And all of this pink charge if you were going to add them all up.
That would be equal to negative six micro cooling.
This way my Goshen surface definitely encloses no net charge because you have six from the purple and
you have negative six from the Pink.
Those charges cancel out which means that the total charging closes zero and the only way I can have
that is if the flux is zero.
And that will ensure that the electric field is zero inside the conductor.
Now there's one more thing to figure out.
Well if I put negative six on the inside wall what happens on the outside wall.
Previously all we had was are 10 micro Coolum on the outside.
That's what we had here.
This is the total charge of the conductor which still has to be true.
However if you think about it the total charge of the conductor has to be whatever's on the inside wall
plus whatever charge is going to be on the outside wall.
We just figured out what was going to be on the inside wall was negative six.
So let's go ahead and do that.
So we have 10 micro cooling.
We have negative six micro cool on for here plus whatever charge is going to be on the outside wall.
So at the end the final expression I get for the outside wall must be 16 micro cooling.
So that means compared to the previous case I'm actually going to have excess positive charge here on
this outside wall
the total charge of my conductor is still 10 but you have positive 16 micro cooling on the outside.
You have negative six on the inside wall and this will ensure that the total electric field inside the
conductor is still zero.
Okay.
In the problems later on I have a shell example.
Similar example to this.
So we'll have a look at this property again.
Okay.