So here we have a new problem here.
Two point charges a five and eight micro Coolum other place inside the queue and they give us the dimensions
of the queue.
Question is what is the net ELECTRIC FLUX passing through the services of the cube.
All right.
So first thing I would do is kind of just imagine here we have our cube try to draw this in three dimensions
Here's the sketch it out.
If something like this and then I have my two charges right.
Yeah this might look like they're not inside the cube depending on how I draw it but all right here
we have the eight micro Coolum and the green one let's just say this is a five micro Coolum.
OK.
So what is the net electric flux.
Well for this one here I would use Gauss as law.
Right.
And in order to find this because the flux member our equation and the net flux what you could do is
if you were really ambitious you could actually calculate the E dot a for the total electric field passing
through all of those services but that would be way too hard right.
If you use Gauss is law it says that the net flux through a close surface.
So I'm going to call this the close surface is the cube.
One other way to calculate the net flux is just to use Gauss as law which says that the flux is equal
to how much charge is enclosed by that surface and divided by our Epsilon 0 that permitted city of free
space.
So at the end all you need to do is find that the net flux through the surface is equal to how much
charges and while both of these charges are inside.
So that means that we have five micro cool plus eight micro cooling and all of this gets divided by
our Epsilon 0 which is just a constant.
So it's eight point eight five times 10 to the negative twelve.
All right just be a little bit careful over here.
This guy here converted into cool arms so get rid of that micro all right at the end what you end up
getting here would be 13 times 10 to the negative six.
That's what we get for micro cooling and divided by eight point eight five times ten to the negative
12.
All right you put that in the calculator you should get a choice C is the correct answer.
All right.
So this is just remember that Gauss is law even though it's a cube surface it doesn't matter.
It goes as law still applies.
The easiest way to find the total flux is to use Gauss as law.
All right let's go scroll down to the next problem over here.
Our next problem.
Scroll down so you can see all the choices.
All right.
So we have a net electric field of a magnitude of this value over here and is directed along the positive
x axis.
All right so when you actually draw with that field looks like.
So we have a field that looks like this and then it's constant.
And the magnitude is six times 10 to the six Nunes curriculum.
All right.
They give us the length of the edge here of the cube this is zero point one and it's oriented like this.
So it's really this is the surface that we are interested in here.
All right.
So what is the electric flux passing through the shaded area.
So this is really just applying our definition of electric flux.
The definition of electric flux was the magnitude of the field multiplied by the magnitude of the area
and multiplied by coast of theta.
That is the angle between the electric field vector and the vector that is perpendicular to the surface.
So in this case here the vector that is perpendicular to the surface is this vector over here.
So both of those vectors are parallel to each other.
So that means that our angle theta here should be zero.
So really all we're doing here is just substituting our values six times ten of the six.
And now the area since it's only a square surface.
What you get is zero point one and you have to square that value.
All right.
So at the end what you end up getting here should be six times ten of the four.
That's the kind of a best answer right here if you substitute that new calculator.
All right.
Here we have a thin spherical shell that has a radius of eight centimeters and this much charge seven
point five micro columns.
What is the electric field a couple different places for a one centimeter above the surface.
All right.
So let's go ahead and draw that one centimeter above the surface might be at this position over here.
Actually it could be any position could be this one so it could be any position on this sphere and this
is kind of not drawn to scale but this distance here would be one centimeter the radius.
They tell us the radius again this is eight centimeters.
OK.
And we're also told how much charge there is on the surface.
Right.
The charge Q On the surface is seven point five times 10 to the negative six columns.
OK so final electric field anywhere on the surface.
This is a problem with spherical symmetry I would probably use Gauss as law.
Right Gauss law says this that the total electric flux going through this blue surface over here is
equal to the charging close by that surface.
Multiply by epsilon zero.
OK.
And the amount of charging close in this case is simply the total charge.
Q So it's Q divided by epsilon 0.
That's the right hand side of Gauss is law.
The left hand side of Gauss is low.
Let's work on that over here.
That's the flux.
So that's going to be the magnitude of the field and multiplied by the area and the area for a sphere
is for pi r squared.
Okay.
So here's what I'm looking for.
So at the end the field is simply q over for Pi Epsilon zero and R squared.
Okay.
So Q we know is this what is our value for this one.
Okay so that's really important.
Our value remember we're looking at this.
This guy right.
This is the area of the blue sphere right.
This is area.
And so here would be nine centimeters.
Okay.
So areas really has to be calculated with the radius equals the nine centimeters because it's the area
of the gaussian surface.
All right.
So at the end my electric field if you put in all the values again remember that one divided by four
pi Epsilon 0 right here.
This is the value K so that's mine nine times 10 to the 9 the value of the charges seven point five
times 10 to the negative six.
And what else.
0 divided by our squared.
So this would be nine centimeters zero point zero nine.
And you have to square that value okay.
At the end put that all on the calculator and you should get a value of eight point three multiplied
times 10 to the six newtons per Coolum.
Okay.
That's just the magnitude of the field anywhere on that blue surface.
All right.
What about B B's a little bit easier actually.
B They want to know at seven centimeters from the center of the sphere.
Okay.
Well let me kind of clean this up a little bit.
Well let's just drawn near the surface.
If you're seven centimeters from the surface you're going to be where you're going to be somewhere on
the inside here.
Right my ocean surface would look like this and the radius of this would be seven centimeters.
Okay.
Well if you think about this let's go back to Gauss as law goes his law says that this flux through
that surface through my green surface this time is equal to Q closed divided by epsilon 0.
Now think about this top term here.
How much charge is enclosed by this green surface All right.
Think about it for a minute.
You should get zero.
Right there should be zero charge because all of the charge is on this black surface right here.
So if you get zero divided by epsilon zero at the end you get zero.
If you think about the left hand side of Gauss is law.
This is the field multiplied by the area.
And the only way I can get zero here is if the electric field is also zero.
So you have everywhere inside this sphere you're actually going to get zero electric field because there's
no charge enclosed in that surface.
OK.
Kind of a nice guess his law problem.
All right let's go to the next one.
OK.
Problem four says we have a metal sphere that has a radius of 10 centimeters of interest draw it again
here's the radius r. This is 10 centimeters it has an excess charge again.
So the Q on the charges to micro cooling.
All right.
And again that charge is all on the surface.
So what's the magnitude of the electric field five centimeters above.
All right.
So if you count five centimeters above this might be where the field is in this distance here is five.
So the distance from the center here would be 15.
Now again you imagine you have a gaussian surface over here
and the ocean surface has a radius
equals the 15 centimeters.
I'll just right here ocean surface radius equals zero point one five meters.
That's 15 centimeters.
All right.
So Gauss is law again.
That's all you have to use for this problem goes is law says that the flux through that surface is the
field multiplied by the area.
Always the same for anything that looks like a spherical geometry.
This here has to be equal to Q enclosed.
So how much charge would be enclosed by my red surface would be all of the charge.
So that's Q divided by epsilon 0.
Okay.
At the end we get Q divided by four pi Epsilon 0 and divided by our squared.
All we have to do now is substitute in all our values one over for Pi Epsilon zero.
That's the K constant.
Nine times ten of the nine Q is two micro columns tend to the negative six and divided by the radius
of my Goshen surface zero point one five and square that thing.
Okay at the end of the day if you plug that in your calculator you should get that the correct answer
is B.
Okay all right.
That's it for that won't scroll down to the last problem for this problem set over here.
Okay.
Problem 5 looks like this says the figure shows for Gaussian surfaces surrounded by a distribution of
charge.
Okay.
So the Gaussian surfaces are here.
So here's let me choose a different color here here's Gaussian surface.
A B C and D.
Okay.
Which Goshen surface surfaces have an electric flux equal to Q divided by epsilon 0.
So this is for a.
And the flux for this one is Q divided by epsilon 0.
It's positive Q So all you have to do is simply find Well which one has a total charge of positive Q
inside right.
Because remember Gauss law is the flux is equal to Q enclosed by a surface divided by epsilon 0.
Okay so we need to find a one of these surfaces so let's look at surface a surface a over here how many
surface A's the big sphere.
It actually encloses everything.
So let's see.
So that means that we have positive to Q We have minus Q And we have plus Q So the total charging close
by this one over here is going to be positive to Q So that's not it.
What about surface B surface.
B Is this one that's kind of this ellipse soil over here and this one you get positive to q minus Q
And that's it.
So again for B it's everything that's enclosed by this surface right here.
So that means we have positive q.
Okay so that works.
And what about C let's go do surface C surface C let's represented here by a different color.
Do the green as a service C as of this one right here.
So how much charge is in close.
Well you have negative Q and positive Q This is zero.
So zero.
And the last one.
Let's do it and read this here.
B D D this one over here.
Let's do it in red.
So that's a lip sort over here only has a single charge in it.
So it's negative Q So negative Q All right.
Again this is not the flux this is this the total charge in close.
This is Q enclosed by each one of those surfaces.
So going back now which one here has a flux of plus q over e so for choice a over here it would have
to be which surface surface B surface
is be OK.
What about B.
Question B over here.
Let's do it down over here.
Which Gaussian surface have no electric flux through them.
If there is no electric flux it means that there is no total charge inside all right that Q and closed
divided by epsilon 0.
If you have zero Q and closed then you're gonna have zero flux.
So the only one that has zero charging close this surface C surface C and that's the correct answer
for Choice B okay.
And that's it.
Right Gauss is law applied to this problem is pretty straightforward right.
It doesn't matter on this complicated shape of the surface it's kind of the remarkable thing about Gauss
is Lord only depends on how much charges and closed.