So let's have a look at these three cases over here.
First of all it's just Remen of our definition for ELECTRIC FLUX e a coasts of our angle theta.
All right.
Again here we have an open surface
and the area is given by the letter A.
Again if it was a square you could simply multiply the length times the width to get what the area is.
NOW LOOK AT THE ELECTRIC FIELD MY ELECTRIC FIELD here points from the left to the right hand side again.
All right points like this and it's uniform you could see that those field lines are evenly distributed.
That's how I know it's uniform.
So again now the area vector the area of vector if this is the plane.
Again the area of vector here would point like this so that there would be perpendicular to the plane.
You could see that here.
So if you apply this definition here that means that the angle between the area or the vector that's
perpendicular to the plane and my electric field in this case the angle theta is zero degrees if you
substitute zero in my electric flux definition what you end up getting here is simply e multiplied by
the area.
OK.
This is the maximum.
FYI I can get.
OK.
That's the maximum flux.
You get the most number of field lines that actually cross that area.
If you have any other angle.
OK.
If we have any other angle that means that we have to use our definition.
So I hear they use the letter 5 but let's just substituted here for theta.
So you can see here that this angle over here right here is my area.
That's kind of tilted a little bit and the dash line represents the line that is perpendicular to that
surface.
So look like this.
This line perpendicular to the surface.
And again it makes an angle theta.
And my electric field again it points from left to right.
And it's uniform.
So again if you would draw both of those vectors you would have e that looks something like this.
I would have my line that is necessary the vector that's perpendicular to the surface that looks like
this.
And the magnitude would simply be the area and then the angle would be theta.
All right.
So if you apply the definition you have to have all three terms here inside this flux definition.
Okay.
All right.
In the case that's actually really really important is the last one over here.
Look what happens when my area is flat.
The vector that is perpendicular to the plane in this case is drawn a little bit to the side here but
it's perpendicular to the surface.
In this case look at my electric field is the same as all of those previous cases and the points from
left to right.
And it's constant uniform in space.
So in this case here if you substitute everything inside my electric flux definition which you end up
getting here is that the flux is given by this the angle between this black vector which is pointing
up the black vector which is pointing straight up in this case and the electric field which is in this
direction here is the vector that's perpendicular to the surface the magnitude is the area you could
see that this angle Phi is 90 degrees in this case if you substitute 90 degrees in my flux equation
what you end up getting is that the electric flux in this case is zero right.
So we go from a maximum when you have the angle equals to zero to a flux equals a minimum value you
could see that having the area down here in the plane there are no field lines that cross that area.
So we say that the electric flux here is zero.