All right now I want to talk about GAUSS LAW.
So goes his law is super important.
So let's see why we would use Gauss his law Gauss his law is allows us to calculate the flux
in a different way OK as opposed versus using the field multiplied by the area times cos of the angle
theta.
We just saw that version give us another way of doing it.
That's what GAUSS LAW is going to do.
The thing goes his law also allows us to do is can be used
just write this down to calculate
Q electric fields which is kind of cool.
OK we're gonna look at a couple of cases.
This case however though is really only in some cases you can use it to calculate electric fields only
for really like symmetric objects.
All right we'll going to look at which cases you can use.
Gauss is a lot of calculate the electric field.
So let me go ahead and define what Gauss is law is.
The other thing that we're going to need to do is we're going to need to uses close surfaces closed
surfaces only
so you can't use open surfaces like the case we just saw before.
OK.
So let me just highlight that.
No open surfaces
all right.
Let's write down what Gauss is law is it simply says that the flux the electric flux just the way we
know it.
However it's through a closed loops through a close surface
the electric flux going through any closed surface is equal to the amount of charge inside that surface
divided by epsilon 0.
And again this here was simply the permitted city of free space.
That was our number that we used before right.
The eight point eight five times tend to the negative twelve.
And this is just the total charge.
Right.
Total charge.
However it has enclosed here so it's really the total charge inside my surface.
This is not obvious.
It's actually a really remarkable result.
So we're gonna go look at a couple of cases we want to use it for really symmetric objects so symmetric
objects is we're going to use it for a point charges that's pretty symmetric.
We're gonna use it for lines of charge and also for kind of 2D planes.
Those are all very symmetric objects.
OK.
So we can actually define close services.
Look at how much charge is inside and then actually use this to find the electric field produced by
each one of these three objects.
So let's go on the next page now and focus a little bit more on both of these terms is so we can practice.
OK.
Because there's really two sides through Gauss is law there's a left hand side is calculating the flux
through close surfaces and then there is evaluating the right hand side which is looking at the enclosed
charge.
OK so let's go look at both of these different sides of Gauss law and how we would evaluate it.