All right.
I now want to use Gauss as law in order to look at the look more at this left hand side of Gauss is
law.
Because what it can do is it can be used in order to calculate the electric field.
OK but really only first symmetric objects.
So let me switch this around.
So for highly symmetric objects we're gonna use it to calculate the electric field.
So one symmetric object is a single point charge.
We know that the electric field produced by a single point charge at a distance are away from it.
For example if I take this point over here if this is a positive charge we know that the field points
like this.
And if it's let me just write this down this would be the distance are the magnitude of the electric
field would be like this k q over our squared we're QS the charge number our constant K is one over
for Pi Epsilon zero.
All right so that's the result that we know.
Well what if I wanted to use Gauss as law in order to evaluate this.
So first of all we're going to introduce this concept of a Goshen surface.
So again it's a simply a closed surface because we want to evaluate a closed surface because we want
to look at this side of Gauss as law.
So let me look at a close surface and the surface should have the same symmetry as the object.
So same symmetry as object.
So if you imagine a point charge a point charges kind of like a small sphere.
So you're Goshen surface should also have a spiritual symmetry.
All right.
This is my Goshen surface this a surface.
It's a closed surface.
So right.
It's a closed surface it's kind of like a sphere around this charge actually so the flux through this
surface is simply Q divided by epsilon 0.
That's what I know right.
And actually what if I drew a bigger one right.
What if instead if I drew a bigger surface which is also a circle here's another surface.
This other surface here has a different radius.
Right.
This is the radius say are to the blue one here might have a radius are 1.
What can you tell me about the flux for the first surface.
The blue one versus the flux going through the second one.
Well if you look at Gauss is law if you look at the right hand side of Gauss is law you could see right
away that the flux has to be the same because both of these surfaces enclose the same amount of charge.
And in both cases you simply have q divided by epsilon 0 doesn't matter which one you pick.
OK.
So let's just pick the blue one because it really doesn't matter which one I pick.
All right.
If I pick the blue one over here I want to now evaluate what is this side of Gauss law.
What's the left hand side of Gauss law.
So this is what it looks like.
So we're gonna work on spiritual objects first
for spherical objects.
How would we evaluate this flux over here.
Well again for constant electric fields we had this we had a course of theta.
So what if I say let's look at the angle theta.
First of all what is this term.
Again everywhere the electric field on this sphere should be pointing away from the charge.
That's what we know doesn't matter which point you pick should be pointing away.
What about the area vector right.
Our area vector if I consider a little patch of area this one should be perpendicular to the surface.
If I pick another one right here you should see that it is perpendicular to the surface.
This one here is perpendicular to the surface.
You can see that everywhere you look the angle theta is really equal to zero everywhere.
So that's kind of important because that will simplify our calculation.
So for this term I'm not even going to worry about it because everywhere for this object we have theta
equals the Zero all right.
Let's look at the area now really to get the total flux is you really have to go everywhere on the surface
and you really have to add up all of the different contributions here.
I don't want to get too much into the calculus here but actually for a spherical object which is what
we're focusing on in this particular case all you really have to know is what is the area of the sphere.
Because the field is going to be the same magnitude everywhere on this sphere.
Right.
So this is same magnitude and it's only the same magnitude because Magna tude it's the same magnitude.
It's only the same magnitude because we have in a spiritual surface that's always the same distance
away from from the charge.
All right.
So every time you're dealing with a spherical object this term basically is always the same.
So it's the magnitude of the field multiplied by the area.
So what is the area of a sphere.
Now it's not the volume of a sphere.
You might remember the volume of a sphere being as four thirds pi our cube.
But that's volume.
What about the area.
This one you might not know.
Okay.
The area here.
Let's just do it in green the area of a sphere is equal to for pi r squared and r is the radius.
So in this case here if the radius is r 1 you'd be r 1 squared.
Okay.
So this is super important for anything that is spherical in shape.
So let's go ahead now and write this down for Gauss is law.
So the left hand side of Gauss is law.
It's always going to be the same.
It's gonna be my field is a constant everywhere.
Again it's only the magnitude here we don't have to worry about the direction and the total area of
my spherical surface is for Pi our squared.
Now that has to be equal to the other side of Gauss is law.
All right.
The right hand side of Gauss is law which we said it's right here.
It's the total charging closed divided by epsilon 0.
So at the end you can see that you have electric field right here.
So I can actually use this to find the electric field.
All I do is I bring this whole term in the bracket down at the bottom.
And if you do that you get my final expression for the electric field.
It's going to be one.
I'll just regroup some of the terms I get a four pi.
I'll put the Epsilon 0 with the 4 pi and then here I'm left with Q divided by.
In this case it's R one squared.
And that's OK.
Are one squared is its R one because that's how I define the radius of the surface.
So it tells me that the field everywhere on the surface which is a distance are one away from the point
charge is given by this.
This is the same as the previous expression that we had for the electric field produced by point charges.
Okay so we can actually use Gauss as law.
Now we're gonna work now more on different shapes.
All right we're gonna work on more spherical symmetric objects but let's have a look at how we evaluate
this left hand side of Gauss is law for different shapes.