All right let's do an example here where we're going to apply Gauss as law and I have a spherical conductor
this physical conductor has a radius of 10 centimeters or point 1 meters as shown in the figure.
And imagine I wanted to now apply Gauss his law to find the electric field at a distance away from the
surface equal to 10 centimeters away from the surface of the conductor.
How would I use Gauss his law in order to solve this problem.
Okay so let's think about it.
We got to evaluate the left hand side of Gauss is law in the right hand side.
We have to place a surface around the object that I want to evaluate it and the surface should have
the same symmetry as the object.
Okay let me show you how to do this problem.
All right step number one for Gauss this law is we need to place a Goshen surface somewhere.
This is a spherical object.
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to trace out a Goshen surface that is also a spherical object.
Now this Goshen surface has a different radius all right.
It's going to have a radius Little R which in this case is going to be equal to zero point two meters.
All right I have a close surface.
Now I can right away think about evaluating both sides of Gauss as law.
All right.
First of all we have this charge here and I've placed five micro Coolum on it.
Now the keyword here is that this is a conductor.
So what do you know about conductors.
First of all you should remember that for conductors the electric field inside a conductor must be equal
to zero.
So that means that this charge over here has to be all on the surface of the conductor.
Let me just keep on drawing a couple more charges so all of the charges for conductor is the net charge
ends up being on the surface.
So let's go now and evaluate are GAUSS LAW.
Let's start here with the right hand side.
How much charge is enclosed by this green surface.
Well again cue total.
It's this guy.
This is five micro Coolum it's going to be spread out on the surface of this conductor.
So this guy over here is simply five micro COOL.
THAT'S FIVE TIMES 10 TO THE NEGATIVE six columns divided by my Epsilon zero.
That's it.
All right.
Now we have to work on this side of GAUSS LAW.
WELL THIS IS MY FIELD multiplied by the area.
What is the area for this green surface over here.
It's going to be for Pi the radius is Little R R squared and that's it.
Right.
This is because we have a spherical surface
all right at the end all we have to do is bring that term in the bracket here.
Down at the bottom and you get that the electric field really again it looks like the same expression
now.
We've always had a four point charges.
This is just cue the total charge.
Let's just call it upper Q. I'm sorry our five micro Coolum divided by r squared is a little R squared.
That's it.
Now you substitute in all the values and you can actually get what the magnitude is.
So you get five times tend to the negative six you get four pi you get Epsilon zero and then you get
actually instead of four pi Epsilon zero it's actually a little bit easier just to write it in terms
of my k constant k constant was nine times tend to the nine.
All right.
And then divided by our squared in this case it's going to be zero point two meters squared.
So let me go ahead and evaluate that using my calculator.
So just bear with me for one second.
So this time's nine each of the nine times five E to the negative six.
All right.
At the end of the day I get an electric field that equals a one point one two five times ten to one
two three four five six tend to the six.
And that should be in units of again as different units for electric field but I like Newton's cool.
OK.
So that's the magnitude of the electric field anywhere on this green surface.
This is how you would apply cool Ohm's Law.
Sorry.
That you would apply Gauss as law in order to solve this problem.
OK.
So remember when you're reading problems and you read the word conductor automatically you should know
that the field inside the conductor is zero.
That means that all of the surface ends up being on the surfaces of conductors.
And this is how you would apply Gauss is a lot of this problem.
You notice that the value that we get over here first physically symmetric objects even know this object
here has a finite size it's a ball.
Right.
It behaves as though it's a point charge right behaves the same way behaves like a point charge
where all of the charge would be concentrated right here at the center.
And you're simply evaluating the distance.
So that's true if you're outside if you're evaluating it on the outside of this spherical object.
If I was evaluating the field on the inside I would have to get zero because it's a conductor.
All right.
Good job.