I now want to look at a different geometry.
Okay I want to now take a whole bunch of point charges and form a line with them.
And what I'm going to do is I'm going to space them evenly so we're gonna say that this line of charge
is that the charge is uniformly distributed along that line.
So I want to think about now how we're going to apply Gauss as law and we we want to find the field
produced by this line of charge.
If I'm a certain distance away from the charge so let me have a look at it right here.
Imagine here I'm at some point and I'm a certain distance little are away from that line of charge.
Again we're going to assume that the line of charge is very long so it extends in both directions.
Kind of like this.
Okay so how do we find what surface would we choose.
That's number one.
And then how do you find the charging close by the surface.
So let's think about this and apply Gauss is law to find the field produced by this line of charge.
Okay.
So for this problem here I'm going to define something called the lambda which is the amount of charge
you have per unit length and this is going to be a constant for this problem.
Okay.
Because I'm going to assume that you have a uniform charge distribution.
The second thing we have to do now is defined a Goshen surface.
So think about this wire over here.
This line of charge.
It really doesn't make sense to use a surface like this that we use for spherical objects.
Actually if you think about a wire Well it looks more like a cylinder.
Okay.
So for anything that has kind of like a cylindrical shape like a wire we're going to use their Gaussian
surface that looks like a wire.
And again we want to have the wire here has a certain length.
Let's call this L and it has a certain radius which I'm calling R and this is really where I want to
evaluate the field.
OK.
So given all of this now.
Well we want to do now is go back to Gauss is law.
Let's find how much charge is enclosed here in this cylinder.
So let's start with that.
So cue enclosed cue enclosed there's going to be my line density my charge density divided by the length
that I have here multiplied by the length.
This gives me the total charge that I have.
So if you go back to go says law now this is the numerator on top of the right hand side.
So let's go back to Gauss as lie with simply right over Epsilon 0.
And this has to be the total flux.
And this is a close surface right.
So this is the total flux.
That's it.
All right.
Now how do we more specifically look at this term.
Now if you think about a line of charge that extends in both directions over here the field produced
by a line of charge has to be in this direction.
It doesn't make sense that there's any component here really that is along the axis and make sure you
understand that part.
And that's because if you think about what produces the field over here all of these charges are going
to produce a field at this point.
If you consider first the field produced by this little charge while that little charge would produce
a tiny little field like this but there's always a charge opposite of that that will produce a field
for example like this at the end if you add both of those vectors you're going to get a vector that
points away from the wire.
There's always charges tops and bottom so that there's never any vertical component of this electric
field.
So the total field really has to be pointing out for any line of charge that's very long.
All right.
So that makes our job a little bit easier because remember we have to evaluate the total flux.
So if I think about all these surfaces here here's the top surface let's call it one.
Here's the bottom surface and call three the side surface.
So if I'm going to write the total flux going through that surface I have to calculate the flux through
surface 1 the flux through surface 2 plus the flux through surface 3 and all this has to be equal to
the right hand side of Gauss is law now.
If you think about our area vector that we've defined there's different ones because these surfaces
are in different orientations.
If you think about a we did that those vectors in black before right let's think about this is the direction
of a vector that is perpendicular to the surface.
Here's a vector that's perpendicular to surface.
Number two and a vector that is perpendicular to surface.
Number three.
You notice that if we have that the field is pointing away from the wire and that our vector is pointing
up for surface one the angle over here between the field and the surface the angle over here is 90 degrees
the angle down over here for Surface 2 is also going to be 90 degrees.
So that really simplifies our expression over here that these flux have to be equal to zero.
There is no electric flux going through both of those surfaces at the top and the bottom of my cylinder.
So all we're really left with is just the sides of this tube.
So how would we write down the flux while you'd write down it would be the electric field multiplied
by the area.
What is the area.
The total area of the side of this cylinder over here.
Well if you think about it it's going to have.
I mean imagine if you unrolled it right.
If you unrolled it it would simply look like a big rectangle.
This here would be the length L and this distance here would be the total circumference of this sill.
This circle over here would be the length L multiplied by the circumference which would be two pi times
little r All right.
This here has to be equal to Lambda my charge density multiplied by the length divided by epsilon 0.
All right.
One thing you notice over here is that the length can actually cancel out because they're on both sides
and at the end we're left with just one expression for my field which looks like this.
So first of all the term in the front is different.
It's two pi Epsilon 0 this time which is different from the point charge and now it also depends on
the line DNC the charge density divided by the radius or the distance away from the wire all right there's
the field.
If you were gonna make a quick sketch of this.
This means as I go far away from the wire that the field drops off.
This is the distance and the magnitude of the field.
You see that the field is proportional to 1 over the distance.
It drops off slower than a point charge for a point charge for example the field dropped off much faster.
All right.
For a point charge the field was proportional to one over our squared.
Here it drops off much more slowly.
All right.
So keep that in mind.
Anyway this is how you apply Gauss his law to an object that has cylindrical symmetry.
So I mean just write down cylindrical symmetry so you would always try to choose a an object that also
are a Goshen surface that is also cylindrical and that makes that the area should be always a term that
looks like this if you're dealing with wires again you typically don't have to worry about the tops
and the bottoms of this Goshen surface.
You really only have to worry about the side.