So here's a nice little fun fact for you, in an environment where we don't have these air particles
impeding the objects, most of the emotion of the piece of paper that makes it kind of dance like this
in a environment where we don't have these air molecules, let's say on the moon or in the vacuum,
the paper being that there is no air interference.
That piece of paper will fall straight down to the ground because there is no air to actually interfere
with the objects motion.
Pretty cool, right?
Well, it is a fun fact, but I wouldn't actually say that's pretty cool, I would actually say, hey,
not show me show me that it would actually do that.
The piece of paper would fall straight to the ground if it has none of this air resistance.
So what I want you to do at home is this.
You have your book.
I want you to take a piece of paper, cut it in half and take that piece of paper and place it directly
on top of the book.
Make sure that none of the corners are sticking out and drop the book.
But before doing this experiment, I want you to tell me, is this so you have your book and you have
your sheet of paper notes that the paper is not having its edges over the size of the book?
Well, I want you to do is tell me this or actually think about this yourself.
Do you think that the book will actually fall and then there will be like left and then the piece of
paper will kind of have like a little separation in here and the book will actually fall and hit the
ground first?
Or will the book and the piece of paper fall and hit the ground together?