So now I'm back.
I actually just literally took my ticket textbook, dropped it from four feet, 11 inches off of the
ground six times.
And these are my recordings.
So if you want, you can actually conduct this experiment yourself.
This is a lot easier with two or three different people or so.
Conduct this experiment.
You can actually do it from a lot higher of a height, maybe like two meters off the ground or 2.5 meters
up the ground.
Yeah, just kind see if you get the same results for our acceleration.
Where I want to do right now is think about this.
So do we want to use all these numbers for our average or maybe there's a number here that looks slightly
like an outlier.
Ideally in experiments, what you do is predetermine the number of the sample size that you want and
then also predetermine if you're going to be excluding any sort of outliers.
So I'm going to calculate the average and I'll be back in a minute.