These are kinematic equations from before, keep in mind, we were using position in the X axis because
we had objects that were moving in the X axis.
Now we're going to be having objects are falling and moving it in the y axis.
So instead of using EXI and F, we're going to be using Y and Y F instead of referring to this as position,
we're going to be referring to it as height.
And doesn't that make sense and everything else is the same, that we're really not going to be talking
much about average velocity.
Just want to give you a little heads up on that.
So all of these kinematic equations, they're going to be the same.
But wherever we do see in Zeph and in EXI, we're just gonna be replacing it with Y and why F.
And here we go, skim through this, and you're able to see instead of having to, we do have these
substitutions here.
OK, so now we're at the point in this experiment where we could be determining which equation we want
to use.
Once again, like I said before, we're not going to be dealing a lot with our average velocities here
in free fall unless it really asks very explicitly we're not going to be dealing with these average
velocity problems.
But let's come through here and look for all the equations that do have the F in it and exclude them
for the equations that we want to be using.
So we have the F right here.
We know we're not going to be using that one coming through here.
Do we have the math?
Yep, we have the effort.
They're not going to be using that one.
Do we have the F in here now?
No, we don't.
And we have AVF right here.
So we know that we're going to be using equation number five to calculate our acceleration.