OK, so now we're going to be discussing Free-Fall.
Well, actually, before that, what I'm going to say to you is a little bit of a reading summit attached
to this video is going to be this PDF, this article right here.
I just kind of want you to go through read this.
Trust me, it's just the two pages.
It shouldn't really take you that long to do.
And alongside of it is a worksheet.
This is a Nessel fill in the blank worksheet as you go on through this worksheet.
It's not really that long either.
It's just that long.
It won't really take too long to do, but it's just going to be like a nice little different way to
go about introducing a topic here.
So I just want to change it up a little bit for the fill in the blank.
Let me just say this.
You're going to go through here and as you're going through here, just lined up is going to be these
answers.
So as you're going through, as you're going down, you're going to actually start to say, hey, and
what this goes along with it, it goes in the exact same order.
There is no oh, I have to be come back up here in order to find these answers are coming all the way
down here to find an answer that is up here now.
Just it scrolls down.
It goes through this.
Try this out.
Attached to this.
The video will also be an answer key.
So if need be, if you actually want to just check your answers and Hanwha actually have over here.
Hey, it's going to be so for this part, it's going to be one, two, three, four words.
This over here.
I'm looking for two words and four words over here.
So it's it's pretty simple, pretty straightforward.
This shouldn't take you any longer than maybe like 10 minutes to complete or so any longer than that.
You're probably spend too much time with it.
So compare answers to the answer sheet and collect your.