So on my desk right now, I have a tissue box.
I'm just going to lift up that tissue box and drop it, and then I'm going to lift up that same tissue
box again and drop it from a different height.
And what I want you to do is tell me your observations and just trust me, just doing exactly what I
said.
So this is going to be from the lower height.
And from the higher height.
From the lower height, from the higher height, when your observations.
And one thing that you might be saying is one, hey, that's annoying, stop doing that.
And maybe you're saying that because, hey, from nowhere is it less annoying?
And you're going to be like, yeah, it is less annoying than from the higher height.
Yeah, it's it's a lot more annoying.
Please stop doing that.
And so, in other words, what's annoying about it?
Well, because it's the loud right.
It's louder when it's dropping from a higher height, maybe at a time in the morning.
You're not wanting to have your teacher standing right next to you drop in a box, having that all that
noise coming into your ears.
So, hey, what's the reason why it's louder coming from the higher height, then?
From the shorter height?
Maybe you're saying yourself, well, because it's it's moving faster, that's the reason why it's actually
creating this of noise, and that's exactly right.
So it is moving faster.
That's the reason why it's created this loud noise.
Now, if it actually does create the same noise from this height as this height.
So if this noise and this noise was the same, maybe you would say, hey, no, it's moving at the same
speed.
But being at this height, it's moving at a faster speed.
Hey, what could you actually say that that's that the object is doing?
It's moving faster over a certain amount of time.
Right.
Can you also say that the object is accelerating?