We're going to be conducting our experiment very soon, but let's discuss something.
OK, so what's going to happen is I'm going to take this object.
I'm going to have it at one point, five meters high.
We're going to let go of it, have the stopwatch started as soon as I let go.
And then it's going to come down here.
It's going to hit the ground.
And as soon as I hear it hit the ground, I'm going to stop a stopwatch and I'll record it will be able
to use our kinematic formulas in order to calculate our acceleration.
And we're going to be good now.
There's going to be some human error involved here.
If I'm actually just using my trusty stopwatch right now.
I mean, I'm not going to be doubting the integrity of the stopwatch.
I'm going to be doubting the integrity of what am I going to be starting and stopping this at the exact
time that I should be or might there be a little bit of error involved here?
OK, so if we're expecting some error, then what could we do in order to help ourselves out with calculating
a more accurate time elapsed?
Maybe you're sending yourself instead of one reading where we're going to be calculating at the time,
maybe we should actually do it two times or possibly three times or four times and actually just use
those.
OK, so now now we're getting onto the right track here.
So instead of actually just taking one measurement here, maybe we should actually take multiple.
And then once we actually do that, what should we do?
Well, what actually makes sense for us to do with this multiple time readings are, you know what say
if we were to take the average of all of these.
And use that number as our Delta T..
OK, that makes a lot more sense, and I like that.
I think that that's exactly what we should do.
So we have our experiment.
We have everything.
Are we are we ready to go right now or is there anything that we're not exactly considered right now?
OK, well, what about this box?
What would be the difference if I was to actually use a let's say let's say I to use a 40 pound weight
and I have this dumbbell over here.
What does it look like?
Something like this?
Yes, sure.
That that's looking about right.
What if I you use a 40 pound weight instead of my tissue box over here or let's say a new one instead
of a 40 pound weight at the same height, we're going to be using a 15 pound weight.
Is this going to make a difference to us?
Well, I'm really not sure.
So let's actually do a experiment to see if the mass of the object or the weight of the object will
make a difference in our experiment.