Hello everyone.
Welcome back to exploring quantum physics.
I'm Charles Clark.
We're now going to continue a simple
variational approach and apply it to
calculating the ground state energy wave
function
of hydrogen atom.
So now we're going to evaluate
a variational technique in three
dimensions of considering the ground-state
energy wave function of the hydrogen atom
and we'll use for that purpose the
three dimensional generalization of our
simple Gaussian function, which is
just a product of the same thing in x, y
and z with the normalization coefficient.
And this is the ground state of an
isotropic harmonic oscillator in three
dimensions when the parameter, d is
related to the mass and the frequency by
this
equation d is root h bar over m omega.
So we're just going to now do a simple
variational calculation do an
expectation value of psi H psi.
Right, so here's, here's the the, the wave
function, the Hamiltonian and here's
the the quantity we're estimating in terms
of the
contribution of the kinetic and the
potential energy parts.
>> Well, the kinetic energy is easy, is
easy because we did that once already.
we know that, that it contains a
contribution of one quarter
h bar squared over md squared from each of
these three terms.
So in this case, it's it's straightforward
to do the calculation in Cartesian
coordinates, even though the
system has spherical symmetry because the
calculation was already done.
I mean, you can just, you can just recall
it, and easily do it again.
So, this the value of this is just a sort
of the universal expression
for the average kinetic energy of a local
a function localized on
a length scale of d.
Now for the the potential energy,
it's it, work is made, very much easier
by going to spherical polar coordinates
because the the potential energy
is spherically symmetric and so I'm just.
He, here are, here are the prefactors.
Note that we get this 1 over d cubed from
the expr,
from the the square of the wave function
and then here is
the here is the expression for the
integrand in spherical polar coordinates.
This 4 pi comes from integrating, over
angles.
so I'm not going to dwell on that.
you know, you really do need to know how
to do integrals
over spherical coordinates versus
Cartesian coordinates
in order to do interesting quantum
mechanics.
So for those who need a review look at our
crash course in math and, practice a few
simple examples.
In any event, I think you can
see that this integral is straightforward
to evaluate.
In fact,
I would say, whenever you're faced with an
integral of the type x to the n
e to the minus x squared, you should know
how to do that.
Find out the general expression, it's a
gamma function.
So least you should recognize that when
you would, whenever you encounter
an expression like this, the integral is
well-known and you can consult
the properties of the gamma function to
find out how
to do it yourself or you can just look it
up.
In any event here's the important result.
And as I mentioned in the previous part,
the contribution of the
kine, the kinetic ener the potential
energy, sorry, goes as 1 over d.
So, you see.
Now there are some factors here, right,
there are some numerical factors but this
approach,
captures the right scaling
of the the, the potential energy
contribution.
That's something very important about the
variational approach that when it's
implemented with
an appropriate wave function like the
Gaussian,
you're going to get the scaling right.
The actual numerical answer may not be
that accurate, but you'll, you'll
capture much of the essential physics and
it's, it's simple to implement.
Okay, so now, to, to find the value of d
we
just minimize this, minimize with
respect to d, and then, and then you, then
use
the absolute value then use the average
value of the energy that we find there.
And when you do that, you'll find that
this is the expression that you get.
I encourage you to work this out.
it's a fairly, if you just use the
ingredients that
we developed here within the past several
minutes, it's straightforward.
It'll give you actual experience in in
solving the, you know,
solving an important physical problem with
a, with a simple approach.
And the answer is that you get here, is
off by,
the exact answer by 15%, which is, I mean,
you know, you need to have better
aspirations than that.
But by doing things this way, you have
captured the right scaling.
So in other words, the dependence, this,
the Rydberg constant is the binding
energy, is
proportional to the binding energy of the
I guess this is, this is actually the
R infinity hc to get the appropriate
energies.
In any, in any event you've captured the
right dependence upon the mass which is
non, that's a non-trivial thing.
The energy of the hydrogen atom as
opposed, opposed to the mass,
of the reduced mass that the, the square
of the nuclear charge.
So
again, this is, this is something you use
as a first approach rather than a, to get
an accurate answer but it gives you very
good guidance.
So let me mention a few other things.
you can explore a wide range of problems
with this approach like you can go
to, ask questions about, large spatial
dimensionality, you know?
What's the volume and surface are of an
N-dimensional sphere?
You can actually you can actually find
that answer with the Gaussian estimate.
you, you might ask, well, what's the, the
energy of an N-dimensional hydrogen atom?
So let's, let's suppose we have, let's
suppose we have
this potential here, but in, but we have N
spatial dimensions.
What's the, you know, what's, what's the
energy?
this is an, sort of an abstract question,
but it's the sort of
thing that If you're a theoretical
physicist,
you like to explore these these issues.
estimating ground states of other power
law
potentials like a quartic or a linear
potential.
And so, once again, these are cases where
if you
have to make an estimate you may not have
insight
as to how to find the exact eigenvalue in
a convenient
way, but you'll always have the ability to
integrate a Gaussian function.
Even if you do it numerically numerical
implementation of that integral is very
easy.
And you have the kinetic energy part
already available for you for free.
Now there was an interesting discussion
put in the, in
one of the student forums last week and,
and I thought
I'd just address it quickly because it,
it, it indicates
another aspect of the harmonic oscillator
that's very important and interesting.
so the question has to do with the
[COUGH],
excuse me, the three dimensional harmonic
oscillator and, what if you place the
[COUGH],
the oscillator in a magnetic or electric
field?
how will that affect the energies?
So
[COUGH],
we'll deal with the magnetic question
later, but this
is a good point to just address this
issue.
What happens if you add an electric, if
you put a harmonic oscillator, a charged
particle, a harmonic oscillator, and apply
an electric field to it?
In fact, this is exactly the same problem
that's encountered in laboratories today.
looking at Bose-Einstein condensation in
ultracold atoms typically
these are confined by a, a harmo a trap
that's effectively harmonic, but the atoms
are also present in the Earth, in the
Earth's gravitational field, which is a
linear potential.
and so exactly this type of, of correction
has to be applied to those systems.
And so it has some interesting
consequences.
In any event, the key point here is that
the electric field is represented
in quantum mechanics.
Effect of electric field is represented by
a linear potential.
So this is, this is the form of the
electric field.
So when we add that, to the harmonic
oscillator
potential then we get this.
But do you see,
we can just define a new coordinate.
We just shift, we just displace.
I've, I've chosen the field to lie along
the x axis for convenience.
It doesn't matter what direction you use.
Just define the x axis as the axis of the
electric field.
And so if you define a set of new
coordinates where the
x, the, the, the field along the the
coordinate that lies along
the field is just, it's origin has just
shifted and the other
two coordinates are the same, then you get
a harmonic oscillator vac
here and then by completing the square on
this
term, you see you get, you get an overall
shift in the energy.
So, in fact the
harmonic potential when you displace it by
a linear potential, the ordering of
levels in the spectrum is the same but
they're all shifted downwards,
by this constant amount.
This constant amount is related to the
polarized ability of,
of the harmonic oscillator, another
quality fundamental interest in physics.
So the last topic that we'll treat in this
part
of the lecture is the introduction of
another trial function.
So, we had, we had an e to the minus r
squared over 2d squared.
That's a nice localized
function, as a radial function.
And we found this is, this is the, the
ground state of a
harmonic oscillator for an appropriate
choice of
frequency mass and the length length
parameter.
So this is another another nicely
localized
function, you know, as a function of r.
it, it falls off, it converges, converges
exponentially so it's
something that is very easy to implement
numerically.
And uh,for your convenience, I've
normalized it here
so you might want to check that
normalization, might want to
verify that integral d cubed r psi squared
is equal to 1.
I mean, I hope I've done it right.
and we can ask, using this constructive
procedure, is it the solution of a
Schrodinger equation?
So I'm asking you that question, and if
you recall, what you do is you say, okay T
plus v
psi equals E psi.
So we get, from
that, sorry, E is equal
to 1 over psi T psi plus v.
You just, compute, you just, this thing
that you, is something you can calculate
and from that, you see if there's a, what
v and E this correspond to.
And so, I'm asking you to do that at the
conclusion.
So we will conclude with in video quiz.
I hope that's straightforward and works
out well
for you and we'll see you next time.