Hello everyone.
Welcome back to Exploring Quantum Physics.
I'm Charles Clark.
We're now going to start to apply
some of the greatest tools that
mathematicians have ever developed,
the special functions, and
apply them to solving problems of
quantum mechanics of simple systems.
Now special functions,
there are many good sources of information
on special functions available.
But it's good to have
a common reference so
that everyone in this course
will be using the same one.
So we're using this, the digital
library of mathematical functions,
from my employer,
the National Institute of Standards and
Technology, it's a free app,
freely available worldwide, and
it contains information on all
the functions that we'll be using in
this course and many more, and well there
are many other things to be said about it.
But when I make a reference to
something like the Airy function,
which will be done later this part.
Then what I mean are the specific
representations that are provided there.
Which they're very much standard.
The same you'll find in Wikipedia but
I encourage you to look at this anyway.
Two, several other resources for you.
A short crash course on mathematics.
That's something that's certainly worth
looking at because it does provide
a constructed by Zach Rains and his
collaborators and gives you a pretty good
idea of the level of mathematical
treatment that's done in this course.
Another one page guide
to the known solutions of the Schrodinger
equation in terms of special functions.
And what else, a sample.
A program written in spreadsheet form
for solving the Schroedinger
equation by numerical integration.
So that's something.
I won't be using that in this part,
but something worth looking at.
There's a discussion there.
And I'll give you some simple guides
as to how to numerically integrate
the Schroedinger equation in cases when
you're dealing with a complex problem for
which there is no known solution.
So, who was the first person
to use this approach?
Solving the Schrodinger equation
using special functions?
No prizes for getting this right,
it was in fact, Schrodinger.
And you might say that his first work,
first papers on the wave equation
were influential for several reasons.
But one lasting development was that it
cast the Schrodinger Equation of quantum
mechanics into a form that had been
well understood by in
classical mechanics and
that was to reduce the Schrodinger
equation, differential
equation that had solutions in terms of
functions that were known at the time.
So what Schrodinger,
what Schrodinger did of course,
the importance of his
work stands on its own.
He explained the spectrum
of the hydrogen atom,
calculated the shifts in spectral lines.
He invented perturbation theory,
all the series of four remarkable papers.
But certainly it's very important for
the wider implementation of his ideas.
That, he developed a framework,
that mapped onto well
developed problems,
of classical mathematical physics.
And so
we're following the same approach here.
So in this part of the lecture,
we're going to look at three,
we're going to stick with
one-dimensional examples, and
we'll look at constant potential,
a linear potential, and
I guess, it will be in the next part,
quadratic potential.
But you might say that these are the three
simplest possible potentials
in terms of development as polynomials.
And the solutions of
the Schrodinger Equation for
these cases are the exponential
function for
the constant potential, the Airy
function for the linear potential.
So this is exponential.
Airy and parabolic cylinder,
for the quadratic.
Now the harmonic is
a special case of that.
But we're going to go through,
in this part,
we're going to go through
these two cases and
try to infer from them some general
principles that are relevant both for
the analytical and numerical solution of
one-dimensional Schrodinger equations.
Right, so
let's start with the linear potential.
We just take V(x) to be a constant.
And so here's the Schrodinger equation.
Now, the point is we want to find
solutions for any value of the energy.
We want to find a general
solution valid for all energies.
Because then, with such solutions in hand,
we can find the particular solutions that
we need to satisfy boundary conditions.
You'll see why this is
important in a moment.
But for example, if we just consider
a case where the potential is
constant over different regions, constant
at different values and different regions.
And you want to find a solution
to a wave equation that is valid.
It'll be sufficient to have this
information so that you can piece,
you can stitch,
the various pieces together.
So, the approach we'd take is to transform
the Schrodinger Equation up
here into a standard type.
In this case,
the standard form that we see
is here where Rho is a scaled variable.
Dimensionless variable.
And then the plus or
minus sign has to do with whether energy
Positive or negative.
We know that energies can be any number on
the real line so we need to account for
both of those cases.
Okay so we just take that system.
We transform,
we find the dimensionless variable
row is kx, k is the wave vector.
Depending on whether
the energy is greater than or
less than, the potential energy well this.
The value of k is determined by that.
And so there's two classes of solution.
So when e is greater than Vo,
we have two independent solutions.
So, let me just say again,
as a second order differential equation.
Any second order differential
equation like this one
has at least two independent solutions.
There are many different ways to
choose them but here I've just,
i've given you two independent solutions,
sin(rho) and the cos(rho).
We'll say a little bit more
about the choice momentarily.
And then in the region
where e is less than
V0, two independent solutions
can be chosen of this form,
e to the rho and e to the minus rho.
So any other solution that exists in this
region is going to be a linear
combination of these two functions.
But that means the generic
behavior is divergence.
Because if you just take a random
choice of these two functions,
then the resulting solution is going
to diverge as row goes to infinity.
And in the exceptional case where you just
choose this function then it diverges
and row goes to infinity.
Now that can be changed by
another boundary condition.
We have to be aware that in this, for
this particular circumstance,
the generic behavior is divergence.
So that means that you have difficult
choices that have to be made.
So I'll make two points about this, in
some sense trivial Schrodinger equation,
which either has oscillatory,
or exponential solutions.
And that is, if you have a general
understanding of the solutions,
then you could do a piecewise
approximate solution, to a, to a real
potential, he had a real potential
that have some arbitrary shape.
You can approximate it on
a piece-wise basis, and
then by knowing how to solve the equation
regions of constant potential
you can sort of propagate solutions
between different such regions.
This is something that's used in modeling
semiconductor heterostructure so
on the photonic band
gap materials are well
understood in terms of
having techniques for
it to propagate an away function across
a constant region and then to stitch the,
you know stitch the transition matrix
together to see what the net result is.
So actually,
why don't we just now apply that
approach to the simplest possible
problem of crossing an interface.
And we're going to look at
an example that you see every day.
If you look through a window,
you see a reflection of yourself.
I mean even if the glass is transparent
there is some reflection and so
it turns out that this
is a phenomenon that's
an example of this sort of the potential
step function in quantum mechanics.
So we have V(x) as a function of x.
This is air.
This is glass.
So the propagation of the light wave
as it enters a window is the same,
very similar mathematically to the problem
of particle moving in a potential.
So the way that that is framed
is that the we have light
incident from a large
distance of negative axis.
That wave function is
a form of e to the ikx.
Then there's a reflected
component which is a type
r with reflections
coefficient times my kx.
And then the transmitted coefficient here.
Now how do we, how do we determine
the effect of glass on light?
Let me refer you to an inline quiz.
So when light goes in to glass its
the refractive index of glass
is about 1.5 that means that
its wave length decreases and
so that is that means
the wave the wave equation spacial wave
equation in the interior as this form.
And so now it's very easy to
determine the reflexion coefficient.
So what we have, we have a wave
function on two sides of an interface.
The air in the glass.
So we have to match the values of
the wave function to the boundaries.
So for x = 0 it's very easy,
that's 1 + r here,
this t here, so
we have to have 1 plus r equals to t.
And then we match the derivatives,
that is the equation of continuity
that's require in quantum mechanics.
So once again it's easy to
differentiate this side and
the answer is Ik1 minus r and
this side is just ik and t.
And so now what do we do?
Well we divide,
we take this side.
And divide it by the other one.
So you see, I'm just taking this divided
by that, equals that divided by that.
Get this simple equation for
the reflectance coefficient.
So you see, the k the wave vector
disappears as does the transmission
coefficient, and that's easy to
invert this equation to get this, so
R = -0.5 over 2.5 = one-fifth.
So the actual reflected
intensity's r squared
coefficient is 0.04, so it's 4%.
This is about right.
When you put light through a window,
normal instance about
4% is reflected.
So in the next part of this lecture
we're going to explore the next
sequence of, next to the sequence of
complexity, the linear potential.