Welcome back, everyone,
to Exploring Quantum Physics.
I'm Charles Clark.
And today,
you're going to follow the bouncing ball.
So just to remind you,
we're working with special functions.
And today, in this part,
we're going to especially be
involved with the area function.
So I encourage you to make this
reference available to you.
Though, everything I'll show
you is self contained but
this is a good source of
additional information.
It's also appropriate for
me to remind you of the short course.
Crash course on mathematics.
Reference on the solution of
known Schrodinger equations.
And access to simple numerical
integrate that runs on a spreadsheet.
In the previous part, we started out and
we treated the first of these three
simple one dimensional examples.
And we're now going to today this part,
look at the linear potential.
And I think actually just,
we will have a very brief discussion
about the quadratic potential at the end.
I think linear potential does, is the best
thing to focus on because it gives one
a very good framework for comprehensive
understanding of the solution of
one-dimensional Schrodinger equation.
Now in the previous part, we solved for
this constant potential and
we found that we could transform the
Schrodinger equation into a standard form.
And the key point about
that standard form,
well there were two variants of it,
difference in size,
according to whether E what was greater
than or less than the constant denote.
But in both cases,
we could have identified two solutions.
Now, I should have brought this
point up in the previous part.
But here's a really good tool for
helping you to
make decisions about choices
of the alternative pairs
of wave functions that you will always
face in solving the Schrodinger equation.
This is the so-called Wronskian.
The Wronskian two
functions is given by fg'.
g prime equals dg dx.
And this is a very good comparison
tool to your decision making.
So the in line quiz,
I'm going to invite you to discover for
yourself the key property the Wronskian
operates on, why it's so useful.
So I guess you can see
that in these two cases,
you can calculate the Wronskian
in these two functions easily.
It's plus or
minus 1 depending upon how you do it.
And here it's plus or minus 2, I guess.
Depending on how you do it.
But perhaps if you think about it,
you'll see that if you have,
If you divergent behavior,
in this case of one function,
then we should be able to find
another one that converges.
Or, maybe it's easier
to say that if you have
oscillatory behavior of one
function in this region and
you pick another one,
then that's also a solution,
it's also going to be oscillating in
order to keep the Wronskian a constant.
The real importance is that these
alternative pairs of solutions,
the Wronskian must be constant.
Now the solution to the linear potential,
a Schrodinger equation
with linear potential.
It's a very nice properties, and
so I suppose that these are,
I suppose the airy functions must be
less familiar to everybody than must
be less familiar than the exponential or
the trigonometric functions to everybody.
But if this is your first exposure to
them, let me point out that this case,
linear potential gives us
two universal solutions that
combine both the oscillatory
behavior of the trigonometric
functions and the exponential diverging or
converging behavior of
the exponential function.
So there's basically a universal
function of each type that covers
behavior in the allowed versus forbidden,
Regions, and that is,
if you have a linear potential,
then eventually,
depending on the choice of V1, eventually,
the potential eventually
gets larger than the energy.
Or, eventually gets smaller than
the energy, either way around.
So in this sense, linear potential,
is a very nice tool for
understanding, the behavior of
quantum mechanical wave functions.
So, again,
in these case there's a demarkation point.
Of course these are two particular
choices of function and
you can find their
definitions in this chapter.
And they both oscillate for
when the argument is less than 0,
and then the Ai converges for
row greater than 0 and Bi diverges.
And these two have implementations
in physical systems and
what we're going to look at in detail
here is the quantum mechanical
bouncing ball but the second type
very function becomes important
in modeling things like
the scanning tunneling microscope.
Now the bouncing ball problem is,
as you'll see,
it's important from a technical
theoretical perspective,
in terms of learning how to
solve a shorting equation, but
actually is something that has been
recently realized a remarkable experiment
of the bouncing of a neutron confined
in a trap and bouncing off a mirror.
And there's actually experiments that
measured the quantum mechanical spectrum
of the neutron subject to
the Earth's gravitational field.
There have also been some implementations
in ultra cool atom systems.
So, we're actually going
to solve the problem with
reference to parameters that are germaine
to this recent experimental realization.
So, here we're going to describe
this amazing neutron experiment.
The starting point is something
from freshman physics.
V is equal to Mgh, or
V is equal to Mgx, so
the potential energy of
the neutron is given by this where
x is the distance going vertically
off the surface of the mirror.
G, acceleration due to
the Earth's gravity,
we'll just take a nominal value
9.8 meters per second squared.
M, the mass of the neutron about
the same as the mass of a proton.
Here's a nominal value, we're just
going to use a round number value.
And now, here is the boundary
condition for x equal to 0.
So in other words the wave function has
to vanish at the surface of the mirror,
that's and
idealization which is largely true.
And then it's got wave function oscillate.
And reach a point of,
whatever the energy is, the wave function
must die off eventually in order for
the neutron to be localized and
continue to bounce back and
forth in the way that we expect.
Now, in order to cast this
equation into appropriate
dimensional form, I'm going to use,
we're going to define,
I've worked this problem out in advance,
so
to define our dimensions coordinate
rho in terms of this transformation,
and I'd like you to look at
that in the in video quiz.
Right, well I hope that you found
that you could solve the quiz.
You saw the quiz question using
dimensional analysis only.
Because if you just look at e over mg,
I mean that tells you the,
that dimensional analysis of this
expression tells you the answer.
Yeah, so in other words, this parameter
alpha has to have the units of energy.
I mean since rho's dimensions this as
well you can see the past quite clear.
Now, in the next brief inline quiz,
just take it a step further and
this has to do with
the relationship between rho and x.
So, if you were to draw a rho axis,
where does it go in this mirror and what?
For example, there's an important issue
regarding, what does rho equal 0 mean?
What is the physical interpretation
of the value that particular match
thiis coordinate?
So, I hope it was obvious,
I hope it was easy, for you to find that
the value of rho equals 0 describes
the classical turning point.
That is the place where
the velocity changes sign,
it represents the maximum distance,
maximum value of x for which is
attained in classical motion.
So that means that the function
that we want is Ai because what,
it obtains its maximum a little
bit before rho equals 0 but
it's the one that dies off as
rho gets large, as rho increases
in the pause of region which is
the class of the forbidden region.
So we know that we must,
of the two solutions that we
are going to use, we must use Ai.
That is the only acceptable solution
In the region rho greater than 0
because the only other possible
solution there would involve
an admixture of Bi because any solution
in this region can be written as
a linear combination of Ai and Bi.
The one unique solution, up to some
constant multiple factor, is Ai.
So if we take that, we now say now how,
knowing that that is the solution,
how do we satisfy the boundary condition
that si of x equals 0 = 0?
Well, we're going to write a wave function
In terms of an airy function so we have
an additional parameter available to us,
which is the constant
offset in the solution.
And so that means that we basically,
we take this airy function and
we start pulling it up
until the node lies at the relevant,
at the surface of the mirror.
So, I think you can see that what we're
going to get, here's the lowest solution
is going to be like that, and
then the next lowest solution, oops.
The first excited state has one node
on the wave function and so on.
So basically, this curve Ai shows
you a universal set of profiles
of the excited states of the bouncing
ball, and they're just obtained
by displacing the surface of the mirror to
each successive node in the solution AI.
Now we'll conclude
actually really with just
a brief description of what goes
on in the quadratic system.
We're not going to discuss
that in a lot of detail.
The most important case of this is
concerns the harmonic oscillator.
Which we've solved elsewhere,
but there's sometimes
things like harmonic oscillator
with impurities in it,
or disruptions, and so
it's nice to have the ability
to solve the general
second order equation and.
I'll point that once again,
it turns out that
the divergent character of
solutions is the generic one.
So for example, in this system, because of
the quadratic dependence of x, eventually,
V is greater than E.
If you go sufficiently far away,
sufficient large values of x,
positive or negative,
you're in the forbidden region.
So, because you have propagation,
because you have a wave
equation in a forbidden region,
you always get a divergent solution,
but then there are special cases,
and these are exactly the Igendouse and
harmonic oscillator here,
you can see the harmonic
oscillator look at the equation.
That when n is an integer
you get bound Igenstate,
this just shows
the characteristics of this so
called parabolic cylinder function.
And we're not going to make practical
use of that in this course.
But, I thought you should see it.
Again, the quadratic equations
solutions to the shortage equates for
a quadratic potential are part of
this systematic family of special
functions that's been developed to solve
the Schrodinger equation in general.
>> Okay that concludes this lecture.
I hope to see you in the next one.