Hello everyone,
welcome back to Exploring Quantum Physics.
I'm Charles Clark,
we're now beginning the last week of
lectures which is going to focus
on current research topics.
And we'll begin with the study of
the state of the art in quantum gasses.
We're going to begin by looking at the
problem of ultra-cold Bose-Einstein gases,
which lead to the famous phenomena
of Bose-Einstein condensation.
So we'll start by seeing how
that concept originated.
And the basic idea began very simply.
Albert Einstein decided to understand how
to quantize many particle systems and
he chose the simplest one,
the ideal gas, to ask the question of
what's the equation of state of an idea
gas when you apply quantum mechanics?
So, the simplest approach is to construct
quantum states of motion for a single
gas atom and then ask how do these get
modified when many atoms are present.
So Einstein decided to try
the following assumption that for
a given quantum state any
number of atoms can occupy it.
So, there's no restriction on the number
of atoms that can be in the same
quantum state of the system.
So, if you think of a particle in a box
the ground state has no nodes and
presumably you can populate that state
with as many atoms as you'd like.
And then, you use statistical mechanics
to calculate the properties of the gas
in thermal equilibrium.
So now, in modern language,
this assumption that any number of
atoms can occupy given a quantum state
is called Bose Einstein statistics
which will apply to bosons,
which have integer spin zero,
one, two, and so on.
So photon is a boson, and
a pair of fairmions is also a boson,
we'll get to that momentarily.
Well, in carrying out this
seemingly simple program,
Einstein discovered something
absolutely amazing.
Here is the original paper
in which he announces it.
And he describes the finding here in blue,
I'll give you my own translation.
He starts by considering the problem
of compressing an ideal gas
at a constant temperature.
So you take a gas that has some particular
value, take the air in the room,
and you keep the temperature
constant while condensing it.
And he finds that for a given temperature,
there's a saturation
density of the ideal gas.
So in other words, as you keep compressing
it you reach a critical pressure
at which suddenly a number
of the molecules of the gas
no longer engage in thermal motion, so
its like you create by increasing
the pressure, a new phase of the gas,
which has zero temperature,
this is very strange.
And in fact Einstein, in this paper,
wondered whether it was simply
a mathematical artifact of the theory and
had any correspondence in reality.
Well when does this condensation
phenomena occur and what is it?
So we're going to go back and
return to classical statistical
mechanics which is what Einstein used.
Now, you might say it's quasi-classical
because it has a Planck's constant in it,
but this is the accepted standard form for
calculating the number of thermally
accessible states of a classical system.
And you will recall that
in the previous lecture,
we discussed the calculation of
the partition function in this form.
So I trust you were able to
evaluate that integral again.
And here's the,
let me rewrite the partition function
by taking the contribution
from the volume out front and
then isolating this contribution from
the momentum divided by h bar cubed.
So this first integral just
has the dimensions of volume.
In fact, we might just have
v equals 0 inside a box and
use that as a volume for
the purposes of thinking about this.
And the second integral also has
the dimensions of volume, or
the inverse dimensions of volume.
You see it's, you can think about
the uncertainty principle p over h
is equal to 1 over x.
So in fact this partition function
takes a simple form, easy to remember.
It's the ratio of the volume to the cube
of the de Broglie wavelength, and
the de Broglie wavelength
is defined as the well,
this integral here is an integral
over three spatial dimensions.
The de Broglie wavelength is defined
as the inverse of the one dimensional
equivalent of that integral.
That's right here, and so
that's the de Broglie wavelength there,
inversely proportional to
the square root of temperature.
Now the conventional
terminology in this field is to
measure quantum gases in terms
of their phase space density.
Which is if you have a gas with a given
number density, say a number of atoms per
cubic centimeter, then the phase
space density is a pure number.
So product of the density and
the cube of the de Broglie wavelength and
it has the interpretation of
being the number of atoms
that exist in the sample per
available quantum state.
So let's see what that implies,
here's a cartoon
from a very nice paper by Eric Cornell,
which you can find additional materials.
It's a good introduction,
an accessible introduction to
Bose-Einstein Condensation.
And it makes note that in an ideal,
classical gas,
there's basically one scale
parameter that describes the gas.
It's the mean distance per particle or
the inverse cube root
of the number density that represents
the average separation of particles.
In the quantum gas there
is a new length scale
that's introduced by the de
Broglie wavelength, and
this is a wave length that
depends upon the temperatures.
It depends upon the mean thermal
energy of the gas, you might say.
So the interesting physics occurs when
these two length scales become comparable,
in other words when the face based
density of the system approaches one.
And what happens then is that
as the phase based density
increases above the critical
value needed for condensation,
a value that depends on circumstances
that we'll discuss a little bit later,
then macroscopic number of atoms
occupy the ground state of the system.
So in other words,
a significant fraction of the system
has effectively zero temperature.
And as the phase based density increases,
a larger quantity of the system
goes into the ground state.
Well let's see how close we are to
Bose-Einstein condensation in
everyday life.
So you see, the air in your room
right now is not very close to
being a Bose-Einstein condensate.
And if you just take a simple
consideration of what would be required to
get it to a phase-based density,
of one, you have two choices.
You either increase number density
by a factor of ten to the seventh.
If you did that,
you'd have a very heavy form of matter.
It would be nothing like an ideal gas and
these ideas of Einstein would
simply be inapplicable.
As an alternative you might decrease the
temperature by a factor of 10 to the 5th.
Well that brings you down
to the milli Kelvin regime,
rather hard to access and
also almost everything freezes
out at such a cold temperature.
And so, basically, the prospects for
Bose-Einstein condensation for a very
long time seemed to be very improbable.
So, here's a very nice book by
Schroedinger, a little essay,
of probably only 100 pages long or
so on on statistical thermodynamics.
He covers a number of interesting
topics in this book, and
here's a quote which represents
the consensus feeling in the scientific
community, that the conditions
of phase-based density are so
demanding, that they're just never
going to apply to ordinary matter.
Nevertheless, there were signs of the
existence of same like the Bose-Einstein
condensation and most notably
the phenomena of Helium super fluidity.
That was discovered in 1938 and
very quickly,
it was suggested by
Fritz London that the super
fluidity of Helium was related in some
way to Bose-Einstein condensation.
However, liquid helium
is a dense system and
very strong interactions
exist between the atoms.
So its not really reasonable to suggest
that it has the dynamics of an ideal gas,
and there are a lot of problems associated
with trying to treat liquid helium
as if it were a Bose-Einstein condensate,
but then about
70 years later, the situation changed
which is the topic of the next part.