Hello everyone, welcome back to exploring
quantum physics, I'm Charles Clark.
In this part,
we're going to look at the experimental
development of Bose-Einstein condensation.
As you saw in the previous lecture,
the theory of BEC
was developed in 1924, and it more less
likely dormant for about 70 years and
then explosive phase of growth
which is still continuing.
70 years after Einstein first proposed
Bose-Einstein condensation on ideal gas,
it was finally observed quite
decisively in experiments.
And that's led to a real revolution in
atomic and condensed matter physics.
So the first production of Bose-Einstein
condensate in a laboratory was done
in 1995 at JILA, the joint institute
of the University of Colorado and
the National Institute of Science and
Technology.
And the key enabling technology for
this work,
was the development of cooling and
trapping of atoms that first came
on the scene in the early 1980s.
This has made it possible to get to much
lower temperatures and has been obtained
in any other material system now down into
the picokelvin machine in some cases.
And the decisive evidence for
Bose-Einstein condensation that
was presented then is a picture of
the clouds of a rubidium
gas after its release
from atomic trap at three
different temperatures.
Now, we'll discuss in a moment how
these temperatures are determined but
what you see are three images
taken at different temperatures.
Going temperatures decreasing
from one frame to the next and
you see a distinctive change in
the density profile of this release cloud.
It's more or less a spherical
cloud at the high temperature and
then a sharp and asymmetric peak
develops as the temperature is lowered.
A very good, accessible account of this
work is given in the additional materials,
written by Eric Cornell, who's, one of
the co-authors of the original experiment.
Let me say something about these
images that you're looking at,
just to try to make them clearer.
It may take a while to
understand their implications.
These are just simple shadow
grams you might say of
the atomic density in the expanded clouds.
So there's a small cloud of atoms here.
Light is incident from the left and
then it's imaged by a microscope which
can scan in the horizontal direction there
and so acquire an image of the density.
It's just determined by the absorption
of the light by the gas.
So what you're seeing is
the integrated density
of the gas in the line of the light.
And the coloring here is just
artificial which is put in
to enhance the visual contrast of
the image, it's just proportional.
It's just a look up table that
reflect the density of the atoms.
So, this asymmetry is a very
interesting aspect of
the formation of the quantum gas.
And if you return to thinking
about classical mechanics,
classical statistical mechanics,
there is is this universal
accounting of states for momentum that's
independent of the trapping potential.
And that has the following implication
that if you have a trap of arbitrary shape
with gas held in it and
then you turn off the trap,
the expanding cloud
eventually becomes spherical completely
independent of the shape of the trap.
Now for a quantum gas on the other hand,
position and momentum don't commute.
And if you have an asymmetric trap,
when you turn it off,
the cloud changes the aspect
ratio of asymmetry.
In other words, the most tightly
bound part of the gas, because of
the uncertainty relation, has the higher
momentum so it expands more rapidly.
There is an analogy of this in optics,
and that,
I'll just state it briefly as follows.
If you have an aperture of arbitrary
shape, here's a strangely shaped aperture,
and it's being illuminated by
light from a thermal source,
an incoherent light source.
And then if you view that
light on a distant screen,
what you'll see is a circularly
symmetric image which is
independent of the shape
of the original aperture.
And you might think about
this in the same way
as the rays coming from
the various part of the aperture.
Just travel at a common speed, and so
they scatter onto the screen at far
distances without retaining any memory
of the particular part of
the aperture from which they came.
For radiation from a coherent source,
on the other hand,
like a laser where all the photons
have the same frequency on
the same directionality,
the common mode structure,
then you get a result similar to what
we just mentioned for the gases.
So if you have coherent radiation
incident on a circular aperture,
well then the far field image is circular.
But, if you have the coherent light
going through an asymmetric aperture
then the far field image reverses the
aspect ratio just as in the case of a gas,
that's for very similar reasons.
So, the inversion of the aspect ratio
as well as a very distinctive density
profile is a very strong sign that
you're producing coherent matter waves,
that is all atoms are in the same
quantum state and with a common phase.
This is illustrated even more
dramatically when one looks at
atoms in optical lattices.
And we'll say something about,
more about optical lattices in
the later part of this lecture.
But you can think of it, for the moment,
it's a just a set of standing light waves
and they form a periodic structure,
not that well represented by my scribbling
here which forms an array of sites.
Just like the sites of a crystal,
atoms in a crystal, and
that can be use as a trap to
form sort of a synthetic lattice
of atoms that are held in
a regular array by light forces.
So when you have a non-condensed gas in
such a trap and you turn the trap off.
Then what you see is spherical
expansion with a little bit of memory
retention of the underlying
lattice structure.
But here is an actual observation
such as system consisting about
150,000 rubidium atoms in a cubic lattice.
So you're seeing a line of sight
image showing a spherical expansion
of the cloud.
Well, if you go into Bose-Einstein
condensate phase where all
the atoms in the lattice
have a common phase, then the expansion
image is radically different.
You can see that the gas
expands really indiscrete
directions that carry the underlying
symmetry of the lattice.
This is really an analog of brag
defraction of x-rays or flight.
And this is not just a fluke,
the last of these images is
the one that's most amazing to me.
And it actually shows that
when you turn off the trap
the cloud falls under
the influence of gravity,
as you would expect, and
that this cubic expansion,
this highly ordered expansion phase is
not just a fluke, it continues forever.
So that's a powerful demonstration,
of the production of coherence
in the matter waves.
How do we understand in detail the
dynamics of the Bose-Einstein condensate?
Well it turns out there's a very useful
framework, originally developed for
the study of liquid helium.
Where it wasn't really that successful
because liquid helium is a strongly
interacting system.
But it has proven to be of incredibly
valuable use in understanding
the dilute Bose-Einstein condensates
that are produced in the lab today.
And let me emphasize,
these gases that show this remarkable
quantum behavior are very dilute.
They have a density about
100,000th that of air, yet
they showed that remarkable
collective phenomenon.
So this equation describes a framework
in which all the atoms in the gas
are said to be characterized to be
of the same wave function psi or
orbital psi you may call it.
The interaction between the atoms is
the two body interaction between a given
pair of atoms is represented by
a direct delta pseudo potential.
The type was discussed in
a previous lecture characterized by
the scattering length which is a proxy for
the full two body interaction potential in
a limited energy range near zero energy.
So called scattered length,
on that is a parameter which is determined
by independent experimental measurements
of the atomic collision physics.
And I emphasize that, in modern work,
there are no adjustable parameters in the
description of a Bose-Einstein condensate.
Everything is determined,
some cases by great accuracy,
by independent types of measurements.
So the time evolution of
the wave function is given by
a variation on the Schrodinger equation.
The first part of which
you should recognize as
the usual single particle
Schroedinger equation that we've
discussed at length in
previous parts of this course.
And then the new element
is this nonlinear term
which reflects the influence of
the interaction between atoms so
it's proportional to the number of
atoms to the scattering length and
then it has a cubic nonlinearity and
the wave function and this gives rise to
typo dynamic that just not seen at all
in the ordinary Schrodinger equation.
Here's an example of
the generation of soliton in
a Bose-Einstein condensate by
the use of optical phase imprinting.
And the way the experiment is done
is that there's a cloud of gas in
the Bose-Einstein condensate, then it's
illuminated by near resonant light,
and there's a mask that shadows half
the condensate from the light and
the part that's illuminated
acquires a phase shift
which is just due to the ac-Stark effect
of the light, the light shift potential.
And then one looks at the evolution
of the condensate after that.
Which is shown here,
an experiment done the year 2000.
This shows the cloud of
the gas at a sequence of
time intervals after this imprinting
of the optical phase and what
you see is the development of a density
notch which propagates along the cloud.
This is actually a matter-wave soliton.
The top row of the images
are experimental measurements and
the bottom are calculations using
the Gross–Pitaevskii equation
with the experimental parameters.
Here's some more recent
work that just shows how
we can generate arbitrary angular
momentum states in the ring-shaped traps.
Prefers experimental
work done by my colleagues at the National
Institute Science and Technology.
And so it uses an optical trap which is
schematized in this frame,
it consist of a supporting light sheet and
then a ring that's created from
symmetric being with a core in it.
And this creates a confining potential
that's of a toroidal shape indicated here.
And then another beam is introduced
that is sort of like a paddle.
It's a light sheet that
cuts through the Taurus
just like you might cut through
a donut with a knife and
then that paddle can be rotated
around to stir the condensate up.
And so you see images here
in this lower frame of how
the cloud of atoms is moved
by the action of this paddle.
So the general characteristics of these
experiments is about half a million sodium
atoms in this ring trap, toroidal trap the
radius of this trap is about 20 microns.
So one starts with a nice
quiet ground state
of the condensate stirs it up and
then releases and measures, the density.
And what is seen there,
here's the experimental data.
These again are these absorption images.
It's a sort of the most common way of
viewing Bose-Einstein condensates.
These are labeled after the fact by
the values of the angular momentum.
We have a donut here and
there is a conserve angular momentum
LZ along the axis perpendicular
to the plane of the donut.
And depending on the stirring conditions
one can generate the successive
values of the quantized angular momentum.
There will be a problem in the final
exam that deals with this and
just to give a hint ahead of time,
you could think about how these angular
momentum could be generated by thinking
along the lines of the bohr model.
In other words, we're going to
stir the atoms with a paddle and
promote them to states of
higher angular momentum.
So you can think about,
well, if the angular momentum is
quantized as proposed by Bohr.
That is the integer multiple
of Planck's constant,
what does that imply about the rotation
frequency of the paddle that
you need to tune to in order
to get that quantized result?
And here is a you might say
the smoking gun for quantization.
These two frames look
at the distribution of
whole sizes that are seen
in various experiments.
The upper frame and the lower,
they represent two modes of release of
the condensate, one of which turns out
to give a more regular set of images.
But what can see is that the whole
sizes come in these quantized groups
which are attributed to the generation of
different values in the angle momentum.
And the use of the Gross–Pitaevskii
equation with the parameters
appropriate to the experiment shows
that there's a relatively good agreement
with some deviation for the various
angle momentum states that observe.
So this frames show images of
the experimental data which is
indicated by the red lines with the
results of theoretical calculations for
different values of the angular momentum.
And they show that the whole size
Increases with angular momentum.
This is a reflection of the sort of
repulsive centrifugal potential that we
found in the discussion of angular
momentum in an earlier lecture.
So finally, I'll mention some more
recent work with this stirring
procedure in which the phenomena
of hysteresis is found.
So this experiment reported
in nature early 2014,
involves stirring and condensate up and
then stirring it back to
return to the original state.
And it has found that there is
an asymmetry in the stirring and
de-stirring procedure.
Much of is seen In classical magnetism,
the magnetic induced is
a function of applied field.
And this is a theme that's pursued
in this work is often referred to
as atomtronics which has a goal
of using coherent matter waves to
implement functionality such
as one has in electronics.
That is to make circuits which use
atoms rather than electrons as
a carrier of information, and
of mass, and of spin, and
to explore the possibilities that are
available there that would perhaps someday
complement conventional electronics for
new functional purposes.
So I'll just conclude by
mention of some accessible
reviews that will show you examples
of things that can be done.
Open source of these articles
is all found on the archives.
And these are also good references
to search against them on Google Scholar
to find examples of more recent work.
I think you'll see it's
a very vibrant field.