Hello everyone,
welcome back to Exploring Quantum Physics.
I'm Charles Clark.
We're going to conclude this lecture by
a look at some of the current research
topics in the area of quantum gases.
Now we're going to look at a few examples
of current research in
ultracold quantum gases.
And we just have time for
a few topics, but
I think you'll see
the richness of the field.
And by looking at references
to these in the open
literature you can find many
other interesting ideas.
So first of all in situ
imaging of individual atoms.
Now this differs from the mode that we've
been using earlier in this lecture.
Where we've been discussing
atomic absorption images,
which don't resolve individual sides.
And there's some amazing
developments in this area.
Another very striking invention,
the cold-atom scanning probe microscope.
So this is something that
might be very suitable
as an extension of
the atomic force microscope
that's based on the use of an atomic
Bose-Einstein condensate as a tip.
It's not just a concept.
It's something that has been implemented.
Atomic, atom interferometry
over very long distances.
10s of meters with flight
times of several seconds.
That can be used to test the equivalence
principle for example, or
do very precise measurements
of Earth rotation.
And then, the optical lattice clock,
whose had an amazing development
reported early in the year 2014.
Making it then,
the world's most accurate clock.
And also as we'll see providing
a sort of laboratory for
studying basic quantum and ebotic physics.
So to the issue of in-situ imaging.
Here's work done by a group of
David Weiss at Penn State University.
You see three images and the glowing
points within each one of these
are individual atoms sitting on
the sites on a cubic optical lattice.
And the different columns here have
the image focused on different
interior planes of the lattice.
So what you see,
if you look at just one of these images.
You see the very bright spots.
Those are individual atoms.
And then there's some fuzzy areas nearby.
Those are atoms in a different plane
that's defocused from the image.
And so you can see that the lattice here
is imperfectly and irregularly filled.
On the other hand, every glowing point
is at an optical lattice site in
sort of a regular crystal array.
The lower row here is the same system.
With a photograph taken three seconds
after the photograph of the upper image.
And so, with this, you can see
that there is both stability and
change in the lattice of many common
sites that are occupied in both.
And then, there are also some changes.
So, this just shows remarkably
how you can get regular
registration of atoms and maintain it
over a significant period of time.
An even more amazing example,
involves the creation of an optical
lattice inside an electron microscope.
And in the lattice sites,
a rubidium atom is held.
And it's fluorescing, so that you see
the light from the rubidium atoms.
And then the electron beam can
be swept over the system and
selectively ionize the rubidium
atoms in certain sites.
So that you make vacant holes in
the lattice where there are no atoms.
Remarkable act of
precision engineering here.
And my colleague noted that the font
design is rather elegant as well.
This is of course
the Schrödinger equation.
Finally, on this imaging frontier,
a tremendous development by
Markus Greiner's group at Harvard
called the quantum gas microscope.
And here you're seeing
a image of ultra-cold atoms,
Bose-Einstein condensate,
held in an optical lattice.
With a field of view of 100
microns tenth of a millimeter.
Very large, and on the right
here is another image taken of
a smaller region where you can clearly
see this signals from individual atoms.
If you like this sort of thing.
I strongly recommend looking
at the videos where you
actually see real time motion of atoms and
optical lattices on a time
scales of fractions of a second.
Just fascinating work.
And so this is making possible
analysis of ultracold
atom systems at a degree of resolution.
Simply was not possible
about five years ago.
Next topic,
cold-atom scanning probe microscopes.
So here's an artist's conception
of an instrument that has
been built at the University of Tumigan,
in Germany.
And it compares, a so
called cold atom tip,
which is just a Bose Einstein condensate,
held in a small electromagnetic trap.
Compared to a traditional
atomic force microscope tip.
So the AFM, or atomic force microscope,
is now a widely use analytical tool for
measuring microstructure.
The BEC based concept gives a tip about
the same size, but it is a lot softer.
So it can measure surface tip
interactions over greater
range than is possible with the standard
conventional atomic force microscopy.
Here's the reality of that schematic
that is shown in the previous figure.
Very impressive, reported in
Nature Nanotechnology in the year 2011.
And this instrument, see here's
the length scale three millimeters.
Consists of a carrier chip, which is here
that can scan a Bose Einstein condensate
back and forth over the sample.
And the sample in this case consists of
carbon nanotubes that have been
grown on the so called nano chip.
And the BEC is scanned over the tubes to
generate a signal that tells you something
about the topography of the tube.
Here is an image from that paper.
The sensing mechanism that's
used in this instrument
is the loss of the atoms
from the condensate.
So when the condensate is brought
near another material system,
there are attractive forces that are
imposed on the atoms in the condensate.
And some of them can leave the condensate.
They typically don't get more
atoms back in the condensate.
And so the method of analysis of
the system involves optical absorption
imaging to determine the population loss,
or its inverse.
The remaining atom fraction.
So this is the spatially resolved signal
that's been obtained from that instrument.
There are many other concepts for this
type of scanning probe microscopy using,
for example, polarized,
in polarized atoms to detect
micro-magnetic structure.
Another really amazing
technical development,
long baseline atom in ofrometry.
This is being implemented in Mark
Kasovich's group at Stanford University.
And, here is a schematic.
It's basically a large atomic
fountain clock where ultracold
atom samples produced down here.
It's subject to some
pulses to mix the states,
a sort of typical atomic clock scheme.
Then it flies up and
back about ten meters.
And this system is being
successfully commissioned and
is designed to test
the Equivalence Principle.
That is, whether the inertial mass and
the gravitational mass
are proportional, or
you might say exactly the same.
By looking at the differential
acceleration of two species.
So, Rb85 and Rb87 can be used in this
system with very similar optical
control because the transition
wavelengths are quite close together.
So this is another application of the use
of isotope shifts in
ultracold atomic physics.
So finally to conclude,
amazing work done recently
in advancing the fundamental
accuracy of clocks.
And as of Spring of 2014,
this accuracy of a few
parts in ten to the 18th,
has gone beyond what was done
previously in a single ion based clock.
The remarkable thing about this instrument
is that it's using many atom system
trapped in an optical lattice.
Though, with minimal multiple
occupancy of lattice sites.
And it has been characterized in
particular by this measurement
of the blackbody radiation
shift on the two clock states.
This is a very subtle effect but
modern clocks have become so
accurate that the determination of
the blackbody radiation effects on
atomic transition frequencies has
become a major effort in the world.
Both theoretically, and experimentally.
Another use for clocks is the sensors.
Because if you can measure shifts and
frequency to a very high accuracy,
you can determine the effects
of environmental influences.
So, things like magnotomatry,
assilamontometry, gidaroscopy, gravity
gradiomantry are all a good applications
area for very high precision clocks.
And also, fundamental scientific study.
So this is an example of one such
use of the optical lattice clock
that was just on the previous slide.
It's used as a laboratory for
understanding some quantum many-body
effects associated with interactions
between atoms in the clock.
So that concludes this very brief survey.
There are many other topics
that could be raised.
But I hope you've captured some of
the excitement and interest in this field.
And seen how it's spawning.
Well, it's not really spawning what
you would call commercial technologies
at the present time.
But it certainly has spawned,
a vast range of improvements in
basic measurement techniques.
Fundamental scientific understanding,
and some applications of sensing
that are based on new previously
unexplored physical principles.
It's all made possible by
the ability to cool, or trap atoms.
Prepare them in a deterministic way,
and analyze them.
And it's a very exciting field of research
that I hope you'll keep track of.