Hello everyone.
Welcome back to Exploring Quantum Physics.
I'm Charles Clark, and
in this part we're going to begin
a study of the Dirac Equation,
which is the foundational equation of
relativistic quantum mechanics for
description of the electron and
other spin one-half particles.
So now we're going to begin,
Introduction to the Dirac equation.
It's an amazing equation with
unbelievable consequences, and
it's really sort of the first
step down the road towards
relativistic quantum mechanics which
is a deep subject in its own right.
And it is rather advanced for
a survey course of this type.
And so, our treatment is going to be
specific but not very comprehensive.
We're going to look at the original
work of Dirac, who early on,
just a few years after the Schrodinger
equation was discovered decided that
he would investigate the extension
of quantum mechanical ideas
to make them consistent with
the theory of relativity.
The Schrodinger equation you see is
a non-relativistic equation based on
a non-relativistic description of
mechanics due to classical mechanics.
So Dirac undertook to understand
the nature of the wave equation for
the electron in a relativistic form.
So we're going to discuss
just the equation for
a free particle in one dimension
to keep things simple.
So here's the Schrodinger equation for
free particle in one dimension.
And it's easy to find
the solutions I mean,
basically the solutions are e to
the i p dot r divided by h bar.
And then an e to the minus i omega t.
With e is equal to h bar omega.
So, Dirac saw to find
a relativistic version
of this equation, which would have
the following very important feature.
It would be homogeneous in time and
spatial variables.
You see the non relativistic
equation is first order in time and
second order in spatial derivative and
because of the Lorentz transformation,
a fully invariant equation would
have to be linear in space and time.
And also there's a reason why you
want there to be an evolution
equation of this form, that is, you want
to preserve the idea of a wave function.
And you want to understand how
a wave function evolves in time.
So the only ingredients at your
disposal are the momentum,
which of course is the p is
equal to h bar over i d dx.
So that has the right
relativistic invariance.
And then there's a requirement,
this is the relativistic dispersion
relation, which describes
the relationship between the energy, and
the momentum and the mass of a particle.
So you want your equation of motion
to satisfy this relativistic
dispersion relation.
So, possibly there should
be another term here,
which would then if you look at this and
think about you'll see that this does.
This does satisfy
the conditions of relativity,
provided that alpha squared and
beta squared are both equal to 1 and
that they satisfy this
anti-commutation relation.
Can you see why that is?
Okay so, you can see that alpha and
beta can't just be pure numbers.
In fact, neither one of them can
be an ordinary number because
the anti-commutation relation
has to be satisfied.
But, in quantum mechanics we're quite
used to using linear operators and
so for
example here are choices of alpha and
beta, you can choose sigma one of
the alpha and sigma 3 of the beta.
These are the so called Pauli matrices and
this has a very straightforward
geometric interpretation.
So, you're familiar with
non-commuting operations.
This one in a two-dimensional system
reflects the vector about the 45 degree
line and
sigma 3 here inverts the coordinates.
So here's how the sigma 1 acts,
here's how sigma 3 acts.
So you can see that the operation sigma 3,
sigma 1 leaves this where
sigma one sigma 3 gives that.
So, that gives us an example of the fact
that these mysterious documenting
quantities can at least be mapped onto
familiar geometrical representation.
So, in fact much of what we do now
is not going to depend on choosing
a specific representation for
alpha and beta.
First of all there are many,
many choices that give the same result and
isn't unique, sort of like the gauge and
variance problem.
What's important is that they
satisfy the commutation relations.
But if you choose two by two
matrices that's easy to solve,
the stationary equation, Dirac equation,
it's just proportional to a plane wave
and the remarkable thing is that, you
get both positive and negative energies.
Now you never get negative energies
in the solution for free particle in
non-relativistic mechanics because that
would require an imaginary momentum and
it would give rise to a non
normalizable wave function.
But as you're going to
find in the homework,
if you have a solution of the Dirac
equation, that's a positive energy.
Then you can find from it, another
solution that has a negative energy.
And it has the same
desirable characteristics
of the positive energy solution.
So there's nothing in the mathematics that
says you can exclude the negative energy
solutions, like there is in
the non-relativistic Schrodinger equation.
And these indicate the existence
of anti-matter, that is,
these negative energy solutions have been
found to be associated with the existence
of anti-particles that are apparently
present for all particles.
Okay, so now another consequence of
the Dirac Equation, very significant one,
was actually found in the two-dimensional
or three-dimensional versions both but
we'll go directly to the three
dimensional equation.
So now you see this is
a straightforward generalization
of the one-dimensional Dirac equation.
It has a contribution from each of the
three spatial coordinates, and when you
go and require that this relativistic
dispersion relation be satisfied,
you find that there's a class
of anti-commutation relations.
So the alphas have to anti-commute among
themselves in the way indicated here.
The alpha have to anti-commute with beta,
and then beta square is equal to one.
Now, this part seems fine, but
what about the conservation
of angular momentum?
That's one of these things that you
would surely wish to see conserved,
but it doesn't commute
with this Hamiltonian.
I think that's quite easy to see
because this has the form of a vector.