Hello everyone,
welcome back to Exploring Quantum Physics.
I'm Charles Clark.
In this part, we're going to look at
some of the applications of spin and
antimatter both in fundamental science,
technology, and aspects of every day life.
This part of the lecture is just going to
be an overview of how many of the things
that we discussed in the previous parts
come together in practical applications.
So, we introduced the Pauli matrices
previously and it turns out,
these constitute most widely
use representation of spins.
So, in other words, for
spin one-half particle, the spin
operator can be written in this way.
This amounts, you might say to
a specific choice of the alpha and
beta that are in draft papers.
And, indeed, the alphas and
betas in the three-dimensional system
are constructed using these poly matrices.
And now, with this necessarily
two-dimensional representation,
we basically have a two by two bases
that describes the spin states.
And so in this bases,
we identify this bases vector as
a spin up and this is spin down.
And indeed when we turn
on magnetic fields for
example we can see that with
choice of the poly matrix.
>> This convention for
the electrons make sense.
In fact, the direction of the angular
momentum of the electron is up and
this one is down.
By up and down we mean the projection
of s upon the third axis is either
plus one half or minus one half
Plus h-bar to a minus h-bar.
So the important spin one-half
particles are the electron, and
various other massive particles.
And the neutrino.
These are all fermions.
And so according to
Wolfgang Pauli they obey something
called the Exclusion Principle, meaning
that total wavefunction has to change sign
under exchange of any
two identical fermions.
So the total wavefunction
includes both space and
spin parts So, it is
useful to distinguish the symmetric and
anti symmetric combinations of
electron spin wave function.
So, here for example, we have a,
let say we have two electrons.
So, since their angular momentum are h bar
over 2 The sum of the two zero and one.
for the state zero, here's the linear
combination of two electron
spin functions that gives a net of zero.
And then there's the states that have one.
Here are the functions.
And so this one's called a singlet,
because there's only one,
this is called a triplet
because there's three.
And this structure is
found in a pervasive way.
For example, let's just have a look
at a topic of recent interest,
has been the world's most accurate clock.
I think that's changed slightly,
still among the world's most accurate,
there's aluminum iron logic enabled
atomic clock developed by David.
And so here are the various energy levels
that are involved in the operation of
this clock.
And the group in blue are spin triplets.
That you might identify the spin triplets.
Then, this one is a spin singlet.
Then, when you turn on magnetic fields
you have possible nuclear spins that
can affect the overall angular momentum,
but by and large this classification
of overall total spin is very useful
in the design operation of atomic logs.
Magnetism feral magnetism or
the existence of permanent
magnets typically associated with elements
that have many spin parallel electrons.
So let's say iron has
six electrons in the so
called 3d orbital, and so
that enables them to largely line up
so in the ground state of iron
you have net magnetic moment.
Of two bohr magnetons.
So iron is of course a very
commonly used magnetic material.
Neodymium is the basis of
the ultra-hard magnets, one of which is
shown in the magnetic levitation demo that
you can see in the additional materials.
Again that's based on the fact that it
has an F shell that can hold up to 14
electrons so you get a,
the ground state in Neodymium
has four parallel spins creating
a large permanent magnetic moment.
Most magnetic atom in the periodic table.
Is gadolinium which has eight
electron spins lined up.
So, the foundations of magnetism
are based on electron spins.
There's an emerging technology, well
it's really an emerging science still,
it has yet to yield.
A wide range of practical devices,
but the read heads on modern
magnetic storage media, are due to a
phenomenon called Giant Magnetoresistance,
which involves the control of electrical
current by magnetic techniques.
So it makes it possible for
a very high density magnetic storage,
and spin tronics refers to the search for
an alternative
to electron charge as a carrier of
current in solids there's a nice
recent review of the spin tronics by and
Stewart Parkin who are the leaders.
Expiremental leaders.
And the foundational device for
this spintronics is something
called the transistor.
Hypothesized 24 years ago and still
a subject to that active to something.
It seems to be Hard to implement for
various reasons but
there's very active research on the use
of spin as a replacement for charge.
Antimatter again is something
that no one knew about.
Or really even imagined
prior to the Dirac equation,
and it is a somewhat exotic sort
of matter, but it is widely used,
positron emission tomography is
a medial diagnostic procedure,
a several million positron emission
tomographs are taken of medical patients
in the United States every year.
Positrons are often used in
sync with pron light sources,
because they have a longer lifetime
in electronic storage ring.
There are various types
of analytical techniques,
for example, for finding voids and
defects in materials.
As various types of positronium
spectroscopy that have been developed.
So these seemingly arcane and
minor features
that are found really only in the Dirac
equation or first revealed there.
A turn out to have a significant
impact even in daily life.
So that concludes this lecture
hope to see you again.