Are problem 27 circuits connected to a 9 volt battery with a net resistance of forty point five ohms.
How much energy is being dissipated by the circuit in a time interval of one minute.
All right.
And be careful.
This is energy in one minute.
All right we basically just have a simple circuit with one battery.
Basically one resistor we know this is Nine volts.
We know our is forty point five.
We can easily calculate the power right the power being dissipated by that resistance is simply V squared
divided by our.
So we get 81.
That's our 9 squared divided by forty point five.
All right.
Now remember what this is.
This is measured in Watts.
That's the rate at which energy is being dissipated.
Now we're given a certain time.
So really this is energy
per unit time per delta-T.
So at the end all we're looking for here is really this guy the energy.
So we need to bring the Delta team on the other side.
So the total energy dissipated in one minute is call it e is going to be equal to my power multiplied
by the time interval.
So the power we just said was 81 divided by forty point five multiply by my time interval now.
Careful you don't put in one minute.
Remember this is in Watts's in Joule per second.
So we need to multiply by 60 seconds in order to get the right units.
We want to get our answer to be measured in joules at the end.
All right put that in the calculator punch it in.
You get 120 joules of energy.
So a correct answer for that one choice a problem 28 a resistor has a value of 1 times 10 to the 6 ohms.
The capacitor is one Daniel Feraud connected in series to a battery and the switch asks What is the
time constant.
Well this is just the definition right the time constant.
You gave it defined as the letter tau and for a simple series circuit like this the time constant is
simply the resistance multiplied by the capacitance.
So in this case we simply get 1 times 10 of the six ohms multiplied by a 1 nano Feraud Nano is 10 of
the minus nine.
So carry that out.
You're left with one times ten to the minus three.
And again that is measured in seconds.
OK so one time 10 of the minus three looks like toys B to me.
All I have the one there but you really don't need the one.