All right in order to measure the current and voltage through a circuit how must an ammeter in a volt
meter be connected.
You can just picture a simple circuit with a DC power supply and you imagine just one resistor here.
OK.
And the way this is always done is you always have an ammeter measures current and you want current
to flow through the meter and the voltage is always kind of between for example two points for example
across this resistor.
You always want to put that volt meter here in parallel with what you're measuring.
OK so the ammeter should not be in peril or should be in series and the volt meter here.
So it can't be any of those choices because the ammeters wrong.
So you're left in the volt meter must be in parallel.
So the volt meter can't be in series given that choice.
So really choice D is the best answer here.
This is kind of what it looks like.
You always want the current to flow through the ammeter and you're always measuring the potential difference
between those points should always be and in parallel are problem 30 a battery with internal resistance.
Are electromotive force supplies a current eye to a light bulb of resistance.
Are the power dissipated by this circuit is what I want.
This is just a simple circuit.
You have an internal resistance.
And now we're going to have a light bulb on this side.
All right.
So here's my electromotive force the internal resistance is UPPER CASE our light bulb is lowercase r
this is basically just a simple series circuit.
So if you want to know the power dissipated Well what's the total resistance right.
Both resistors dissipate power.
So the total equivalent resistor you simply are plus lowercase r.
Now if you want to know the power dissipated Well again you know the power supplied is multiplied by
the current and that has to be equal to the total power dissipated.
So what is the current flowing through here.
Leave this one the way it is the current flowing through it that's just given by Ohm's law.
Right.
The current is going to be given by the voltage divided by the total resistance which is our Plus our.
So at the end of the day we get e squared divided by the total equivalent resistance.
That's how much power is being dissipated in the circuit and that's it.
So we've got the light bulb that's dissipating power and we also have the internal resistance that that
is dissipating power.