All right let's tackle some of these multiple choice questions.
First question says a 60 watt bulb operating on a 120 volt household circuit has a resistance closest
to what will 60 watt tells me the power at 60 and voltage is 120.
Now even though it's a C that's not a really big concern.
We can still use what we know again or ask to solve for the resistance.
Well one thing you could do is you could just calculate what the current is and once you know the current
then you can go through and use Ohm's law and calculate with the resistance.
Or you could just write it right from the first step.
You know that the power equation we wrote three different ways.
One way it was written like this.
All right this was the power dissipated Imay resistance R if it had a voltage across it equal to some
value.
So here we just rearrange this equation isolate our So you get v squared over the.
And now we simply substitute This is 120 squared.
Well that's 120 multiplied by 120 and divided by 60.
All right.
Now we can simplify.
Cut out one of the zeros.
The 12 or the six.
You left with the two.
And at the end two multiplied with the 120.
Well let's try that again.
240 and 240 ohms.
Therefore C is the correct answer for this one.
All right.
How about the second one.
Which of the following is equivalent to the unit of electrical resistance.
All right so now we have different choices that involve cool ohms volts for an amp.
We have Duell we have anyway a whole bunch of different units here for electrical resistance.
Actually C might not be for cool.
I'm actually probably pretty sure who it is but so electrical resistance.
I would never ask you for units of something.
Try to remember a simple equation that involves that quantities.
So here we go.
Ohm's law.
So we know that the units of electrical resistance should be in units of volts divided by current.
So that should be something in volts and current is measured in amperes So at the end of the day what
you get is choice B that's volts divided by our peers.
Pretty straightforward problem either is the first two.
Hopefully you've got those.