I'll read Question Five says we have two tungsten wires with different cross sections.
One is a the other one is to a different Currence they're shown here and at the end they want to know
what is the ratio of the drift velocity of the particles in the second wire to that first wire.
All right.
So we're looking for VD that's the drif philosophy and we're basically given things about the geometry
of the wire and information about the current flowing through it.
So if you remember now that let's do a wire one over here call this wire two over here.
All right.
And really the equation we need is that the current How is that related to the drift velocity if you
remember it was the number density and it was the charge of the electron multiplied by the cross-sectional
area and multiplied by the drift velocity is how we related our current to that drift velocity of the
electrons flowing down the wire.
So the end is the number density is the charge of each electron.
Both of these are going to be the same because we're talking about two tungsten wires so n is a material
property is just the basic charge of the electron So that's the same for both.
So what are really doing then.
And we want to know the drift velocity so let's just isolate the drift philosophy for wire 1.
So we have that the drift velocity here is going to be equal to the current the current is simply I
see over this one here it's simply an email divided by the cross-sectional area.
Now for the second wire the drift velocity in this case the current now is four.
I.
What else.
And an e remain the same.
And now the cross-section is to a.
So this one here we could simplify this a little bit at the end the expression becomes two.
And again I and E multiplied by a I just divided for over two and just took that term outside.
So you see at the end now what we're left with if we're asked for the drift velocity of the second wire
this one divided by this one which you're going to end up doing now is we're going to end up getting
the value of two because it's two times bigger.
So that's it for number five.
All right here's number six says the following graphs represent the resistivity as a function of the
absolute temperature.
Keep that in mind as a function of temperature which are the graph shows the resistivity change of a
metallic wire.
All right.
So metal what happens when I increase the temperature it is the resist Dev-T change.
Or does it get lower or does it get bigger.
What certainly doesn't stay constant.
It's actually just crossed that one out.
All right this means that the resistivity would not depend on the temperature and you should remember
from the class that for metals the resistivity increases with temperature so can't be that one it's
really can't be this one.
All right so we're left with both of those and this was one of the properties that as you increase the
temperature over a pretty broad range for most metals you can get a linear dependence which means that
the resistivity is proportional to the absolute temperature.
OK.
So there you have it folks so this one.
Just knowing a little bit of how material properties change with temperature you'd be able to answer
that question.