All right for problem 7 we have an electric current of one eyup flows through a circuit the part of
the circuit contains a 12 volt battery with an internal resistance of two ohms.
What is the volt meter reading so you apply a volt meter and you connected to this side and that side
of the terminals of the battery.
So if you call this point A and Point B what would you actually measure was the voltage.
VB mine is effectively for this one you're basically just going to start at point 8 we're going to move
across point B we're going across a resistor across a battery.
So the way you do this now is if I start out Point am at some potential vitæ and now I'm going to a
resistor in the direction of the current.
I know there's one amp going through here.
So mine has to multiply by one that's the voltage drop across that internal resistance.
And now I'm going to gain 12 volts and then I eventually get to Point B.
So it just re-arranges this is minus to plus 12 gives me 10.
So VB.
Mine is V.A simply equal to 10 volts.
OK so you get a little bit less than what the ideal MF is of that battery.
OK so 10 volts see is the correct answer for this one for problem.
Kind of a similar setup different battery different direction of the battery also different internal
resistance different current.
So now we have electric current of two amps flows through a circuit part of the battery six volt internal
resistance is point five.
What does the volt meter read.
I notice in this case all the answers are positive numbers.
So again we're going to proceed to using the same method it worked for the last problem probably worked
for this one.
All right.
Define those two points.
And now we simply start at point a move toward Point B.
So we have V.A now we're going across a resistor We're going across a resistor in the direction of the
current.
So we get a voltage drop given by two multiplied by 0.5 value of the resistance.
And now we're going across a battery set.
Looking now we're going from the high to the low potential so therefore we get a voltage drop given
by 6 volts and then we end up going to point B V.A is what.
So this here is minus one and minus 6.
Gives me VB.
All right in this case we have V-A.
Mine is VB equal to 7.
If you did it the other way around if you got VB.
Mine is V.A you get minus 7.
Again here they're really just talking about a magnitude of the Volt volt meter reading.
So the correct answer for this one would be a no negative answer.
So there's not really a technically it would you'd have to kind of define which side is which.
But you'd get Plus-X plus seven or minus seven depending on how you hook it up.