It for problem 13 says the EAF of the batteries six volts when the battery delivers a current of 0.5
amps to the external circuit the potential difference between the terminals of the battery is five point
eight volts.
The internal resistance of the battery is what.
So again all we have to do for this one let's just consider a ideal battery is a six volt battery and
it has some internal resistance trying to find and just consider this small segment of current.
Now we're going to say there we're going to assume there is a current eye going through and the current
EIS 0.5 amps.
This ideal battery six volts we're really looking for what are is.
And when we measure the potential difference between the ends what do we end up measuring is five point
eight.
So you can imagine here if we call this point A and Point B.
So the difference of potential is 5.8 between points and point B.
So let's just go from point A to Point B what would we get good V-A is equal to.
Sorry.
You get V-A where you start and now you go through those six full battery you get an increase of potential
of six and then I get a drop equal to the current flowing through it multiplied by the internal resistance.
Then you end up going all the way to point B.
So let me just rearrange just a little bit so you get six minus I are equal to VB minus v.
All right and VB VI of mine is V-A is my 5.8 volts.
All right.
So the only unknown again we know the current here is 0.5.
So you simply have to just rearrange this equation a little bit.
So you're going to get six minus five point eight equals to zero point five multiplied by R..
This guy gives me 0.2 0.5 r.
So at the end you get Rs 0.4 ohms OK.
0.2 divided by 0.5.
So the correct answer for this one has to be choice.
All right.
Hubble 14:14 says a wire is connected to a battery of a constant voltage and negligible internal resistance
by decreasing which of the following.
Can we increase the power dissipated in the wire.
Rs.
So what we have here again with value for the resistance is the resists Dev-T the length and divided
by the area.
Now we have different choices here.
We can play with the length.
Here let me maybe switch the notation here so that we have the same thing.
D is the diameter of the wire row's the resistivity.
So all we want to do if we want to increase the power we have a fixed voltage.
Again our power now is simply this V squared over r.
So how would I increase the power I want to make.
Are as small as possible and I do that by well.
If I make l small thats going to make the resistance small.
If I make d small Now thats going to make the resistance big because I'm going to make the cross-sectional
area small if I divide by a small number that's going to increase my resistance.
So certainly can't be Alan.
How about choice C choice C has decrease L and the resistivity both of those are in the numerator over
here.
So if you do decrease both of those you're going to end up decreasing the resistance which is what we
want so that one works.
We've already said it can't be d so it's not only the resistance L it's really both of them have the
same effect of increasing the power dissipated in that wire.
It seems the correct answer for this point.