All right here's a problem.
Fifteen two resistors with resistances three home and two OAM are connected in series with a 12 volt
battery.
The current in the circuit is two apes.
What is the internal resistance down although they don't really show you the internal resistance.
You can always kind of assume that there is one especially if the questions asking you that to calculate
what the internal resistance is.
So first thing we're going to do well let's do a loop rule around here.
Right if we do a loop rule around here we know there's two amps.
So right away we're going to first see there's going to be a voltage drop across this internal resistance.
Let me just call it lower case r.
So we get minus two multiply by little are now going across the battery I'm going to get a 12 volt battery
and then I'm going to just combine the three and the two over here again is going to be a voltage drop
given by five multiplied by the current the current flowing through it is two.
OK.
And that there has to be equal to zero.
So let's simplify this a little bit.
So this becomes 12 that is 10 and minus two times are has to be equal to zero.
All right.
So we get two must be equal to two times.
R R should be equal to one point zero ohms.
Correct answer for this one is choice a ok problem 16 is similar you have two resistors this time in
parallel 30 and 60 ohm they're connected to a 6 volt battery.
They tell us the current is flowing through the battery here 0.25 amps.
What's the internal resistance.
Again it doesn't look like there's one in the drawing but you just put one in there right next to the
battery it's in series with the battery.
OK so one day I would probably do to begin with here is probably to combine both of these into one equivalent
resistance since there's only two.
It's very easy the equivalent resistance if they're in parallel.
You just multiply them and divided by the sum so you get 180 over 9.
Should give me 20 ohms.
OK.
So now I could start at one corner and do a complete loop around.
So and do a loop rule that's it.
So first thing I'm going to get a voltage drop across this internal resistance that's given by the current
0.25 multiplied by the value of the unknown internal resistance plus 6 volts.
And then I get another voltage drop across this eq. 20 ohm resistor and the current is still zero point
twenty five.
Now that's multiplied by 20 and that's equal to zero.
OK you just have to do a little bit of math.
Let me bring this term on the other side.
So you get 0.25 are going to be equal to 6 minus.
This is one over four multiplied by 20.
Should Give me five OK six minus five gives me one.
So ours should be equal to four.
All right.
One divided by 0.25 gives me forums.
So at the end I should get a choice.
DS The correct answer for a problem 16.
OK.
Kind of the same procedure as the previous one just resistors in parallel.
Pretty straightforward.