If you really want me to go into a little bit more depth in detail with motion diagrams, just let me
know in the comments section and I will do that.
But for this next example, you could feel free to try this on your own.
Just keep in mind that when you're doing this, this phrasing here is not the greatest.
I understand that.
But just understand that when they're jogging back there, jogging back 40 miles past home, if homes
located at zero meters where 40 meters past I'm going to be and what we're referring to this over here.
So just keep that in mind when you're going past home, try this out.
I'm not going to give an explanation on how to do this in the video, but I will include the answer
key along with the resources.
So check that out.
Compare your answers and good luck to you.