So the instruction tell us to create the plot on the position versus time graph, then calculate the
velocities and plot them on the velocities first time graph.
So the given information is we are at home right now and it says location on the right hand side.
That home is located at position of zero meters.
We're in a rush to get to the grocery store in 15 minutes.
OK, so it's going to take us 15 minutes to get to the grocery store, which is located at the position
of 60.
We're going to shop for food for ten minutes at the grocery store, which is that position 60.
And we're no longer in a rush to get to our friend's house, which is a 10 minute drive.
The friend's house is at the position 40.
So I'm just going to take these and just plot them notes that we have position in the Y axis and time
in minutes on the X axis.
So we're at home right now, which is position zero.
That's the reason why we're starting over here, is because we're at position zero at zero minutes.
So if you're looking at the X axis, you have five right here, 10, 15.
OK, so in 15 minutes, we're going to be going to the grocery store.
So we're in a rush to get to the grocery store, which is a position of 60 meters.
OK, so we have our 60 meters over here.
We have a 15 minutes over here.
Let's just drive dot right there.
All right, so this is looking good right now, we're in the creation process of our motion diagram
and we're going to be spending 10 minutes shopping for food at the grocery store.
So keep in mind that each one of these tick marks, it represents five minutes.
So we're going to be spending 10 minutes here at the grocery store.
Apposition, 60, so we're now leaving the grocery store and we're going to our friend's house, which
is located at position 40, and it's going to take us 10 minutes to get there.
OK, so we're over here right now and it's going to take us 10 minutes to get there over at position
40.
So we're just to draw another dot right here.
Don't look at this 40 and say, hey, you know what?
Oh, that's 40.
So therefore, we're going to go there because keeping in mind that this is time and this is our position.
So we want to go to the position of 40 and we're just going to draw our line over here and now I know
that does say this in the instructions, but we're just coming hang out our friends house, watching
the football game, doing whatever.
So this is our position versus time graph for our motion diagram.