Now, let's think of different examples of velocity.
Well, think about the traffic signs that you saw on your drive to school today.
So maybe you actually saw a sign here in the United States.
You might see a sign that says, hey and what the speed limit is 25 miles per hour.
Maybe it was actually written like this 25 mph, but that's the same thing, say 25 miles an hour,
written like this.
And what does that mean?
Hey, no, once again, I think I actually mentioned this in the previous lectures, but it's.
Going at this velocity, you'll be moving 25 miles in one hour.
That's what this means.
So you're changing your position of 25 miles over the certain amount of time, which is one hour, for
our example, over here, we're changing our position four meters in one minute.
And that's what its velocity is.
The velocity is a change in position over a certain amount of time.