Hello, everyone.
Welcome back to Exploring Quantum Physics.
I'm Charles Clark, and
we'll now start using some of the tools
that we developed in the previous session
to get the basic commutation relations for
the angular momentum operators.
Now once again I have to emphasize, and
I've been there myself, the only way
to develop facility with these
techniques is to actually practice them.
So, in the interest of time,
I'm going to outline a number of the key
things that have to be done to develop
a working set of angular momentum tools.
But really,
if you want to understand it it's not
going to do you good just to look at that.
You will have to do some
of the computations.
And, for some people, those sorts of
calculations turn out to be enjoyable.
Others can't stand them, so
you'll get a sense of what it's like and
some of you, I think, will not only
benefit from this but come to enjoy it and
value it, at least hope so.
Okay so, once again, here's the definition
of the angular momentum operator.
Now I break it down, and
so here's what we started with at
the beginning of the first part.
Here's the Einstein summation condition.
Here's the Einstein summation
condition with the levi-cicita symbol.
By the way, I, here,
is the square root of minus one, and
I try to avoid using
I as a running index when we have
a square root of minus one present.
So just keep your eyes out for that.
But there's no significance as
to whether the symbol's u, v,
w, a, b, c, d, e, f,
anything that appears here as
a running index, and the particular
choice of symbol that's used to represent
it is just something arbitrary.
Now, in fact, everything that's going
to be done in this part is based on
the commutation relationship
between position momentum.
But, as you can see,
when you have products, then there's a bit
of bookkeeping that's required to make
sure that everything turns out right.
So, just to start with
something very basic,
let's try a simple application of this
commutation relationship in Video Quiz.
Okay, so I hope you're able
to derive this expression
from the uncertainty principle.
We'll see many examples
like this later on.
Here's our basic definition again,
just to keep everything clear
before you on the screen.
Here is the fundamental
commutation relation,
that which everything else is based.
Yes, now here is this identity
that you just derived.
So now, here's a very important
expression, what's the commutation
relation of the angular momentum with,
let's say, the position operator?
Well all right, here's computated LaXb,
that's just very simple
expressing what that means.
We now decompose the angular
momentum operator into its
basic parts, its r cross p.
Then we apply this,
from this expression up here,
we applied contraction and we get this,
this is a very significant identity,
which you will see is generic.
In other words, if we have any
vector valued operator in here,
we have the same identity for
the momentum,
we get this congregate LaXb
is h bar epsilon a b cXc.
I rather like expressing
that in this way because
it emphasizes the difference between
classical mechanics and quantum mechanics.
Do you see that, in classical mechanics,
this expression would vanish
identically because A cross B,
is equal to minus B cross A,
for classical operators.
So, here we have these two,
real observable operators,
the sum of these two cross products,
is an imaginary number times the vector.
So, this really is about
as quantum as it gets.
And indeed, note that the limit,
H bar goes to zero,
this produces the right answer,
in that you get back the same
classical cross product.
So, there are a number of identities
that you'll see that look like this,
in quantum mechanics.
So once again, where are we?
Okay, we have the basic relations,
the one that you derived.
So, we're about to conclude here.
Strongly recommend that you
verify the following things.
So, for example, here's the analog, the
identity we proved on the previous slide,
with X we get the same type of thing for
P.
Now here's, sort of,
the most important one, the commutator of
the different components of
angular momentum with themselves,
again, is really of the same form,
because L is a vector.
So this allows us to write another,
amusingly, quantum expression.
The cross product of something with itself
is an imaginary number, times that thing.
So this is truly a quantum identity.
And then finally,
so I'd say these two are more or
less the same thing.
But this is of central importance.
So any two components of
the angular momentum operator,
in general, they don't commute, but,
any component of the square of the angular
momentum operator, so L squared.
I should have written this as LkLk just so
as not to confuse you, or LaLa.
So let me just write this,
La LbLb equals 0,
is the identity that you're
being asked to verify.
In other words, that any component
of the angular momentum operator
commutes with the square magnitude
of the angular momentum operator.
Okay do take some time to work on those,
I think you'll find it rewarding.