As you will notice here, we do have our motion diagrams and there's something a little bit different
about this.
Nothing really too much.
But you do actually see that I do have the letter X here for these problems.
Initially, what we're going to be doing for these kinematic can McFoy problems, what we're going to
deal with is actually having a car on the road and it's going to go in a certain direction and notice
that this is along the X axis as opposed to being on the Y axis.
That's the reason why we're using an X here, is because it's just describing the access that we're
working on and that's the change in position.
What I want to do here is you should actually just be reviewing this and make sure that this makes sense
to you.
I know that there's a horrible squiggle.
I meant to do something like this, bam, right there.
All right.
So this should actually make sense to you, considering that we went over motion diagrams in the previous
lectures.
Now, what I want to do right here is I know that we're using Wyeth Mazwai over EXI.
Let's just do a little substitution.
So this A-T, what does this represent.
Well that's the final position, right.
And the final position.
We're going to be declaring that the letter X. So instead of using Wyeth, I'm going to use F because
once again we're using this X here and that's the final position of this object minus.
And the T represents the initial position, which is once again denoted to this X.
So this is the initial exposition divide that by and the denominator we have the three minus one.
What is the three represent?
Well, that's the time.
That is the time in the final possession or the final time, I should actually say minus the initial
time.
And once again, this represents our velocity.
This is our average velocity.
Another way to go about writing are T minus T.
We're just going to write it like this, this is a triangle.
This is called Delta.
This is a Greek symbol, the Greek symbol, Delta.
It just represents the change in.
So it's the change in the amount of time.
This is one of our kinematic formulas that we will be using.
Now, what's going to velocity?
What is that?
It's the change in position
over a certain amount of.
Time, which is exactly what we have represented here, this is our average velocity.
OK.
Well, how else do you actually get an average thing about this, say, if I have the numbers three
and five, how do I get the average of these two numbers?
Oh, wait a minute.
I could just add them and divide by two.
So we have eight over two, which is equal to four.
And that's the average four is the average of three and five.
So keeping this concept in mind, if I'm given an initial velocity and a final velocity, can't I just
add this up, divide them by two and also get our average velocity?
Well, yeah, and that's a nother kinematic formula right there.
So these two formulas both describe how to calculate the average velocity.