We have Formula One, which represents our average philosophy and formulative, which represents our
average velocity, when I'm going to do right now is this I'm just going to rewrite the both of them.
And set them equal to each other.
Now, what I'm do is I'm going to solve this out for Veth I'm sorry EXIF and we'll get ourselves a third
kinematic formula.
So how do I go about doing this.
OK, well if I want to isolate the access, I have a division of Delta T over here.
So what do I have to do.
I have to multiply Delta T on both sides of the equation.
OK, so now that we have that let's add exi to both sides of the equation.
All right.
And we're just going to do one last thing here.
Looking at this, the eye plus de'ath divided by two isn't that's taking one half of the eye plus the
math.
Isn't that just taking a half of it.
I could rewrite this and the very last thing is I'm just going to rearrange this.
I'm just going to put our exile in the front.
And this is our third kinematic equation.