OK, so now we're back over here.
Notice that we do have our can magic formula that we just saw for them and there's a reason why I actually
brought back over here.
And that's because what we're going to do right now is this.
We have our final velocity right here and we know that final velocity is equal to V.I. plus a times
Delta T.
So I'm going to do is I'm just going to do a little substitution and then we're just going to simplify
this.
So here we go, we have x, f.
Is equal to V.I. Plus, instead of writing are the F, I'm just going to write in the eye plus our acceleration
times Delta T.
And that's going to get multiplied by our Delta t notice once again.
That this got substituted in right in here.
OK, so I'm just going to do a little simplification over here, what we do is first we have like terms,
so let's combine these like terms.
So we have XPath is equal two times to the I.
Plus, our acceleration times Delta T.
Times, Delta tape, and now what we're going to do is this we're going to do two different distributions,
Ron distribute.
The one 1/2 to both of the terms and then we're going to distribute our Delta T.
To both of the terms as well.
We're just to do this all in one step, so we have X, F is he go to X I.
Plus.
So one half of two is just one.
So we have V.I. over here and we're going to multiply that by R Delta T so we have the I times Delta
T.
And then we have our one 1/2 times a times delta, so that's one half a Delta two, and then we have
Delta t.P multiply by that source, Delta T squared.
And this is another one of our kinematic formulas.