Bear with me here, this is going to be the very last formula.
There's a lot that goes into this one.
So we do have our average philosophy here, and that's equal to X Mass, X I divide by Delta T. Let's
take this and solve it up for X F.
So how do we do this?
Let's multiply both sides by Delta T. and then add xxxi onto both sides of the equation minus X by adding
to both sides equation.
We have the times, Delta T plus X I and that's equal to X f..
Now this is once again our average velocity and we know that average velocity is equal to this over
here.
So let's do a substitution.
So we have the I.
Plus, VLF.
Divide by two.
And our Delta t hey now, what do you remember this formula from before?
I know that we actually solved this out to say that the physical TVI plus acceleration times Delta T,
but in this form, what we can actually do is solve this out for Delta T and the easiest way to actually
go about doing this once again, I explain this to you before, is we could do a simple switch out.
So we have Delta T is equal to the F minus V I divided by acceleration.
So Binet, this is what Delta is equal to.
Let's do a substitution so we have average velocity.
Times are Delta T.
And we're just going to do that substitution, so this is going to be multiplication because we're just
going to be dropping down our multiplication sign, right?
And this is going to be plus X, Y, and that's going to be equal to X F multiplying the denominators,
that's going to be fairly simple, right, because it's just to a multiply the numerators.
We're going to have to do a foil first outer inner west.
I'll tell you what, all math teachers, I hate the idea that everyone teachers foil.
All I actually think about this is it's a double distribution.
This is where I think about foil first.
Outr, isn't that just a distribution followed by another distribution, her?
Last, I think about this as it's a double distribution foil.
OK, that's just another thing to memorize.
I like to conceptually think about it like this.
OK, so let's do the multiplication on this, let's just multiply this out.
All right, so the Times Veth.
OK, so that's the first one, and then we have a positive V.I. times, a negative V.I. So this is going
to give us a negative V.I. squared.
A positive becomes a positive.
Well, they'll give us a positive, the F squared I know, I just said V.I. there.
I'm sorry.
I apologize for that.
And then we have a positive V.I. times.
I'm sorry, a positive VEF times, a negative V.I. and that gives us a negative the I, the F and this
is all over to a I'm sorry, I apologize for mixing up the vehicles and Viarsa in my audio explanation
there and this is plus X Y and that's equal to X F.
OK, we have a little cancellation here.
We have a positive the times the F minus the items to be F, so these two will cancel out with each
other.
You see that?
So this is a positive.
This is a negative these to cancel out.
And all that we're left with is I'm just going to do a little reordering here, we have the F squared
minus V I squared.
Divided by two a.
Plus X, Y, and that's equal to F.
Now I'm gonna do is solve this out for the F squared.
So here we go.
Let's subtract X on both sides of the equation.
OK, now, once again, we're solving for the F squared, so let's get rid of this division of Twohey
by multiplying both sides of the equation by two.
I'm just gonna come over here to do that.
And now continuing to sell out for the squared, let's add the square to both sides of the equation.
And keep in mind, this is a positive to a times, this quantity over here, so.
And that is our final kinematic equation.