In this lecture we're going to discuss
a very interesting quantum effect,
namely, the phenomenon
of superconductivity.
Which is rather amazing field because
superconductors have a number of
remarkable properties such as,
for instance, so shown here,
the phenomenon of levitation.
So here I'm showing a high
temperature superconductor,
wrapped up in a tissue to avoid heating,
levitating on top of a magnet.
And this phenomenon is actually unique
in this form to superconductor, and
is based on expulsion of magnetic
flux with Meissner effect.
So here I'm actually showing you
a movie of this same effect,
which was recorded by my
experiental colleague,
Johnpierre Paglione in
the Joint Quantum Institute,
here a superconductor moving
around on top of magnet.
So this phenomenon of levitation is
indeed, well, quite remarkable and
it's oftentimes used to impress
visitors at various science shows.
But it's just one of many exciting
phenomena that appear in relation to
superconductivity, and some of them
we're going to discuss later today.
But let me just mention
that superconductivity
is an extremely rich field.
So suffice it to say that it has so
far resulted in about ten Nobel Prizes
that have been awarded for
various discoveries in superconductivity.
And furthermore,
there are definitely a lot of major
mysteries that still remain in the field.
And obviously we cannot discuss everything
in one lecture, so I'm going to focus
towards the end of the lecture on a key
theoretical concept that sort of underlies
the theory, so-called Bardeen Cooper
Schrieffer theory of superconductivity.
And this is the phenomenon of Cooper
pairing, which is responsible,
to a large degree, for
the appearance of the.
But let me start with discussing
the main property of a superconductor,
namely, the state of zero resistance,
which is also
the reason why superconductors
are actually called superconductors.
And to do so, let me go back in time
a little more than 100 years ago,
to 1911, when this happy-looking guy,
Heike Kamerlingh Onnes,
was performing various low-temperature
experiments to liquefy helium.
And during these experiments he noticed
that the resistivity of mercury dropped
exactly to zero below a certain
critical temperature of 4.2 K.
So this was very surprising, and
actually it is very surprising.
It also should surprise you,
in particular,
if you recall what we discussed
in the fourth lecture,
in the last lecture last week, where we
talked about the resistivity of metals.
And so
I mentioned that in all real materials,
there always are imperfections that
give rise to disorder that in turn
give rise to scattering and
finite resistance.
So what you would expect in a normal
metal would be that the resistance, well,
it can go down, but you would want it to
saturate to a certain finite value because
there is no localization.
If there is localization it
will actually shoot up and
go to infinity while there is
no sort of a reasonable sort of
a priori reason why it would
drop down to exactly zero.
Not to a small value,
not to tiny value, to exactly zero.
And this is what
Kamerlingh Onnes observed, and
this was the birth of superconductivity.
It was the first time people
saw superconductivity, and
it was truly amazing.
In fact, and
in particular because of that,
he was awarded the 1913
Nobel Prize in physics.
Now another effect which we already
discussed in relation to this levitation
was magnetic flux expulsion.
This is probably a second
very interesting phenomenon.
And well, if you have a metal,
let's say if you heat up this
material up to room temperature, let's
say, and penetrate it with magnetic flux,
the flux will more or less just go
through the material above the critical
temperature and there will be no
significant distortion of the flux.
So it's sort of amazing phenomenon
that happens once you go
into the superconducting phase,
is that the magnetic field now
tries to avoid the superconductor.
So instead of going through it,
it goes around it.
And so you may say that it's
expelled from the superconductor and
this effect is called the Meissner effect.
So returning to this picture of a high
temperature superconductor levitating
on top of a magnet, what's actually going
on here is that the magnetic field lines
primarily go around this superconductor.
And you may see that this superconductor
is sort of sitting on this on this flux,
because it's energetically not
favorable for it to go down.
It would increase the energy
of the system, and
therefore it's supported by this flux.
Well, just a short comment here, though,
is that I'm a bit
oversimplifying this picture.
So as a matter of fact,
there is indeed the Meissner effect.
But apart from the Meissner effect,
there is also a little bit
of penetration of the superconductor
by a magnetic field.
But this penetration happens in
the form of so-called vortices
which are if you look at
the cross-section of the superconductor,
two dimensional cross-section.
Sorry, let me just plot it here, so
there will be this superconductor.
And most of this cross-section
is magnetic field free, but
there are certain regions which are very
narrow regions, very small regions,
where you do have a magnetic field sort
of penetrating through very thin lines.
And these lines are called vortices.
So in superconductors, these magnetic
field lines are called vortices.
And these vortices tend to appear in
the regions where superconductivity is
suppressed due to various
kinds of imperfections and
disorders we already discussed.
And this in turn leads to the pinning
of this magnetic field line.
So as a matter of fact,
if you perform this experiment with a true
simple type 2 superconductor
which allows these flux lines,
you not only will be able to see that it
can be levitating on top of a magnet.
You can actually turn
it any way you see fit.
You can turn it at any angle and
it's still going to retain its position.
And this actually even more impressive
phenomenon is due to these flux lines and
this pinning.
But to discuss it further would
be a bit going too far, so
let me just stop here and
say that all in all so this magnetic field
expulsion is responsible for
this phenomenon of levitation.
On a different note,
interestingly the Meissner effect,
this expulsion of the magnetic flux, on
the theoretical side is, to some degree,
equivalent to the Higgs mechanism that
occurs in elementary particle physics.
I'm sure many of you have heard about the
discovery of so-called the God particle or
Higgs particle last year, but
actually the mathematical theory of
this Higgs mechanism in a different
context of [INAUDIBLE] physics was put
together before Higgs by Phil Anderson.
And speaking, I would actually
call it Anderson-Higgs mechanism.
I'm not going to go into details of
why this expulsion of magnetic flux is
equivalent to Higgs, but
you may have heard that Higgs really is
important elementary particle physics,
because it gives rise to masses for
some elementary particles.
Here you may see that the Higgs
mechanism in this form gives rise to
mass of the magnetic field.
So it becomes energetically
unfavorable for
the magnetic field to be
inside the superconductor.
And well, this energy to be there is
sort of proportional to the so-called
superconducting water parameter that
appears below the critical temperature.
So I already advertised the fact
that superconductors caused
an amazing variety of
various new phenomena, and
the discoveries of these phenomena have
in turn led to at least ten Nobel Prizes.
And I list here these major discoveries,
sort of these hallmark
discoveries in the field.
And the first one we talked about,
this is Kamerlingh Onnes discovery
of the effect itself back in 1911.
Then John Bardeen, Leon Cooper, and
Bob Schrieffer got a 1972 Nobel Prize for
developing microscopic
theory of superconductivity.
In the 50s, Brian Josephson and
Ivar Giaever got the 1973 Nobel Prize for
discovering very interesting
tunneling effects in superconductors,
in particular quantum Josephson effect,
the Josephson effect.
We're not going to be talking about it,
but it's very interesting.
So these guys made a major
breakthrough in the field,
I'm going to mention it in the next slide,
by discovering a so-called
family of high temperature
superconductors.
And finally, just ten years ago,
Alexei Abrikosov and
Vitaly Ginzburg, along with Tony Leggett,
got a Nobel Prize.
And in particular, these two gentlemen
have put together a theory of vortices,
topological excitations that
appear in these quantum fluids.
And I'm also including
here a future Nobel Prize,
which I almost guarantee it to be
awarded sometime in the future, for
a theory of these high temperature
superconductors that I just mentioned.
We don't really know yet
the nature of this.
We know they exist, we know a lot of their
properties, very unusual properties,
but what's really going
on there we don't know.
So maybe it's going to be you.
Who knows?
But you should hurry because I think the
new experiments are getting us closer and
closer to understanding the uncovering
the mystery of these high temperature.
In any case, what I want to emphasize
here on this slide is a very
large time gap between the discovery and
the corresponding prize for
the first superconductor and the
microscopic theory of superconductivity,
which was put together about 40,
50 years later.
And it's not for a lack of trying.
People had tried very hard and
couldn't succeed.
So it turned out to be very difficult
to explain the basic nature
of superconductors.
Even though it took a while for
the theorists to provide an explanation of
superconductivity, the experimental
work on this, in fact,
has never really stopped since 1911,
since the discovery by Kamerlingh Onnes.
And the motivation for these experiments
is really easy to understand.
So as I mentioned,
of course, superconductors are special in
that they have exactly zero resistance.
So they have no losses whatsoever, and
they are able to conduct
electricity with no heating.
So if we were able to have
a superconductor at room temperature,
such room temperature superconducting
wires would have been able to
transport electricity over
large distances with no losses.
This, of course, would have been great,
especially now in the view of
this looming energy crisis.
Of course, now we transport electricity
from where we produce it to where we use
it using, well, normal wires,
metallic wires.
And those involved resistance and heating.
And so this heat we just lose,
so this goes nowhere.
So to have a room temperature
superconductor would be really great.
But unfortunately at this stage,
we don't really know
whether such a material may exist,
whether it's possible at all.
But there has been lot of progress growing
materials which have a much higher
transition temperatures than the first
4.2 Kelvin superconductor, back here.
So this is the discovery
of superconductors, and
this plot here is really a diagram.
So here is the year from the early
1900s up to almost now, and
the points here correspond to compounds
with various transition temperatures.
And so you see that for
the first 70 or so years,
the progress has been really slow.
But then in the 80s there is
a huge jump up to here and
this class of materials
are what I already mentioned,
the high temperature superconductors,
so-called Cooper superconductors,
which are getting somehow dangerously
close to room temperature.
But they are not there yet.
So they're close, but
we still have about 100 Kelvin to go.
Now and also, very recently, there was
a discovery of a new class of material,
a so-called iron-based superconductor
that also looked promising.
But so far, although this raised,
increased the transition temperatures in
superconductors, hasn't
really involved much theory.
It's mostly about experimental
magic of growing materials and
trying out different compounds.
To emphasize this fact,
in the last slide in this segment,
let me actually mention
a guy who was really,
really good at finding
new superconductors.
He was an experimentalist
working at Bell Labs.
His name was Bernd Matthias.
And he was a legend in this business.
And he, back in the 50s and 60s,
he came up with a set of rules to
help others discover new superconductors,
and here is his list of those rules.
I don't expect you to understand their
significance, actually they're not to
be taken too seriously because in these
high temperature superconductors,
most of those rules actually violate it.
But let me go over them.
So he said that high symmetry is good,
cubic symmetry is best.
You want to stay away from oxygen,
stay away from magnetism,
stay away from insulators.
By the way,
this is all we find in superconductors.
And the most important rule due to
Matthias was to stay away from theorists.
And this was really bad, we know,
but it was deserved because,
again, for many years there was
no theory of superconductivity.
But fortunately,
the situation has changed in
the 1950s when Leon Cooper and
then John Bardeen and
Bob Schrieffer came up with the very
clear explanation of the effect.
And in the remaining three segments we
are going to go over this explanation,
but in the next video
I'm going to mostly talk
about the preliminary material
we need to know to get there.