In the end of the previous video,
I advertised to some degree,
the main result that we're going to
derive, namely that the electrons near
the firmer surface at low temperatures
are going to form this bounce states of
two electrons which are going to
condense and form this superconductor.
And now we're entering the technical
part of the lecture where we actually
would want to get this calculation done
and to see how it actually happens,
and it connects somewhat to the
calculations we were doing in the previous
lecture where we were studying
particles in various potential.
So there we were dealing with a single
particle quantum mechanics so
it was an externally imposed potential
in which a single particle was moving
which was localize there.
Now, what we want to do, we want to
start actually two particle problem.
With two particles here
describing effectively
the two electrons near the Fermi surface
in the context of superconductivity.
And it turns out that actually
two particle problems often times
in quantum mechanics reduce
to single particle problems.
And in this segment, I'm going to
illustrate how exactly it happens.
So here we're interested in analyzing
this two-particle Schrodinger equation.
And to make things general, for
the sake of lectures later in the course,
I'm coursering here actually two
different particles with masses m1 and
m2, but in the next segment we'll
work with the two electron problem,
where m1 is actually equal to.
So, what we have here, is essentially
kinetic energy of two particles, so
this response to the P1 squared over
2 m1 kinetic energy the first particle,
plus P2 squared over 2m2,
kinetic energy of the second particle and
the interaction between them
which we expect to depend only on
the distance between the particles.
And now we have weight function and
that depends on both coordinates
of the particle r1 and r2 and
well the right hand side is
the usual energy times psi.
So we're going to solve this equation.
Now, the goal of this video is to show
that actually instead of solving this
complicated looking differential equation,
it would depend on two vectors r1 and
r2, we can reduce it to the good old
single particle Schrodinger equations
you already know how to solve.
And to see how it happens, let's do
the following change of variables so
we will go from the coordinates r1 and
r2 to the actual coordinates of
each individual particles to
this capital R and lowercase r,
so the formula represents the center
of mass of our particles.
So it's defined as so, and the second one
is the distance between the particles.
So the relative distance
between particles r1 and r2.
Now what we're going to do,
we're going to rewrite this equation in
terms of this capital R and lettercase r.
So in order to do this, we,
well first we notice that of course
the potential energy depends
only on the distance.
Basically by construction,
we chosen this way.
And the only non-trivial part which we
have to analyze is this kinetic energy.
Degree which this applies which
in here in this brackets.
So we're going to work
with these guys now.
So to calculate this part
of the kinetic energy,
we can focus for the sake of simplicity
on just one component of this Laplacian.
Laplacian is a sum of second
derivative with the respect
to each of the directions in our
problem x- z, so let's just focus on x,
and in this case, the capital case
X is going to be the center of mass
X component and this is going to be
a relative coordinate in the x direction.
Now in order to change
the variables in the Laplacian,
we can go from the derivative of
this delta x1 to derivative with
a respect to a capital X and
a lower case X.
And this transformation can be done by
rewriting it as so, so we basically
adding some sense in the derivative of
m in the numerator and the nominator.
And so this derivative of d capital
X over x1 is calculated from here.
And this derivative of d lower case
x over x1 is calculated from here.
And the first one is, as you can see,
gives us m1 over the total mass,
and the second one is given us basically
minus sign, so this is resolve,
this when express, capital axis, small x.
We can do the same thing of course for
X2, and this is the result,
with the only difference here being m2 and
hre being plus sign.
And that's pretty much it.
So we can actually calculate
the quantity that we're after,
written here,
by essentially squaring this result.
So this would give us the x part of
the Laplacian for the first particle, and
this guy squared will give us the x
component applies to the second particle.
So therefore this guy goes here and
this result goes here.
And so you can see if we square root
this operation, these derivatives,
we're going to get the second derivative
with respect to the center of mass,
the second derivative with respect
to the relative coordinate but
also we're going to get the cross terms.
And actually the coordinates were chosen
in such a way that the cross terms
in these two brackets cancel each other
out because of the minus sign here and
plus sign here.
So, well, you can verify this of
course just by breaking it down or
just by staring at it for a minute or
so but it's going to be pretty clear.
So if you put everything
together from these two brackets,
a very straightforward calculation,
this is what we're going to get.
So this is essentially result for
the x component of this quantity we're
calculating and so Laplacian for x1 and
x2 can now be written essentially as
a combination of two Laplacians with the,
yeah, there should be,
of course, a plus sign.
Here there are no minus signs so
it was a typo.
And so the first Laplacian with respect
to this center of mass involves the total
mass in the denominator.
And the second Laplacian with respect
to the relative coordinate will
this guy which actually is
called the reduced mass.
So now that we've tried it is s o m 1,
m 2 divided by m 1 + m 2, and
this is called reduced mass.
So now we're in the position to
actually put everything together,
so what we have proven as
a mater of fact is that,
minus h squared over 2m, 1,
Laplacian with respect to 1,
the kinetic energy, the first
particle minus a squared over 2m, 2.
Laplacian of two,
the kinetic energy of the second
particle can be written as
minus h squared over 2 m 1
plus m 2 Laplacian with respect to the
center of mass minus h squared over 2 mew,
the reduced mass that I
introduced in the previous
slide Laplacian with respect
to the relative coordinate.
So if I stick it into
the Schrodinger equation,
I will get, therefore, the full length,
I will get minus h squared over 2,
this Laplacian of R m1 plus + m2,
plus Laplacian lower case r over
mew plus the potential energy,
the interaction energy between
the two particles which
depends only on this relative coordinate
acting on my wave function and
the right hand side is
just the energy as usual.
So what I see from this equation is
that there is just one part which
depends on the relative coordinate and
which involves interaction and
this part represents essentially
a free Schrodinger equation for
a combined particle with a mass, m1 + m2.
Essentially describes a free motion
of two particles, as a whole.
So for instance, if they were to form
a bond state this is exactly what we're
going to be discussing in
the last video in this lecture.
So, this term essentially describes
the motion of this bond state,
this sort of molecule like state,
as a whole.
And so to sort of extract this overall
motion, we can just look for a solution.
This side thilde of capital R and lower
case r can be written as a solution to
this sort of free Schroedinger equation,
simply a plain wave as we know,
it's E to the I, some momentum of
this bond state, or whatever it is,
times capital R, divided by H bar
times the wave function which
depends on the relative coordinate
that we actually want to find.
And the energy of this motion from here
is going to be just this capital P,
squared divided by m1,
plus m2, twice m1 plus m2.
So, which is just the a parameter,
it doesn't appear anywhere
else in the problem and
we can just move it to the right hand side
subtract the total energy from
of this energy, and that's it.
The final result that we're going to get,
which doesn't want to include
this term is going to look,
let me just write it here,
is going to look as so.
So, it's going to be minus h squared
over 2 mew, so this reduced mass.
So these Laplacian in which I can write
as d2 over dr squared plus v of r.
Side of r, and
the reckon side is going to be this
e minus p squared over 2 m1 plus m2,
so let me just write it
as e prime psi of r.
And this, as you can see, looks like
single-particle Schroedinger equation.
So, the wave function
depends only one coordinate.
Everything else is exactly the same,
the only difference is that here
I'm dealing with some reduced mass.
So, let's see in the context of
the problem of two electrons
that we're actually going to study,
so E of m1 is equal to m2.
So E of m1 is equal to m2.
So then, of course,
the total mass is equal to 2m.
And the reduced mass, this mew is equal
to m squared over 2m or just m over 2.
So therefore, in our electron problem,
this guy is going to be
just the electron mass.
And, just to summarize
what we have proven,
why the brute force straight
forward calculation is that
in the simple two particle problem,
in two particle quantum mechanics,
we can always get rid of one
unnecessary coordinate that
describes a motion of our
two particles as a whole.
And we can reduce our problem to the
standard single-particle quantum mechanics
which makes things much easier
because we can now use the results and
some of the conclusions of
single-particle quantum mechanics that we
discussed in the previous lecture.