So this final part of the lecture
we'll solve the Cooper problem
which is a problem of weakly
attractive electrons near the Fermi
surface that form pairs, so called Cooper
pairs, balance states of two electrons.
And as we discussed, these Cooper pairs,
at low temperatures,
they Bose condense into Bose-Einstein
condensate, which becomes superfluid.
And this is this amazing state
that we know as a superconductor.
I should mention that this, we'll see
actually the solution to the Cooper
problem will involve essentially
the same method we used in
the first lecture this week in the context
of single particle quantum mechanics.
It's going to be actually very simple,
technically very simple solution for
a Nobel Prize winning work, anyway.
So it's not trivial, but
this is a very important work.
So here I'm actually showing you the title
of the original paper by Leon Cooper.
And this work of Cooper eventually has
progressed, has developed into a much
more sophisticated theory, which is
the Bardeen-Cooper-Schrieffer theory
of super conductivity, so, BCS-theory.
So and
this theory has been the cornerstone of
the theory of superconductivity for
many, many years.
And frankly there is nothing better
on the market, in some sense.
So this BCS-theory describes very well
most conventional superconductors.
And it provides some of the setting
also in the physics of unconventional
superconductors, although they are such as
the high-temperature superconductors, for
example, though there
the understanding is not complete.
Now let's say.
Well, I showed many times already
the citations for various Nobel Prizes and
I discussed briefly a number of Nobel
Prize winning works and I should mention.
I should admit that in
most of these cases,
I had to sort of simplify
things enormously
when I was providing explanations,
sort of dumb it down to some degree.
So here, well,
I'm not going to discuss BCS-theory.
This is a very complicated theory, but
the paper of Cooper is actually very,
very simple.
So the original paper, we started though
is very simple and we will be able
to understand, essentially,
its main message and the delegation.
Now but before I go into this delegation,
let me discuss the origin of
this attractive interaction.
So I basically, what I want to solve
again is a problem of electrons
Interacting by an attractive potential.
But where exactly it's coming from?
So this is actually very complicated and
tricky question, and well, in some sense,
the mystery of, let's say, high
temperature and superconductivities and
that we don't really know
where this sort of glue,
this attractive interaction
might be coming from.
So the origin of electron attraction
in conventional superconductors
is also far from obvious actually.
So but there was a breakthrough paper
back in the beginning of the 50's so
I'm showing here the title of this paper.
Superconductivity of Isotopes of Mercury
and to appreciate the importance of
this paper, let me just remind you,
the basic picture of what a metal is.
So well, if you have a metallic system,
well, a solid system,
the reason it's a solid is because
the ions form a crystal lattice.
So they're positioned in space
in a regular fashion, so
I'm just drawing here for the sake of
simplicity a square lattice in 2-g,
but in reality would
be a more complicated.
Three dimensional lattice and you should
think about having a positive ions sitting
here in this sites,
on these lattice sites.
This lattice is a sort of elastic,
well it's a regent object,
but it can have oscillation.
Waves running through it.
And we're going to discuss it
a little bit in a few weeks.
And so this oscillations of
the lattice are called phonons.
Now electrons in the metal
are moving around,
they're free to move around, but they move
around on the background of this lattice.
So these red guys here are electrons,
okay?
And so this is pretty much what, well,
it's very cold model a simplified,
over simplified model
of a metallic source.
Now so this paper, what this paper has
achieved is that it looked at different
isotopes of mercury, which is a super
conductor and let me remind you
that isotopes are essentially different
versions of the same chemical elements.
And the basically everything is the same
for different isotopes apart from
the number of neutrons in each
ion sitting on the lattice side.
So basically with different isotopes
means that everything is the same but
the only difference is the mass of
this objects on the lattice sides,
Which maybe shouldn't affect
to much superconductivity,
because really superconductivity is
coming from whatever electrons are doing.
And it shouldn't have much to
do with the lattice, right?
So because these guys are actually, well,
they can oscillate a little bit near their
equilibrium positions, but
they cannot conduct electricity.
So what it turned out, and
this is really the main message of the
paper that the transition temperature into
a super conductor, the temperature at
which the resistivity drops exactly to 0,
depended very strongly on
the mass of these guys, okay?
So the ions,
the lower was the transition temperature.
See here, maybe it's hard to see so
there are a few points.
This says average mass number and
this says transition
temperature so
this is basically if you write a TC and
this is the mass of these
Ions on lattice side, okay?
So this was a very clear-cut trend and
it was a smoking gun of that
superconductivity has something
to do with interactions between
the electrons and the crystal lattice.
So a little later people realize
that what actually happens is that
these electrons moving around,
whenever the electron passes
through a region in a lattice, essentially
because electron's negatively charged, and
the ion's sitting on lattice
size are positively charged.
So this electron polarizes the lattice
locally, and it takes some time for
the lattice sort of to relax back and
then if a second electron comes in.
So let's say I have here
now this guy goes away and
there is a second electron which
comes into the same region.
So, this second electron is
attracted in some sense To
this region and
this results in an effective correlation.
Effective phonon negated
attraction between the electrons.
It's a very tricky business.
If you don't understand it
well don't be surprised.
I don't understand it either actually.
So but that's how it works.
So we'll have to just accept this fact.
So that what happens is that electrons
in some sense, they exchange waves.
Elastic waves which are called phonons and
this leads to effective attraction.
Well and by the way for the module,
for the actual solution,
when I present the origin of the
attraction, it doesn't matter that much.
It will be just some attractions
are constant minus or
not but it's good to know the physics.
For the actual calculation we'll need
specific mathematical model of
this electron electron attraction.
And the true interaction
is quite complicated.
So here we'll represent
what I call a Spherical-cow
model of the phonon-mediated
attraction between electrons
Which I should say actually is used
commonly even in research papers.
So it works perfectly well.
And even though we know how
to write the true model,
which would involve all
the complications of the theory,
so the results, the outcome, so
we simplify the model in the and
more complicated model
are pretty close to each other.
So there's really no reason for
us to complicate things.
So in any case, so
what we're talking about is that again,
electrons moving around in
the presence of a crystal lattice,
this changes wave strength through
this lattice, these phonons and
so this diagram is an example
of a phonon-like diagram,
which shows this kind of exchange.
And in any process like this,
we must satisfy basic conservation laws,
in particular we must
ensure that both energy.
And momentum are conserved.
So and therefore, what's important
here in understanding the structure
of this interaction is the typical
energies involved in such processes.
So what we know,
what we already discussed is the typical
energy of the electrons in the metal.
And this typical energy, I denote it as
E sub F, the Fermi energy, divided by
the Boltzmann constant, sort of to convert
it into a more familiar temperature units.
So the corresponding typical sort of
temperature of electrons is going to be
about 10,000 Kelvin.
So these guys which are actually
the main players of the theory have
the energy which is received
with this temperature scale.
Now it turns out that the phonons.
It's not obvious from the previous
discussion that Is not
something we can derive.
I'm just sort of giving
you an experimental fact,
is that if the typical energy of
the phonons which I will call as age
times omega divide called bio-frequency
divided by the Boscom constant,
so when I wrote it into
temperature it's about 400 kelvin.
A few hundred kelvin,
which is two orders of magnitude
smaller than the energy of the lattice.
So what we should think about is that
this phonon as actually being changed by
the electrons have energy which is much,
much more then the energy life,
the electron energy itself.
And this puts certain
constraints on the possible
momentum energies of the electrons that
may experience this sort of a process.
And the simplest sort of version of the
interaction which takes this into account
is presented here.
So this is an equation for an interaction,
momentum-dependent interaction
between the two electrons, V(p) And
what it tells us is that the two electrons
attract each other in this language
if they're located in the narrow
shell near the thermo-surface.
And the width of the shell is of
the order of this phonon energy.
So basically if two electrons can
exchange phonons they do so and
this results in the interaction
which is manifested here through
this negative coefficient
that we know as sum constant.
And if two electrons are located
well beyond this narrow region.
So then they don't have a mechanism
to attract each other and
their interaction therefore is zero.
So if we move just at the upper part,
so V of P is equal to minus V zero so
this would correspond to essentially
a local attraction real space, so this
is something we actually saw In lecture
number five with the Delta potential.
So this is the kind of
problem we discussed already.
But however then we were talking
about one particle in a quantum well.
So now we're talking about two particles,
two excitations interacting with
each other via this potential.
But per, well, per the results of
the previous segment in this lecture,
we know that the two particle problem in
quantum mechanics is to a large degree,
equivalent to a single particle
quantum mechanical problems.
And as we discussed in the previous video,
the only difference between the single
particle problem and a potential VFr and
two particle problem of
two particles interacting.
Why the same potential Is that
in the lecture, we will get
the reduced mass instead of the mass
of each individual particle.
And in the case of two
identical electrons,
the reduced mass is equal to m over two,
so we have simply this here equation.
And here I write it first in real speed,
sort of, while keeping in mind that there
are in fact additional
constraints on the interaction.
So if we follow the same
route as we did in lecture number five and
do free transform.
So we can write this
equation in this form, so
delta of r acting on psi
of r picks up psi of 0.
And so here I'm going to have this
integrate of over, of momentum but
basically we do introduce constraints on
the potential that we just discussed.
Would be to limit the integration or
momentum here by only
momenta that appear in the vicinity
of the Fermi surface so
that the possibility of
phonon exchange exists.
And so this equation, essentially,
these two equations with
the proper sort of caveats.
About where the interaction is possible,
is exactly the Cooper pairing problem.
And as you can see, it's essentially
identical mathematically to the Kaiser
problems we saw in lecture number five
in single particle quantum mechanics.
And so
well we can follow the same route, but
at this stage you may be a little bit
surprised at by this resemblance.
Because I mentioned that this eventually,
the result of this calculation,
is going to be the appearance of a bounce
state between the two electrons.
But as we discussed,
weak attraction in three dimensions,
and this is a three dimensional problem,
does not result in a bounce state.
So delta function, potentially 3D
does not have a bounce however,
an interesting thing that happens here
is that because electrons that really
play a role in this pairing,
in this interaction with phonons,
they exist in the vicinity
of this Fermi surface.
And this surface is two dimensional.
This gives rise, in a sense,
to a reduction of dimensionality,
even though in real space we started
with a three dimensional system.
So this effectively, what we're dealing
with here has a reduced dimension.
And this gives rise to the appearance of
a bond state in a very unexpected way.
So to see this, we essentially have
to repeat exactly the same steps as
we did in parts three and
four of lecture number five.
So, the only difference here is
due to the fact that this energy
on the right hand side that we want
to find really consists of two parts.
So, this is the n ratio of the electrons
that already have a finite energy at
the Fermi surface, so
remember is that we're
talking here about these excitations
that have the energy of two e-Fermi.
And then there is an energy due to the
interaction which we want to be negative.
So if this guy delta is negative, it
means that we can have former bond state.
And by doing so, lower the energy so and
well this fact actually makes
all the difference actually.
This is how mathematically the fact that
we are dealing with this 3 dimensional
Fermi surface when it fixes itself.
Since the remaining calculation follows
almost 1 to 1 back in lecture number 5.
And I also present this
particular calculation and
all the details in additional materials so
you can read through this.
So I'm not going to repeat this again
in this video, so what I'm going to do,
I'm going to just present the final
result for this key parameter delta.
Which again is the energy of
the bound state of two electrons
that forms sort of a large morticle if you
want, which is called Cooper pair here.
So, and this delta is going to
be of of the order of minus
so this is a phonon energy,
typical phonon energy that we
discussed in the previous slide.
But the key thing here is that there are
multiplied by a exponential of minus 1,
some constant, I'll call it N not and
define it in a second, times V not.
So where N not is equal to m P Fermi, so
this is threshold momentum
divided by 4 Pi squared h cubed.
So this is just a constant but
what I want to emphasize,
well first of all there is a solution.
Which is great.
So the electrons indeed can find a way
to lower their energy by forming these
bizarre new Cooper pairs that
eventually form the superconductor.
But what is not so great is that
these small interaction energy
appears in the exponential minus 1 or
V not.
So if V0 is small, then, well,
the energy of the bounce state,
the so-called superconducting gap,
is exponentially small.
And this is exactly what happens.
And those of you who followed
all of segments in lecture
number five can recognize this
result is a result that we
have seen actually in the context of two
dimensional single particle problem.
And this reflects this reduction in
dimensionality that I mentioned before.
So, the last two things I'm going to
mention in the end is first of all this
result for delta is a function of
V not is very unusual function,
which we have already seen.
But this function is,
again, is special because it
doesn't have a Taylor expansion.
So there is no way one
can approach this result
by doing so-called perturbation theory.
And this may be one of
the reasons why It took so
long for people to figure out
the key to superconductivity
because there was no way to approach
it sort of in a pejorative way.
And the last thing I'm
going to mention is that well,
if we did not have this exponential,
if we were to imagine that this Delta or
the water of this funnel energy.
This would have actually implied
that we can get superconductivity
at very high temperatures,
up to room temperature.
So this would have been great.
We would have the ability to
transport electricity with no losses.
So this is really the grand
challenge in the field,
so how to you go beyond
this weak coupling.
So weak coupling, here in model so how to
first of all to describe the situation
where the interactions are strong and
how to enhance, how to get rid
of this exponential essentially.
This is a sort of practical problem
that has no solution at the moment.