Hello, everyone.
Welcome back to Exploring Quantum Physics.
We're now going to proceed on the work
done in the previous lecture and
start applying it to
problems of atomic structure
using the old quantum theory and
then work on towards new.
Once again, let me remind you
of the relevance of Bohr's
original paper to the discussion
that we're having today.
So to remind you where we left off
at the end of the last lecture.
We solved the problem for
the motion of the hydrogen-like systems,
one electron,
one nucleus in classical mechanics.
We found a sort of generic,
fairly simple solution.
It allows for
any real value of the total energy.
When that energy is negative,
the orbits, they're not only bounded,
but they close on themselves,
a very non-generic fact in dynamics.
And when the energy is positive,
then they travel off to infinity.
Now I strongly encourage
reading this paper,
which is contained in
the additional materials.
I mean, not from start to end, but
just to get a sense of the great
thing that it accomplished.
And you have to go rather
far down into the paper, and
this is one of the homework problems,
is to go find and analyze the language
that is used in this section.
And we give some hints as to what page to
look at in the guidance to the homework.
And the really fantastic thing that
Bohr did that still survives.
His foundational idea is that it's
the quantization of angular momentum.
So he found the series of
circular orbits that he
thought should be stationary states.
And he actually sort of mentions
this almost as an after thought,
that the selection criteria
that he used amounts to
requiring that the angular
momentum is an integral
value of the reduced blast cause in h bar.
So you see, when you do that,
you get an instant
solution for the discrete energy levels.
So you require that the angular
momentum be an intern multiple of
h bar running from one to infinity.
Now actually, in modern quantum mechanics
the value of zero is allowed as well so
let's be very clear about that.
But in any event, here is
an expression for the energy levels,
which I've casted here
in sort of modern form.
Alpha's the so-called
fine-structure constant.
Again, the definition depends upon
the choice of electrical units.
You might see a four pi epsilon naught
in the denominator depending on
the choice of units.
But in any event,
the fine structure constant is a pure
number, it's approximately equal to that.
And so if you want a mnemonic for
remembering what the Bohr
energy levels are,
it's kind of like e is
equal to mc squared.
So all the dimensionality of energy
that appears in this expression is
due to the rest mass energy of
the electron, Einstein's rest mass energy.
And then the coupling constant,
this is a pure number,
z alpha squared over 2n squared.
I'm going to phrase that in a slightly
different way in the inline quiz,
have a look and see if you come
up with the same conclusion.
So the Bohr energy equation gives rise to
a very important fundamental constant.
One of the most accurately measured,
the so called Rydberg constant,
which takes this value in
units of inverse meters.
And so the energy levels
of the hydrogen atom can be
conveniently expressed
in complete dimensional
form in terms of the product,
the Rydberg constant,
and Planck's constant,
and the speed of light.
And this number R infinity hc
is approximately equal to this
number in electron volts.
That's the energy change that
you get by moving an electron
through a potential difference of 13.6
volts, about the voltage of a car battery.
Now another thing that falls out very
nicely from the Bohr theory, and
at least this type of scaling is
retained in modern quantum mechanics,
is the relationship between
the radius of the orbit and
the so-called principle quantum number.
So the radius goes as a square,
the principal quantum number, and
the coefficient of proportionality's
the length, the Bohr radius,
which takes this value.
I guess you'd say that's 53
picometers approximately.
Now there's another important relation,
which I'll just let you
discover in the inline quiz.
So the varial relationship that you got
through working through the inline quiz,
yet again, the constants of
proportionality that connect the total
energy with the expectation value of the
kinetic energy and the potential energy.
Those are preserved in
modern quantum mechanics.
Now, well,
we said Bohr had a great breakthrough.
What's the basis for that judgement?
One was just these spectacular
agreement with experiment.
So again, the frequency of the spectral
line, the inverse of the wavelength and
spectral line is given
by an energy difference.
And so it was possible to
compute all the possible
energy differences according
to the Bohr formula.
And, this as we shall see,
gave an account of all the known
lines of hydrogen,
solved some other problems and predict