Hello, everyone.
Welcome back to Exploring Quantum Physics.
I'm Charles Clark.
Now we're going to look briefly at some of
the many applications of the Bohr model.
I'll remind you again that
it can be found, sorry,
a copy of Bohr's paper can be
found in the original scientific
literature, and
you probably will need to look at that
in order to successfully
complete the homework.
Plus, and
I'll try not to keep saying this over and
over again,
if you read some of Bohr's original work,
then you'll be a step above most
physicists, who have never done so.
They've only read of his work by
people who have interpreted it,
so it's a chance to do something
original and creative, in my opinion.
Okay, so here's Bohr's energy
expression once again,
so reminding you R infinity has
the dimensions of inverse length,
H bar c is energy times length,
n is an integer.
And so
the basic idea that Bohr had was that
these define a system of
stationary states, but
those stationary states
can be disturbed by
the electromagnetic field
which can cause transitions.
So absorption of a quantum of light
can either increase the energy,
raise the electron from
a lower to a higher orbit.
Or emission of a photon can cause an
excited state to fall to the ground state.
And this idea is still an essential
part of quantum theory.
The main point is there is
fundamentally a lowest state.
So in the fullness of time
things will radiate down there.
So these are the expressions
that one gets for
the inverse wavelength.
This is why the Rydberg
constant is expressed
in this strange unit of inverse meters.
It's in some sense a historical
artifact that the wavelength of light
is something that was very easy to measure
by diffraction interference experiments.
Frequency, on the other hand,
is hard to measure directly, even today.
So the inverse wavelengths of the light
are given by this simple formula.
So for the infinite nuclear mass it's
just a Rydberg constant divided by these
integers.
For finite mass,
which is something we're going to talk
about momentarily,
there is a factor of the value of
the reduced mass divided by
the mass of the electron.
So these famous lines seen both
in emission and absorption,
the Balmer series, the visible part
of the spectrum of atomic hydrogen,
were all explained by the Bohr model.
Furthermore, There
were other lines that were known
at the time in the infrared,
the so-called Paschen series,
and Bohr also applied
to his model to helium-plus,
where you change the value of z and
now you get predictions of where
the lines of helium-plus should be.
And so in the paper that we have
available in the additional materials,
he shows that he can explain all the known
lines of hydrogen, and then also
explained the so-called Pickering series
lines as being lines of helium-plus.
There was some uncertainty
at the time as to whether,
many people thought they were for
hydrogen.
Then immediately following Bohr's work,
within early the next year,
Lyman, a famous spectroscopist
at Harvard University,
looked in the far ultraviolet
region of the spectrum.
It's a very difficult technological
region that hadn't really been explored
previously.
And he found lines with n1 = 1,
that's the lowest value of n1.
n1 must be greater than or
equal to 1 in Bohr's theory.
So he found another series.
1922, the series with n1 = 2,
n1 = 3 were accounted for at the time.
n1 = 4 was discovered 1922.
Shortly thereafter when the n1 = 5,
and so on.
They just keep going and going and going.
At some point they stop naming,
actually not a some point, at n = 6,
they stopped naming these
series after their discoverer,
because it became appreciated there's
an infinite number of these series.
Indeed, here's a fairly
recent paper that shows just
how striking this phenomenon
of the Bohr-like series is.
These are absorption lines seen, so
there's an interstellar
cloud that is between us and
the supernova remnant Cassiopeia A.
And this is a spectrum, I don't know
if you can read it that clearly here,
in the radio frequency region.
These are numbers like 25 MHz.
And you see this regular
series of absorption lines,
all very sharp, and
they satisfy the Bohr formula but
now the values of n are not
of the order of 1, but
range up to about 1,000.
Now if you recall,
the radius in the Bohr model
goes as the square of
the principal quantum number, so
these are atoms that are 1 million
times larger than hydrogen.
They're the size of a bacteria.
And so this relationship,
the Bohr frequency of from
what you've seen now,
it's observed to hold over
eight decades of frequency.
This is sort of
the the Lyman-alpha region,
optical frequencies down
into the radio waves.
So it's a great unifying concept, and
even though, as we'll see or
as you must know,
Bohr described things purely in
terms of the classical orbit.
He didn't have the essence of
quantum mechanics in terms of
the superposition principle and
the existence of wave function.
Nevertheless, it's extremely valuable
mnemonic and organizing concept.
Now I want to mention another
aspect of the Bohr model which
is very important in a fundamental
discovery in nuclear physics,
the discovery of the heavy
isotope of hydrogen.
So as of this year, 1931,
which was 20 years after the Bohr model
approximately had been articulated,
atoms were thought to be made
of protons and electrons.
The neutron was not known, but
there was this curious phenomenon
that many elements had constituents
that had slightly different masses.
They were chemically similar, but
they had sightly different masses.
And this is a plot made by
a man named Harold Urey,
a great chemist,
which showed the filled dots
are the known isotopes,
isotopes known at the time.
And he perceived a pattern
here that led down
to the possible prediction of isotopes
that had not yet been observed.
There are some other clues, and
actually in the additional materials
there's some guidance
to those discoveries.
Those are these two contributions.
The discovery of deuterium, which is
a collection of the original papers,
and then a sort of a simplified
account written for, well,
a professional association journal,
which is a summary account of how
deuterium was discovered by Urey.
I should mention that at the time,
virtually all of the isotopes that
had been discovered had been discovered
by mass spectrometry, in which
you put particles through a combination
of cross-magnetic and electric fields and
find a deflection that is dependent
upon the charge-to-mass ratio.
In the case of hydrogen,
there's a stable molecular ion,
H2+ which has the mass of two expected,
two units of proton mass
that would be expected of
the heavy isotope of hydrogen and
the same charge.
And there's a lot of interference
from the electric signal, so
there was no conclusive proof of
the existence of heavy hydrogen.
So Urey had the idea of looking for
this heavy isotope of hydrogen in
the optical spectrum of atomic hydrogen.
And here is how he states his idea.
This is taken from his
Nobel lecture of 1934.
Bohr's theory, given some 20 years ago,
permits the calculation
of the Ballmer spectrum of the heavier
isotopes of hydrogen from this spectrum
of hydrogen by the well-known theoretical
formula for the Rydberg constant.
So even though by this time, 1934,
we had Schroedinger mechanics,
And Urey was the first American
author of a monograph-type
textbook on quantum mechanics,
very familiar with the subject.
He preferred to describe to
the general audience the plausibility
of his idea in terms of
Bohr's well-accepted theory.
Now basically,
the difference in the spectrum of
a heavy isotope of hydrogen from regular
hydrogen in the Bohr theory can just be
traced to the reduced mass difference.
So in the online quiz,
you get a chance to think about that.
So no one had seen a heavy
isotope of hydrogen.
Urey thought it might be detected in
the optical spectrum of atomic hydrogen.
But how to prove that decisively?
He had the idea of taking large
quantities of liquid hydrogen,
cryogenic fluid, evaporating the liquid,
in which in the process of evaporation,
presumably the lighter isotope
will evaporate more rapidly and
so the heavier isotope will be
concentrated in the residue.
So he recruited a man named
Ferdinand Graft Brickwedde,
who was United States' leading expert in
low-temperature physics at that time.
He was the first person to produce
liquid helium in the United States,
and so Brickwedde carried out
this distillation process.
You can read about it in the summary
article if you're interested,
and produced a sample,
In which it was possible
to find the evidence for
the heavy isotope hydrogen.
So this is an emissions
spectrum.
In this particular figure it happens to be
from the Balmer beta line in this spectrum
that we've been talking
about all this time.
And here's the central peak, so really
this peak continues up off the scale.
And now here is the prediction
from the Bohr theory
of where an isotope of mass 2 should be.
And you see that these three
curves are spectra taken under
different hypothetical
concentration of the heavy isotope.
And so
that predicted feature grows as expected.
There's no evidence for a mass 3 isotope.
There is a mass 3 isotope, tritium, but
it's unstable and
it has a very low abundance.
So this is a nice application of
a very simple reduced mass picture
provided by Bohr.
The discovery of a substance that in 1931,
no one knew it existed.