And now I want to again illustrate this with another example how he can use conservation of energy in
order to solve problems.
So here's the problem I have I have again my two micro cooling charge.
I'm going to assume that that charge is fixed in space and 30 meters away I'm going to place a negative
three micro cooling charge.
So those are attracted to each other.
I'm going to release the negative three micro cooling charge so it's going to have a force acting toward
the positive one.
And it's going to start to speed up.
So the question is when it's five meters away now how fast is the charge moving.
All right so I've got it illustrated above.
So this is the speed that I'm looking for.
So let's go see how we can use conservation of energy.
Look at the total energy at one position the initial and set that equal to the total energy of the final
position and then solve for the unknown.
The nice thing about using conservation of energy is you typically only have one equation to solve for.
OK.
That's the conservation of energy so if you're able to write down that statement you look at what the
unknown is and that's typically what you have to solve for let me show you how you use conservation
of energy now to solve this problem.
So again the total energy at the initial position is the kinetic plus the initial potential and that
has to be equal to the final kinetic plus the final potential.
Now we can substitute here again if I'm releasing the particle here the charge from arrest.
They don't have to worry about the initial kinetic energy.
I will have some initial electrical potential energy and I will have some final right because I'm not
at an infinite distance away anywhere.
So I do have to keep all these other terms I'm looking for the speed and the speed is going to be tucked
inside this final kinetic energy.
Let's start writing down our expressions.
So that's what we have.
K. Q1 Q2 divided by our 1 are our initial rather.
That's my initial potential energy at equals 2 1 1/2 m v final squared.
That's our final kinetic energy and plus K. Q1 Q2 divided by our final by our final in this case is
five meters.
So now we have to do a little bit of algebra in order to get an expression for the speed you could substitute
the numbers here and get numbers for all this and that's fine there's nothing wrong with that.
I'm going to just do it algebraic Lee for now and at the end I'll get one number.
OK.
So I'm going to bring this final potential energy on the other side.
And I'll bring the kinetic energy.
Let me just write it like this.
All right.
So my kinetic energy my final kinetic energy then becomes somebody whose terms are the same so I can
actually factor them out.
That's pretty easy.
And here I'm going to get one divided by our initial minus one divided by our final.
OK.
So that's not too bad.
And now some of the math.
Now if I want to just get one final expression I'm going to get V final there's going to be a square
root and it's gonna be kind of a lengthy term.
All right it's going to be two K Q1 Q2 divided by the mass and again I have this term here of 1 divided
by our initial minus 1 divided by our final.
OK.
So we could start substituting the numbers in here now
and everything is going to work out.
Again we have to put in all the signs.
OK.
So we have to we have nine times tend to the nine.
That's the K value.
The first charge is to micro cool on positive to tend to the negative six.
The second one was negative.
Don't worry the negative side is not going to appear under the square root at the end you'll see that
the term in the bracket here is also going to be negative.
So this charges negative three micro columns.
I'm going to divide by the mass of the mass I said was 2.5 times 10 to the negative three for this problem.
OK.
And now I still have this remaining term.
So 1 divided by the initial which is 30.
That's gonna be a small number minus one over five okay.
So after evaluating then the calculator you should get a number that looks like did things correctly
I think I got a number that was approximately two point seven meters per second.
Okay.
So that's kind of how you would do a problem like this using conservation of energy.
All right really really powerful technique especially when they're asking you for quantities that are
scalar is like calculating the speed.