We just saw that four point charges.
This is what the electrical potential is.
And again it is a scalar quantity.
All right.
We can't forget that.
And if I was three meters away I calculated that the potential at this point relative to this one is
six thousand volts.
Let's have a look at my equation over here first of all what happens if our goes all the way to infinity
if I'm very very far away.
If you look at my equation right here I have my k constant the charge and now I'm dividing by a really
big number.
So in this limit what we would find is that the potential actually would tend towards zero volts when
you're really really far away.
This is for a single point charge.
If my point P was located over here and guess what if it was still three meters away if my distance
is three meters I would say that.
Well guess what.
The potential since it's a scalar the voltage right here is six thousand volts.
Again I could draw a circle or actually a if it was like in three dimensions right.
You could draw a circle around this charge and everywhere.
This is not the best one but close enough a little closer on this side.
Right.
But everywhere on this path you would find that the voltage is six thousand volts.
If I put a point over here and that distance again is three meters from the point charge you would write
the voltage is equal to six thousand.
All right what about now.
If I had an inner sphere right.
If I have an inner sphere that is closer.
What if my sphere is something like this.
Right.
In this case here the radius is just one meter.
What would be the voltage over here on this position right here.
Well again all you would have to do is you use my equation same equation right.
Let's do it an orange since we're calculating the voltage everywhere on the sphere you'd right at the
voltage is K the constant nine times 10 to the nine.
All right the charge is still to micro cool arms that's two times 10 to the negative six and divided
by one meter in this case.
All right.
So here you would get eighteen thousand volts.
I notice that the electrical potential is bigger as I go closer to positive charges.
Let me write that down on the figure here.
All right.
So anyway that's pretty straightforward as I go farther away the potential gets smaller when I'm really
really far away the potential is zero volts.
All right.
Now let's consider what happens if I have a negative charge over here what is the electrical potential
produced by negative charges.
So let me kind of make some room over here.
Let's consider a slightly different situation again.
There are always going to be point charges.
All right.
So let's go ahead with this one let's produce one point charge here right at the center.
I'm going to say it's a negative charge and the magnitude of that charge is going to be CU negative
1 micro cooling.
All right.
So we have a negative value here.
Well let's go see if I am a distance of let's say one meter away.
This is my distance are in this case is one meter.
What is the voltage everywhere on this sphere.
Well again you just use the equation now again since it's a scalar quantity the important thing is that
we actually substitute in the negative value for the charge.
So the K value is nine times 10 to the nine.
The charge now is negative 1 times 10 to the negative 6.
And if I am one meter away from that charge then I'm just dividing by 1.
So at the end the voltage for this case here has to be negative nine thousand volts.
All right.
So this is what the voltage is everywhere on this sphere.
Now how about if I go a little bit further away again.
What if I go three meters away from this charge.
You try to draw a better sphere this is a sphere.
Again in this case I don't have to do the calculation really fast all I have to do now is divide this
number by three.
So what do we get.
We're going to get negative three thousand volts and again in this case this sphere is a distance R
which is equal to three meters away so the closer I get the more negative it becomes the farther I get
again.
It's going to approach zero but it approaches it from the negative side okay.
Now these surfaces here notice that everywhere on here I'm going to get negative three thousand volts
everywhere on the orange one.
Doesn't matter if it's on this side if it's on this side since I'm always the same distance I'm always
going to get nine thousand volts these surfaces are given a very very special name since they have these
same potential the same voltage everywhere.
You write this down if they have the same potential we call these equal potentials so let's try that
again equal potential.
These are equal potential surfaces.
OK.
Now what would happen if I place a place another charge here.
Let's Plays a two micro cool home charge right here on this equal potential that's negative nine thousand
volts.
What is the potential energy of the system if I place another charge here.
Now you could go and start by calculating K Q1 Q2 over ah you could do that.
However if we know the voltage at this specific position in space right away I can calculate what is
the potential energy because it's simply the charge multiplied by the voltage at that specific spot.
So in this case it's two micro cooling two times 10 to the negative six.
And what else.
What's multiplied by the voltage and again it's negative nine thousand.
It's important to keep the negative sign there.
So the potential energy can be positive it can be negative.
In this case here I'm going to get negative 18 multiplied by ten to the negative six oh so I tend to
the negative three rather let's try that again.
All right.
And that is measured in Joules.
All right if I take the same charge and I place it over here on this equal potential.
So again I'm going to place a positive to micro cool erm charge I can easily calculate what is the potential
energy of the system because I have a negative charge that produces a voltage of negative three thousand
over here.
So let's do the calculation.
So the potential energy right here or of the system rather is simply going to be Q multiplied by the
voltage again two times 10 to the negative six is the charge that I'm placing here and the voltage we
said we calculated this was an equal potential of 3000 volts.
So at the end you're going to get negative six and times tend to the negative three if you work it out
Jules.
So this kind of formula right here is so practical especially if you know the voltage or the scalar
field everywhere in space.