All right I want to look at some eggy potentials here so I have this positive charge here at the center.
The charge that I placed here was a one nano Coolum charge so that's 1 times 10 to the negative 9 coolant.
The green lines are some of the equity potentials produced by this actually the closest the smallest
circle over here.
That's a 40 volt equip potential.
The next biggest one is 30.
This guy over here is 20 volts then 10 and the smallest the largest circle here is five volts.
And again those would simply be calculated by the potential for a point charge.
All right.
So we can calculate the distance the arrows here represent the directions of the electric field produced
by this charge.
It's positive and one thing you notice is that the electric field points away from it.
If I take a look at a couple of those electric field vectors over here you could see something that
is starting to emerge.
Hopefully you could see it right the electric field is a vector the way you would calculate the magnitude
of the electric field.
Again it looks similar however it's divided by R squared.
And we know that the electric field gets smaller as I go away and it's stronger over here.
However if you just look at the direction of the electric field pointing away look at it relative to
the equity potential surfaces and you should notice something that jumps out at you.
Let's focus specifically on this one right here right.
This is the equity potential surface and my electric field point in this direction.
Right.
Notice the electric field.
So let's look at some general property electric field points goes from high toward low electrical potential.
OK.
So electric field direction
goes from high goes from high potential
toward low potential
that's very very important.
The other property is has to do with the direction of the field relative to the equity potential services.
Right.
The one thing we also notice from this diagram that you should notice is that the electric field direction
is what is perpendicular to the equity potentials.
All right.
I can't emphasize how important this is so we're gonna be able to kind of if you're giving electric
field direction we should be able to draw with the equity potentials look like.
In addition if you're given a diagram with equity potentials you should be able they at least have an
idea of what direction the electric field goes in.
You notice that the electric field is pointing perpendicular to all of these equity potential surfaces.
And notice that there is no component of an electric field that has anything parallel to the equity
potential.
It's always perpendicular.
We never have a case like this always perpendicular.
OK.
So this is super super important.
I mean let me highlight this second point here.
This one's even more important than the first.