Right I now want to do is just look at the mathematical relationship between the electric field and
the electrical potential.
We saw the connection four point charges electric fuel's point out radiantly away from the point charge
and the equip potential services were perpendicular to those field lines.
And I also show you for the dipole the same thing happens the field is more complicated but the equip
potentials were always perpendicular to those.
So remember the field lines always go from high potential toward low potential.
So you need the electrical potential to change for there to be an electric field.
All right.
So let's look at that and then we're going to apply our equation to look at parallel plates.
That was the other configuration where we looked at the electric field.
That case is a mathematically a little bit simpler because we said if we have parallel PLATES THE ELECTRIC
FIELD IS CONSTANT.
Right.
It goes from the positive plate toward the negative plate.
Let's see what that means in terms of the electrical potential in terms of the voltage All right.
So here is the expression over here and I'm just gonna write it down as the magnitude and let's consider
a place where the voltage varies linearly in space.
The way you would write this here is minus the change of voltage over a change in spatial coordinate.
So here's the situation I'm describing.
Let's see something like this.
This is my x axis and for now let's just take these are we potential surfaces and let's assume that
they kind of look like this and take this here to be kind of 50 volts maybe twenty five volts 0 volts
and negative twenty five volts.
Okay.
The spacing here could be kind of 0 meters one meter two meter three meters and so forth.
If I wanted to evaluate the electric field again there's only gonna be an electric field in this direction
because that is where the voltage is changing.
There is no component of the electric field that has to be up and down.
Right you can't have this because the voltage doesn't change along that direction right here.
All right.
So let me just get rid of that.
So we will have an electric field that goes like this.
And if it varies linearly with distance again I could choose kind of this point and this point.
So there are different voltages and they're separated by a certain distance.
So if I wanted to find the electric field in this case again the Deltas are always a final value minus
an initial value.
And again this is going to be my final position minus my initial position.
So let's go ahead and do that so we get minus.
So the final voltage let's take this point over here so we get minus 25 and minus the initial voltage
This is 50.
Okay.
And all of this divided by the change of space here.
This is at three meters that's the final and minus zero meters like this.
OK.
So if you look at this term is 75 or negative 75 multiplied by that one becomes 75 over three.
In this case we get 25 and this is measured in volts per meter.
OK so the electric field would be 25 volts per meter OK.
Notice we get a positive number.
Positive number is indicative of some that point toward the positive x direction right here.
OK.
So that here is the electric field magnitude for that direction.
All right what I said was kind of an approximation in reality really what you want to do is if you want
to find the electric field this is kind of how it's represented here.
Now this looks rather complicated.
This here is called a gradient.
And I'll define it what it is in just a second so I can write this a gradient here as a partial derivative.
So it's only along one direction here of the voltage and that gives me the component of the field along
the x direction.
Okay.
But I could have in general the voltage that varies in other directions.
So actually the gradient right here actually has three components if I write it in Cartesian coordinates.
If the voltage varies in the y direction again I'm going to have a y component of the electric field.
This is what I would call E Y and the last term you can also have spatial variation of the voltage again
along the z direction.
And this is what would be called the Z component of the electric field
for the case that I considered earlier this is if I'm working in Cartesian coordinates for the point
charge that I considered earlier we know that the magnitude of the voltage from a certain point away
the voltage I can write out as k q over are okay.
The way that you would write down the electric field for this case again I would have to write out this
gradient here in spherical coordinates.
Again this is kind of mathematical but the only component that I'm going to get here is how does the
voltage change as a function of distance away from the charge.
All right.
And while I'm gonna write this as k q and I'll bring the R to the top and I can do that as long as I
just change the exponent to a negative.
And how do you take a derivative of this function.
This is pretty straightforward.
You get minus one from the exponent.
This is K Q and it becomes R to the minus two.
Now can't forget the other negative sine I have there so that actually converts that one into a positive
right and now the direction of this is always kind of pointing away in this case.
Okay so that is how you would evaluate it for this point charge.
So at the end the expression that I get at least for the full vector right here would be k q I'll bring
the r square at the bottom and again it's pointing away from that point charge.
So at any point again my electric field kind of looks like this.
So this expression here is sort more like this one here.
This is more for spherical.
And this here is more for Cartesian coordinates.
All right your class might not be going into this level of detail here but the key is that as long as
you have voltage that changes in space you're going to have an electric field.