All right.
Let's have a look at parallel plates now parallel plates we've spent quite a bit of time looking at
them.
So let's assume that our top plate is positively charged and our bottom plate is negatively charged
and these plates are separated by five centimeters.
All right.
One thing I know is that the electric field produced by parallel plates.
Again if you're more or less in the center of the plates the electric field is uniform it's constant
everywhere.
Right.
And it goes from positive toward negative.
So this would be the electric field that would be the direction like this.
So again if I wanted to let's assume here that we have a Y axis like this.
Let's take this plate here to be at zero and this played here to be at positive five centimeters.
All right.
So my definition for electric field if I wanted to calculate it again it would be.
What is the change of voltage relative to the change in position.
OK.
So again it's going to be the final minus V initial divided by in this case it's Y final minus Y initial.
Okay.
So that's what's going to be my final and my initial really doesn't matter this could be my initial
and this here could be my final.
Okay.
So my final voltage is 30 volts minus the initial voltage which is negative 30 volts.
OK.
The final position is five centimeters
five times tend to the negative two and minus zero.
OK.
So let's evaluate this determine the bracket over here it gives me positive 60 volts.
That's the difference in voltage between the top and the bottom and there's a negative there.
Right.
So I should get negative 60 and divided by five times 10 to the negative two.
OK.
So to do this math here I would do kind of five over maybe 100 something like this and 60 over five
gives me twelve.
All right I think I did the math correctly or I should get 12 hundred and this would be volts per meter.
Now this is really a field in the y direction.
So the electric field in the y direction notice I get a negative sine the negative sine is simply telling
me the direction
of the electric field.
Okay.
And it is pointing down right my positive is pointing up here.
That's the positive direction is the way I've defined it using this coordinate system right here.
All right.
And again if you're just worried about kind of what the magnitude of the field is all you have to do
is just take the difference of voltage divided by the separation of the plates.
Right.
And you'd get twelve hundred.
You don't have to worry about kind of having this extra negative sine we already know the direction
of the electric field just by looking at it.
So what would the equate potential surfaces look like now for this.
Well again right between the plates if this one is positive 30 and this one is negative 30 right between
the plates.
Guess what I would get I would get a zero volts as I would go kind of a quarter of the way.
That's what I would get positive 15 volts and as I go kind of a quarter of the way I would get minus
15 volts.
These are the echoey potential surfaces.
They are perpendicular to all of the field lines and that's consistent with what we said and we would
get the same electric field here even if we chose kind of this to be my starting point in this to be
my final point okay.
It really doesn't matter because here we'd have a change of 30 volts but we'd have let's just imagine
we're going to do the calculation between initial and final point here.
My delta v here would be 30 volts and the spacing difference now is over 2.5 centimeters.
OK guys that's 2.5 centimeters times tend to the negative 2.
All right.
Again if you do the calculation you should get in the negative sign if you want to carry that in the
front but you're going to get negative twelve hundred volts per meter.
So it really doesn't matter whether you take the full distance or just half or even just a little bit
because it varies linearly here with the electrical potential.