I want to cover this example here so we have is parallel plates.
One side is positively charged the other side is negatively charged and what I'm doing now is I am placing
a positive charge here inside this and I'm going to release it.
I want to compare what's going to happen to the charge on the other side.
I'm going to have a negative charge again I'm going to place it inside this electric field in the electric
field goes from positive to negative in both cases that's represented by the green lines over here and
have a look.
We know that the force for this positive charge is going to be to the right.
It's in the same direction as the electric field.
That's easy.
The force on the electron or the negative charge is going to be it's attracted to all these positive
it's being repelled by all of those negatives.
Force is going to be to the left.
All right.
This should be pretty straightforward right.
Remember our force is always given by QE.
So that means that if it's positive the force in the is in the same direction as the electric field.
If the charge is negative the force is in the opposite direction of the field.
All right.
Now think about it in terms of the energy.
If I release it from resin it starts to speed up.
Over here we would say it has a high potential energy.
That's a P stands for.
On the other hand it's converting some of this potential energy into kinetic energy.
But again the total energy has to be conserved.
So over here the potential energy goes down.
All right.
Same thing with this one.
OK.
This one here starts with high potential energy and let's say that the kinetic energy initially 0 for
that one Katie kinetic energy is high over here so that the total when you add both of those contributions
up has to be a constant.
So again we're starting with high potential energy even though it's negative it's close to another negative.
When you multiply those together you're going to get a positive number.
That's a high potential energy.
So both charges move from high potential energy toward low potential energy because they speed up right.
They get some kinetic energy at the end kinetic energy over here is high.
If I have low potential energy.
Now what makes them different is the last thing I remember we always talk about electrical potential
the electrical potential is higher and it's positive.
Near the positive plate.
That's true for both of them.
Look what happens to charges positive charges move from high potential toward low potential.
Yeah that's the direction of the electric field that's what we said but look what happens to negative
charges negative charges do the opposite.
But that makes sense when you draw it out but they move from low electrical potential.
Right.
It could be like negative 50 volts on the side it might be positive 50 volts a negative charge wants
to move toward a region wave of high electrical potential and when it moves here it actually lowers
its potential energy.
OK.
So being able to distinguish potential energy from potential.
All right.
Hopefully this example kind of shed some light on it.
Again I always like to put some numbers to some of these variables sometimes just to make it clear to
me.
Oh yeah.
If it's a positively charged plate let me just say is plus 50 volts.
That's negative.
Let me set it as negative 50 volts.
Now it's clear what the positive charge wants to do.
All right.
Hopefully this makes a little bit more sense to you.