So here's the first question here we have as a proton moves in the direction of electric field lines.
Then we have some choices is moving from low to high potential gaining potential energy.
Then we have all of kind of the different variations.
All right.
So I think what I would suggest over here is you just kind of draw what's going on so let's draw an
electric field.
All right.
Let's take the simplest case over here.
Right.
Here's an electric field and draw a proton right.
Here's a proton so there would be a force acting on the proton which would be QE.
All right.
So that's from the force perspective.
But what about the potential.
Now if I have field lines that point from the left to the right it means that this side over here imagine
what would produce an electric field like this.
Right.
We might have a positive plate.
And if the electric field lines finish over here that would mean that this side here would be negative.
Right.
Because that would give me a force that would be the reason why the proton would move toward the right.
Right move toward the negative plate.
So if this is positive right.
We say that this here is at a high voltage.
This is high.
For example let's just set it to 30 volts imagine this one here this one here might be negative 30 volts
that would be the potential.
All right.
So let's go see what is.
It's moving from a low potential to high potential.
No it's moving from high potential toward low potential.
It can't be that can't be in Choice C Right Choice C says oh sorry to a C could still be right or it
can't be choice B B says it's moving from low to high.
OK.
So we can't do that.
So it has to be from high potential toward low potential.
The second part deals with the energy.
OK.
So what happens to the energy as it moves both its potential remain constant.
It's not going to remain constant so let's get rid of choice e because it's moving like this.
All right.
So what happens to the potential energy if you remember potential energy.
We read it as queue times V for now let's just assume that the proton charge as we know it's positive.
But let's just set it to one cooling.
So what would that mean for the potential energy over here the potential energy on this side would be
well que times V so it'd be one times 30 and this would be positive.
Right.
Positive 30 joules and then what happens while over here it would be you final would be Q would be one.
The potential is negative 30.
Right.
So it'd be negative 30 joules so it has to lose electrical potential energy because what's happening
it's going faster down over here.
Right.
It's gaining kinetic energy over here.
If something gains kinetic energy it has to come from somewhere.
OK so it has to be losing electrical potential energy.
So really D has to be the right case over here.
It can't be gaining electrical potential energy.
All right.
So that's it for the first problem.
Hopefully you understand that one.
All right.
So there's the next problem.
If the electrical potential is zero at some place in space then they talk about the electric field at
that point must be negative zero uniform positive impossible to determine.
All right.
So first we have to figure out well what happens when the potential is zero.
What I would suggest in this case is we try to figure out the simplest possible case where the potential
is zero.
I'm going to use point charges.
Right.
And we know that right over here at this right at the midpoint if these charges are the same.
So if this is kind of plus q and this guy's negative Q that V at the center should be equal to zero
because they would cancel out.
Right.
You would have k q over R and then you would have K and negative q over our member having the sign of
the charge is important when you calculate the electrical potential.
So we would get zero volts right here at the center.
What else do we know.
What is the electrical field at that point.
Well the electrical field we know is points away from positive toward negative right.
The electric field is in this direction over here.
So we can't really say if it's negative right.
Negative just tells us the direction is definitely not zero.
It's not necessarily going to be uniform.
The electric field I mean it's just that one point I'm positive again you can't really say I would say
he is probably the best answer for this problem right here based on what's given.
The only thing I could say is that there is an electric field at that point even though the voltage
is zero.
OK.
Kind of a little bit of a tricky question.
Here's problem three we have four charges here.
Two of them are positive to a negative and they're in this kind of three dimensions over here.
They have the same magnitude.
They just have different signs.
All right.
OK.
Let me kind of highlight which ones are negative over here make those in red.
They pop out a bit more.
All right they're all the same distance from the origin which is over here.
What is the electrical potential at point p due to these charges.
OK.
So if we think about is it going to be zero positive negative or impossible to determine.
Well if they're all arranged like this one thing we should know is they're all kind of the same distance
right.
They're all the same distance because the distance from the origin is the same.
They're all a certain distance.
Let's call it D from the origin which means that this distance R is also all the same for both of them.
So if you would be calculating the total electrical potential what you would do is I mean for the first
one over here what you would do is you would have k q over R you'd have another term like this for the
second charge which we k q over R and then you would have two terms with negative charges.
I would put negative Q here and then over R and then I'd have another term right.
Plus K negative q over R.
So at the end when I would add all of those things I'd have two positive ones and two negatives I would
have zero volts.
So we'd have zero electrical potential.
So again the best choice for this one here is probably a choice a all right.
Let's now look at this problem over here what we have is an electron and a proton they're release from
rest and there's only electrostatic forces acting between them which are the following statements must
be true.
And they said there could be more than one charge.
All right.
So they talk about the energy potential energy either increasing or decreasing the kinetic energy and
the acceleration keeps decreasing.
All right.
So let's have a look at it first of all.
So let's just draw it out.
Imagine we have a proton and an electron it doesn't matter what we put for the charges.
So what we could do is here let's just call this 1 1 cool dome and negative 1.
Cool.
It doesn't matter whether we have the right charge.
We just want to look at what's going to happen.
The key is that one is positive.
The other one is negative.
All right.
So what happens to the potential energy.
Well as they get closer remember there's a force acting on and they are attracted to each other.
So they're going to move closer together.
So at some point they're going to look like this.
So they're going to get closer.
Right the distance are here is going to get smaller.
Here it was kind of big.
Right.
All right.
So they get closer let's call this are 1 and are 2.
So the potential energy in the first case over here if you think about it how do we write it down.
It's K Q1 Q2 and this one here would be a positive one negative one and divided by our one.
Here I would get negative K over R1 I could get a number for that for example but notice that it is
negative and that's important right.
So I start off with some negative value.
That's my initial potential energy.
What about my final potential energy final potential energy is again k 1 minus one what happens to our
two imagine our one is put a number in there what if this is ten right ten meters apart let's get rid
of this one if I write this as ten and in this case here what if I write this as one meter.
Right.
So they're getting close together won't be just one.
So at the end here you get minus K over 1.
So you notice that this is.
All right.
This guy here is is more negative.
This guy here is more negative
so we notice that it is smaller.
If something is more negative it is smaller.
So that means that the potential energy is actually getting more negative which means it's decreasing.
All right.
So it's not increasing it's decreasing right here.
It's kind of a little tricky.
Now if there's a force acting on it all what happens.
They start to accelerate.
Right.
That's given by cool ohms Laura for.
So it'd be k Q1 Q2 divided by our 1 squared.
What would it be down over here.
It would be k Q1 Q2 divided by R2 squared.
Notice that the distance is smaller over here.
So the force would be bigger.
Whatever force you have here this force is bigger this force here is smaller.
So a smaller force because the distance changes bigger force.
All right.
So the acceleration doesn't decrease.
Right.
If the force is getting bigger it means the acceleration is increasing.
So can't be that one.
All right what about the energy concept.
What do you think happens to the kinetic energy.
Does it increase or decrease.
Well again it should increase if things are moving faster.
The kinetic energy should increase and it definitely doesn't decrease.
OK.
So that's kind of how I would argue all of this one for a problem for right here's problem five.
We have a region of space that has a uniform electric field that is constant.
It points from the left to the right as shown in the figure.
Which statement is correct.
All right.
The potential out of all these three points is the same or the potential at a and b are the same and
c is at high higher potential a B or the same potential that C is lower or a B A is higher than B and
so forth.
Choice D right here.
So one thing they tell us is that the field is uniform.
Well let's think about what would produce a uniform electric field right here.
What would what would this side look like versus this side.
Again this looks like a parallel plate capacitor to me.
So that means that this side here would be positive and this side here would be negatively charged that
would produce an electric field that goes like this.
So for example this side here might be at 10 volts and this side here might be at negative 10 volts.
The center in that case would be zero volts.
We know that the electric field tells us how the voltage changes with respect to the position.
Now if this is constant
that means that the voltage varies with the distance has a constant slope.
That means I go from plus 10 to negative 10.
In kind of a straight line all right.
If you were going to actually make a plot of voltage versus position Well I would start over here at
10 Volts and I would end up at negative 10 volts once I reach the other plate.
Imagine the other plate finishes here so this would be a graph like this.
The slope of that line would give us the electric field right here and you'd also be at 0 volts right
at the center.
So that means that remember we also talked about the equal potential.
If electric field lines are going like this it means that the equal potential lines have to look like
this.
This might be 9 Volts.
The center here you might get 5 volts right 0 volts at the center.
Negative 5 volts write down some values here as I get closer I am approaching negative 10.
So again these are equal potential lines we call those equal potentials
okay.
So kind of different ways of looking at it.
So that means that a and b would be at the same potential and C would be at a lower electrical potential.
So definitely not the same everywhere.
Okay a and b are equal.
That's fine.
The potential at point C is higher.
No we just said it has to be lower because the electric field is pointing that way.
Potential C is lower this one here makes sense to me.
Let's look at choice D the potential potential at Point A is highest low A and B have to be at the same
potential.
So kind of a little bit of a tricky question also but again using the concept of equal potential lines
they have to be perpendicular to the electric field perpendicular to E field.
All right that's it for the quiz guys hopefully you understood some of this.