All right so let's imagine we have this for Coolum charge here.
And again if I release it's positive.
So it wants to be repelled by these positives and wants to be attracted by the negatives.
Right.
So it's going to have an electric force acting on it in this direction right here.
Let's calculate.
So it's going to speed up.
Right.
If I release it from ress be right before hit the plate.
It should be moving pretty fast.
The question's pretty straightforward.
Let's calculate the work done by this electric field.
All right.
So the definition is the magnitude of the force and scalar product with the displacement in the vertical
direction.
All right.
So the way I write that down in terms of the quantities it would be the forces the electric force the
displacement the magnitude is delta y and coast of the angle between the force and the displacement.
That's the work done by this electric force.
All right how do we write the electric force I write it as the charge which has four columns multiplied
by the electric field the displacement now I was going to write the displacement as a vector I mean
this is what the displacement looks like.
Right.
And the magnitude is simply the distance between the plates.
So I'm just going to write this is D guy and coasts of the angle.
Now what's the angle between the force and the displacement.
Again both of those vectors point in the same direction.
So I'd have coast of zero degrees right here.
All right.
So the work done by the electric field boils down to something pretty straightforward.
QED.
All right.
So we could just substitute the numbers we get for cool homes our electric field magnitude is two hundred
and fifty and the distance between the plate is six centimetres zero point zero six.
All right that is the work done by the electric field.
All right.
So my final answer now is a numerical number.
What I would get would be four times 250 times zero point zero six gives me 60 Joules.
Notice the number is positive.
Does that make sense to you it's positive because the force and the displacement are parallel to each
other.
They're in the same direction.
So the work does the field does positive work.
All right.
So kind of a nice little example.