All right guys I want to say a few things now about conservative forces and then we'll move on to potential
energy in more detail but let me give you some examples of conservative forces that you may have already
seen before.
A force of gravity I mean write all these down.
OK.
So the force of gravity is an example of a conservative force for example the weight of an object right.
M times little G.
That was an example of a conservative force.
Another example would be forces from springs on blocks right.
We call that hooks law.
Okay.
So let me just call it as a spring force.
This was also another example of a conservative force that forced from a spring typically written as
negative K times X and X is a certain displacement from the equilibrium.
All right what's really important now for this section is that we have a new conservative forces a new
conservative force.
So this electrical force or cool Ohm's Law god just call it an electrical force is also an example of
a conservative force.
Let me give you an example that's not a conservative force so non-conservative
a non conservative force one example that is kind of standard is the force of friction.
OK.
Friction is a non conservative force.
So what do we mean by this.
Notice that all of these forces over here the force of gravity and the spring force.
If you studied those in any detail we always had a potential energy associated to those forces.
OK.
For example for gravity we would talk about a gravitational potential energy and maybe you remember
that one that was M.G. maybe times the height that was the potential energy associated to gravity.
Right.
If I lift something high it has more gravitational potential energy.
How about a spring force maybe you don't remember this formula but if I stretch a spring I do work because
it's hard to do that.
And when I stretch the spring I store energy and that system I store energy in that spring in the form
of spring potential energy.
The formulas was often written as something like this one 1/2 K X square that was the spring potential
energy.
So what we're going to do in the next video is we're going to start now talking about what is the potential
energy associated to charges.
OK.
So I'm going to call it again a potential energy use and I'll give you the equation after and it's going
to be an electrical potential energy.
All right.
Maybe put a little subscript e in there.
So what is the difference now between conservative versus non-conservative.
Let me show you what that means.
So let's go back to our parallel plate capacitor.
All right.
Again I'm going to make one of the charges sorry one of the plates positive and I'm going to make the
other plate negative.
All right.
So put them charge on these plates and the previous example that we did we calculated how much work
it was required to bring this positive charge from the negative plate all the way to the top.
Now what why I didn't tell you about this problem was I didn't tell you how I was going to bring that
charge from the initial position down here to the final position at the top.
So we did the example what if I just bring it along this direct path and I had a displacement which
was just like this right.
This was my displacement for that problem.
And I applied a force over that displacement.
What if on the other hand if I took a different path.
What if instead if I went like this in this direction first and I took a little break.
There is the charge.
And then I went on say this diagonal.
Right.
And I went to the same final position.
If I calculated how much work was done by the electrical force for this purple path what I would do
is I would find the exact same answer as I did for the blue path.
All right.
So the work done by the electric field in this case is the exact same as the work done right here when
I go directly straight up.
OK.
The work is going to be the same.
And that is really the definition of a conservative force is that it really doesn't matter the path
that you take.
It only depends on where you start and where you finish and that's it.
That's the only thing you need in order to calculate the work done by that particular force.
OK.
So here's an example I could take this positive charge and I could bring it over this very complicated
looking path and then finish at the same position.
The work done in this case since the electrical force is conservative the work done would be the same
because I started at the same position and I finished at the same position.
So once I show you the equation to calculate the work after you'll understand why if you go to this
purple section again over this segment right here there's actually no work being done.
And let me show you why again the electrical force as I'm going from this position all the way to the
right here the electrical force would be straight down.
Right.
Because it be attracted to the negative plate down here.
And if you think about just this segment right here the displacement for this segment is in this direction.
Let's just call this delta x.
You notice that both of those vectors are perpendicular to each other.
So that means that the angle theta for that first segment right here when I'm going from here to there
is actually 90 degrees.
And whenever you have a force and a displacement that are perpendicular to each other it means that
the work over this first segment by the electrical force is actually zero.
So the only component that is going to end up contributing to the work is the component of the force
that is parallel to the displacement.
So even if you would break down this diagonal component you can break it down into kind of small little
staircases any segment here that is flat.
There is no work contributions.
The only the purpose only the vertical component right here is going to end up doing some work is going
end up contributing to the work.
All right.
Let's now look at the definition of the potential energy associated to two charges.