All right.
Have a look at two kind of silly examples over here we only have two point chargers in the top figure
and we want to use my equation to calculate now the total electrical potential energy in the system.
So I have two micro columns and a four micro column point charger separated by three meters.
So again the formula is exactly the same.
So we have nine times 10 to the 9 that's the K value same as before.
And now I'm going to have two times ten to the negative six.
I'm going to have four times 10 to the negative six.
And at the end here I have to divide by the distance and it's only three.
So you've got gotta be a little bit careful and that's it.
Now we put the number in the calculator and we get zero point zero to four.
Now that is measured in Joules pretty straightforward.
How about the second case.
So this case a little bit different to micro column a negative 5 micro column and separated by 5 meters
in this case.
What is the electrical potential energy in the system.
So I would go nine times 10 to the nine what else.
Two times ten to the negative six.
Ha.
Now the key here.
Notice I have the negative side.
Negative five times 10 to the negative six and divided by five in this case.
All right put that number in the calculator and lo and behold I'm gonna get a negative number and zero
point zero one eight.
Jules this is OK.
This can be negative.
OK.
So don't let that scare you.
Right what if I did a third case and let's just keep it rather simple instead of having a positive to
micro cool on.
Let's have a negative in this case and another negative.
We'll keep this one the same minus five micro cool on and let's convert this one to negative to micro
cool on and we'll keep the same spacing.
Let's see what happens in this case.
Again the formula is the same again it's going to look the exact same except 10 to the 9.
OK.
Now I've switched the sine here so it's important for me to have that sign here because I'm calculating
a scalar quantity.
And actually the sign is important.
Times 10 to the negative 6.
So both of those are negative charges and multiply.
Sorry divided by five meters again.
So what are we going to get in this case again these two negative signs are going to cancel out and
we're going to be left with a positive zero point zero one eight jewels.
So notice when I have two positive charges I'm going to have positive potential energy when I have two
negatives.
I'm also going to have positive potential energy.
And when I have charges that are of different sign like in the second case right here I'm going to end
up having negative electrical potential energy.
And that's OK.
Now the other thing to notice is that when r gets very very big when it tends toward infinity the electrical
potential energy tends toward zero.
OK.
So that's kind of the other important thing.
All right.
If you understand this we're off to the races.