All right.
The big advantage of having a potential energy at our disposal and the fact that the electrical force
is a conservative force is it allows us to use conservation of energy to solve problems.
So let's consider the same problem a two and a four micro cooling charge separated by three meters.
I said initially I'm going to have it like this so I have some electrical potential energy in the system.
Now the two micro cool home charge is going to be fixed in this problem.
And the four micro cooling charges free to move around.
I'm going to release it from rest.
And so it's going to start to accelerate because there's a force acting on it.
And as it starts to accelerate it starts to speed up.
Right.
So it's going to start moving away and it's going to be increasing its speed faster and faster and faster.
Eventually it's going to be really really far away from the two micro cooling charge.
The question is now how fast is that charge moving when it's really really far away.
Let's see how we can now use this concept and use conservation of total energy in order to solve a whole
bunch of problems.
So here's our example again we have to inform micro cool on this one is fixed and this one I'm going
to release it from rest so right at this position I'd be able to calculate the force right just using
cool Ohm's law all the distance I know the magnitude of the charge so I would get a force for example
of X number of cool ohms X in the first Newton's actually acting on that charge.
So it's going to start to speed up.
The question I have is when it's really really far away down over here how fast is it moving.
So in order to use this what we're going to use is conservation of total energy.
OK.
So let me go ahead write that.
And the reason I can have conservation of total energy is because the electric force is a conservative
force
so the energy in this problem is made up of two different kinds.
We're going to have electrical potential energy.
And once it starts moving we're also going to have energy associated the motion and that is called kinetic
energy.
So this is what we do we have to define the initial position and the final position.
So let me go ahead and call this the initial position and I'm going to call this here the final position
and what I want to do is I want to write the total energy at each point.
So the total energy for example initial has to be equal to the total energy at any other position.
In this case it'll be the final.
All right.
The total energy is composed of two terms.
It's going to be I'm going to move over here it's going to be the initial kinetic energy plus the initial
electrical potential energy.
And this here has to be equal to the final kinetic energy plus the final electrical potential energy.
Now what I'm going to do now is substitute my equations in here.
So what is the initial kinetic energy What's 1 1/2 and V initial squared plus what's the initial electrical
potential energy.
Well it's going to be k Q1 Q2 and divided by whatever the initial spacing was between them and this
here has to be equal to the final kinetic energy
plus the final potential energy
divided by our final.
All right now there's a lot of terms here that are going to be equal to zero.
First of all if I'm initially at rest that means it's initially not moving.
So that means that this term here has to be equal to zero.
What else.
Initially I have some potential energy I calculated that I actually have zero point to four jewels of
electrical potential energy all of that now is eventually going to get converted into kinetic energy.
And what happens when I'm really really far away.
That means that the spacing between the charges basically tends toward infinity.
So if I divide by something that's really really big this term here is going to go to zero.
So here you're transferring all of this potential energy into kinetic energy.
My goal is define how fast the charge is moving.
So let's go over here and we have actually an expression that we could use.
So again this whole term here is basically what I calculated before the zero point zero to four.
So I'm actually just going to leave that number the way it is.
And I want to get an expression for the speed using this.
So if I bring the two on the other side and this is my initial potential energy I also have to get rid
of the mass and then at the end I'll have to take the square root in order to get the expression for
the speed.
All right.
Now we could substitute in all our numbers.
So we have two zero point zero to four joules and the mass now is actually important.
Now the mass of the particle I've given you right here is 1 times tend to the negative 6 kilograms.
All right.
We put everything in here you're gonna get a number that is should be around two hundred nineteen meters
per second.
Right.
When I'm really really far away this is the answer I get.
Now if I wasn't really really far away imagine I wanted to know how fast it's moving when it's six meters
away.
In that case I wouldn't be able to make this simplification right here.
This term would not be equal to zero.
So I'd have to keep that there.
All right but this is how you can use conservation of energy now to solve problems.