All right.
So far in our journey to force this nice universal conception of the universe, we ended up completely
redefining our basic notions of kinematics and spacetime in particular.
What we found is that the poshest the special relativity, which really gave birth to these weird,
wacky effects such as time dilation and length contraction, challenged our notion of the universe as
a whole.
But in doing so, it really allowed us to bridge the gap between an infinite set of perceptions and
allowed us to form this map, known as the Lorenz transformation, which really allowed us to talk intelligently
about a infinite set of perceptions of the universe.
Now, with these monumental ideas being introduced in special relativity, it's natural to assume that
they would have a cascading effect upon physical theories that are closely related to the ideas that
are imbued within them.
For example, maybe ideas that depend upon velocity, space and time would also give rise to special
relativistic effects.
And that's what we're going to find in this video.
OK.
In fact, much like throwing a rock into a still peaceful lake in nature, we're going to find that
taking these huge ideas, these impactful ideas and throwing them into the body of physics is going
to lead to a ripple effect that drastic effects a lot of different physical theories such as momentum,
energy, so on and so forth.
Furthermore, what we're going to find is that much like when you throw a rock into a pond and that
creates the ripples that expand out from the source of that effect, the rock hitting the water, we're
going to find that when we introduced this idea into a body of physics, physical theories which are
closely tied to space-time kinematics, so on and so forth are going to be drastically affected.
It's going to be very impactful theoretical implications associated with them.
But once we start getting away from time and kinematics, the effects are going to be minimized.
And it's not going to be as impactful.
For example, we would expect that idea, such as momentum, kinetic energy, total energy, which are
dependent upon velocity to get these quantities in classical physics.
At least we'd expect them to have some weird effects pop out as a result of introducing these interesting
special relativity concepts.
However, ideas such as, you know, electrodynamics, which aren't as prominently influenced by kinematics,
so on and so forth, may not have as many effects.
They will have slight effects, but it won't be as drastic now.
In this video, we're going to start taking a look at those ripple effects.
We're going to see how introducing these ideas that we spend so much time coming up with in terms of
kinematics in spacetime, how special relativity effects that we're going to find that the ripple effect
drastically affects momentum in particular.
That's what we're going to focus on in this video now jumping into the idea of momentum.
Classically, we would expect that our notions, our classical notions are preserved, right?
Classically, we know that momentum, which is defined as M times V and as a factor, we would expect
that conservation of momentum to also be preserved.
OK, so we know that momentum is always conserved.
We'd expect this result preserved at high velocities, even after accepting the implications of special
relativity.
So we know right momentum is lost as mass times velocity.
And because our conservation of momentum implies that our initial momentum must be equivalent to a our
final momentum.
OK.
And then this can be reduced down to this guy right here.
So we would expect this to hold in special relativity because if it didn't, that would have huge implications,
right?
If momentum did not hold, then force Newton's second law.
You know, f is equal to the derivative of momentum of this back to time.
That would also break down, and they'll have huge implications, right?
We like Newtonian mechanics.
We like classical physics.
We want it to translate pretty well into special relativity.
So let's investigate this.
And in order to do that, what we're going to do is we're going to employ our best friends, right?
Terrance and Phillip, what they did is they had similar notions.
They thought that all these ideas would be drastically impacted by changing our basic notions of kinematics
in space time, and they want to investigate that.
What effect is this going to have upon momentum to do that?
What they're going to do is they're going to carry out.
A classical experiment that demonstrates momentum, but they're going to do it at high speeds, and
they're going to see how that high velocity.
Affects their notions, the classical notions of momentum, basically the conservation momentum, does
it hold up?
Does it fall apart or does it give rise to a new effect?
That's what we're going to investigate.
Let's do this.
They're going to take the classical experiment of a a ball or maybe some kind of any kind of object
coming in at the same velocities, hitting each other and having a perfectly elastic collision such
that they come out at the same velocity.
They're going to use this a bouncy ball, and Terence is going to hold that ball and spaceship that's
traveling close to the speed of light.
We're going to use zero point eight seven times the speed of light.
See, but you can use any kind of last thing you want.
And we're going to have Philip up on the ground watching him fly right by the both going to hold a bouncy
ball.
Now they timed it out such that at times equals zero and terrorists a little bit to the left of Philip.
They're both going to throw the ball in their respective reference frames straight down and straight
up.
Throws it down.
Philip throws it up and what's going to happen is they're going to hit at this point here at the same
speed.
Remember, they're going to bounce off in the perfectly elastic collision.
And then terrorists, it's going to catch it.
And Philip is going to catch hits.
This is a classical experiment.
We don't know what's going to happen at high speeds now to make this easy and straightforward.
Let's try and tabulate the different velocities of the balls at different times.
We're not two events, then no one when they the actually throw the ball and event number two when they
actually catch that ball.
Now, initially, when they both throw it, they're going to throw it either up or down with a velocity
of you.
Not.
So for even one over here, Philip Ball is going to throw it up with no exit velocity, but with a positive
y velocity of you not.
So that means that to fill up his philosophy in the X direction for event one is zero.
But his velocity in the Y direction for event one is you not.
And then in turns his ball in his reference frame.
What we're going to find is and I got to put a little.
Apostrophe right here to indicate that Terrance is the one measuring it's met, it's measured in reference
s prime.
What we find is that in the X direction, since he's throwing a straight down, it's going to look like
it goes straight down and it goes up.
Right?
There's going to be no x component.
So in the X, direction is lost near zero and in the Y direction, his ball has a velocity of negative.
You not go straight down with a speed of, you know, that's what they measure now from classical physics.
We know that in a perfectly elastic collision, right?
If the balls come up, let's say it's going to look something like this like that.
We're going to have a ball of mass m a ball mass m.
There's going to be you, not that's you, not then they're going to collide, they have to come back
with an equal but opposite.
Velocity.
Right.
That's what's implied by conservation of momentum, right?
That's what we get.
So what we know is that.
I can work it out.
This a very simple deduction, right?
So if we have that, they both have a massive and.
We have and you not.
That's Phillips Ball.
Minus and you not.
All right, so I'll call this guy, Phillip.
This guy, Terrence.
That must be equal to the final guy here, which would be Anton.
Some velocity plus and another velocity.
Basically, the final guy right here is going to be P.
This is T from this, we can deduce that.
This guy has to be negative, you not.
This guy has the positive you not.
And they reverse in sight.
Right?
This is straightforward ideas for physics, one to one.
So.
The Philippines has actually measure the velocity on the ball that they receive.
But we could deduce from classical physics and this is the beauty of conservation of momentum.
That the following is a true event to after a time Delta T Phillips ball, as measured by him, is going
to have a negative y component, you know, as we just discovered from the conservation of momentum,
but it did not change in the X direction, right?
So from from him, what we're going to say is that, oh, that guy zero four, the the X component of
the velocity and Terrence's ball, it's going to come straight up at that same velocity or same speed.
You're not.
So the y component of the velocity is positive, you not.
And the X component, as observed by parents, we need to put a little.
Posh, be there to signify that we are in the prime reference frame.
That's going to be zero.
Now we took these quantities.
It would appear as though conservation of momentum is guaranteed.
OK?
But.
We know that when you travel close to the speed of light, as we just discovered through Velocity Edition.
The each individual's conception of that losses and speed is going to be different in different reference
range, right?
Your experience of the phenomenon is contingent upon how you view it, your perspective, right?
This is what we've been discussing in the course that's the main tenet, the main idea.
So we would expect that if conservation of momentum.
Is true in in one reference frame.
It must be true in all initial reference frames, right?
That's just a restatement of the first of the special relativity.
So what we want to see is that using all of these ideas that we came up with from special relativity
lost the additional time dilation length contraction.
We want to see if this still holds right.
In every initial reference frame.
OK, so what we're going to do is we're going to do the same experiment.
But from Phillip's standpoint, in order to do that, what we need to do is we need to take these velocities
as measured by parents and translate them into the reference frame the rest frame in Phillips rest frame.
So let's do that now.
Fortunately, in our last video at the end of the class, the last section.
We found that we could quickly relate and put together this nice map in the last transformation to allow
Philip to talk intelligently about Terrence's velocities.
So let's do that right now.
OK?
What we're going to do is we're going to take those formulas exactly as they are and write them up.
So we're going to have to do it for the X direction and also the Y direction.
Let's focus first on the extraction.
What we're going to find is that.
The v x t Terrence's bond x direction for you, that one we're going to find is that we could get our
Velocity Edition formula and calculate it direct.
This is no different than the X prime, plus the relative.
Divide it by one.
Plus the relative.
Over C squared.
Times, V.X, Prof.
OK, so we could basically just plug and chug this guy.
We know that the prime this guy I'll put in the.
Exact notation, so we avoid confusion here, but we can throw this guy straight in here.
Bam.
That's zero bam zero one on the bottom, we get one plus zero.
Oh, this guy is nothing more than just derail the relative velocity.
This is what we find initially, and we could do the same thing.
For Event two, because we know this guy and we know that in inertial reference frame, the relative
remains concerned he zooms via the cause of last.
Well, we know that this guy is not changing, so we would get the same result, right?
This changes to a two of the team's two, a two.
We plug that guy straight in.
We end up with the same result.
So what we could do is we could just put the X to two that is equal to that guy and we get the result.
That's not surprising to somebody, stat. If you drop, if you're going at speed B and you drop a rock,
it's going to continue in the X direction.
Nothing is going to prevent it or stop it from traveling in the X direction.
This makes sense.
This drives well for our intuition.
We're on good track here, and that's why Philip is happy.
He's super happy.
Like all.
Yeah, baby, this is agreeing with my intuition, his degree of physics.
Let's continue.
We're going to find a conservation.
LATAM is concern to my preference for him.
I'm confident, you know, this is a classic idea.
It has to hold, has to hold no matter what.
OK, so what he does is, he says, OK, to continue this exercise, I need to figure out the Y component
so I can just pull out of my my bag of tricks.
Michael asked the addition formula, and I can calculate the wide Terrence's ball for state one event
one.
Well, I know from, you know, my my my hat tricks.
This guy is no more than v y t.
One, Prime.
Divided by our Lorentz factor times, one plus B rule, the relative over C squared.
Times.
The direction.
All right.
So what we can do.
Literally plug and chug, baby.
So we come down here, the next one, that's zero.
This guy cancels out.
That cancels, so we get one plus here, that's one we get a gallon bottom and we get nothing more than
a falling.
We could plug this guy in right down here, so that's a negative.
You not.
Over Gamma, and I'm going to write this guy in just so.
We can see the actual values this is negative.
You cannot divide it by the square root.
One minus v relative over C.
And it's quantity squared.
Basically, the Lorentz factor be OK, so that's what we end up with VI t two.
And we could do a similar calculation for event number two.
And we see the only difference is that you not.
The sign in front of you not changes, so you could deduce that, oh, we know this guy in here right
there, you know, we're going to get him on the bottom and we end up with the whitey.
Two is nothing more than positive.
You not.
Over the square root.
Of one minus the relative or C quantity squared is the same result, but it's opposite that.
That's what we discovered from using our classical idea is that the velocity is the same magnitude,
but has an opposite direction.
OK, so that's not very surprising.
But now we have all the ingredients to take this guy here.
Our conservation rule, and that's a formula for all these guys in and see what really happens.
But before we do that, what I want to do is record these ideas so you have them right in front of you.
What I'm going to say is that I put it down here the X.
He won.
Is equal to the relative.
So we get that guy there.
And to put the wine.
T one.
We're gonna bring that guy over there.
We're going to write it in here.
We get negative view, not.
Over square root one minus B or C.
On squared.
Little difficult to see that, and I'm just going to highlight this.
Sort of running out of board space here, I apologize.
So we end up with that result.
And we also want to record the same exact result right over here.
So we end up with the X T.
That's also a relative, and the Y Terrence's ball or state two is a positive.
You know what, the square root of one minus the relative or C squared?
All right.
So we end up with these guys.
Very important results.
And what we want to do is now plug them in the conservation of momentum formula.