Now what we've just discovered, namely that the conservation of momentum does not hold up at high velocities.
It's quite disturbing because if that is true and if conservation of momentum is not actually a conservation
law that has huge, huge implications upon Newtonian mechanics and energy and everything we really take
for granted in physics that we learn if it's one right.
We don't want that to happen.
The implications are too huge.
So rather than taking momentum and discarding in the trash can, what we're going to do is we're going
to bring that back, examined a bit further and try to modify it a bit to make it work with special
relativity and our original conceptions of conservation of momentum.
OK.
This should not be a very surprising idea to take right because we've done this many times already in
this course, and I study a special relativity right when we found that our notions of time and space
didn't really hold up at high velocities, what we did is we preserve what they were but modified them.
They massage them a bit to work with.
The additional theory is a high velocities.
So if we do the same thing here to try and save momentum, we're not really stepping outside of the
bounds of what we normally do.
We've done this already.
We're familiar with it.
Let's apply it to momentum, OK?
And in order to help us do this, what we're going to do is take everything we've learned with special
relativity so far, which I have summarized here and I'm going to walk through.
We're going to use this as a guide as to how we're going to modify momentum and make it work with conservation
and then momentum once again, just because that's a super, super important theoretical idea.
OK, we don't want to throw it away.
We don't want to discard.
So what we learn is special relativity so far compared to classical physics is the form.
If we have a velocity and we travel close to the speed of light, as we see here in this graph, which
plots up the relative velocity with respect to the time span accelerating, we know that classically,
if you accelerate something we know V is equal to a Delta T, right?
That's the linear equation.
We get a straight line.
But what special relativity does is implement the second postulate special relativity, which states
that what is it you should be telling me now?
I've mentioned it so many times before.
It states that you cannot travel faster than the speed of light, and it tries to enforce that parameter.
And as a result of enforcing this, we get all these weird effects.
So we see that we have this cap on velocity where the relativistic result.
It gets capped out ambient Eq. one or velocity equal to C.
And this weird effect gives rise or this idea because rised weird effects, namely length, contraction
and time.
What are we find with these guys if we plot up our time in a rest frame, roll up to a proper time in
a moving frame?
We know that that plotted against the relative velocity.
Classically, we would say that over time it just is.
It's an absolute quantity, but we know that time is relative.
It's contingent upon our reference frame that is actually viewing it so real.
Basically, we find that as we travel to high velocities, this effect of capping the velocity modifies
our conception of space time and the time the rest frame shoots up.
This ratio here shoots up to make sure that we do not exceed all the last you've ever seen.
OK.
It doesn't matter how, how, how much you force that obstacle, faster time is going to differentiate
between these two reference frames.
It's just a relativistic effect that's time dilation.
Similarly, if we took a meter stick and measured the length contraction, the length of it classically
would say a meter stick is a meter stick.
That's one meter, no matter what.
You can look at it however you want.
That's not going to change its length.
But because of this, we're cap on velocity.
What we found is that as you travel close to the speed of light, the length tends to shrink it contracts.
It contracts that moving meter stick contracts to somebody at rest.
So eventually it looks like it has no length, which is a weird idea.
But that's where relativity tells us right.
We're trying to force this cap, so we find two important things.
These effects give rise due to enforcing the second part of the special relativity escape velocity,
and also they tend to occur at a high velocity.
So using these two ideas, these two principles.
What we find is that we could take momentum and we could preserve what we originally defined as us as
envy.
But I mean, we can multiply it by some factor that's dependent upon the velocity that kicks in the
play and high velocity.
So we get relativistic effects modifying our momentum.
But at low velocities, it gets kicked out of the scene and we converge upon the classical result,
namely that P is equal to envy.
Sorry about that.
So what we're going to do?
We're going to come up with a new candidate momentum as such, and we're going to try to use this idea.
To really push forward a modified version of momentum that saves the day and retains conservation,
the momentum that conservation law is super, super important.
We don't want to discard that out of whack.
So what are we going to do?
What we're going to do is we're going to say, OK, let's take a look at time, relation a bit more
and see what we can get out of it.
What we found is that in time dilation reference frames that are not going as fast as the moving body,
they're going to see that time dilates, but they agree on one thing what is that namely the proper
time, right?
What do we find time dilation as described by TENIAN in any reference frames equal to gamma times the
proper time, the time measured by the moving body?
OK.
And what everybody agrees on, they agree that in that reference frame, you're going to have a proper
time to not.
It doesn't matter how the time is experienced in your reference frame or any other reference frame.
Everybody would agree that in the proper time, it's going to be defined as not.
So maybe if we're trying to get this universal conception of moment on using this new candidate, we
can focus on calculating the momentum with respect to the moving body.
That way, everybody would agree upon that quantity.
And maybe it would be conserved any time after which we measure it.
Right?
So that's the name of the game.
What we're going to do is going to redefine momentum as such, and we're going to focus on the proper
time round three, the moving reference frame and try to get this form that pop out.
Now if we do that, the way in which we are defining momentum is as follows.
So the momentum p, which again is still a vector, is defined as end times velocity, which is R the
T not.
This is this new definition because we're going to focus on the moving reference frame this teenage
guy right here.
OK.
So when we do that, we know that, you know, r the position vector is determined by four variables
we have X, Y and Z, and it's also a function of time because as can be a function of time, Y can
be a function.
Time Z can be a function of time.
But we also know that from time dilation this time T, which are dependent upon is defined as gamma
times, not the proper time.
So if the quantity are that we're trying to differentiate in terms of does not have a not in it.
If you know this guy is really this should really be like sub T y city.
The city.
Right.
That brought a little odd.
What we know is that we have to differentiate first in terms of tea.
And then we take the turn of tea.
You expect the tea not.
And we get the exact value that we're trying to calculate this guy right here.
So another way of writing this, which it's very sloppy, but what this really should be looking like
is x tea.
Not if we want that the chain effect to really shine right here in the mathematics.
So what we find is that in order to make this calculation that everybody would agree upon and the moving
reference frame, we'd have to do the following we take the derivative ah, with respect to basically
first, this tea party in that particular reference frame, which you know, everybody would disagree
about what TRT the velocity they observe, right?
Because that's that's the name of the game is special relativity or relativity in general.
So we would get this guy.
Well, if you differentiate, respect the tea, that's a function of tin, also of tea, not changes.
Tea is going to change, so you need to account for that fact, right?
She wrote Capital One B.
So you have to multiply by the tea.
Not this extra term that pops up.
And the way which I like to think about this bothers you is we're taking this guy, but you could sort
of like to cancel those guys out and you retain that DADT.
Not a sort of what's happening here.
That's the way I like to think about it in my mind.
That's how I did cop one, Juan.
You can use that if you want to do a little trick.
So as a result of doing this, well, we could do we could say, Oh, it's not, oh, we can take this
guy here before I see this guy with respect to the proper time.
Oh, look at that.
A gamma pops out that gamma pops out.
So when this happens, what we get is the following candidate for relativistic momentum.
And we see if we compare this back to here what we postulated based upon these effects here and this
is the name of the game.
This is what's really driving a change in relativistic momentum.
What we find is that this guy is no different than the gamma factor gamma sub V, where a catastrophe
is defined as one over the square root one minus the magnitude v overseas squared.
Now it's important to note that this guy here is the velocity of the object.
If the object moving, not necessarily your reference rate, right, because you can have a reference
frame that's moving at a different velocity.
Well, what we did here is we got the velocity of the moving object.
That's a big change compared to other ideas.
So in the future, I may put a gamma so b to signify this fact, but keep it in the back of your mind
when you do relativistic momentum calculations.
You have to use a gamma that is defined in terms of a policy of the object that is moving.
So we have a candidate idea right here.
Candidate trial for relativistic momentum.
If this was true, then if we can serve this quantity in both Phillips reference frame and terrorists
reference frame, as we discovered in the experiment they're putting together, this should be conserved.
Basically, we want to take this guy thrown into that equation that we we drive for momentum, conservation
of momentum, and we want to show that conservation momentum holds for this guy.
If this really is the correct form, it should halt.
OK, so what we're going to do is we're going to do that.
We're going to run through that to give you some experience working with this weird quantity here.
And then if it is true, if that is the true candidate, we will take a step back and be like, Whoa,
whoa, this is a weird -- equation.
What am I going to do?
What am I?
How do I interpret this?
What does this actually mean?
Because there are a lot of different interpretations of this, and I'm going to walk you guys through
that.
But first, let's try and run through that experiment with this new candidate momentum.