All right, so we finally confirmed that there is indeed a ripple effect that's going on with momentum
that changes our conception of momentum at high velocities.
Now what we want to do is we want to take a look at that ripple and identify the implications, understand
what in the world is going on here.
Because when you look at this are real relativistic momentum.
You look at this here like, Whoa, what in the world is going on?
We have this gamma, which is a function of the velocity times, our original conception of momentum.
OK, what's cool is that we know that this guy Lorentz factor was the upon the relative velocity.
If it moves out of lusty, that's much less than the speed of light, see?
And this simplifies down to our classical result, which is good.
It converges upon what we see in reality.
Well, what in the world is this imply at high velocities?
Now this is a contentious topic that a lot of physicists actually argue about do not agree fully upon
in this day and age.
And in fact, Einstein.
When he discovered this, he made an error himself in taking a look at this.
At first, he described something that is known as a variable mass, which sounds weird.
I know I'll get to that shortly.
But eventually he came around saying that he greatly regrets introducing that concept and backtracked
behind back to his original idea that we want to use what is known as a rest mass.
What?
When, where am I talking about here?
I'll get to that in a second.
Let's look at the charts here because what I like to say is that this should be driven by the observations
you have in front of you, the information, the data, and that should drive the concepts that are,
I guess, extract it out of your observations.
If you diverge from that paradigm, you run into problems because you try to force ideas to crop up
outside of the universe outside of your experience.
And that leads the problem.
So let's focus on the physics.
Let's focus on the regular implications that they actually have.
What I have drawn up here to match what we looked at previously for time dilation, length, contraction
and what we see with the cap on velocity as I've plotted up this relativistic velocity relativistic
momentum.
Sorry for that.
So this guy is plotted in terms of our relativistic velocity, and we see that classically, you know,
this is a linear function momentum.
This is a linear function.
What is happening is at high velocities, we see the momentum spikes up, and that's because we can
never get this guy.
That's an effect on the cap of velocity.
But if this guy spikes up what is causing that spike, right, we know that here we see that the velocity
isn't increasing much.
Right, it's harder to increase that velocity.
Well, what exactly is going on?
So physicists postulate that there was actually a variable mass that as you travel faster, your mass
gets larger, which is implied by here.
They could redefined this gamma and not the mass.
We would conceive an object as if it was at rest and was studying on a scale.
They redefined that as a new variable called the variable mass, and that allows us to sort of reflect
the original form we have.
We would have basically an end the M.V., the variable mass times, the V, and that looks just like
our regular momentum equation, but that has some problems with it.
But let's let's let's take a look at that.
So what it's saying is that instead of actually increasing velocity when you try to push an object closer
to the speed of light, what it's asserting is that relativistic effects come into play and build up
that that mass.
So it looks massive and looks heavier, and that extra exertion is being dumped into the object's mass,
which makes the momentum sky rocket.
Now, that's problematic for many reasons.
The first of which is if you redefine your mass, which is a basic constituent used in a lot of physics
equations, what if you take the variable mass and you throw that into the equation for gravity?
What's going to happen then you're a gravitational force is going to change a lot of students get confused,
they start throwing around this idea in different equations where it does not belong and they run into
problems.
So what actually, I like to conceive of and a lot of physicist at higher levels like to use, they'd
like to avoid this variable math problem.
And what we say is that our conception of math is a little misguided.
We must understand what we mean by math.
So math has multiple properties.
We use math really to convey gravity, basically somebodies weight.
The more massive you are, the fatter you are, the heavier you are.
Your gravitational force is larger, in essence.
But at the same time, we use math to describe inertia, the resistance to change in motion, right?
So we have, let's say, a tractor trailer that's going really fast.
It's very massive.
It has a lot of mass in it.
It's going to take a larger force to stop that than a little toy car, maybe about one 1000, the mass
of that guy.
And that's because mass has inertia, right?
If something is moving really fast, a lot of mass, it wants to continue to move really fast with a
lot of mass.
Conversely, if something doesn't have a lot of mass, it's easy to stop it when it's moving right.
This is our notion of inertia, and it sort of comes into play with our conception of gravity associated
with mass.
OK.
But what I'm going to say is that the physics here says that if you're trying to speed up, you're trying
to speed up close to the speed of light.
Further, that extra effort has resistance.
There's resistance, there's an additional inertia.
So you want to think about this as as you start pushing that object further, you're building up that
inertial inertial resistance to speeding up further.
So when you build up that inertia, this is what skyrockets the momentum.
And Lisa, this guy here.
But the interesting thing is that when you apply your relativistic momentum.
Related to your classical result, we find that they match up and let me backtrack bit when you plot
momentum with respect to the time spent accelerating.
We see the full picture here.
This tells the full story.
We know that.
The velocity isn't going to increase much as you push it further close to the speed of light, but the
momentum.
It stays consistent with our classical result because the object appears to get heavier, it gets more
inertia, more resistance to speeding up.
So you can continue to try to accelerate, try to force that guy.
And that resistance is good and that is the relativistic effect.
That is the key.
That is the idea which allows us to express the second of special relativity again.
Same idea time relation length contraction.
We get weird effects that try to enforce this cap on velocity, and that's cropping up again in momentum.
So what we like to say is that physicists at higher levels generally ignore this variable mask idea.
It's sort of it leads to the correct conception, but it can lead to a lot of theoretical and mathematical
fallacies.
We're going to avoid that in this class.
We're going to say that you know what, an object has a rest mass and not that is measured at measured
at rest.
So you take that object.
May you stop moving.
Put it on a scale.
That's mass.
That's the mass it's going to retain in history, as well as our intuition.
Because if an object moves really fast, that doesn't change its its weight, it doesn't affect its
gravity, right?
We want that to be consistent.
What is happening when it moves fast is inertia builds up, so it's harder to move that guy further
along.
Right?
That's spelled out right here in LA Plot's.
If we want to get closer to the speed of light, it's going to be harder to push.
It's going to be harder to get more velocity.
And that's because we're getting more inertia that building that guy up.
As a result, it allows the relativistic effect to be equivalent to the classical definition of momentum.
And there you have it, that is relativistic momentum.
It's a weird idea.
It's an idea that's usually very confused in a lot of textbooks.
You're going to see this variable mass mentioned.
Some books, especially introductory books, are going to get started as a fact.
But what you want to think about is your conception of mass.
How can we sort of like a gravitational idea and an inertial idea and you want to think about as you
go?
Of course, the speed of light resistance builds up.
To trying to resist that extra velocity to enforce this cap on velocity so you don't get faster than
the speed of light.
And as a result, the momentum blows up.
You get this guy here that's identical to the classical result.
And what is important about this is it implies that if this is true, what we can do is and what we'll
do in the next few videos is we can say, Oh, well, that was just DDT, right?
We could save that guy.
Our classic definition knew and second law and we can charge ahead, use the same idea as me, modify
them a bit.
But we know that they still hold.
We know that conservation will make them holds.
We are seeing the conservation of energy holds could be a little weird, but we're going to see that
this idea here is sort of reminiscent of an idea that mass is are similar to an equivalent to energy.
Weird idea.
That's going to sound very weird.
We're going to derivable that in the next few videos.
Stay tuned.
I hope you enjoyed that.
I hope you got the proper definition of an item out of that.
And I hope you really understood what I was trying to convey here, because this is a very this is a
very precise point, a nuanced point.
And it's important for you to understand that really there's a resistance to speeding up and that changes
our conception of momentum.
But in essence, when we modify it a bit, our conservation laws still apply.
OK.
Stay tuned.