All right.
So we start off with some basic things, some things that you might already know even before kind of
studying anything to do with electrostatic.
The first statement I have here is that like charges, they repel each other.
So let's consider the two cases of like charges.
Right?
We have positive and a positive charge.
Another case we would have would be a negative charge separated by a certain distance from another negative
charge.
All right.
So these are the like charges.
And, well, one thing we can do is write down the force acting between the like charges.
So if a positive is next to a positive, there would be a force acting like this, acting on the left
charge.
And we're going to have a force acting to the right on this or on the left and the right.
How about two negatives right next to each other?
Again, they would feel a repulsive force between both of them.
And I'm going to label that force just with the same letter F.
All right.
So a couple of things.
These forces are opposite.
They're equal magnitude.
Right.
And they're acting on the different charges.
Let's consider the last statement over here says Opposite charges attract to each other.
Now, I can plot it any way I want, but let's just do it this way.
We have the positive separated from a negative by a certain distance.
Again, now they attract each other.
So that means the force that you would add would be like this one forces acting on the positive charge,
the other force would be acting on the negative charge, and that's it.
Now these forces form action reaction pairs, right?
This is really Newton's third law at work here.
So let me just write down that down.
Newton's third law and third law says for every action there is an equal and opposite reaction.
And you need three things for Newton's third law, right?
We need the same force.
That's what we have.
We need opposite direction.
I'll just write opposite.
And number three.
What we do need are different objects.
Right.
In this case, what are the objects?
We have different charges.
Okay, that is what's going on.
So these action reaction pairs, this force here obeys Newton's third law.
All right, so just get us started over here.