OK so our universe is made up of atoms.
OK.
So let's have a look at.
So all atoms are made up of kind of three different kind of parts.
We have positive charges and the positive charges are usually in the nucleus.
That's kind of the center of the atoms.
OK.
And they're surrounded by these tiny little electrons and you can think of it as a cloud of electrons
If you want to consider as a point particle kind of circulating in some orbit that's also OK for now
but it's more of a cloud.
There's a kind of a probability distribution that electrons are somewhere in space.
OK.
So we have electrons protons and we also have neutrons.
So one thing that we're going to see a lot here is that the charge OK the charge of these tiny little
guys Well for now we're just going to say that the protons are going to be positive.
We'll see a little bit later what they're charged charges it's actually written down here.
But in the charge of electrons are negative.
OK.
And neutrons have zero charge OK.
So these are the basic constituents of atoms.
Actually if you have a look at the size of atoms if this kind of black line here represents a 1 Angstrom.
OK.
If you remember what an angstrom is is ten to the negative 10 meters.
That is one Angstrom it's a way way smaller right the center of a helium atom is kind of this little
pink and purple dot down over here.
And this is actually to the size you're going to right a size down.
It would be at the Fermi meter.
OK Fermi meter effect is actually a fem dough meter I'm sorry a phantom meter is ten to the negative
15 meters.
OK.
So they are really really small.
So you could see kind of zooming in here that the nucleus.
This is an example of a helium atom.
So we actually would have two protons This is more of the pink center over here and the black kind of
cloud around it.
These would represent it's two electrons so they are very very far away from the center right relative
to the size of the nucleus right.
They could actually be very very far away.