So we've seen we have two kinds of charges.
We now want to talk about how big that charges.
OK.
So now we're going to talk about the magnitude of the charge and let's focus on the proton and on the
electron.
So again we've discussed that the difference between the two is that one of them is positive.
And the other one here we say is negatively charged.
All right.
This brings us to something called the elementary charge of the elementary charge the symbol for the
elementary charges the little letter E..
OK.
And its value is one point six multiplied by ten to the negative 19.
Let me clear that up here tend to the negative 19 columns.
OK.
The symbol here this refers to cool homes and this is the S.I. unit for charge a unit for charge.
All right.
So this is super important.
So that means if I have a one proton if I draw one proton over here it would have a charge of I can
write it as positive E that would be the charge of the proton positive one point six times ten to the
negative 19 columns.
If I have one electron draw an electron down over here.
All right I put a little negative sign.
I would write its charge as being well I would go over here and I would write as negative E OK.
And that would be negative one point six times ten to the negative 19 columns.
If I go back and look at my helium for example my helium atom and let's just look at the helium nucleus.
So forget about the electrons only the protons.
So what you would have would be two positive charges that are close to each other.
And if I just kind of just circle around here.
OK.
I would say that the total charge for this helium atom would be well.
So total charge
is simply going to be two multiplied by each.
So it would be three point two loops.
That's three point two and I wrote three point six three point two times 10 to the negative 19.
Cool.
OK.
If you take any object it doesn't matter what it is.
If I take any object and imagine it's positively charged.
So it has a whole bunch of protons and no electrons so I've stripped away all the electrons that I know
how many we have here.
But the total charge of any object I can write it as q q is usually the letter we use for charge.
And if I write it as Q total.
The important thing is that it's always going to be some number N multiplied by the elementary charge.
Again this is really really important because charge we say is quantized it comes in these packets over
here that are all one point six times ten of the negative 19 and over here should be just a number.
Okay.
Example it could be 15 it could be ten thousand.
Okay it could be whatever two million times tend to the six.
It's simply a number which refers to the number of charges that we have got.
So in this case if you're going to count them all we'd have one two three four five six seven eight
nine ten eleven twelve thirteen.
So in this case little Ed would be 13 and the total charge would simply be 13 multiplied by one point
six times ten to the negative 19 columns.
So at the end the total charge.
Let me use my calculator here.
So 13 times one point six.
Now this gives me 20.
And again point eight times 10 to the negative 19 columns.
That would be the total charge for this object here in green.
All right.
So a couple of important concepts elementary charge and the total charge is always some number multiplied
by that elementary charge.