So let's talk about cool homes now cool Ohm's law now.
Well we're going to first assume is that we have two small charges usually these are referred to as
kind of point charges and they are separated by a certain distance.
Are so are as measured from center to center.
We already know the direction.
OK.
So we don't have to worry about the direction of the force because we just look at it.
If there are two positive charges the force is repelling.
If they're two negatives that also repels so direction of force is known or now interested in is what
is the magnitude.
So how big is the force how big is f.
OK and that's given by cool law cool homes law you can write as something like this.
The force is equal to there is a constant in the front which is one over for pi.
There's this other value here which I'll get to in just a second.
And the important stuff is right here.
Q1 the magnitude Q2 the magnitude I put absolute values in there and divided bytes depends on how far
they are.
But it's the distance squared.
So let's look at this equation in just a little bit more detail.
So first of all this guy right here Epsilon 0.
This is a constant.
And it's referred to as the permitting city of free space.
So all you have to do is open your book and just find its value.
OK.
So people have kind of measured that and in a value is eight point eight five times 10 to the negative
twelve.
The units for this again at the end of the day I need to have Newton's on the left hand side of cool
Ohm's Law in an order for all that to work out.
You're going to need cool loam squared.
Per Newton in meters square it's something like this.
These are going to be the units that I'm going to need if at the end of the day this guy is measured
in Newton's because I'll have to cancel cool ohms twice and I'll have to cancel meters squared also.
This is referred to as a inverse square law.
You might have seen the force of gravity.
Right.
Newton's Law of Gravitation is also an inverse square law which means that its inverse.
So the distance between the charges square it appears in the denominator here.
That's why the inverse squared law.
All right.
Now to simplify things a little bit rather than kind of writing it like this a lot of people just kind
of simplify they'll represent everything here in the bracket.
And again since that's all one constant term you can evaluate that sometimes you rewrite Coombs law
the same law will write it like this or write it as F is some other constant k.
And again everything else is the same Q1 Q2 and again over our squared.
In this case you could see that this value K is nothing more than one over for Pi Epsilon 0.
If you actually take your calculator and evaluate this you should get approximately nine point nine
so a nine point zero times ten to the nine.
Okay.
Now the units are going to be different.
Here here we're gonna have units of Newton's meters squared per Coolum Square they're actually the inverse
of the units of the permitting of free space.
Okay.
So depending on the textbook that you use I kind of like this form is just kind of easier to calculate.
Again it's just a constant term and these are the two things are that are important as to charges here
in the numerator and distance squared in the denominator.
Okay.
So this tells you how big the charges how big the forces sorry how big the forces between both of these
charges.