OK so here's problem two again we're going to look at the net force acting on charged Q3.
Except now it's kind of like a two dimensional problem.
So let's first start again by labeling all the forces acting on Q3.
So there's an interaction between Q1 and Q3 since Q1 is positive and Q3 is negative.
There is an attractive force on Q3 and that force should be in this direction over here.
We're gonna call this force F 1 again all right.
That's the direction what else.
We also have an interaction between Q2 and Q3.
If I'm looking at all the forces acting on Q3 that means I need to add another vector I need to add
this vector over here.
We're gonna call this f 2 again.
Again these may not be the same we're going to evaluate how big those vectors are.
But for now let's just label them like this.
So the first thing we're going to do is want to apply cool Ohm's Law.
Let's calculate how big is EF 1 what's the magnitude of this vector.
OK.
So in order to do this.
So let's write down our equation so we have EF 1.
Again it's the constant K that's the same Q1 Q3 and divided by again it's the distance squared.
What's the distance in this case.
If I go back to the figure it's going to be the distance between this guy and this guy.
This is the distance D1 in this case it's different.
All right.
It's not the same as what we previously had.
So this is D 1 squared.
So actually what you need to do now is you need to do a little bit of math in order to find what is
D 1.
Well this we can use just Pythagorean Theorem right.
We know that one side is zero point for the other is zero point two.
So that means that d 1 simply going to be root of zero point four squared plus zero point two squared.
All right.
Put those numbers in the calculator.
Now you should get it's approximately zero point four five meters.
All right.
Now you can go ahead and substitute everything define how big this forces.
So we get nine times tend to the nine.
Q1 was five times tend to the negative six.
What else.
Q3 is still negative to micro cool homes I'm not going to put the negative sign again that only tells
me the direction of the force and at the end now I need to divide by zero point four or five and square
that value.
Okay.
You substitute in all the numbers here.
What you should find now is a force that's approximately equal to zero point four four Newtons.
And this is the direction here it's kind of at an angle.
All right.
Our other goal is to find what is EF 2 Well EF 2 should be pretty much identical to the previous case
that we found.
Right.
Because we haven't changed anything so let's just write it down just for completeness we get K we get
Q2 we get Q3 and our distance.
Now this is our distance d to the distance between both of those charges.
So we should get zero point.
Well let's just call it D2 over here D2 and we have to square that value.
All right you could tell that the value of the magnitude of this force is going to be the exact same
which we had one point three five Newtons.
All right.
Let me go ahead and write this in the top figure.
So we have both of our forces our goal now is really to find what is the net force.
So what you have to do now is you have to add these up as vector quantities so we're going to do in
order to do that.
We're gonna do a little bit of math.
So we're gonna have to break the force F one down into two components
let's start off by making a little bit of extra space we already have all our magnitudes Syriza and
get rid of this information.
What else I already have my magnitude on my vector diagram over there.
OK.
Now let's go back to this figure.
Now what I'm gonna do now is I'm simply going to move this to give me a little bit of extra space but
this is a f one I'll just move it over here.
All right.
Now let's look at our diagram.
This is what I'm going to do here.
I have a line which is the x axis here.
I'm gonna go ahead and I'm going to kind of draw a parallel line to that one.
Now on the inside over here if I call this angle here theta what I want to do is I should notice that
this here should also be the same angle theta.
And my goal now is simply to break the force down into components.
So f 1 is a vector along this angle.
What I'm going to do is I'm going to break it down into two components.
This here is going to be the x component of f 1 and the y component of f 1 is going to be pointing down
like this.
So this is gonna be the y component of that force.
Now if you do a little bit of trigonometry you should realize that f 1 x should be equal to the magnitude
of f 1 multiplied by coast of that angle and f 1 y should be equal to EF 1 sign of the angle theta.
So it would be nice if we know what that angle theta is but we can actually determine the angle theta
by looking at our first diagram right the angle theta.
You could find right here and I can use any of the trigonometric functions in order to find this.
I'm going to use tangent.
OK.
If you write down tangent of theta you should say that's opposite over adjacent right.
Zero point two over zero point four which is just equal to one half.
So at the end if you take the inverse function ten negative 1 of 1 1/2 you should get an angle equal
to approximately twenty six point six degrees.
All right now I'm in good shape and go back and actually find what the magnitude of both of those forces
are.
So for this guy here I substitute zero point four four for F one and then I do coasts of twenty six
point six for the next one at zero point four four multiply by sign of twenty six point six.
All right.
So we have two magnitudes.
Now we're gonna have f one x and f one y.
We know the direction by looking at our diagram F1 X and I substituted things I got approximately zero
point three nine Newtons and F1 Y was approximately zero point two Newtons.
Okay so I got to use these two values now and in order to find the net force you have to find the net
force in each direction.
So let's go ahead and do that now find the net force all you have to do now is find the net force or
the component of each one.
OK.
So let's go ahead and write down our equations for the net force in each direction.
Again this simply means I add up all of the forces and I only add up their x components in this case
there's only one and what I'm gonna do to add them up I'm going to choose just a standard x y coordinate
system so everything pointing to the right is positive everything pointing up will also be positive.
There's only one force in the x direction here it's this one component.
And I'm going to set it as negative because it's pointing to the left.
So zero point three nine again positives or negatives are only telling you something about the direction.
All right.
So we have that one how about the forces in the vertical direction.
We have to add up all the forces in the vertical direction there's two.
All right I have F two and that one's pointing up.
I'm going to call that positive and there's only one component acting down it's only this component
of f one which we calculated here is zero point two.
So notice these have two different signs because they're in different directions.
So at the end the net force in the vertical direction is simply going to be one point one five.
All right.
Perfect.
Now the last step now is we have it in components so we may want to calculate how big is the net force
and what does it look like on a diagram.
So we have a component of this net force let's just make it black over here.
We have a component of the net force which is in the x direction.
And we also have a component which is in the vertical direction.
So at the end if you add up both of those I should have a vector that kind of looks like this.
This is really the net force direction first thing I could do is I can calculate what is the magnitude
of this net force since you know everything about the vector you know both of its components you simply
use Pythagorean Theorem in order to solve this three nine squared plus one point one five squared again
I don't have the negative sign because at the end I just end up squaring it.
Whether you write it in there or not it doesn't bother me one point two Newtons is the magnitude of
this net force.
Now the other thing you may want to do also is say define what is the angle and I say define this angle
here Alpha something like this again if you know both components you know the x component of that force
F net x and f net why we should be able to use our trigonometry in order to write down an expression
for what is this angle alpha.
Let me go ahead and do that over here.
Let's make some space so what I'm going to use is tangent again kind of like the used tangent.
So you should be able to write that tangent of this angle alpha tangent is going to be the opposite
over the adjacent.
So it's f net
y over f net X a substitute in our numbers and at the end you want to take the inverse.
So Alpha is tan of negative 1 F net Y was one point one five and F net was f net X. We had zero point
three nine the magnitude.
Okay.
You should get an angle alpha that's approximately equal to seventy one point two degrees.
Okay go ahead and draw that one here in this figure seventy one point two degrees.
Now depending on how you define it you could have defined this angle at the end that doesn't really
matter as long as you have a vector where you have a magnitude and you have some direction or you could
also just write it down in two components.
We have an X and a y component.
We've defined the total force acting on a charge q three.