So back in the day, the early 1980s, we were doing kind of calculations and measurements like this,
and a lot of astronomers were looking at the light that comes back from different case hours, galaxies
and nebulae.
One particular astronomer, VMC lifer at the local observatory in 1912, what he did is he measured
these Doppler shifts and he made a very stark conclusion.
He concluded that surrounding nebula and a nebula is that could be a galaxy of basically any kind of
dust arrangement that is being held together by gravity.
But he concluded, the surrounding nebula to our Milky Way galaxy are receding away from us at high
velocities.
OK, so that was a very important note that was thought to suggest that perhaps the universe is woohp
expanding, continually expanding, which would support what it would support the Big Bang Theory and
sort of disprove another notion that was around during the day that perhaps the universe is the steady
stays stagnant kind of entity, which we know to be false to this day.
So that was his contribution.
That's why this was superimposed the redshift classically and from a historical context, because this
individual cipher, you know, we were making these measurements and we could deduce that the universe
is expanding.
But he didn't have really the full picture.
So Edwin Hubble, after he saw some some of these conclusions coming from Cypher, he worked quite diligently
for about 20 or so years with another individual.
And by 1935, what he was doing is he was compiling the velocities and distances of hundreds of galaxies,
a form of a nebula to deduce that the universe is.
It's expanding, it's expanding what's really supported.
The notion of the Big Bang Theory is what he did is he made these nice, precise measurements, which
are very difficult to make, and he took that information.
He measured the distance, the approximate distance that these galaxies were located from us, and he
plotted up their recessional velocity calculated using this guy right here.
It's pretty easy to calculate here because you measure these, this, this redshift and multiply by
C. You can get the relative velocity pretty easily.
This one is a bit more complicated.
Again, we're increasing the complexity so you get more accuracy.
But he plotted all these guys and we feel that we can regretfully fit a lie to this, right?
We just need a straight line.
And what he came up with next using all this information was a quite an amazing conclusion.
You can have what is known as Hubble's law that the universe is expanding and at different distances.
The last year, which it expands, is different and I've lost.
He was described using this chart as false.
He said the velocity of expansion of the universe at any distance are away from the Earth is described
linearly using this constant h.
And as it became known as the Hubble parameter, it's important to note that it is not static, it's
always changing.
And that's because at different areas in the universe, in an isotropic.
Spacetime kind of kind of picture.
We know that the universe is expanding and expanding and expanding at different rates.
And the way you want to think about the universe is twofold.
You can think about the universe in different galaxies located on the spacetime as there are two analogies
one you can think of it as.
A balloon that's expanding and you have little dots on the outside of the balloon.
And we know that even though the Earth is not at the center of the blue, it does not have to be at
the center of the universe.
This is not conclude that we're at the center of the universe, that the dots as you blow up the balloon,
they're going to move away from each other on the surface of that balloon of that curvature.
So we're going to get some recessional and some there might be some dots actually move close to us.
And these lifer and Hubble actually did observe that maybe one or two galaxies were being blue shifted,
if you will.
But in general, the universe is expanding at a different rate, at different areas along along that
balloon, so that supports this sort of idea here.
Another way to look at it is sort of like raisins in bread.
So when you put raisins and bread and you bake it and the bread starts to expand, the raisins gradually
move away from each other.
But they've lost the air, which they're expanding is contingent upon the radial distance from the center,
for example, or from each other.
So the further away you get your velocity, your obsessional velocity tends to increase linearly.
OK.
And.
This each term is going to change based upon heredity, the universe's characteristics are going to
change and evolve over time.
So this snapshot that Hubble generated back in what?
Oh, 1935, it's going to be different.
It's going to be different, slightly different than the snapshot we would generate now because the
universe is expanding at a different rate.
Right.
Time has evolved how the universe behaves.
So what we also have is we can take this sort of beyond the scope of this course.
I'll go over it briefly.
And what I want you to understand after I talk about this conceptually is the cosmological redshift,
which I'll get to that.
But.
An individual named Friedman, he solved the Friedman equation, which should have been a solution to
Einstein's field equations and general relativity, which helped to give a sense of the form of spacetime
or different metrics that are being observed in our universe.
And in doing so, we were able to see that this parameter is going to change.
It's going to evolve with time based upon a skill factor of that metric space.
One over a is the scale factor.
But the Hubble parameter changes as one of her a times DADT.
OK, so the details about this are very complex, very convoluted.
It's a bit beyond the scope of this course.
If you want to look up the freedman equation, and I think it's far RTW metrics based on Google Wikipedia.
If you feel like you have enough mathematical background for that.
But what I want you to understand is that the universe is expanding and at the velocity at which it
expands.
Is different words, a function of the radial distance you are?
From other objects, OK.
So.
As you can see, the relativistic Doppler shift can be used a lot in cosmology can be used a lot in
astrophysics.
And it really helped us deduce from this redshift that the universe is indeed expanding.
And when we combine that with other information such as there's sort of like a background radiation
that we always observe, which is sort of from the beginning of the the birth of the universe.
All this really supported the Big Bang Theory because the Big Bang Theory states that we had this most
condense or rather dense ball of matter that exploded and we are continually expanding as a result of
that.
This supports that theory, supports that theory.
OK, so the last thing I want to talk about in this particular video is the notion of the cosmological
redshift.
Now what we talked about here is literally a change in wavelength of frequency, which is really driven
by the recessional or approach velocity of different objects.
But based upon this information here, we found that the universe is expanding.
Space is expanding.
So this gives rise to another type of redshift that is sometimes confused.
With a Doppler based red shift, and this is called a cosmological redshift, because what it's saying
is that if you have two galaxies and light is traveling from, let's say, this galaxy here to this
galaxy there know that's a big distance that's like millions of light years.
It's a very large distance.
So as it's traveling, the universe is expanding.
So as the light from the sky is coming over here, these guys are moving apart.
Spacetime is moving, which means that the wavelength gets longer.
It gets red, shifted right.
So we do get a redshift as a result of the fact that the universe is expanding and that expansion increase
the distance that light has to travel.
That's going to change a frequency, right?
That's what we learn.
That's the basic concept of Doppler shift.
OK.
So as a result of this, sometimes there's a cosmological redshift.
It's not going to really do off in this course, but just for reference, our redshift parameters seeing
as a different form.
We find that one plus is equal to it.
It's it's equal to the scaling factor at different periods of time.
So the scaling factor now compared to at a different time in the past, that's going to give our redshift.
And that sort of makes sense because if you're expanding at a different rate now than when you were
previously right, that's going to change the distance between the two different objects.
And that sort of gives rise to this cosmological redshift, which is indeed different than a Doppler
based redshift.
The only thing I want to make note of is that this phenomenon is so interesting because it gives rise
to situations in which it looks like objects are traveling faster than the speed of light.
Whoa.
Wait a second.
I hope you're thinking, Hey buddy, you told me that we can't travel faster than the speed of light.
Are we got that from our time dilation equation that crops up many times in this course?
What's going on here?
What I'm trying to insinuate here is that.
If the distance between here is expanding.
It may appear as though this object is moving super fast, faster than the speed of light because of
its expansion.
But in actuality, it's an illusion, right?
If you would open your eyes and take a deeper look at the situation, what you find is that as we studied
in the first video in a section right, we're just expanding the distance that the the light has to
travel over, so we expand on and off.
It may appear, or it may seem like.
You're traveling at the speed of light.
But in essence, what is happening is you're just expanding so much while you travel like millions of
light years that it may appear as though this galaxy is moving away from us faster than the speed of
light.
But indeed, it is not.
It's just.
It's just an artifact that's the proper word of the expansion of the universe, so there you have it.
That's the red shift.
That's how it was used in astrophysics and cosmology to show that the universe is expanding.
And it shows us that, yes, indeed, the relativistic Doppler shift does provide valuable information
that can allow us to make some stark conclusions regarding the evolution of the universe.
I hope you enjoyed that.
Next, we're going to run through an example, and then I'm going to be some practice problems to work
through so you can become a master of both the Doppler shift and the redshift.
Stay tuned.