All right.
Well, I just noted Terrance shoots out his radar gun.
He misses fill up and he's really -- off because he really wants to give you a ticket so he hops
into his car and drives after him and shoots the radar gun.
But in this time, he's traveling at a constant 20 meters per second as opposed to being stationary
and just shooting that gun straight at him.
So what happens is as he's looking at it and he's debugging his radar gun, he's shooting in, what
he finds is that the change in his frequency is it's a little smaller instead of ten thousand three
hundred and twenty or ten point three two kilohertz.
He finds that he gets a negative five point five two kilohertz, and he thinks that he might be getting
the incorrect result.
So to check that what he does is he quickly runs through the calculation in use, and he's smart now
because he knows he can use the non relativistic equation based upon what we've done previously in this
example.
So he immediately jumps to this equation right here, and he just plugs and shrugs.
OK, so what he gets is he plugs it in here.
He says, OK, all I need to is is one minus the original frequency I'm sending out.
It's still, you know, my my waveform is being sent out as 36 gigahertz, so it's one minus thirty
six times 10 to the nine hertz.
And then the delta is just a negative five, five thousand five hundred and twenty hertz.
You plug that baby in there and just divide by the original frequency, which is 36 gigahertz and multiply
by the speed of light and divide by two.
When he does that, he finds that we have a minute.
The last thing you measured is 23 meters per second.
Well, that is not the speed of Philip as we know previously, right?
And it really doesn't make much sense to him to because, you know, he's traveling at 20 meters per
second and it doesn't look like he's just changing in front of him in three meters per second.
He's going, it looks like he's going much faster.
So he knows that this is inherently wrong.
And this brings us to one little problem you might encounter when you design a radar system because
what you normally see when you send it out, if you look at a spectrum, the spectrum of the different
frequencies that are being received back with the y axis being the intensity you're seeing that usually
you see that you find your source frequency f not right here, you get a huge peak and that is when
you're stationary, you get a huge peak.
That is that is mostly due to what is known as clutter, which is basically you're hitting stationary
objects that get sent back and you're picking that up in your Doppler spectrum, your frequency spectrum.
So what you're really, really concerned about is the change from your source frequency because that's
an object, a target that is moving because it got Doppler shifted, right?
So what Terence does do is take a step back and he's like, I've discovered a time relation and all
these cool relativistic effects I can figure this out is his travels.
So what he says is he looks at especially like this is the one he gets, and he says, Well, this is
pretty interesting, right?
I don't see any source frequency and I see my target for him, so I know my target, he's moving away.
The thing is, he has to decrease the this spike right here that I'm getting back.
That probably corresponds to my target.
Right, that makes sense, right?
We even see that right here are Delta F has to be a negative five five two.
So we see the negative 5.5 to which actually did not right up here, which I'll do that right now.
It's negative five thousand five hundred and twenty hertz that he receives back.
So like, what?
What can I do here?
How can I fix this?
I thought, This is amazing design what's going on here?
So if you take a closer look at this diagram, what you will see is that the clutter which used to be,
if not, has changed.
Why is this?
We have another peak right here, which I'm going to say for now is the clutter.
What's going on here?
Why don't we increase in the frequency?
Well, what's going on is that as parents is traveling in the positive X direction with the velocity
of 20 meters per second, when he shoots off his radar gun, it's going to hit.
Maybe if he's in the desert, it's going to hit a cactus and that cactus is going to send that signal
back.
But because the cactus are stationary now and he's moving towards it, he's moving towards it.
This sign gets flipped right.
We originally had one minus two v roll over.
See, it becomes one plus.
So now the distance between Terrence, it's Terrence, Real, Terrence and the Cactus.
It's getting smaller as the wave travels back and forth.
So as a result, your frequency has to increase because your wavelength decreases, right?
As the same concept we've been studying in a section so far.
So what happens is clutter now gets a Doppler shift, but it's in the opposite direction than that of
your target, assuming it's moving away from you still.
Right?
So relative to terrorism, it looks like Philip is going in twenty three meters per second.
And that's why if he's really going forty three metres per second, as we determined in the first part
of this problem, it has to be 23 due to the shift.
And that frequency has to be smaller because relative to him, it's only going 23, right?
In essence, when he travels out, when he's when there's a stationary, the distance is getting.
It's increasing at a higher rate than if he's moving towards him, right?
So is that this is a smaller than the Doppler shift is not as prominent.
We only get, you know, we get a smaller frequency change and we get a smaller, measured velocity.
So this is incorrect.
You describe the other systems, you do not account for the fact that you are moving.
You would get the wrong result.
But that still begs the question how can Terrence fix his design and make it converge upon reality?
Well, what you can do is you can take a look at the spectrum and the answer lies in this frequency
plot right here.
So what we did in the first portion of this problem is we measured his velocity with respect to somebody
who is stationary.
So what if we did the same exact thing here, even though Terrence is moving?
Well, you're like, Whoa, how do I do that?
That's that sounds a little weird, right?
That's a little.
Let's take a closer look at it.
Well, if we measure the frequency change with respect to the clutter, the cactus, that stationary.
That would give us the speed difference relative to somebody in the stationary reference frame, right?
So what we could do is we could take.
The frequency change from here, this peak to this peak, and that would tell us the relative velocity
of our targets with respect to the cluttered, which is stationary.
Let's try and do that.
Let's see what happens.
So if we take our frequency, so from a stationary object, it would look like the frequency change
would be 400 plus five thousand five hundred twenty and would be a negative change.
So that would be.
Well, what does that come out to be?
Oh, that's so nine thousand plus 13 hundredths?
That's ten thousand three hundred.
That's ten thousand three hundred twenty.
Whoa.
Wait, a second.
Didn't we have that number before?
This might sound familiar.
That's number we had in part a right.
Part A. So what happens?
What happens if we use it?
Let's work through the math.
So we take the same exact equation we have here.
We know this guy with respect to somebody on the on the ground.
Let's say the cactus is right here and be a terrible drawing, but I'll just do it.
As a cactus.
Abortion is hitting this cactus is being sent back.
Another portion is sending that, but we spoke to the cactus.
This guy has to be going 43 three meters per person, so.
We had this guy here, and the point of that was I'm trying to indicate that it's still he still moving
away from the source, in essence.
This guy's the source now, so plugging in our numbers.
All right, we are the originally from we sent out its 36000 on Hertz.
We're going to subtract these two guys out together.
The forty eight hundred and fifty five twenty.
We're going to abide by our original waveform frequency and then just multiply by the Sierra two three
times 10 to the second over two.
Now when we do that, we get to the forty three meters per second back, which is the correct result
for something which is known as a moving radar.
What did you learn?
What did you learn when you learned that you have to be very cognizant about how you're measuring your
velocity?
What is it in terms of if you want this in terms of an absolute sort of an absolute value measured by
a stationary object?
You have to do some little tricks with your frequency domain, your frequency spectrum.
And you know this entire science.
I don't know a lot about this, but radar signal processing, that's a huge part of designing a radar
system because, for example, let's let's assess some different situations.
Let's say we are taking part one of this problem, and we had a cluttered which is centered on our source
frequency and we get this big large peak.
We get this big large that peak.
So our race has been let's say it's like instead of that little thin peak, we get this big, big fat
peak.
Maybe it's composed of multiple peaks and we'll see.
That's due to a lot of different maybe certain things are moving.
Other things aren't moving.
We get this big fat peak.
Well, what happens if our Doppler shift?
It's very small.
If the target is moving very slowly with respect to us, well, what could happen is the frequency could
be inside or I'll use a different color here.
These beautiful blue?
It would be inside this peak.
And you would not be able to resolve the frequency out, right?
How would you know where the peak is?
How would you know where that built is if that happened, your radar system?
It would just.
Well, what would it be able to get a result because you would not be able to identify that guy right
there.
So there are a lot of albums you can do that for trying to get rid of your clutter, your background
noise and trying to amplify and focus upon the frequency of your target.
So radar algorithms can be very complex, very convoluted, and there's a huge big science between that
where you know, you look at a lot of things in the frequency domain.
You take Fourier series and you can take a look at some of the signals you send that usually send out
a signal where if they post signal like this and you do that, you can derive something called a zinc
sync function, which tries to reconcile what this looks like in a frequency domain.
So you can find that delta from your source that you send out and try to resolve what the actual frequency
is of your target to get the velocity.
If that's what you're interested in, in particular for trying to track the target and figuring out
where it's actually located in physical space.
OK, so that's the example problem for this section.
I hope you enjoyed designing your first radar system.
That's pretty cool, right?
I can brag about that to your friends.
You joined Terrance and Phillip in their experiments, and parents in particular with this section is
very happy that he redesigned his reader system because now that smirk again, he can give Philip a
ticket and get revenge on him doing all these wacky, insane experiments.
OK?
So I hope you enjoyed that.
Next, we're going to jump into mechanics, look at some really intriguing ideas such as relativistic
momentum, relativistic energy, and you're probably going to encounter some of the most famous IDF
in special relativity.
I hope you're excited.
I'm excited to teach you, but the first thing you need to do is run through some problems of your own
so you can become a master Jedi.
All these ideas and you know it's your exam ace your designs in real life as an engineer, so on and
so forth.
Stay tuned.