All right.
And our last video, we had our first encounter with a concept known as a Doppler shift.
What do we find in that video?
We discovered that any kind of relative motion, whether it's closing the gap or opening the gap between
a source, an observer of any kind of waveform experiences, a change, a relative shift in that frequency,
and it's due to the relative motion between that observer and the source.
OK, so what the helped us do?
It helped us extend our universal conception of reality such that we could further bridge the gap between
different perspectives and get a nice, all inclusive perspective of the universe.
Now what I want to do in this video is take another look, another perspective of that same phenomenon
and derive the same exact result.
But this time, instead of taking a physical approach by using our physical observation and understanding
of the phenomenon at hand, what I want to do is take a more organic mathematical approach by taking
a look at ENM waves.
That's electro and magnetism waves.
OK.
So in order to do that first, what I want to do is I want to review what happens with the traveling,
propagating wave, and I want to use that information and some, some input we had in the beginning
of this course for the non relativistic shift between different perspectives.
We're going to use that to derive the same result to strengthen what we obtained and increase our confidence
in that result.
OK.
So first and foremost, traveling waves, OK?
We're going to we're going to go over the key characteristics of sir.
So any kind of traveling way of what we have is just like we saw previously in the last video on some
function, which the function of X and time this is at time equals zero.
The independent variable is X.
When you have a source that emits wave, it's going to go up and down in a cyclical fashion.
It's going to have an amplitude, a that's going to be the maximum point of the crest and the travel
and one is propagating.
We know that the wave moves in the right direction.
Now you study physics before, maybe also to throw away phenomenon some kind of stuff like that.
What you find is that we can describe this wave mathematically in two ways.
First.
What we can do is we can use the Euler identity to describe in terms of cool signs and signs that function,
which is the function of X and T, usually describe as the amplitude.
And this exponential function with J.
We're J is the square root of negative one.
An imaginary number times the quantity omega T minus K X. This representation.
Is intended to describe a wave of travels in the X direction, and I'm going to go over the difference
between traveling in the X direction and traveling in the negative X direction because they are a little
different.
And that's going to drive what we talk about in this lesson here.
First and foremost, what in the world is so mega?
And one, the world is this Kater?
And he studied the stuff previously.
You've probably found that K, which is the propagation constant or the wave number.
It describes how many radians are transpired per each wavelength of our waves.
The wave ones, as we described previously, is once like one complete cycle that wave.
And it's generally defined as K is equal to two pi over land at the wavelength.
That's the wave number.
We're trying to figure out how the angle changes with respect to one one wavelength.
Right?
It's in terms of distance.
We also have omega, which is the angular frequency.
So conversely, to the propagation concept with wave number, this is how much time progresses or rather
how many radius progress per one period one cycle.
OK, so we know one cycle is going to be you two pi going from beginning to the end, OK?
So omega is defined as two pi over the period C, and we also discovered in the last video that one
or T one of the period.
That's basically the frequency, right?
So this is defined as two pi times frequency.
OK, so that's our angular frequency.
And what I what I want to point your attention to is a wave that's traveling in a positive direction
and the negative direction.
Why is this guy traveling in the opposite direction?
The trick I like to use for figuring that out is to take any points.
It's got any point on the way we take this crest right here as it moves.
It's going to move only in the X direction, but.
If we want to describe this point as a muse after a time's up at sea, it might be over here.
We know that the theta is constant, right?
So for example, if we're trying to describe when F Vex equals zero at this point here, we know that
this is always occurs at an angle of two pot.
Right.
And it could be two multiples of two pirate two, and it lets you describe this, that this the angle
has three main thing is try the same exact point as it moves in the X direction.
So that means is that.
The angular term, which is described right here, omega seed has three main causes, so if we take
omega T.
Minus K X equals zero.
Right.
There's no no change.
What we can do is we can say, OK.
If it increases, we don't want any change in the sky, we want the Anglo angler part remain the same
and where the anger comes into play, sometimes we have a face constant.
So you could add a.
Little face constant, they're added, they're in this case, I'm thinking it to be zero.
That's our reference point.
But if we want to maintain that same point, right, this has to be true.
Um, so well, maybe it's the must equal access of time.
It's increasing.
You never go backwards in time.
And we want this to remain the same X as that increases.
As such.
Actually increases, and we see that this guy balances out because of these relationships here.
So in order for it to travel in the X direction, this guy must be zero.
This is positive that that works.
So this is truly an extraction because as as X increases and time increases.
We have no change in the angular displacement.
Now, if we want travel in the opposite direction, what we would have to do is we just change the sign
omega t plus.
OK.
And the reason why this works is because as time increases, acts as a function of time.
We find out if he's traveling in the negative direction.
X must decrease because if it's going this way.
It's going to decrease, so in the same sense, this negative term cancels out with that positive turn.
And we still have a constant value.
We still get that phase term right there.
OK, so that's how you can determine whether a wave travels in the right direction or the left direction.
OK.
And you might see this rate as let me make some more space here really fast for you guys.
You might see this term written a little bit differently, but I can show you that they're actually
equivalent.
So you might see it written as K acts.
Minus Omega T.
Some textbooks or if you do a search online and it's the same thing because as T increases.
X must increase in the right direction.
This guy is constant.
That's the trick I've always used for determining if a wave that I'm provided is going in the positive
direction or negative x direction, and I hope that makes sense for you guys.
So in this situation, when we're we're going to look at this.
Um.
It's going in the right direction and the observed entity, it's going to be in the positive right direction.
Awesome.
OK.
So one last key term, I want to go before we actually jump into the analysis.
It's got two options.
I'll go over briefly is.
Usually, we don't want to deal with a lot of cases and fines.
So we want to work with the real term, not the imaginary term, because if we remember from Euler's
identity e to the I X is equal to cosine x plus, I can sign X and I switched off the guy with a j here.
Usually, physics uses a j.
Mathematics uses an AI, but regardless what you use, it's going to the square root of negative one.
If we're dealing with real entities of physics, we had to take the real part all the oil or identity.
So this wave is usually expressed as eight times the cosine, which is the real part of this right.
The amplitude pops out and the cosine and then the angular term in here.
OK, so that's what we're going to use the analysis.
And one last thing I want to note is that if we take definitions of the frequency, the wavelength,
the angular frequency and the wave number, we can relate them.
And we're going to use that throughout our analysis.
Let's run through that.
We know previously that the frequency was defined as see over the wavelength.
OK.
And this seemed to work out in terms of units meters per second, divided by meters because you won
over a second, which is the units where the frequency if we take this term here.
And we plug in what we have for Lander, so we multiply the story to get a two pie arc to buy comes
down here, the cave flips up, we get a KC over two PI.
And if we note that to pie in the sky over a times, F is equal to a mega.
We can find that Casey is equal to Omega.
So that's a term which we can relate these two guys.
And it's going to help us pop this guy out in some of our analysis and get the result that we're trying
to look.
OK, so now what I want to do, you have some background, some understanding of traveling or propagating
ENM waves.
We're going to take that definition and just organically derive a Doppler shift by working through the
mathematics that are behind this.
Some textbooks take the approach that I took in the last video.
That's sort of an elementary approach.
More of a sophisticated, complex physics approach that you'll probably see at higher levels is the
approach I'm going to take here.
So let's delve into that and do that now.
OK.
So if we make use of the non relativistic relationship we derived in our first video, we are trying
to bridge the gap between two different perspectives of the same phenomenon.
What we found is that if you don't account for relativistic effects, we find that a moving reference
frame ex-prime can be related to a non-moving referencing X.
By the relative motion between them, we find that as prime is equal to X minus B T.
And we also found that there is no difference between the moving reference frames conception of time
and original ones, which is unlike what we saw with relativistic effects, where we observe time dilation,
where time sees the tick at a different rate.
OK, so we're ignoring those effects for now.
We'll jump into that in subsequent videos.
But if we just take these simple relationships and take what we've just discovered for propagating plane
waves, we can take f x see a wave that is a function of x A. We know that's defined as a cosine omega
T minus K X, and what we could do is we can just plop these guys straight.
So here we have a time to adjust changes to T Prime.
And here we have an X.
Well, we can take this and we can say OK, if we plus v t x is equal to x prime loss v t.
And you know, you could actually observe that pretty clearly.
Like if we have x y here and I show this in the video, it's confusing.
Jump back to the first few videos.
Of course we get x y if we have an x prime y prime.
That's moving in a positive direction.
Well, if you want to figure out X, you can take what X Prize is to this point here.
It's going to be there for there, plus the distance that has elapsed.
Right?
The same thing works for X Prize, right?
If you want prime, you can take the distance of this guy all the way from there with respect to X minus
the distance to travel there.
And then you would get that guy, which is just the measurement and the moving reference.
OK.
So we can use this stuff we get.
This relationship is universal conception of reality to make use of it, make use of it, right?
We invested all that time and writing this let's actually use it.
So if we plug in for x x prime plus b t right, we get the mega C prime minus K x prize plus beauty.
We use this relationship here.
And then if we distribute all these guys, we get omega t prime minus K v t prime.
Minus K X. Prime, and then we can group the terms sort of make use of some of the relationships we
have, right?
We can come back up here.
We say, Oh, we have a mega, we have an AK.
I want to group the TS so that we can find some relationship because we know from this definition here,
whatever is in front of a T is the frequency of our weight.
That's how it works.
That's what the angular frequency is defined as.
So if we try to get rid of the K, define it in terms of our original frequency.
We know that this relationship off here that we establish a mega is equal to Casey.
So if we divide by C, we know that K is equal to a mega over C.
We plop this guy in there and we end up with is a cosine times or negative line minus a mega tonnes
b over C.
Right?
We just plug this straight into here.
Put a mega receiver omega over C and then we see that we have a common omega and T prime between the
terms.
So we're not really interested in this guy, but we can just pull out straight ahead.
Now, Megan, to Prime Omega's prime, what are we left with?
One?
And an Omega tribe has VRC one minus B or C.
That that's the result we're looking for, so if we take this literally a mathematical reduction of
everything we have been doing, what we can do is we could say OK, based upon that, based on our mathematics,
based upon our relationships, we found that just because of this relative motion, right?
The V between this guy and this guy.
That says that our apparent frequency, what we're supposed to observe in the wave is literally as follows.
It's really this parameter here.
So we get the observed frequency at omega prime equal to one minus B or C omega, which looks very similar
to the previous term.
We observed, right?
However, right.
That was in terms of the frequency, not the angular frequency.
So, you know, we know that this is just different by a parameter of one of two PI.
So if we take this guy multiply by one hour two pi, that is equal to f you multiply on the left, you
multiply on the right that maintains the equality and then omega two.
What about two?
Pi is no different than the frequency.
So mega primes becomes um.
F Prime.
Which I should make note of that the apparent observed frequency and that is just the quantity one minus
B or C times the original frequency.
And I know, wait a minute, you're thinking, what's going on here?
This is a different sign.
That's just because based upon how we derived all this stuff.
Our original derivation was assuming a V in the positive direction, positive direction when we derived
the previous one, the the V was in the opposite direction.
So the results are synonymous.
We've got the same exact result.
This if it's going in a positive direction, right?
We're adding that on top of the city, the the distance, the way it travels, that's traveled an extra
distance to get to that observed and that observer, right?
We get less crisp hitting that observer that results in less cycles completed per second, which he
observes or results in a lower frequency.
This is the result.
We expect this is the result.
We got the same as we previously had.
That strengthens our confidence.
That's awesome.
OK.
But but this was option number one we worked with, and it makes use of a previous result, which sort
of uses from relativity.
What we could do right is just purely by mathematical means.
I mean, pretty cool, right?
That would strengthen.
The validity of the argument and increase our confidence, so next, what we're going to do, we're
going to one more derivation.
Stick with me.
We're going to get the same result.
But doing it purely just by the physics, the math and what we've put up here.
Stay tuned.