All right, Rob.
More discussion on the derivation of opposites.
What I want to do is go over one last derivation of the equation to do this.
What we're going to do is we're going to make no use of any prior results that we have derived and it's
going to be 100 percent organic.
We're just going to run through the math, the physics and the representations we have for waves, and
we're going to find out the same exact real result actually drops out of what we're working on.
And that's going to strengthen our confidence and make us feel very, very confident that the bridge
we built to sort of bridge the gap between different perspectives and reference frames is bad, is good
and is the correct way of interpreting frequency shifts with these different observers.
So to do this, what we're going to do is we're going to make use of what we just talked about with
ENM waves with a propagating wave to the right, and we're going to have some kind of target a plane
that's fly to the right with a velocity V.
What we know is that the distance to that plane is going to change with time from the source of the
wave all the way to the the actual object, the type we're trying to detect.
And that's going to have a distance of X as a function of T. So what we do is we take the equation for
a propagating wave traveling in the positive x direction.
Write that down.
We found in the last video that was the function, which is the function of X A. is equivalent to the
amplitude a times the cosine and the angle is omega t minus K, where again omega is the angular frequency
and K is the propagation number or wave number that we talked about previously.
So using this, the first thing we want to do is put in our definitions we have for again, the propagation
constant and the angular frequency.
We take omega and plug in to pi f not we know that omega naught, which is this guy right here.
This is equal to two by f Nazi.
We plug that guy in there.
Basically plop that straight in and for the wave number of propagation constant, we know that is equivalent
to two pi over land and off the original wavelength that is observed transmitted from the radar system.
Next, what we want to do is we want to get rid of this wavelength here and inject the frequency.
What we're really interested in.
So as we've seen previously, we've done this in the previous video.
We've done it in our original derivation.
We know that the frequency is related to lambda by C over lambda.
This is the equation we have derived.
OK.
Again, I always bring up the units we take me to for second, divided by mean meters, we get one over
second, one over time.
Those are the dimensions of frequency, so it seems to make sense and jive well with our intuition.
OK, now what we want to do is we want to take this and move the ladder over here and the frequency
down so that we can plug it straight into here what we're going to use.
If we take this, we find that ladder, not the original wavelength, is equivalent to the C, the speed
of light divided by F, not the original frequency.
So we pop this guy in C gets on the bottom, f not pop up.
And what we find is that we have common terms in here.
We have an f, not that we're trying to get with an X and we have the speed of light.
OK, but we know that the Doppler shift is in terms of relative motion between the source and the observer,
the target that we're trying to detect.
So when the world, what's going on here in order to make progress, we must first make note that inside
here, this is the angular argument, OK?
So here if we group the two pi f not.
We end up with a T minus X over C or something like this, we know this is the angle that described
any position on this way as it propagates in time.
Next, what we want to do is we need to make note of a relationship that we derived or whether we didn't
derive is just physical intuition that crops up in classical mechanics.
And this is the fact that the angular frequency omega.
If if we take the Omega that is observed by the target, this guy is equal to two pi times f prime,
but it's also equal to the change in that angle, right?
This is the angular frequency, it's how it's changing d theta d t, it's that derivative, right?
We've made use quite extensive use of this in basic mechanics.
It crops up in dynamics, so on and so forth.
This is a intuitive physical quantity right here.
So if we take this this result here and we're trying to figure out how the frequency where the angular
frequency observed at the target is different than the original produced frequency of the wave.
What we can do is we can isolate FPI by divide it by one or two pi of heredity, and we get this relationship
right here.
Well, we know what the angular quantity is because we just tried to previously right here.
And all we need to do is basically just take the derivative of this guy.
So we plop it straight in, straight and down here, throw it into that derivative and we distribute
this through all turns.
We know that two PI, if not the original frequency, is a constant.
It's not changing.
That pops out right here.
We can divide by the two pi right there that cancels, and then we just have to distribute this through
these terms.
The T minus x the receipt.
Well, the trade with respect to time of time is just one, which is what we get here.
And the derivative of a C is a little tricky to actually compute that.
We know that C is the speed of light that's constant that pops out.
But the X here, the X, we must remember, is the position going to our target?
So this is a function of time.
But the derivative, this becomes the velocity.
It's the distance between here and and the target.
So you know, that is increasing by a a quantity of the relative motion.
And that's where the relative motion between our source and our observer comes into play.
This is how it jumps into the equation.
OK.
So the duration of this is one third of X, it's just B.
And when we put that into play here, we end up with the same exact equation that the angular frequency
f prime is equal to one minus V or c f not.
OK.
So this is going to be when the source.
The source.
An observer.
Are moving.
Away from each other.
And then we could take this guy and say that f prime is equal to one plus the oversea.
If not for.
Moving closer.
So.
The sign of the paucity of that relative motion dictates the arrival of that different phenomena, the
Doppler shift that we've been talking about, and I want to make note about these two differences here.
Because when you're if you're doing any kind of problem that you're working on.
If they're coming together, you want to use this guy, right?
Because the frequency is going to increase.
Right, it's moving into the wave train, so it's seeing that crest more frequently.
And then if they're moving away from each other, you use this guy where the frequency decreases because
you're moving away from that wave that's coming towards it.
So the wave has to move over a longer distance.
You see that wave less frequently.
It leads to a smaller Doppler shift, OK?
Or rather, the frequency is lower.
OK, now what?
We have just arrived throughout this video in the previous videos is the fact that.
If we're trying to detect a target with radar in this particular application, what this guy sees is
this.
But when you're dealing with radar, what you're trying to do is you're trying to emit a light, some
kind of wave, some kind of beam, you're trying to hit a target.
And then that gets reflected back.
To your source towards your dish.
Right?
So this is only half of the picture, right?
It doesn't help to know the frequency here.
We want to know the return frequency here.
So the way in which we think about this is if this guy is moving in this direction, right?
You increase the distance between the wave and the object that decreases the frequency as we have just
arrived.
However, when it hits this, it's going to bounce off and come back and the time difference between
when it hits this.
And it moves and then another one hits it means that you have to add on that extra vote, that extra
distance.
So there's a Doppler shift that this observes and then there's a Doppler shift from this frequency.
So this guy black that we have there, so there's a double Doppler shift.
I want to make sure you understand that.
Do you understand that?
So initially, this guy sees something different because it's moving away, it's adding in distance.
But this guy wanted to reflect it back.
This becomes the source and the source is moving away.
So this guy observes, you get extra distance that keeps adding up incrementally.
And that means that you see that same beam less frequently back here, right?
It bounces off.
There's a time delay.
So we're going to have to have another Doppler shift.
What this guy sees is not this.
It's not that.
So let's do it.
OK, well, this tells us that I'm going to rewrite this.
This is the source frequency right here.
I'll put a little se here.
And this is the target.
Hours, yeah, so the target sees this Doppler shift at frequency.
But now what we want is the frequency at the receiver, so the frequency.
At the receiver, it's going to be the same exact idea, right?
Based upon this, looks like this guy's moving away, so we're increasing that distance again.
It gets Doppler shift, we get another decrease.
So what actually ends up happening is if the same exact formula we get one minus v over C, well, this
time it's on the target.
See, this is the produced frequency.
And we want to see how that's shifted back to the receiver.
So what you end up having is you get this one minus B or C.
And then we just put this guy in, we know what the target is.
So that's another one minus B or C.
Times the source frequency.
Which is something you know, right, right, when you admit that frequency in your signal processor,
you know what's being generated, you know what you're modulating and what you're sending out.
So that's what we know.
OK.
So if we take this and work through the math we end up with is one minus two B or C.
Plus B squared.
Overseas Square.
OK.
And I hope you're thinking when you see this, there's some of the stuff we would have previously.
If B or C is small as it is in a non role, it is the case.
If you square a small turn, it gets even smaller, so this relative to this, which is multiplying
by two, is drastically smaller.
So when you open up a radar textbook, what you're going to find is that this is going to be reduced.
You're going to get something that looks sort of like this.
You're going to get there are seat frequency.
Is equal to one minus two the oversea.
Times that guy.
OK, so that would be what the dish.
The Signal processor actually observes when the signal is actually received back at the dish.
OK.
And another way of actually dividing this is you might see sometimes people say there's like a two way
Doppler shift.
In my opinion, it's not quite right because it doesn't capture what's going on.
They would change X to two x here becomes two x oversee the distance actually traveled because it has
to go out and then come back.
Well, that's not.
That's not 100 percent kosher, if not now, because you have multiple phenomena occurring here.
And if you did that, you get this result, but this term would fall out.
We get a sort of similar term if we work on it and do it in a relativistic sense, which you'll see
in subsequent videos, but.
What's important to note here in the application is if you know your source frequency which you send
out, you're going to know that because you generate the beam that's actually sent out to your target
and you measure what comes back.
If you relate to as such, you can determine the velocity of your target.
And I can give you a lot of information now in terms of the signal processing of this.
It's a lot of weird stuff that's going on.
Usually you have sort of a post signal.
Something like this where you send out a beam.
You energize your your dish and then you wait to receive, you energize.
Waiter Steve Um, it's known as like a peeler up pri pulse repetition interval.
Um, something like this when you actually process it.
The resolution you get is dependent upon, you know, how long you sent our signal, how long you wait
for it.
And that can affect the Fourier transform you receive back, which might not be able to to show this
shift, the Doppler shift.
So there's a lot of interesting things that go into play with radar systems.
That's just a general idea of what's going on, but for the most part, your Doppler shift.
It's showing you when something is moving, one and two allows you to compute the velocity of that guy.
So this can tell us, Hey, you have a nuke that's coming in super, super frickin fast.
Freak out, do something or you can see that it's some target that's remaining still, which would be
like a mountain, for example, something where you don't want to engage a target that's coming in to
take it down before it blows up your town.
OK, so you get that information from it.
What I want to do is to wrap this up.
Just talk about some other applications of this.
Doppler shift is not off the relativistic Doppler shift.
I talked about the ambulance, what you hear on an everyday basis.
Another application is the radar gun that policemen generally use, like in their car shoot out a beam.
And when it comes back, that can allow them to determine the velocity that you are traveling right
because it's going to hit your car instead of a plane, a car, and it's going to come back and it could
use something like this.
It probably would use the relativistic quantity because that's more accurate.
But if you're going slow, it could technically use this guy right here.
And that gives you a quantity.
You're right.
You can measure the receive frequency versus frequency, and you could figure out how fast somebody
is going, I can tell.
Are they traveling within the speed limits of the law?
You can pull them over and, you know, get tickets for that reason.
So when you get tickets, yes, this is pretty accurate.
That gun.
Another application you've probably heard of is Doppler radar, which is used a lot in meteorology and
weather systems.
The way in which that works is you have like a big dome that's sending out signals, light waves.
It's going to hit a cloud and then it's going to come back, one that signifies the presence of storms,
but also based upon the frequency that you receive back.
That's going to tell you whether there's a storm moving in or whether it's receding and moving away
from your location.
So when you see, like on TV, you see Doppler maps where you have like green areas for precipitation
that signifies the velocity.
When you get a tornado, for example, when it's rotating around, you have a portion that's moving
to you and a portion on the other side that's moving away from you.
So if you start getting a very green color over here in a red color over there that signifies the rotation
of particles, debris or any kind of wind, so on and so forth, and that allows you to determine that,
hey, you know, we have some kind of circular cyclone kind of thing.
Perhaps there is severe weather or some kind of tornado that comes that comes in.
So that's sort of how Doppler is used in a weather sense.
But that's that that's the Doppler shift, the non relativistic term.
What I want you to pay attention to when you use this is whether the target is coming in together or
the target is moving, moving away from the source.
Depending upon that, you use one of these equations that controls the sign.
Um, but yes, the Doppler frequency.
I hope you enjoy that after we run through some practice problems.
Next, what we're going to do is we're going to jump into the relativistic Doppler shift.
We're going to modify this a bit by using some of the information we have learned, such as the Lorenz
transformation, time dilation, length contraction, so on and so forth.
So they can.