All right.
In the last few videos, we derived a Doppler shift equation that is used for determining the apparent
frequency from a reference frame that's moving away from some kind of radar source.
Now in those videos, I noticed that when we got the equation, which I have right here, when we derive
that equation, I thought that it was inherently a non relativistic result.
And as we ran through the derivation, you yourself probably should have noted that I was making certain
assumptions that were not quite true, given what you currently know about time dilation, length,
contraction, so on and so forth.
OK.
So in those videos, what I I asserted was that time was absolute between a moving reference frame in
a stationary reference frame attached to a radar source.
And we know that to be inherently wrong because we study time dilation and we know that a moving body
is observed, its clock is observed to tick slow.
So if we don't account for that result, wouldn't that insinuate that the Doppler shift equation we
derive right here is not correct?
And it would yield incorrect predictions on the frequency observed by somebody in a moving reference
frame.
You would think that, but in order to assess how valid or how invalid our previous result is, we have
to take a look at the general relative velocities we observe in everyday situations.
And then what we're going to do is we're going to derive a more accurate and more precise Doppler shift
equation that accounts for relativistic effects and accounts for what we learned for when we study time
dilation.
OK?
But back it up.
What we want to do is want to take a look at the relative speeds we're going to observe in any kind
of radar system.
Now, a radar system.
Generally, what it's trying to do is trying to detect any kind of enemy, target, man-made kind of
vehicle that fly through the air for defense purposes.
And that's the main objective and a missile defense system.
OK.
So what I've tabulated, I've searched you, Google, and I found the fastest manmade vehicle, which
is actually a vehicle designed by one of my previous companies, Lockheed Martin.
It's an SLR 71 Blackbird.
And what we found is that this can travel up to speeds of approximately 20 100 miles per hour.
So that's a very fast speed.
But relative to the speed of light, is that faster?
Is that slow?
Whoa, you look at this, you know, like, whoa, wait a minute.
I don't usually deal at the speed of light in terms of miles per hour, right?
I like the seafood assistance.
So let's first calculate the relative velocity by by converting our speed of light and then throwing
it into our general equation we generally use.
So we know that the world have lost EBITA is equal to the velocity of our target, oversee the speed
of light.
So we have the maximum loss who had ever observed with a manmade vehicle up to twenty one hundred miles
per hour.
And then when we convert the speed of light, you can use Google, you can use Mathematica, you can
use MATLAB, or you can do the calculation by hand, right?
You need to convert meters to miles, seconds, two hours.
We get that it comes out to be six point seven zero six times 10 to the eight miles per hour.
So you can see this is this is out of the ballpark compared to this guy.
But so when we do the calculation, we find that the relative velocity is three point one times 10 to
the minus six, and that is unit less tuneless.
So we get a result like this based on what you study previously.
What does that tell us?
What does that indicate that indicates that our Lorenz factor this guy right here, this guy is going
to be approximately equal to one, right?
It's going to be approximately equal to one because what we have found is that that equation.
Right.
It goes where this is one, it basically goes one for a lot of.
Portion and then it shoots up and becomes often that high rollers have lost.
So we know that we are probably closer to this region here.
What that tells us is that relativistic effects should not really arise if and this is the conditional,
the important conditional.
If we're only trying to detect manmade vehicles, which cannot go close to the speed of light yet,
OK, so relativistic effects should not arise for manmade targets and the equation we derived this guy
right here is still quite accurate.
And that is why if you look up some radar textbooks, you're going to find this equation and you're
going to see it sometimes in computations.
There's going to be a slight error, but that error is in essence negligible unless you're going into
very precise measurements you're trying to make.
So there is value in using this equation equation, which is derived.
And you know, we went through the two way Doppler shift to figure out what the frequency would be back
here.
So that can give us some accurate results and still make use of that.
But let's say we want stuff that is 100 percent accurate, something that converges completely upon
reality, right?
We're trying to get this universal conception of reality.
That's the point, of course.
So if we're going to do that, what we can do is we can go to Tarrance and fill up and say, Hey, guys,
help us out here.
We want to do another experiment.
What you did was it's not quite right.
Fix it, fix.
And they say, Hey, man, since we talked, we quit our job as scientists and we became actors.
So we're actors on the set of Star Trek.
And what we found is that, you know, they have a lot of manmade vehicles that travel close to the
speed of light.
Whether or not this is true and ours is possible actually found, but this is not quite possible based
on physical laws that these guys can go faster than the speed of light.
But we're going to assume it's going to go close to the speed of light.
And.
Tears of Philip say, Hey, this is pretty interesting, I'm going to dive back into my science.
They're going to help us out there to help us derive the relativistic Doppler shift.
And Rudy is USS Enterprise won't assume it's going to fly straight out to the right.
We're not parachuting beans at it trying to figure out.
How long or the apparent frequency?
That the US has enterprise actually observes, and you could use any kind of fast vehicle.
We have to generally use fancy.
I'm not a big Star Trek fan.
Maybe you could use Star Wars Millennium Falcon going straight out.
The point is, we want the relative velocity to be approximately equal to the speed of light and maybe
point nine, nine times C, I say at minimum point five times the speed of light to get from relativistic
effects, we get to this point on the curve where it's awesome.
OK, so if we take this, we can say, Oh, I'm not going to do these convoluted derivations because
previously I found this result and this for a target moving away from the source, moving away from
the radar.
OK, so we know that's true because if it's moving away, we know that the distance each wave has to
travel is going to be an extra v delta T.
So with the crest this guy sees, they're going to be separated by the distance.
The frequency is going to decrease.
Right?
OK, so we got this result and it's not quite right because we know that from time dilation, we cannot
assume, as we did in the previous generation, that Delta T prime equals Delta T or the.
The time difference, as observed by the USS Enterprise, cannot be equivalent to what terrorist measures
we got fill up on the U.S. enterprise, and he's going to measure a different time.
Right?
Space time tends to bend to account for the second posture, the special relativity.
That's what we learned, right?
Let's put it to use right now.
So we say that, OK, well, when time was observed by somebody who stationary or Terence Delta T,
it has to be delayed by this Lorentz factor.
We have the gamma times deputy prime reguilon's defined as such.
So what we could do is we could take a look at the times that are measured in our equation here.
So.
When Terence shoots out these pins every time he sees a crest or the frequency cycles per second, this
is measured in terms of his reference range in terms of Delta T.
In other words, he's measuring the number of press emitted for a time period.
Delta T observed in the radar system.
What Tarrant or Philip is interested in on the USS Enterprise is he wants something a bit different.
He still wants to measure these red crests hitting his vehicle.
However, he's measuring the number of press received for a time period Delta T Prime.
Which is different, a novelty as we learn in time dilation.
He wants it for a time for Delta T Prime observed in the U.S. enterprise.
The time he sees would be different than the time Terrence seized.
So if that's what we're really looking for, then this equation we start off with cannot be quite right
because Philip, once cycles per deputy prime, the number of cycles per his time measurement.
But he's calculating it in terms of these quantities in X source is the number of cycles per regular
delta, the Delta T in the radar system.
So what we need to do is we need to convert this time and if we can do that.
Then we can get the correct result, so we go back to time relation.
And we say, OK, Delta T is equal to Gamma Deputy Prime.
We can flip, we can flip.
Both of these to get one Delta T equals one of a gamma delta T prime and multiply the game over to the
left, and we get this equation here.
We see that if we multiply gamma over here, we get a camera T or get gamma over Delta team and that
transforms into a one over a deputy prime, which would get what we really want because what we have
now if fill up.
Takes everything on the right.
He would get cycles of respect to Terrence's clock.
So we want to convert it over.
OK, so what we could do is.
We would take this Lawrence factor, multiply it in here.
Laurence Packer, Delta T, I guess this one of Delta T Prime the number here, he's really measuring
this.
But when we multiply by gamma, it turns into what we once were the cycle per Delta T prime.
OK, so this is important.
Make sure you understand this is a conceptual derivation.
We'll go back, take a more convoluted or a more mathematically intensive approach next.
But if we just want to convert this result into a relativistic result, we just have to make note that,
OK, we're calculating in terms of clock multiply by gamma that will make it in terms of the USS Enterprise
s clock and what we want right here.
OK, so when we do that, we multiply by gamma.
Right.
On both sides, actually, and then this turns into the correct form we want as measured by the.
And all we need to do is just plug in this guy right here, so we just take the gavel, that's a one
over square root of one, minus the relative over C squared.
This guy comes along for the ride, the one minus the relative ever c times the source frequency.
And then we just need to do some math.
OK.
So what we could do is.
Well, you know that one minus x squared is equal to one minus x times one plus x, right?
So we could do that on the bottom and we get the square root one minus the rail or C and one plus Fiorillo
C, and that on the top, we can make note that this guy is no different than this quantity squared
or two of them.
And then you take the square root, so the top becomes the square root of one minus v relevancy has
one minus the irrelevancy.
I didn't do anything because it's technically this guy squared.
Take the square root band.
You recover the original term, right?
We didn't do anything.
We didn't do anything special.
So if we take this guy and we say, Oh, look at this man, look at that.
We can cancel out parliamentarians, bam, we cancel that with that guy right there.
And what we end up with is our relativistic result quite quickly.
Just by taking our understanding of time and swapping those guys out with the rest factor, we end up
with the following equation, which is a bit more convoluted than our previous result.
Not as nice, but it gives us that the observed frequency at the target as measured as measured by fill
up.
It's going to be the square root of one minus relative velocity of a C over the square root of one.
Plus the relative velocity oversea times the source frequency, and it's important to note that this
only applies for a target moving away from the source.
If we want to move towards the source right, the relative, the sign with swish must be coming in this
direction.
All we need to do is change the signs.
And you should be able to reason through it because if it's going away, you would expect the frequency
to be lower.
So currently, one minus the quantity, you may get a 0.5 five, you're taking like a fraction of something.
Divide it by one plus you divide it by like one or two.
So this is making the frequency smaller as expected.
Switch the signs.
We're going to get one plus a ratio.
So that's going to increase it divided by one minus.
So we're dividing dividing by a fraction, which means it's going to increase it further.
So then as it travels close, you're increasing that frequency because you're decreasing the distance
each wave has to travel.
So the apparent frequency to fill up would be increased.
So if you were really concerned about accuracy, really concerned about maybe your radar algorithm being
precise and converging from reality, you want to use this equation here.
This is the relativistic Doppler shift we obtained.
What I want to do next is, you know, there were sort of sort of felt like we're doing some hand waving.
I want to do a more direct derivation of back up in terms of what we're doing for this guide and show
you how we can derive this exactly.
And why is that important?
Why is that important?
Because if you derive a result once, that's nice, it's fine.
And.
But if you can derive it twice or three times, that would increase the validity of the result you get.
It increases your confidence.
OK, so let's do that.
I want you to be confident in this result and understand where it came from.