All right, so finally, if you're still not 100 percent convinced by a derivation, we can get the
same result by making use of a Lawrence transformation that we painstakingly derived previously.
OK, so this is also going to give you some more experience, more exposure to how we actually use the
Lawrence transformations, what we found previously.
The last transformation, in fact, is sort of the inverse Lawrence transformation.
This is what it's sometimes called in textbooks is that if we only have measurements as measured by
somebody in the moving reference frame or fill up in the USS Enterprise, in this case, we can figure
out the measurements of around the length X and the time T. as measured by somebody in the radar station,
for example, such as Terence.
Through the following expressions, and so this is a previous assault we obtained.
What we do is we could take another look at the the electromagnetic we that's being transmitted out
from this radar station.
So recall again, we've been using that Terence and his reference frame.
He said that as measured by my radar system, the actual way that sent out is some kind of amplitude
a times cosine times a mega T minus K X-ray.
You should be really familiar with the sky now.
So in order to figure out what the wave looks like in fill ups reference frame, we need the function
in terms of x prime and prime not to index.
So to do that, all we need to do is would use this guide.
This is our map.
This is our bridge that helps us walk over to the other side to see things from a different perspective.
So we take out our trusty map.
We look up what we want.
We say, OK, I want to see what X is in terms of X Priority Prime, and we literally plug in shot baby.
So we take this guy and we see that we want to get rid of T.
So for T for this portion here, and I'll make it easy for you guys to see what's going on this guy
here, this is T.
So for T, we know that gamma times t prime plus v rel um.
Or rather, let's back up.
So what we want is to see and what we could do is receive a T right here.
We love that game and that's just gamma times T prime plus v real times x prime over c squared.
Literally just plug it in.
Then we have a minus K and make it easier.
This guy is X.
Our XTerm, so we know from our trusty map, and this tells us that it should actually be gamma times
x prime plus v real time Steve.
OK.
All I did is substitute in some parameters here, and all we need to do is just simplify and see what
happens.
So what we could do is we could say initially we got, oh, for the first time, we got a gamma omega
t prime.
That's that guy.
And then we have to add a gamma omega times v relative times x prime or C squared.
That's this guy right here.
Now we subtract the K Omega and x prime.
That's that guy right there and then subtract a K omega v relative times to prime, which is that guy
right there.
And what we want to do now is try to combine terms and find what is in front of the Omega.
See how the omega is modified.
So we want to put it back to this central form here.
One Omega times T minus K times x.
So let's try and group the omega T prime terms.
And if we do that, what we do is first I'm going to group them next to each other.
So for this step, right here, we got a gamma omega T, right, and we want to get this guy close to
here.
In order to do that, we make we have to make note that K is equal to Omega oversee or rather.
Yeah, Omega is equal to Casey Omega over sea is equal to K, and we use this to go from here.
Down to there.
So we take this guy.
We plank up back, put a mega oversee in there and we get a subtraction side a minus, or let's back
up, let's make sure we're keeping track of our time.
So we've got this term here.
Now we're going to get this term, which is right down here.
I'll check out down here.
So this term is just minus gamma omega oversee the Omega, there's a c Typekit prime and then we need
our B relative.
So that's that term, then we're going to get this term next.
So, yeah, plus gamma omega well, for X Prime, we want something that looks like this, so we want
to get rid of that omega and get a K in there.
So that's omega is just KC.
So this is going to be plus Gamma K and C. It cancels with that guy.
So we get Gamma K v relative, oversee that guy right there.
Bam, we're done with that.
So we only have one more turn and this is a minus gamma k x prime and we got that guy right there.
And now all we need to do is group terms.
So again, we want to put it in this form and see what we're really interested in is what this looks
like in this reference frame.
The X prime time reference frame.
OK, so we're going to try and figure out what that looks like by grouping Omega TS to make a Prime
T primes and figure out what's in front.
So what we have is we see common terms of.
And here a gamma omega t prime, there's a cameo omega t prime.
So that's the commentary.
I'm going to pull that out.
We got a gamma omega t from.
So that is multiply by one minus v relative a receipt.
That's that term right there.
And we could do the same thing for K Richard in that.
We're interested really in the frequency.
So it's not going to be much use to us, but authors do that anyway.
So we know we want a minus K X..
And all I want to do is with the key terms over here, find common factors, be a mechanic prime that's
common here.
So we Malta or rather we subtract gamma k x gamma k x times one for this term, which gives you the
negative and an a minus.
The minus can't get a plus sign right there, minus the relative over C that's that term.
So or interested in is this guy right here?
We're going to pull that off the equation.
And in essence, all we did just back up a little bit is we took out our trusty map, the Lorenz transformation.
We're trying to bridge the gap between an infinite set of perceptions of the universe, and that allowed
us to really transition over to different ways of measuring things.
A different perspective, if you will.
So we translated this equation here into a different equation as measured by fill up, and we got the
following assertion.
This tells us that our new omega, which is always the term in front of the T, is this gamma one minus
v relativistic omega?
This guy?
Well, if you recall.
Omega is just two PI.
Times the frequency.
So if we want to get our terms back, we could say if we multiply by one or two pot each on mega on
both sides, we get our frequencies back.
And what can you tell me about this equation?
Right over to that.
This is the same result that we obtained previously, so again, we've done this three times, you feel
very comfortable with the relativistic Doppler shift that we are getting the correct precise result.
Next, we want to do is, if you recall, this is just what we call up seas on the USS Enterprise,
but we know that he's also going to send signals back when this bounces off a target.
And that's going to fly another Doppler shift, as we talked about previously.
And we want to figure out the two way Doppler shift that results due to this.
OK, so that's what we're going to tackle next.