All right.
To wrap this video up on the relativistic Doppler shift, what we're going to do is we're going to calculate
the two way Doppler shift because we know from our previous discussions that the the equation for the
frequency at the target is not exactly what the radar is going to see return back to it.
We know that we have to fly to Doppler shifts, and we only calculated that with a non relativistic
value.
Let's do the same thing here for the relativistic value.
So to do that?
To try and calculate the frequency that is received by Terence and his radar station, and I put a little
relative sign here to indicate that we're using relativistic quantities.
We know that that is going to equal basically our Doppler shift equation, the one minus variable over
C square root of that divided by the square root of one plus b relevancy times the frequency at the
target that Philip sees.
And again, that's the relative term.
And we know that what we just arrived is that the frequency of the target is basically the same huge
radical term right here times the frequency in the source that parents emits up.
So to make progress on this, we're going to do the same exact thing we did previously.
We're going to take this guy right here, which I will box in for you.
And we're going to literally throw it right there.
We're going to plug it straight into this guy.
So when we do that, we retain this guy here and basically we get the same exact quantity multiplied
out.
So we got a lot of radical sides.
The little it's not super nice, but I'll show you it's not going to be too bad.
And then we multiply by the frequency of the source, which is right here.
We have the fine.
So if we're going to take the terms on the square roots and multiply it together and ban the square,
it's drop out and we get this equation here for the two way Doppler shift.
OK, so what this is is the receive frequency is equal to one minus V relative of a C divided by the
quantity one plus v relative or mercy times the source frequency that is the minute by Terence in his
radio station.
So when you see something like this compared to our previous term, which was, I mean, it was like
one minus two times the relative velocity or C times the source frequency.
It's not quite as nice as a lot more terms.
It would take a lot more effort to do that computation program it up, so on and so forth.
So what I want to do is I want to try and compare this to that previous result.
And the way in which we do that is we take this guy here.
We try and get rid of this fractional term, right?
Because fractional term makes it really hard to deal with.
How do we do that?
How do we get rid of this guy?
We want to take an expense.
You want to expand this out and see how it's expressed in terms of polynomials.
We do that by a serious binomial expansion, so on and so forth.
Luckily, we saw previously in this section when we're dealing with the Doppler shift that we could
take an expansion.
We can recall the expansion from earlier.
So pilots that one over one plus x is the following it's one minus x plus x squared minus excuse, so
on and so forth.
You can see the pattern that is arising straight out of this.
So if we take that, we can apply to both these terms and we'll have to do it separately because it's
much more convoluted and you can see why working with the relativistic opposite might be a little bit
of a pain.
It's not as elegant.
It's not as nice as the other one.
So what we could do is we could split up one over one plus B relevancy as one terminal can have a not
another term, which is minus Berala to C developed by one plus B or C.
And we're going to set our X term here.
We're going to set this guy equal to row over C.
OK, so we're going to do that in two steps and then we're going to add them together.
OK.
So the first third, which is one over one plus the C, when we do that, all we need to do is just
plug this guy into that guy.
So the X becomes a V rollover c.
So we have one minus B relevancy plus v relevancy squared minus BRL over C cubed as models, plus an
infinite number of polynomials.
And we can drop this off when it starts to approach zero as the relevancy ratio.
But we know that we're going to have relativistic double shifts.
We'll probably traveling close to the speed of light, so we're going to go out, have to go up very
far before we find negligible terms.
So it might not be as feasible to expand this out and use the expanded term, but I'm doing this to
show you something pretty cool.
Stick with me.
So next we got the one term we want to take care of the minus B relative or C divided by the denominator.
So in order to do that, we have to do that in two states, it's not as nice.
So first, what we're going to do is we could take basically this term here, this guy right here and
throw it down into the brackets.
So this is basically.
This entire term here.
We throw down into the brackets and we just have to multiply by negative zero.
So when we do that and we multiply everything through, what we end up with is a negative relative ever
seen plus zero or c squared.
Minus bureaucracy.
Cute.
Plus, the relevancy, so forth, so on and so forth, so we could take this result and add it to this
result right here.
When we do that, we basically recover back this guy right here, which is that guy right there.
So when we do that, we see we got a one, a one right there.
Minus a B relevancy plus of euro, plus a negative vitriol, see, so again, that's one minus five
euros the minus the euro or C, so that gives us a one minus two B rollover C.
And then we go back up, we see we have a very c squared.
Well, we have that also in gesture here, so we get two times that and a minus.
We're so cute.
We have that.
Also over here is a minus two.
And basically what happens is we just get two times the power using the same kind of pattern.
You can see the pattern that's arising from that expansion.
OK.
So when we get this result in corporates who are not relativistic scenario, we find something interesting.
So I got the result down here that this this guy goes all the way up over here and our frequency, our
C frequency and relativistic sense.
If we expand it out, it's going to be one minus two times virality of over 30 plus two times B relative
or C squared, minus two times the rest of our C cute.
We have to keep on going until these terms can really dampen out that they don't contribute anything
additional depending upon the precision we're looking for.
And then we multiply by our source frequency.
So if we take this.
And compare it to our non relativistic result when we expanded it out.
What we had was one minus two times virale over C, but we sort of locked in as this turns the source
frequency.
But initially in the expansion we saw, we had a plus viral load of C squared and we could continue
expanding it out now.
We decided to drop this term here because a small ratio when the relative velocity is much less than
C a small ratio squared, it's much smaller than the ratio itself, right?
So it's insignificant.
But what's really cool is that we see these initial terms line up with a relativistic result and then
we get a V relative of a C squared term popping out.
But it's missing this, too.
And if we continued, we would get similar results that are popping out.
So we see that.
The moral to the stick result.
It's sort of like the relativistic result.
And as the speeds start to slow down, this will converge upon this.
That's what we would find.
But in situations such as the USS Enterprise, the Millennium Falcon, a lot of fictional ideas so far
so far.
We would want to use this relativistic result, and we've got it right here.
So whatever you're doing this, you want really precise results.
You can use this guy, you know this guy right here and this for radar systems when you want to the
two way Doppler shift.
You can tell, you know, it's not as nice to work with, but it would get you that nice, precise result
for manmade vehicles, we found that beta is much smaller than one or the velocity is much lower than
the speed of light.
And we could get away actually with using this nice, simplified equation if we want a more precision.
Right.
Instead of taking one minus two times B rather c, we can add in the square turn and hold just a bit
closer to the relative term here.
OK.
So there you have it.
The moral to the relativistic result is more convenient, easier to work with, but this guy's going
to converge upon reality and this is what we want if we really want to bridge the gap between an infinite
set of perceptions of the universe.
OK, so whatever you do, any problem like this pay attention to your relative velocity and let this
guide your logic in choosing what equation you want.
I hope you enjoy the video.
Stay tuned for the next section.
When we start jumping into more wacky ideas, crazy effects related to momentum, energy and maybe other
interesting ideas.
I'm not going to ruin it for you right now.
Stay tuned.